<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:base="deployment_intro.xml" version="5.0" xml:id="preface-deployment">
 <title>About This Guide</title>
 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker/>
        <dm:translation>no</dm:translation>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <para>
  Installations of <phrase role="productname"><phrase os="sled">SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop</phrase></phrase> are possible in different ways. It is
  impossible to cover all combinations of boot, or installation server,
  automated installations or deploying images. This manual should help with
  selecting the appropriate method of deployment for your installation.
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part-deployment"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Most tasks that are needed during installations are described here. This
     includes the manual setup of your computer and installation of additional
     software, and cloning disk images and performing the setup remotely.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part-customize-media"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If you need or want to modify the regular SUSE® Linux Enterprise installation images
     (for virtual environments, to create minimal boot images, or to customize
     modules, extensions, and repositories), this part describes how to do so.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part-installserver"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <phrase role="productname"><phrase os="sled">SUSE® Linux Enterprise Desktop</phrase></phrase> can be installed in different ways. Apart from the usual
     media installation, you can choose from various network-based approaches.
     This part describes setting up an installation server and how to prepare
     the boot of the target system for installation.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part-sysconfig"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Learn how to configure your system after installation. This part covers
     common tasks like setting up hardware components, installing or removing
     software, managing users, or changing settings with YaST.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_available_doc_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_feedback_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_typografie_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_lifecycle_support_i.xml"/>
</preface>
