<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="/usr/share/xml/geekodoc/rng/geekodoc5-flat.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="sec-bootproblem-aarch64">
 <title>Dealing with boot and installation problems</title>

 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>

 <para>
  Although &productnamereg; undergoes an extensive test program, problems may
  occasionally occur during boot or installation.
 </para>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-bootproblem-aarch64-boot">
  <title>Boot problems</title>
  <para>
   Boot problems may prevent the &yast; installer from starting on your system.
   Another symptom is failure to boot after the installation has been
   completed.
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Machine boots the installed system instead of the installation medium</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Change the boot sequence in your machine's BIOS. Refer to the
      documentation supplied with your hardware for further information.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>The system hangs</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Change the console on your system so that the kernel outputs are
      visible. Be sure to check the last few lines of output. This is normally
      done by pressing
      <keycombo><keycap function="control"/><keycap
      function="alt"/><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>.
      If you cannot resolve the problem, consult the &productname; support
      staff. To log all system messages at boot time, use a serial connection
      as described in
      <xref
      linkend="sec-x86-prep-installation-methods"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Boot disk</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The boot disk is a useful interim solution for boot issues. If you have
      difficulties setting the other configurations, or if you want to postpone
      the decision regarding the final boot mechanism, use a boot
      disk.<phrase os="sles"> For more details on creating boot disks, see
      <xref linkend="vle-grub2-mkrescue"/>.</phrase>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-bootproblem-aarch64-install">
  <title>Problems installing</title>
  <para>
   If an unexpected problem occurs during installation, information is needed
   to determine the cause of the problem. Use the following directions to help
   with troubleshooting:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check the outputs on the various consoles. You can switch consoles with
     the key combination <keycombo>
     <keycap function="control"/><keycap function="alt"/><keycap>Fn</keycap></keycombo>.
     For example, obtain a shell in which to execute various commands by
     pressing <keycombo>
     <keycap function="control"/><keycap function="alt"/><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Try launching the installation with <quote>Safe Settings</quote> (press
     <keycap>F5</keycap> on the installation screen and choose <guimenu>Safe
     Settings</guimenu>). If the installation works without problems in this
     case, there is an incompatibility that causes either
     <systemitem>ACPI</systemitem> or <systemitem>APIC</systemitem> to fail. In
     some cases, a firmware update fixes this problem.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check the system messages on a console in the installation system by
     entering the command <command>dmesg -T</command>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-bootproblem-aarch64-redirect">
  <title>Initiating installation instead of booting</title>
  <para>
   The default option in the boot menu of the installation medium for
   &productname; boots the machine into the already installed system. To initiate
   the installation process instead, choose one of the
   available installation options in the boot menu.
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
