<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.kgraft" xml:lang="en">
<?suse-quickstart color="suse"?>
 <title>Live Patching the Linux Kernel Using &kg;</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    This document describes the basic principles of the &kg; live patching
    technology and provides usage guidelines for the SLE Live Patching service.
   </para>

   <para>
    &kg; is a live patching technology for runtime patching of the Linux
    kernel, without stopping the kernel. This maximizes system uptime, and thus
    system availability, which is important for mission-critical systems. By
    allowing dynamic patching of the kernel, the technology also encourages
    users to install critical security updates without deferring them to a
    scheduled downtime.
   </para>

   <para>
    A &kg; patch is a kernel module, intended for replacing whole functions in
    the kernel. &kg; primarily offers in-kernel infrastructure for integration
    of the patched code with base kernel code at runtime.
   </para>

   <para>
    SLE Live Patching is a service provided on top of regular SUSE Linux
    Enterprise Server maintenance. &kg; patches distributed through SLE Live
    Patching supplement regular SLES maintenance updates. Common update stack
    and procedures can be used for SLE Live Patching deployment.
   </para>

   <para>
    Information provided further are related to the &amd64;/&intel64; architecture only. In case you use a different architecture, the procedures may differ.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>
 <xi:include href="kgraft.xml"/>
</chapter>
