<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!-- fs 2009-02-25: Todo Code 11:

* split Chapter 2 (apparmor_profiles.xml) into:
  - basic profile (basic file rules, and profile syntax)
  - advanced (all the newer stuff, owner rules, link pairs,
    unattached profiles, ...)
* External Local Profiles and Hats (in appendix?)
* /sys/kernel/security/apparmor/matching (for scripts):
  pattern=aadfa audit perms=rwxamlk/ user::other

  pattern=aadfa - means the matching is done by the aadfa engine, the old
                engine was individual rule based on pcre.  The aadfa
                engine is a lot faster and cleaner kernel side but
                requires the user side to do significantly more work
                setting things up.

                This tells the parser which set of routines to use.
  audit - means that rule auditing and quieting is supported
  perms=rwxamlk/ - is the list of perms supported.  / means that directory
                 are match by trailing / in policy.  This wasn't the
                 case pre AppArmor 2.1 (opensuse 10.3).
                 10.3 perms string looks like
                     pattern=aadfa perms=rwxamlz
                 the z is a bug it is supposed to be k, but it was also
                 had another bug because it was missing /, so z now = k/
                 to the tools.

                 if you look at SP2 perms it will look like
                    pattern=aadfa perms=rwxml
                 because it doesn't support everything that 10.3 does

  user::other - indicates the permission are support for both user and
              other matching.  Internally AA does something very similar
              to unix dac permission checking of user, group, other,
              except AA's is user, extended user acl, other.

              owner rules set the user set, none owner rules set the
              user and other set.  By the way it is actually possible to
              write an other rule.

                 other /bin/foo r,   # only matches files not owned by
                                       the user, nor matched by extended
                                       owner checks.
              But the syntax isn't set in stone yet, and I didn't add
              support to the tools yet.

              The extended permission acl (which replaces unix group
              check) will allow for specifying who the file is owned by.

                 owner=root /bin/foo rw,  # only allow access if the
                                            file is owned by root.
  
* the ability to drop/migrate events out of the events db
* mount rules (implemented)?

-->
<chapter id="cha.apparmor.concept">
 <title>Immunizing Programs</title>
 <para>
  Effective hardening of a computer system requires minimizing the number of
  programs that mediate privilege, then securing the programs as much as
  possible. With &aa;, you only need to profile the programs that are
  exposed to attack in your environment, which drastically reduces the
  amount of work required to harden your computer. &aa; profiles enforce
  policies to make sure that programs do what they are supposed to do, but
  nothing else.
 </para>
 <para>
  &aareg; provides immunization technologies that protect applications from
  the inherent vulnerabilities they possess. After installing &aa;, setting
  up &aa; profiles, and rebooting the computer, your system becomes
  immunized because it begins to enforce the &aa; security policies.
  Protecting programs with &aa; is referred to as
  <emphasis>immunizing</emphasis>.
 </para>
 <para>
  Administrators need only concern themselves with the applications that are
  vulnerable to attacks, and generate profiles for these. Hardening a system
  thus comes down to building and maintaining the &aa; profile set and
  monitoring any policy violations or exceptions logged by &aa;'s reporting
  facility.
 </para>
 <para>
  Users should not notice &aa; at all. It runs <quote>behind the
  scenes</quote> and does not require any user interaction. Performance is
  not noticeably affected by &aa;. If some activity of the application is
  not covered by an &aa; profile or if some activity of the application is
  prevented by &aa;, the administrator needs to adjust the profile of this
  application to cover this kind of behavior.
 </para>
 <para>
  &aa; sets up a collection of default application profiles to protect
  standard Linux services. To protect other applications, use the &aa; tools
  to create profiles for the applications that you want protected. This
  chapter introduces the philosophy of immunizing programs. Proceed to
  <xref
   linkend="cha.apparmor.profiles"/>,
  <xref linkend="cha.apparmor.yast"/>, or
  <xref linkend="cha.apparmor.commandline"/> if you are ready to build and
  manage &aa; profiles.
 </para>
 <para>
  &aa; provides streamlined access control for network services by
  specifying which files each program is allowed to read, write, and
  execute, and which type of network it is allowed to access. This ensures
  that each program does what it is supposed to do, and nothing else. &aa;
  quarantines programs to protect the rest of the system from being damaged
  by a compromised process.
 </para>
 <para>
  &aa; is a host intrusion prevention or mandatory access control scheme.
  Previously, access control schemes were centered around users because they
  were built for large timeshare systems. Alternatively, modern network
  servers largely do not permit users to log in, but instead provide a
  variety of network services for users (such as Web, mail, file, and print
  servers). &aa; controls the access given to network services and other
  programs to prevent weaknesses from being exploited.
 </para>
 <tip>
  <title>Background Information for &aa;</title>
  <para>
   To get a more in-depth overview of &aa; and the overall concept behind
   it, refer to <xref
    linkend="sec.apparmor.intro.background"></xref>.
  </para>
 </tip>
 <sect1 id="sec.apparmor.concept.tools">
  <title>Introducing the &aa; Framework</title>

  <para>
   This section provides a very basic understanding of what is happening
   <quote>behind the scenes</quote> (and under the hood of the &yast;
   interface) when you run &aa;.
  </para>

  <para>
   An &aa; profile is a plain text file containing path entries and access
   permissions. See <xref linkend="sec.apparmor.profiles.parts"/> for a
   detailed reference profile. The directives contained in this text file
   are then enforced by the &aa; routines to quarantine the process or
   program.
  </para>

  <para>
   The following tools interact in the building and enforcement of &aa;
   profiles and policies:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>aa-status</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>aa-status</command> reports various aspects of the current
      state of the running &aa; confinement.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>aa-unconfined</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>aa-unconfined</command> detects any application running on
      your system that listens for network connections and is not protected
      by an &aa; profile. Refer to
      <xref linkend="sec.apparmor.commandline.profiling.summary.unconfined"/>
      for detailed information about this tool.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>aa-autodep</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>aa-autodep</command> creates a basic framework of a profile
      that needs to be fleshed out before it is put to use in production.
      The resulting profile is loaded and put into complain mode, reporting
      any behavior of the application that is not (yet) covered by &aa;
      rules. Refer to
      <xref linkend="sec.apparmor.commandline.profiling.summary.autodep"/>
      for detailed information about this tool.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>aa-genprof</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>aa-genprof</command> generates a basic profile and asks you
      to refine this profile by executing the application and generating log
      events that need to be taken care of by &aa; policies. You are guided
      through a series of questions to deal with the log events that have
      been triggered during the application's execution. After the profile
      has been generated, it is loaded and put into enforce mode. Refer to
      <xref
       linkend="sec.apparmor.commandline.profiling.summary.genprof"/>
      for detailed information about this tool.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>aa-logprof</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>aa-logprof</command> interactively scans and reviews the log
      entries generated by an application that is confined by an &aa;
      profile in both complain and enforced modes. It assists you in
      generating new entries in the profile concerned. Refer to
      <xref linkend="sec.apparmor.commandline.profiling.summary.logprof"/>
      for detailed information about this tool.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>aa-easyprof</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>aa-easyprof</command> provides an easy to use interface for
      &aa; profile generation. <command>aa-easyprof</command> supports the
      use of templates and policy groups to quickly profile an application.
      Please note that while this tool can help with policy generation, its
      utility is dependent on the quality of the templates, policy groups
      and abstractions used. <command>aa-easyprof</command> may create a
      profile which is less restricted than creating the profile with
      <command>aa-genprof</command> and <command>aa-logprof</command>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>aa-complain</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>aa-complain</command> toggles the mode of an &aa; profile
      from enforce to complain. Exceptions to rules set in a profile are
      logged, but the profile is not enforced. Refer to
      <xref linkend="sec.apparmor.commandline.profiling.summary.complain"/>
      for detailed information about this tool.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>aa-enforce</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>aa-enforce</command> toggles the mode of an &aa; profile from
      complain to enforce. Exceptions to rules set in a profile are logged,
      but not permitted&mdash;the profile is enforced. Refer to
      <xref
       linkend="sec.apparmor.commandline.profiling.summary.enforce"/>
      for detailed information about this tool.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>aa-disable</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>aa-disable</command> disables the enforcement mode for one or
      more &aa; profiles. This command will unload the profile from the
      Kernel and prevent it from being loaded on &aa; start-up. The
      <command>aa-enforce</command> and <command>aa-complain</command>
      utilities may be used to change this behavior.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>aa-exec</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>aa-exec</command> launches a program confined by the
      specified &aa; profile and/or namespace. If both a profile and
      namespace are specified, the command will be confined by the profile
      in the new policy namespace. If only a namespace is specified, the
      profile name of the current confinement will be used. If neither a
      profile or namespace is specified, the command will be run using
      standard profile attachment&mdash;as if run without
      <command>aa-exec</command>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>aa-notify</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>aa-notify</command> is a handy utility that displays &aa;
      notifications in your desktop environment. You can also configure it to
      display a summary of notifications for the specified number of recent days.
      For more information, see <xref
      linkend="commandline.profiling.summary.aa-notify"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.apparmor.concept.determine">
  <title>Determining Programs to Immunize</title>

  <para>
   Now that you have familiarized yourself with &aa;, start selecting the
   applications for which to build profiles. Programs that need profiling
   are those that mediate privilege. The following programs have access to
   resources that the person using the program does not have, so they grant
   the privilege to the user when used:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>cron Jobs</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Programs that are run periodically by cron. Such programs read input
      from a variety of sources and can run with special privileges,
      sometimes with as much as &rootuser; privilege. For example, cron can
      run <command>/usr/sbin/logrotate</command> daily to rotate, compress,
      or even mail system logs. For instructions for finding these types of
      programs, refer to
      <xref xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage" linkend="sec.apparmor.concept.cron"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Web Applications</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Programs that can be invoked through a Web browser, including CGI Perl
      scripts, PHP pages, and more complex Web applications. For
      instructions for finding these types of programs, refer to
      <xref xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage" linkend="sec.apparmor.concept.network.web"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Network Agents</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Programs (servers and clients) that have open network ports. User
      clients, such as mail clients and Web browsers mediate privilege.
      These programs run with the privilege to write to the user's home
      directory and they process input from potentially hostile remote
      sources, such as hostile Web sites and e-mailed malicious code. For
      instructions for finding these types of programs, refer to
      <xref xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage" linkend="sec.apparmor.concept.network.agents"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   Conversely, unprivileged programs do not need to be profiled. For
   instance, a shell script might invoke the <command>cp</command> program
   to copy a file. Because <command>cp</command> does not by default have its own
   profile or subprofile, it inherits the profile of the parent shell script, so can copy
   any files that the parent shell script's profile can read and write.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.apparmor.concept.cron">
  <title>Immunizing cron Jobs</title>

  <para>
   To find programs that are run by cron, inspect your local cron
   configuration. Unfortunately, cron configuration is rather complex, so
   there are numerous files to inspect. Periodic cron jobs are run from
   these files:
  </para>

<screen>/etc/crontab 
/etc/cron.d/* 
/etc/cron.daily/* 
/etc/cron.hourly/*
/etc/cron.monthly/* 
/etc/cron.weekly/*
</screen>

  <para>
   The <command>crontab</command> command lists/edits the current user's
   crontab. To manipulate &rootuser;'s cron jobs, first become &rootuser;,
   and then edit the tasks with <command>crontab -e</command> and list them
   with <command>crontab -l</command>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.apparmor.concept.network">
  <title>Immunizing Network Applications</title>

  <para>
   An automated method for finding network server daemons that should be
   profiled is to use the <command>aa-unconfined</command> tool.
<!-- fs 2011-11-09 - see bnc #722915
     (reporting is not available in 12.1 (aa-eventd isn't maintained upstream,
      and doesn't understand the (not-so-)new audit.log format))
   You can
   also simply view a report of this information in the &yast; module (refer
   to
   <xref xrefstyle="HeadingOnPage" linkend="sec.apparmor.managing.config_reports.view.audit"/>
   for instructions).
-->
  </para>

  <!-- bnc#880080: netstat vs. ss/ip -->
  <para>
   The <command>aa-unconfined</command> tool uses the command
   <command>netstat -nlp</command> to inspect your open ports from inside
   your computer, detect the programs associated with those ports, and
   inspect the set of &aa; profiles that you have loaded.
   <command>aa-unconfined</command> then reports these programs along with
   the &aa; profile associated with each program, or reports
   <quote>none</quote> (if the program is not confined).
  </para>

  <note>
   <para>
    If you create a new profile, you must restart the program that has been
    profiled to have it be effectively confined by &aa;.
   </para>
  </note>


  <para>
   Below is a sample <command>aa-unconfined</command> output:
  </para>

<screen>3702<co id="co.apparmor.concept.network.id"/> /usr/sbin/sshd<co id="co.apparmor.concept.network.string"/> confined
   by '/usr/sbin/sshd<co id="co.apparmor.concept.network.confine"/> (enforce)' 
4040 /usr/sbin/ntpd confined by '/usr/sbin/ntpd (enforce)' 
4373 /usr/lib/postfix/master confined by '/usr/lib/postfix/master (enforce)' 
4505 /usr/sbin/httpd2-prefork confined by '/usr/sbin/httpd2-prefork (enforce)'
646 /usr/lib/wicked/bin/wickedd-dhcp4 not confined
647 /usr/lib/wicked/bin/wickedd-dhcp6 not confined
5592 /usr/bin/ssh not confined
7146 /usr/sbin/cupsd confined by '/usr/sbin/cupsd (complain)'</screen>

  <calloutlist>
   <callout arearefs="co.apparmor.concept.network.id">
    <para>
     The first portion is a number. This number is the process ID number
     (PID) of the listening program.
    </para>
   </callout>
   <callout arearefs="co.apparmor.concept.network.string">
    <para>
     The second portion is a string that represents the absolute path of the
     listening program
    </para>
   </callout>
   <callout arearefs="co.apparmor.concept.network.confine">
    <para>
     The final portion indicates the profile confining the program, if any.
    </para>
   </callout>
  </calloutlist>

  <note>
   <para>
    <command>aa-unconfined</command> requires &rootuser; privileges and
    should not be run from a shell that is confined by an &aa; profile.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   <command>aa-unconfined</command> does not distinguish between one network
   interface and another, so it reports all unconfined processes, even those
   that might be listening to an internal LAN interface.
  </para>

  <para>
   Finding user network client applications is dependent on your user
   preferences. The <command>aa-unconfined</command> tool detects and
   reports network ports opened by client applications, but only those
   client applications that are running at the time the
   <command>aa-unconfined</command> analysis is performed. This is a problem
   because network services tend to be running all the time, while network
   client applications tend only to be running when the user is interested
   in them.
  </para>

  <para>
   Applying &aa; profiles to user network client applications is also
   dependent on user preferences. Therefore, we leave the profiling of user
   network client applications as an exercise for the user.
  </para>


  <para>
   To aggressively confine desktop applications, the
   <command>aa-unconfined</command> command supports a
   <option>--paranoid</option> option, which reports all processes running
   and the corresponding &aa; profiles that might or might not be associated
   with each process. The user can then decide whether each of these
   programs needs an &aa; profile.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you have new or modified profiles, you can submit them to the <ulink
   url="mailto:AppArmor@lists.ubuntu.com">AppArmor@lists.ubuntu.com</ulink>
   mailing list along with a use case for the application behavior that you
   exercised. The &aa; team reviews and may submit the work into &productname;.
   We cannot guarantee that every profile will be included, but we make a
   sincere effort to include as much as possible so that end users can
   contribute to the security profiles that ship in &productname;.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.apparmor.concept.network.web">
   <title>Immunizing Web Applications</title>
   <para>
    To find Web applications, investigate your Web server configuration. The
    Apache Web server is highly configurable and Web applications can be
    stored in many directories, depending on your local configuration.
    &productname;, by default, stores Web applications in
    <filename>/srv/www/cgi-bin/</filename>. To the maximum extent possible,
    each Web application should have an &aa; profile.
   </para>
   <para>
    Once you find these programs, you can use the
    <command>aa-genprof</command> and <command>aa-logprof</command> tools to
    create/tune/update &aa; profiles for them.
   </para>
   <para>
    Because CGI programs are executed by the Apache Web server, the profile
    for Apache itself, <filename>usr.sbin.httpd2-prefork</filename> for
    Apache2 on &productname;, must be modified to add execute permissions to
    each of these programs.  For instance, adding the line
    <literal>/srv/www/cgi-bin/my_hit_counter.pl rPx</literal> grants Apache
    permission to execute the Perl script
    <filename>my_hit_counter.pl</filename> and requires that there be a
    dedicated profile for <filename>my_hit_counter.pl</filename>. If
    <filename>my_hit_counter.pl</filename> does not have a dedicated profile
    associated with it, the rule should say
    <literal>/srv/www/cgi-bin/my_hit_counter.pl rix</literal> to cause
    <filename>my_hit_counter.pl</filename> to inherit the
    <filename>usr.sbin.httpd2-prefork</filename> profile.
   </para>
   <para>
    Some users might find it inconvenient to specify execute permission for
    every CGI script that Apache might invoke. Instead, the administrator
    can grant controlled access to collections of CGI scripts. For instance,
    adding the line <literal>/srv/www/cgi-bin/*.{pl,py,pyc} rix</literal>
    allows Apache to execute all files in
    <literal>/srv/www/cgi-bin/</literal> ending in <filename>.pl</filename>
    (Perl scripts) and <filename>.py</filename> or <filename>.pyc</filename>
    (Python scripts). As above, the <literal>ix</literal> part of the rule
    causes Python scripts to inherit the Apache profile, which is
    appropriate if you do not want to write individual profiles for each
    Python script.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     If you want the subprocess confinement module
     (<filename>apache2-mod-apparmor</filename>) functionality when Web
     applications handle Apache modules (<filename>mod_perl</filename> and
     <filename>mod_php</filename>), use the ChangeHat features when you add
     a profile in &yast; or at the command line. To take advantage of the
     subprocess confinement, refer to
     <xref xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage" linkend="sec.apparmor.hat.apache.managing"/>.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    Profiling Web applications that use <filename>mod_perl</filename> and
    <filename>mod_php</filename> requires slightly different handling. In
    this case, the <quote>program</quote> is a script interpreted directly
    by the module within the Apache process, so no exec happens. Instead,
    the &aa; version of Apache calls <command>change_hat()</command> using a
    subprofile (a <quote>hat</quote>) corresponding to the name of the URI
    requested.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     The name presented for the script to execute might not be the URI,
     depending on how Apache has been configured for where to look for
     module scripts. If you have configured your Apache to place scripts in
     a different place, the different names appear in log file when &aa;
     complains about access violations. See
     <xref
	linkend="cha.apparmor.managing"/>.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    For <filename>mod_perl</filename> and <filename>mod_php</filename>
    scripts, this is the name of the Perl script or the PHP page requested.
    For example, adding this subprofile allows the
    <filename>localtime.php</filename> page to execute and access the local
    system time:
   </para>
   <remark condition="clarity">
    2007-08-28 - jjaeger: someone, please check
    </remark>
<screen>/usr/bin/httpd2-prefork {
  # ...
  ^/cgi-bin/localtime.php {
    /etc/localtime                  r,
    /srv/www/cgi-bin/localtime.php  r,
    /usr/lib/locale/**              r,
  }
}
</screen>
   <para>
    If no subprofile has been defined, the &aa; version of Apache applies
    the <systemitem>DEFAULT_URI</systemitem> hat. This subprofile is
    sufficient to display an HTML Web page. The
    <systemitem>DEFAULT_URI</systemitem> hat that &aa; provides by default
    is the following:
   </para>
<screen>^DEFAULT_URI {
    /usr/sbin/suexec2                  mixr,
    /var/log/apache2/**                rwl,
    @{HOME}/public_html                r,
    @{HOME}/public_html/**             r,
    /srv/www/htdocs                    r,
    /srv/www/htdocs/**                 r,
    /srv/www/icons/*.{gif,jpg,png}     r,
    /srv/www/vhosts                    r,
    /srv/www/vhosts/**                 r,
    /usr/share/apache2/**              r,
    /var/lib/php/sess_*                rwl 
}
    </screen>
   <para>
    To use a single &aa; profile for all Web pages and CGI scripts served by
    Apache, a good approach is to edit the
    <systemitem>DEFAULT_URI</systemitem> subprofile. For more information on
    confining Web applications with Apache, see
    <xref linkend="cha.apparmor.hat"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.apparmor.concept.network.agents">
   <title>Immunizing Network Agents</title>
   <para>
    To find network server daemons and network clients (such as fetchmail or
    Firefox) that need to be profiled, you should inspect the open ports on
    your machine, consider the programs that are answering on those ports, and
    provide profiles for as many of those programs as possible. If you provide
    profiles for all programs with open network ports, an attacker cannot get
    to the file system on your machine without passing through a &aa; profile
    policy.
   </para>
   <!-- bnc#880080: netstat vs. ss/ip -->
   <para>
    Scan your server for open network ports manually from outside the
    machine using a scanner (such as nmap), or from inside the machine using
    the <command>netstat --inet -n -p</command> command. Then, inspect the
    machine to determine which programs are answering on the discovered open
    ports.
   </para>
   <tip>
    <!-- bnc#880080: netstat vs. ss/ip -->
    <para>
     Refer to the man page of the <command>netstat</command> command for a
     detailed reference of all possible options.
    </para>
   </tip>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
