<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.apparmor.hat">
 <title>Profiling Your Web Applications Using ChangeHat</title>
 <para>
  An &aareg; profile represents the security policy for an individual
  program instance or process. It applies to an executable program, but if a
  portion of the program needs different access permissions than other
  portions, the program can <quote>change hats</quote> to use a different
  security context, distinctive from the access of the main program. This is
  known as a <emphasis>hat</emphasis> or <emphasis>subprofile</emphasis>.
 </para>
 <para>
  ChangeHat enables programs to change to or from a <emphasis>hat</emphasis>
  within a &aa; profile. It enables you to define security at a finer level
  than the process. This feature requires that each application be made
  <quote>ChangeHat aware</quote>, meaning that it is modified to make a
  request to the &aa; module to switch security domains at arbitrary times
  during the application execution. One example of an change_hat-aware
  applications is the Apache Web server.
 </para>
 <para>
  A profile can have an arbitrary number of subprofiles, but there are only
  two levels: a subprofile cannot have further sub-subprofiles. A subprofile
  is written as a separate profile and named as the containing profile
  followed by the subprofile name, separated by a <literal>^</literal>.
  Subprofiles are either stored in the same file as the parent profile, or
  in a separate file. The latter case is recommended on sites with a large
  number of hats&mdash;it allows the policy caching to handle changes at the
  per hat level. If all the hats are in the same file as the parent profile,
  then the parent profile and all hats must be recompiled.
 </para>
 <para>
  An external subprofile that is going to be used as a hat, must begin with
  'hat' or '^' string.
 </para>
 <para>
  The following two subprofiles <emphasis>cannot</emphasis> be used as a
  hat:
 </para>
<screen>/foo//bar { }</screen>
 <para>
  or
 </para>
<screen>profile /foo//bar { }</screen>
 <para>
  While the following two are treated as hats:
 </para>
<screen>^/foo//bar { }</screen>
 <para>
  or
 </para>
<screen>hat /foo//bar { }</screen>
 <para>
  Note that the security of hats is considerably weaker than that of full
  profiles. That is to say, if attackers can find just the right kind of bug
  in a program, they may be able to escape from a hat into the containing
  profile. This is because the security of hats is determined by a secret
  key handled by the containing process, and the code running in the hat
  must not have access to the key. Thus change_hat is most useful in
  conjunction with application servers, where a language interpreter (such
  as PERL, PHP, or Java) is isolating pieces of code such that they do not
  have direct access to the memory of the containing process.
 </para>
 <para>
  The rest of this chapter describes using change_hat in conjunction with
  Apache, to contain Web server components run using mod_perl and mod_php.
  Similar approaches can be used with any application server by providing an
  application module similar to the mod_apparmor described next in
  <xref
   linkend="sec.apparmor.hat.config.directives"/>.
 </para>
 <tip>
  <title>For More Information</title>
  <para>
   For more information, see the <command>change_hat</command> man page.
  </para>
 </tip>
 <sect1 id="sec.apparmor.hat.config" role="General">
  <title>Configuring Apache for <systemitem>mod_apparmor</systemitem></title>

  <para>
   <phrase os="sles;sled">&aa; provides a <literal>mod_apparmor</literal>
   module (package
   <systemitem class="resource">apache2-mod-apparmor</systemitem>) for the
   Apache program (only included in &sls;).</phrase> <phrase os="osuse">&aa;
   provides a <literal>mod_apparmor</literal> module (package
   <systemitem
     class="resource">apache2-mod_apparmor</systemitem>) for
   the Apache program.</phrase> This module makes the Apache Web server
   ChangeHat aware. Install it along with Apache.
  </para>

  <para>
   When Apache is ChangeHat aware, it checks for the following customized
   &aa; security profiles in the order given for every URI request that it
   receives.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     URI-specific hat. For example,
     <filename>^www_app_name/templates/classic/images/bar_left.gif</filename>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>DEFAULT_URI</literal>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>HANDLING_UNTRUSTED_INPUT</literal>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <note>
   <title>Apache Configuration</title>
   <para>
    If you install
    <phrase os="sles;sled;slert"><systemitem class="resource"
      >apache2-mod-apparmor</systemitem></phrase><phrase os="osuse"><systemitem class="resource"
      >apache2-mod_apparmor</systemitem></phrase>,
    make sure the module is enabled, and then restart Apache by executing
    the following command:
   </para>
<screen>a2enmod apparmor &amp;&amp; rcapache2 restart</screen>
  </note>

  <para>
   Apache is configured by placing directives in plain text configuration
   files. The main configuration file is usually
   <filename>/etc/apache2/httpd.conf</filename>. When you compile Apache,
   you can indicate the location of this file. Directives can be placed in
   any of these configuration files to alter the way Apache behaves. When
   you make changes to the main configuration files, you need to reload
   Apache with <command>sudo systemctl reload apache2.service</command>, 
   so the changes are recognized.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.apparmor.hat.config.vhost">
   <title>Virtual Host Directives</title>
   <para>
    Virtual host directives control whether requests that contain trailing
    pathname information following an actual filename (or that refer to a
    nonexistent file in an existing directory) are accepted or rejected. For
    Apache documentation on virtual host directives, refer to
    <ulink
     url="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.4/en/mod/core.html#virtualhost"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The ChangeHat-specific configuration keyword is
    <literal>AADefaultHatName</literal>. It is used similarly to
    <literal>AAHatName</literal>, for example, <literal>AADefaultHatName
    My_Funky_Default_Hat</literal>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The configuration option is actually based on a server directive, which
    enables you to use the keyword outside of other options, setting it for
    the default server. Virtual hosts are considered internally within
    Apache to be separate <quote>servers,</quote> so you can set a default
    hat name for the default server as well as one for each virtual host, if
    desired.
   </para>
   <para>
    When a request comes in, the following steps reflect the sequence in
    which <literal>mod_apparmor</literal> attempts to apply hats.
   </para>
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A location or directory hat as specified by the
      <literal>AAHatName</literal> keyword
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A hat named by the entire URI path
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A default server hat as specified by the
      <literal>AADefaultHatName</literal> keyword
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>DEFAULT_URI</literal> (if none of those exist, it goes back
      to the <quote>parent</quote> Apache hat)
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.apparmor.hat.config.directives">
   <title>Location and Directory Directives</title>
   <para>
    Location and directory directives specify hat names in the program
    configuration file so the program calls the hat regarding its security.
    For Apache, you can find documentation about the location and directory
    directives at
    <ulink
     url="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.4/en/sections.html"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The location directive example below specifies that, for a given
    location, <literal>mod_apparmor</literal> should use a specific hat:
   </para>
<screen>&lt;Location /foo/&gt;
  AAHatName MY_HAT_NAME
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>
   <para>
    This tries to use <literal>MY_HAT_NAME</literal> for any URI beginning
    with <filename>/foo/</filename> (<filename>/foo/</filename>,
    <filename>/foo/bar</filename>,
    <filename>/foo/cgi/path/blah_blah/blah</filename>, etc.).
   </para>
   <para>
    The directory directive works similarly to the location directive,
    except it refers to a path in the file system as in the following
    example:
   </para>
<screen>
&lt;Directory "/srv/www/www.immunix.com/docs"&gt; 
  # Note lack of trailing slash 
  AAHatName immunix.com 
&lt;/Directory&gt;</screen>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.apparmor.hat.apache.managing">
  <title>Managing ChangeHat-Aware Applications</title>

  <para>
   In the previous section you learned about <literal>mod_apparmor</literal>
   and the way it helps you securing a specific Web application. This
   section walks you through a real life example of creating a hat for a Web
   application, and making use of &aa;'s change_hat feature to secure it.
   Note that this chapter focuses on &aa;'s command line tools, as &yast;
   &aa; module has limited functionality.
  </para>

  <para>
   For illustration purposes, I chose the Web application called
   <emphasis>Adminer</emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.adminer.org/en/"/>).
   It is a full-featured SQL database management tool written in PHP, yet
   consisting of a single PHP file. For Adminer to work, you need to set up
   an Apache Web server, PHP and its Apache module, and one of database
   drivers available for PHP - &mysql; in this example. You can install the
   required packages with
  </para>

<screen>zypper in apache2 apache2-mod_apparmor apache2-mod_php5 php5 php5-mysql
</screen>

  <para>
   To set up the Web environment for running Adminer, follow these steps:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Setting up Web server environment</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Make sure <literal>apparmor</literal> and <literal>php5</literal>
     modules are enabled for Apache. If unsure, run
    </para>
<screen>a2enmod apparmor php5</screen>
    <para>
     and then restart Apache with
    </para>
    <screen>sudo systemctl restart apache2.service</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Make sure &mysql; is running. If unsure, restart it with
    </para>
    <screen>sudo systemctl restart mysql.service</screen>
    <remark>taroth 2014-02-26: at the moment, there is no mariadb.service, starting
     mysql seems to be the right way - wrote
     mail to mhrusecky to ask if this is bound to change anytime soon for SLE
     12</remark>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Download Adminer from <ulink url="http://www.adminer.org"/>, copy it to
     <filename>/srv/www/htdocs/adminer/</filename>, and rename it to
     <filename>adminer.php</filename>, so that its full path is
     <filename>/srv/www/htdocs/adminer/adminer.php</filename>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Test Adminer in your Web browser by entering
     <literal>http://localhost/adminer/adminer.php</literal> in its URI
     address field. If you installed Adminer to remote a server, replace
     <literal>localhost</literal> with the real hostname of the server.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Adminer login page</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="aa_changehat_adminer.png" width="75%" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="aa_changehat_adminer.png" width="40%"
	 format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <tip>
     <para>
      If you encounter problems viewing the Adminer login page, try to look
      for help in the Apache error log
      <filename>/var/log/apache2/error.log</filename>. Another reason why
      you may not access the Web page may be the fact that your Apache is
      already under &aa; control and its &aa; profile is too tight to permit
      viewing Adminer. Check it with <command>aa-status</command>, and if
      needed, set Apache temporarily in complain mode with
     </para>
<screen>aa-complain usr.sbin.httpd2-prefork</screen>
    </tip>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   After the Web environment for Adminer is ready, you need to configure
   Apache's mod_apparmor, so that &aa; can detect accesses to Adminer and
   change to the specific <quote>hat</quote>.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Configuring mod_apparmor</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Apache has several configuration files under
     <filename>/etc/apache2/</filename> and
     <filename>/etc/apache2/conf.d/</filename>. Choose your preferred one
     and open it in your favorite text editor. In this example, I use the
     <command>vim</command> editor, and prefer to create a new configuration
     file <filename>/etc/apache2/conf.d/apparmor.conf</filename>.
    </para>
<screen>vim /etc/apache2/conf.d/apparmor.conf</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Copy the following snippet in the edited file.
    </para>
<screen>&lt;Directory /srv/www/htdocs/adminer>
  AAHatName adminer
&lt;/Directory></screen>
    <para>
     It tells Apache to let &aa; know about a change_hat event when the Web
     user accesses the directory <filename>/adminer</filename> (and any
     file/directory inside) in Apache's document root. Remember - we placed
     the <filename>adminer.php</filename> application there.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Save the file, close the editor, and restart Apache with
    </para>
    <screen>sudo systemctl restart apache2.service</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   Apache now knows about our Adminer and changing a <quote>hat</quote> for
   it. It is time to create the related hat for Adminer in the &aa;
   configuration. If you do not have an &aa; profile yet, create one before
   proceeding. Remember that if your Apache's main binary is
   <filename>/usr/sbin/httpd2-prefork</filename>, then the related profile
   is named <filename>/etc/apparmor.d/usr.sbin.httpd2-prefork</filename>.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Creating a Hat for Adminer</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open (or create one if it does not exist) the file
     <filename>/etc/apparmor.d/usr.sbin.httpd2-prefork</filename> in a text
     editor. Its contents should be similar to the following:
    </para>
<screen>#include &lt;tunables/global>

/usr/sbin/httpd2-prefork {
  #include &lt;abstractions/apache2-common>
  #include &lt;abstractions/base>
  #include &lt;abstractions/php5>

  capability kill,
  capability setgid,
  capability setuid,

  /etc/apache2/** r,
  /run/httpd.pid rw,
  /usr/lib{,32,64}/apache2*/** mr,
  /var/log/apache2/** rw,

  ^DEFAULT_URI {
    #include &lt;abstractions/apache2-common>
    /var/log/apache2/** rw,
  }

  ^HANDLING_UNTRUSTED_INPUT {
    #include &lt;abstractions/apache2-common>
    /var/log/apache2/** w,
  }
}</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Before the last closing curly bracket (<literal>}</literal>), insert
     the following section:
    </para>
<screen>^adminer flags=(complain) {
}</screen>
    <para>
     Note the <literal>(complain)</literal> addition after the hat name - it
     tells &aa; to leave the adminer hat in complain mode. That is because
     we need to learn the hat profile by accessing Adminer later on.
     <remark>@cboltz: i did it this way myself and it worked perfectly</remark>
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Save the file, and then restart &aa;, then Apache.
    </para>
<screen>systemctl reload apparmor.service apache2.service</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Check if the adminer hat really is in complain mode.
    </para>
<screen># aa-status 
apparmor module is loaded.
39 profiles are loaded.
37 profiles are in enforce mode.
[...]
   /usr/sbin/httpd2-prefork
   /usr/sbin/httpd2-prefork//DEFAULT_URI
   /usr/sbin/httpd2-prefork//HANDLING_UNTRUSTED_INPUT
[...]
2 profiles are in complain mode.
   /usr/bin/getopt
   /usr/sbin/httpd2-prefork//adminer
[...]
</screen>
    <para>
     As we can see, the <literal>httpd2-prefork//adminer</literal> is loaded
     in complain mode. Good.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   Our last task is to find out the right set of rules for the adminer hat.
   That is why we set the adminer hat into complain mode - the logging
   facility collects useful information about
   <filename>adminer.php</filename>'s access requirements as we use it via
   the Web browser. <command>aa-logprof</command> then helps us with
   creating the hat's profile itself.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Generating Rules for the Adminer Hat</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open Adminer in the Web browser. If you installed it locally, then the
     URI is <literal>http://localhost/adminer/adminer.php</literal>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Choose the database engine you want to use (&mysql; in our case), and
     log in to Adminer using existing database username and password. You do
     not have to specify the database name as you can do so after logging
     in. Perform any operations with Adminer you like - create a new
     database, create a new table for it, set user privileges, and so on.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After the short testing of Adminer's user interface, switch back to
     console and examine the log for collected data.
    </para>
<screen># aa-logprof 
Reading log entries from /var/log/messages.
Updating AppArmor profiles in /etc/apparmor.d.
Complain-mode changes:

Profile:  /usr/sbin/httpd2-prefork^adminer
Path:     /dev/urandom
Mode:     r
Severity: 3

  1 - #include &lt;abstractions/apache2-common>
[...]  
 [8 - /dev/urandom]

[(A)llow] / (D)eny / (G)lob / Glob w/(E)xt / (N)ew / Abo(r)t / (F)inish / (O)pts</screen>
    <para>
     From the <command>aa-logprof</command>'s message it is clear that our
     new adminer hat was correctly detected - notice the line
    </para>
<screen>Profile:  /usr/sbin/httpd2-prefork^adminer</screen>
    <para>
     The <command>aa-logprof</command> will ask you to pick the right rule
     for each discovered &aa; event. Specify the one you want to use, and
     confirm with <guimenu>Allow</guimenu>. For more information on working
     with <command>aa-genprof</command> and <command>aa-logprof</command>
     interface, see
     <xref linkend="sec.apparmor.commandline.profiling.summary.genprof"/>.
    </para>
    <tip>
     <para>
      <command>aa-logprof</command> usually offers several valid rules for
      the examined event. Some of them are <emphasis>abstractions</emphasis>
      - predefined set of rules affecting a specific common group of
      targets. Sometimes it is useful to include such abstraction instead of
      a direct URI rule:
     </para>
<screen> 1 - #include &lt;abstractions/php5> 
 [2 - /var/lib/php5/sess_3jdmii9cacj1e3jnahbtopajl7p064ai242]</screen>
     <para>
      In the example above, I recommend hitting <guimenu>1</guimenu> and
      confirm with <guimenu>A</guimenu> to allow the abstraction.
     </para>
    </tip>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After the last change, you will be asked to save the changed profile.
    </para>
<screen>The following local profiles were changed. Would you like to save them?
 [1 - /usr/sbin/httpd2-prefork]

 (S)ave Changes / [(V)iew Changes] / Abo(r)t</screen>
    <para>
     Hit <guimenu>S</guimenu> to save the changes.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Set the profile to enforce mode with <command>aa-enforce</command>
    </para>
<screen>aa-enforce usr.sbin.httpd2-prefork</screen>
    <para>
     and check its status with <command>aa-status</command>
    </para>
<screen># aa-status
apparmor module is loaded.
39 profiles are loaded.
38 profiles are in enforce mode.
[...]
   /usr/sbin/httpd2-prefork
   /usr/sbin/httpd2-prefork//DEFAULT_URI
   /usr/sbin/httpd2-prefork//HANDLING_UNTRUSTED_INPUT
   /usr/sbin/httpd2-prefork//adminer
[...]</screen>
    <para>
     As you can see, the <literal>//adminer</literal> hat jumped from
     <emphasis>complain</emphasis> to <emphasis>enforce</emphasis> mode.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Try to run Adminer in the Web browser, and if you encounter problems
     running it, switch it to the complain mode, repeat the steps that
     previously did not work well, and update the profile with
     <command>aa-logprof</command> until you are satisfied with the
     application functionality.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <note>
   <title>Hat and Parent Profile Relationship</title>
   <para>
    The profile <filename>^adminer</filename> is only available in the
    context of a process running under the parent profile
    <filename>usr.sbin.httpd2-prefork</filename>.
   </para>
  </note>

  <sect2 id="sec.apparmor.hat.apache.managing.add">
   <title>Adding Hats and Entries to Hats in &yast;</title>
   <para>
    When you use the <guimenu>Edit Profile</guimenu> dialog (for
    instructions, refer to
    <xref xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage" linkend="sec.apparmor.yast.edit"/>) or
    when you add a new profile using <guimenu>Manually Add Profile</guimenu>
    (for instructions, refer to
    <xref xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage" linkend="sec.apparmor.yast.add"/>),
    you are given the option of adding hats (subprofiles) to your &aa;
    profiles. Add a ChangeHat subprofile from the <guimenu>&aa; Profile
    Dialog</guimenu> window as in the following.
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <textobject role="description"><phrase>&aa; profile dialog</phrase>
     </textobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="hats_in_profiles.png" width="75%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="hats_in_profiles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      From the <guimenu>&aa; Profile Dialog</guimenu> window, click
      <guimenu>Add Entry</guimenu> then select <guimenu>Hat</guimenu>. The
      <guimenu>Enter Hat Name</guimenu> dialog box opens:
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <textobject role="description"><phrase>Enter hat name</phrase>
       </textobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="hat_createhat.png" width="50%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="hat_createhat.png" width="35%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Enter the name of the hat to add to the &aa; profile. The name is the
      URI that, when accessed, receives the permissions set in the hat.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Create Hat</guimenu>. You are returned to the
      <guimenu>&aa; Profile Dialog</guimenu> screen.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      After adding the new hat, click <guimenu>Done</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
