<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.apparmor.glossary">
 <title>&aa; Glossary</title>
 <info>
    <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
    </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Abstraction</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     See <emphasis>profile foundation classes</emphasis> below.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Apache</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Apache is a freely-available Unix-based Web server. It is currently the
     most commonly used Web server on the Internet. Find more information
     about Apache at the Apache Web site at
     <link xlink:href="http://www.apache.org"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>application fire-walling</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &aa; confines applications and limits the actions they are permitted
     to take. It uses privilege confinement to prevent attackers from using
     malicious programs on the protected server and even using trusted
     applications in unintended ways.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>attack signature</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Pattern in system or network activity that alerts of a possible virus
     or hacker attack. Intrusion detection systems might use attack
     signatures to distinguish between legitimate and potentially malicious
     activity.
    </para>
    <para>
     By not relying on attack signatures, &aa; provides "proactive"
     instead of "reactive" defense from attacks. This is better because
     there is no window of vulnerability where the attack signature must be
     defined for &aa; as it does for products using attack signatures.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>GUI</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Graphical user interface. Refers to a software front-end meant to
     provide an attractive and easy-to-use interface between a computer user
     and application. Its elements include windows, icons, buttons, cursors,
     and scroll bars.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>globbing</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     File name substitution. Instead of specifying explicit file name paths,
     you can use helper characters <literal>*</literal> (substitutes any
     number of characters except special ones such as <literal>/</literal>
     or <literal>?</literal>) and <literal>?</literal> (substitutes exactly
     one character) to address multiple files/directories at once.
     <literal>**</literal> is a special substitution that matches any file
     or directory below the current directory.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>HIP</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Host intrusion prevention. Works with the operating system kernel to
     block abnormal application behavior in the expectation that the
     abnormal behavior represents an unknown attack. Blocks malicious
     packets on the host at the network level before they can
     <quote>hurt</quote> the application they target.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>mandatory access control</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A means of restricting access to objects that is based on fixed
     security attributes assigned to users, files, and other objects. The
     controls are mandatory in the sense that they cannot be modified by
     users or their programs.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>profile</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &aa; profile completely defines what system resources an individual
     application can access, and with what privileges.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>profile foundation classes</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Profile building blocks needed for common application activities, such
     as DNS lookup and user authentication.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>RPM</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The RPM Package Manager. An open packaging system available for anyone
     to use. It works on Red Hat Linux, &productname;, and other Linux
     and Unix systems. It is capable of installing, uninstalling, verifying,
     querying, and updating computer software packages. See
     <link xlink:href="http://www.rpm.org/"/> for more information.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>SSH</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Secure Shell. A service that allows you to access your server from a
     remote computer and issue text commands through a secure connection.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>streamlined access control</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &aa; provides streamlined access control for network services by
     specifying which files each program is allowed to read, write, and
     execute. This ensures that each program does what it is supposed to do
     and nothing else.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>URI</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Universal resource identifier. The generic term for all types of names
     and addresses that refer to objects on the World Wide Web. A URL is one
     kind of URI.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>URL</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Uniform Resource Locator. The global address of documents and other
     resources on the Web.
    </para>
    <para>
     The first part of the address indicates what protocol to use and the
     second part specifies the IP address or the domain name where the
     resource is located.
    </para>
    <para>
     For example, when you visit <literal>http://www.suse.com</literal>, you
     are using the HTTP protocol, as the beginning of the URL indicates.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>vulnerabilities</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     An aspect of a system or network that leaves it open to attack.
     Characteristics of computer systems that allow an individual to keep it
     from correctly operating or that allows unauthorized users to take
     control of the system. Design, administrative, or implementation
     weaknesses or flaws in hardware, firmware, or software. If exploited, a
     vulnerability could lead to an unacceptable impact in the form of
     unauthorized access to information or the disruption of critical
     processing.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
</chapter>
