<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!--taroth 2013-02-18: SLED 11 SP3 contains pidgin 2.6.6-->
<chapter id="cha.gnome.pidgin">
 <title>Pidgin: Instant Messaging</title>
 <para>
  Pidgin (formerly called Gaim) is an instant messaging (IM) client that
  allows you to connect to multiple accounts simultaneously. Chat live with
  your contacts in one tabbed interface, regardless of which IM system they
  use. Pidgin supports the following instant messaging protocols: AOL*
  Instant Messenger (AIM), Bonjour, Gadu-Gadu, Google Talk, GroupWise
  Messenger, ICQ, IRC, Jabber/XMPP, MSN Messenger,
  <phrase os="sled">Microsoft Live Communication Server (LCS/OCS),
  </phrase>MXit, MySpaceIM, QQ, SIMPLE, Yahoo!*, and Zephyr*. Pidgin also
  supports many features of the various networks, such as file transfer,
  away messages, and typing notification.
 </para>
 <para>
  In the following, learn how to set up Pidgin and how to communicate with
  your contacts.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.pidgin.configure">
  <title>Configuring Accounts</title>

  <para>
   To use Pidgin, you must already have accounts on the systems you want to
   use. For example, to use Pidgin for your AIM account, you must first have
   an AIM account. Once you have those accounts, set them up in the Pidgin
   <guimenu>Add Account</guimenu> dialog.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Adding and Editing Accounts</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start Pidgin from the main menu or press <keycombo>
     <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter
     <command>pidgin</command>. If Pidgin does not start, check if the
     package <systemitem class="resource">pidgin</systemitem> is installed.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you start Pidgin for the first time, a message appears, prompting
     you to configure an account. Otherwise, Pidgin opens the Buddy List
     window, showing your contacts.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To add or edit an account from there, select <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Accounts</guimenu> <guimenu>Manage Accounts</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Accounts</guimenu> dialog, click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>
     to add a new account or select an existing account and click
     <guimenu>Modify</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Basic</guimenu> tab, select the protocol. The dialog to
     add or modify accounts differs for each protocol, depending on what
     setup options are available for that protocol.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="pidgin_addaccount.png" width="48%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="pidgin_addaccount.png" width="48%" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the data received on registration with the messaging service.
     This usually consists of the user name or e-mail address and a password.
     Your protocol might support additional options, such as a buddy icon,
     alias, login options, or others.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> tab, enter the
     <guimenu>Server</guimenu> and <guimenu>Port</guimenu> you got from your
     messaging service or system administrator.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Save</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If needed, add accounts for each additional protocol, as described
     above.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   After an account is added, you can log in to that account by entering
   your password in the Pidgin login dialog. Use the
   <guimenu>Accounts</guimenu> menu to view and enable or disable accounts
   that you have configured.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.pidgin.buddy_list">
  <title>Managing Your Contacts</title>

  <para>
   Use the Buddy List to manage your contacts, also known as buddies. You
   can add and remove buddies from your Buddy List, and you can organize
   your buddies in groups so they are easy to find.
  </para>

  <para>
   After your accounts are set up, all buddies who are online appear in your
   Buddy List. If you want your buddies who are not online to appear in the
   Buddy List, click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Buddies</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Show</guimenu> <guimenu>Offline Buddies</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Pidgin Buddy List</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="pidgin_buddylist.png" width="28%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="pidgin_buddylist.png" width="28%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   To add a buddy to your Buddy List, click <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Buddies</guimenu> <guimenu>Add Buddy</guimenu> </menuchoice>,
   then enter the information about that buddy.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>Adding Contacts for Certain Protocols</title>
   <para>
    For some protocols, you cannot add a buddy in the Pidgin interface. You
    must use the client for those protocols if you want to add to your buddy
    list. After you have added a buddy in the protocol’s client, that
    buddy appears in your Buddy List.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   To remove a buddy from the list of contacts, right-click that buddy’s
   name in the Buddy List and click <guimenu>Remove</guimenu>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.pidgin.chat">
  <title>Chatting with Friends</title>

  <para>
   It is necessary to be connected to the Internet to be able to chat with
   other participants. After a successful login, you are usually marked as
   <guimenu>Available</guimenu> in the Buddy List, and thus visible to
   others. To change your status, click the drop-down box at the bottom of
   the Buddy List and select another option.
  </para>

  <para>
   To open a chat session, double-click a buddy name in the Buddy List. The
   Chat screen opens. Type your message, then press <guimenu>Enter</guimenu>
   to send.
  </para>

  <para>
   Each chat session you open appears as a tab in the Chat screen. Click
   a buddy’s tab to chat with that buddy. Close a chat session by closing
   the tab for that buddy.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Pidgin Chat Session</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="pidgin_chat.png" width="55%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="pidgin_chat.png" width="55%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.pidgin.more">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   This chapter explained the Pidgin options you need to know about to set
   up Pidgin and communicate with your contacts. It does not explain all of
   Pidgin’s features and options. For more information, open Pidgin, then
   click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Help</guimenu> <guimenu>Online Help</guimenu>
   </menuchoice> or press <keycap>F1</keycap>.
  </para>

  <para>
   For updates about new features and for the latest information, refer to
   the project's home page at <ulink url="http://www.pidgin.im"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
