<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
  ]>
<!--

fs 2010-09-08:
from doccomment 11715:

i could not find any basic configuration for pulse to be able to record sound.
Basic the sound is running, but there are to many configuration which are confusion.
Again: every good mathematic book explain the rule and than give a real example with figure to understand the story.
In your manual there is missing how to record sound! (Basic setting)

taroth 2011-08-04: use pavucontrol but still not sure about the options on the
configuration tab:

Analog stereo Duplex means you get both a stereo input and a stereo output.
Analog Stereo Output means you get only a stereo output, no input.
Digital connections carry digital signals, so normally you wouldn't be
able to connect those directly to speakers or microphones.

Normally you would choose Analog Stereo Duplex.
-->
<chapter id="cha.sound">
 <title>&amarok;, Kaffeine and More: Playing Music and Movies</title>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   During installation, &yast; normally identifies and configures the sound
   cards of your computer automatically. Otherwise (or if you installed a
   new sound card), start &yast; and configure the sound card manually in
   the <guimenu>Sound</guimenu> module. There, you can also disable the
   PulseAudio sound system, if needed. For details, refer to
   <xref
    linkend="sec.y2.hw.sound"/>. When your sound card has been
   configured, you can control the volume and balance with a mixer and start
   other sound applications.
  </para>

  <para>
   Linux includes a wide range of sound and multimedia applications. Some of
   these applications are installed on your Linux system by default. With
   the applications described here you can control the volume and balance of
   playback and play CDs, music and movie files. You can also record and
   compress your own audio data.
  </para>

  <para>
   In case one of the listed applications is not installed by default on
   your system, use &yast; to install the missing packages. Use the search
   function of the &yast; package management tool to find the package names.
   For details on installing software, see <xref linkend="cha.y2.sw"/>.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <sect1 id="sec.sound.mixers">
  <title>Mixers</title><indexterm>

  <primary>sound</primary>

  <secondary>mixers</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Mixers provide a convenient means of controlling the volume and balance
   of the sound output and input of computers.
  </para>

  <para>
   The main difference between the various mixers is the outward appearance
   of the user interface. However, there are a number of mixers that are
   designed for specific hardware. From the mixers available, select the one
   that best suits your needs.
  </para>

  <para>
   The default KDE mixer application is KMix. If the mixer icon (a
   loudspeaker symbol) is not visible in the panel of your desktop, press
   <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and
   enter <command>kmix</command> or start the mixer from the main menu. By
   default, clicking the KMix icon in the system tray shows the master
   controller with which to control the overall volume. To fine-tune your
   sound settings for several channels, right-click the KMix icon and select
   <guimenu>Show Mixer Window</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can mute and increase or decrease the volume for all of the channels
   separately. If you need or want to change the channel to be used as
   master channel, right-click the KMix icon and click <guimenu>Select
   Master Channel</guimenu>. If you want more or less channels to appear in
   the mixer window, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Configure Channels</guimenu> </menuchoice> and select the ones
   you want to show.
<!--taroth 091015: online help not updated to KDE 4 version yet, therefore commenting for
    now: For further information about KMix, refer to the online help.-->
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.sound.kmix">
   <title>KMix Mixer Window</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="sound_kmix.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="sound_kmix.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <tip>
   <title>Starting the Mixer</title>
   <para>
    Generally, it is advisable to open a mixer application before opening
    other sound applications. Use the mixer to test and adjust the control
    settings for the input and output of the sound card.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
   If you use the PulseAudio sound system, you can control both the volume
   of hardware devices and of each playback stream separately using
   <guimenu>PulseAudio Volume Control</guimenu>, a mixer-like application
   (<systemitem class="resource">pavucontrol</systemitem> package).
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.sound.players">
  <title>Playing Music Files</title><indexterm>

  <primary>sound</primary>

  <secondary>players</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   In Linux, find a variety of programs for playing music files, such as Ogg
   Vorbis or WAV. Ogg Vorbis is a free audio compression format that is now
   supported by the majority of audio players and even portable MP3 players.
   The file types supported by the applications depend on the engine used.
  </para>

  <note os="osuse">
   <title>Playing MP3 Files</title>
   <para>
    &opensuse; currently does not benefit from an MP3 codec agreement.
    However, community support for MP3 and alternatives is strong. For more
    information and any options that might work for you legally and
    technically, refer to
    <ulink url="http://opensuse-community.org/Restricted_Formats"/> and
    <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/Restricted_Formats#Possible_Solutions_2"
    />.
   </para>
  </note>

  <sect2 id="sec.sound.players.amarok">
   <title>&amarok; Music Player</title><indexterm>
<!--taroth 2011-08-04: documented here: amarok 2.1.1, KDE 4.3.5-->
   <primary>sound</primary>
   <secondary>players</secondary>
   <tertiary>&amarok;</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>&amarok;</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>applications</primary>
   <secondary>multimedia</secondary>
   <tertiary>&amarok;</tertiary></indexterm>
   <para>
    The &amarok; music player allows you to play various audio formats,
    create playlists,
<!--import music from removable media such as portable MP3
    players or external hard disks (or upload files to removable media), -->
    and to listen to streaming audio broadcasts of radio stations on the
    Internet. The file types supported depend on the engine used.
   </para>
   <para>
    To start &amarok;, press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
    <keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo> and enter <command>amarok</command>.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.sound.players.amarok.main">
    <title>&amarok; Main Window</title>
    <para>
     By default, the &amarok; main window is divided into three main parts:
     the browser pane on the left, the context view in the middle and the
     playlist on the right side. Both the browser pane and the context view
     include several tabs. Click a tab to switch views and to access the
     information available there. Clicking a tab twice in the browser pane
     hides the browser pane and expands the context view to the left.
    </para>
    <figure id="fig.sound.amarok.main">
     <title>&amarok;&mdash;Main Window</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="amarok_main.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="amarok_main.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Browser Pane</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Includes the following tabs:
       </para>
       <formalpara>
        <title>Collection:</title>
        <para>
         Shows your personal music collection. The search field on top
         allows you to create filters to search for certain artists or
         titles. Click the wrench icon at the right of the browser pane, if
         you want to configure the way your collection is displayed, or to
         reorganize the collection. For more information about customizing
         the <guimenu>Collection</guimenu> tab, refer to
         <xref
          linkend="pro.amarok.custom.collection"/>.
        </para>
       </formalpara>
       <formalpara>
        <title>Internet:</title>
        <para>
         Shows the Internet services configured for &amarok;. For details on
         how to configure the services, refer to
         <xref
          linkend="sec.sound.players.amarok.configure"/>.
         Click an entry to access the respective service. To get back to the
         list of services, click the arrow icon in the top left corner.
        </para>
       </formalpara>
       <formalpara>
        <title>Playlists:</title>
        <para>
         Lets you generate <guimenu>Dynamic Playlists</guimenu> based on
         certain criteria. To access and organize any playlist you have
         saved before, click <guimenu>My Playlist</guimenu>. From the
         playlist tab, you can also add or update
         <guimenu>Podcasts</guimenu>. For more information about playlists,
         refer to <xref
          linkend="pro.amarok.playlists"/>. To learn
         more about podcasts, refer to
         <xref linkend="pro.amarok.podcasts"/>.
        </para>
       </formalpara>
       <formalpara>
        <title>Filelists:</title>
        <para>
         Shows a file browser that corresponds to the standard KDE file
         manager. This view is designed for finding audio files you want to
         play, but not to add to your collection. Use the icons at the top
         to navigate the file system, change the view or to create
         bookmarks.
        </para>
       </formalpara>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Context View</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Shows information about the currently played track. Depending on
        your configuration of this view, the following tabs are available:
        <guimenu>Albums</guimenu>, <guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu>,
        <guimenu>Current Track</guimenu>, <guimenu>Lyrics</guimenu>,
        <guimenu>Media Devices</guimenu>, <guimenu>Services</guimenu>, and
        <guimenu>Wikipedia</guimenu>. To change views, click one of the
        tabs. To learn how to configure the context view, refer to
        <xref linkend="pro.amarok.custom.context"
        />.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Playlist</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <remark>taroth 091020: amarok audio CD support starts again with
         amarok 2.2, thus integrate for next revision</remark>
        Shows the list of tracks that has been added there to be played.
        This can include tracks from your music collection, streams from the
        Internet, or podcasts.
<!--or tracks from a CD-->
        The currently played track is highlighted in the list. Use the icons
        at the bottom of the playlist to clear, modify, save or export the
        current playlist or click the wrench icon to configure the playlist
        layout. For more information about playlists, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.sound.players.amarok.playlists"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.sound.players.amarok.listen">
    <title>Listening to Music and Podcasts</title>
    <remark>taroth 091020: audio CD support + support of external
     devices starts again with amarok 2.2,  thus integrate for next revision</remark>
    <para>
     With &amarok;, you can listen to music from various
     sources&mdash;whether from your music collection on hard disc
<!--, or
      extranel devices, audio CDs -->
     or streams from the Internet.
    </para>
    <para>
     To fill the playlist area, just drag and drop items from the browser
     pane on the left to the playlist pane on the right (or double-click to
     move them to the playlist). This works for items on the
     <guimenu>Collection</guimenu>, the <guimenu>Internet</guimenu> or the
     <guimenu>Files</guimenu> tab. To select multiple items, keep
     <keycap function="shift"/> or <keycap function="control"/> pressed
     while selecting the items. Alternatively, right-click an item on one of
     the tabs and select if to append it to the playlist or if to replace
     the current playlist with this item.
    </para>
    <para>
     Double-click an item in the playlist to play it. Alternatively, use the
     control buttons in the upper part of the &amarok; main window to play,
     pause, stop or skip items in the playlist.
    </para>
    <para>
     For example, to listen to the music of your <guimenu>Last.fm</guimenu>
     neighbors, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Internet</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Last.fm</guimenu> <guimenu>My Neighborhood</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>, add this entry to the playlist and start playing.
    </para>
    <para>
     Usually, &amarok; plays all tracks displayed in the playlist pane from
     top to bottom and stops after the last track. To modify play mode and
     behavior, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Playlist</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Random</guimenu> </menuchoice> or <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Playlist</guimenu> <guimenu>Repeat</guimenu> </menuchoice> and
     select the desired options. Instead of manually adding items to the
     playlist and then playing them in random order, you can also let
     &amarok; create dynamic playlists as described in
     <xref linkend="pro.amarok.playlists.dynamic"/>.
    </para>
    <procedure id="pro.amarok.podcasts">
     <title>Subscribing and Listening to Podcasts</title>
     <para>
      Podcasts are series of audio (or video) files that are released
      periodically and can be downloaded automatically by subscribing to a
      Web feed. You can add and manage podcasts on the
      <guimenu>Playlist</guimenu> tab of the browser pane. If the
      <guimenu>Podcast Directory</guimenu> Web service is configured for
      &amarok;, you can also access a huge number of podcasts from there.
     </para>
     <step id="step.amarok.podcasts.1">
      <para>
       To add a podcast channel that you already know the URL of, switch to
       the <guimenu>Playlists</guimenu> tab and click <guimenu>Add
       Podcast</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step id="step.amarok.podcasts.2">
      <para>
       Copy or enter the podcast URL into the next dialog and confirm with
       <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step id="step.amarok.podcasts.3">
      <para>
       Right-click a podcast channel to open a context-menu allowing you to
       append or load the podcast to the playlist, to download an episode,
       to configure the podcast, to remove your subscription or to update
       the podcast channel.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If you want &amarok; to automatically scan for updates on this
       podcast channel or to automatically download new episodes,
       right-click the podcast channel and select
       <guimenu>Configure</guimenu>. In the podcast configuration dialog you
       can also define the location to where &amarok; should save this
       podcast or limit the number of episodes stored.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To use the integrated Web service to browse for available podcasts,
       switch to the <guimenu>Internet</guimenu> tab and click
       <guimenu>Podcast Directory</guimenu>. For more information about the
       &amarok; Web services, refer to
       <xref
        linkend="pro.amarok.config.basic"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
       When clicking <guimenu>Podcast Directory</guimenu> for the first
       time, &amarok; automatically fetches the list of podcasts, which
       takes a few seconds. Otherwise click <guimenu>Update</guimenu> to
       enforce a reload of the list. The available podcasts are sorted into
       categories.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Browse the list of podcasts or enter a term in the search field to
       filter for certain podcasts.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To get automatic updates for a podcast, select the podcast and click
       <guimenu>Subscribe</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       View and manage the podcasts that you have subscribed to as described
       in steps <xref linkend="step.amarok.podcasts.1"/> to
       <xref linkend="step.amarok.podcasts.1"/> above.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <remark>taroth 091020: no time left now, but for next revision,
     mention bookmarking feature</remark>
<!--Bookmarking - in two types, automatic and manual. When you are listening to a long podcast,
     audiobook (or any other track longer than 10 minutes) Amarok will
     automatically mark the last listened to position and auto resume playback
     when you return to the track. You can also manually bookmark a position in
     any track to save for later. -->
<!--http://" before this podcast's name. When the entry starts simply with
    "www" the program does nothing. -->
    <procedure id="pro.amarok.radio">
     <title>Listening to Web Radio</title>
     <para>
      When listening to Web radio streams, &amarok; also displays the
      current title and track played by the station.
     </para>
     <step>
      <para>
       To listen to a certain stream (like for example, a Web radio
       channel), select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Playlist</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Add Stream</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Copy or enter the stream URL into the next dialog and confirm with
       <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. The stream is automatically added to the
       playlist pane on the right.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Double-click the stream entry in the playlist to start listening.
       Alternatively, use the control buttons in the upper part of the
       &amarok; main window to play, pause, or stop the stream.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.sound.players.amarok.playlists">
    <title>Using Playlists</title>
    <para>
     If you have added several items form your music collection to the
     playlist pane on the right, you can also save and export the current
     tracks as playlist for later reuse.
    </para>
    <para>
     Instead of manually adding items to the playlist pane and setting a
     certain play mode, &amarok; can also make use of dynamic playlists.
     Dynamic playlists allow you to play tracks from your collection in a
     random order or to define how &amarok; should mix the music an then
     turn the dynamic mode on.
    </para>
    <procedure id="pro.amarok.playlists">
     <title>Saving and Exporting Playlists</title>
     <para>
      If you <emphasis>save</emphasis> a playlist, it can be played again
      later with &amarok; by accessing it from the
      <guimenu>Playlists</guimenu> tab. In contrast to this,
      <emphasis>exporting</emphasis> a playlist allows you to store and use
      it also outside of &amarok;.
     </para>
     <step>
      <para>
       To save a playlist, either click the <guimenu>Save Playlist</guimenu>
       icon at the bottom of the playlist pane.
      </para>
      <para>
       The browser pane automatically switches to the
       <guimenu>Playlists</guimenu> tab. It shows the newly added playlist
       below <guimenu>My Playlists</guimenu> and prompts you to enter a name
       for the playlist. If you do not enter a name, date and time of
       creation are automatically set as name for the playlist.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To create folders in <guimenu>My Playlists</guimenu>, click the
       <guimenu>Add Folder</guimenu> icon.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       You can also modify an already saved playlist by dragging and
       dropping new items from the playlist pane on the right onto the
       playlist entry shown below <guimenu>My Playlists</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To load, rename or delete a playlist, right-click the playlist and
       select the appropriate menu item from the context menu.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To use a playlist in players other than &amarok;, click the
       <guimenu>Export Playlist</guimenu> icon at the bottom of the playlist
       pane.
      </para>
      <note>
       <title>Sharing Playlists with Other Players</title>
       <para>
        Save playlists in <literal>m3u</literal> format, so you can share
        them with any other players using this format.
       </para>
      </note>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select or enter a location and filename for your playlist and click
       <guimenu>Save</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <procedure id="pro.amarok.playlists.dynamic">
     <title>Creating Dynamic Playlists</title>
     <para>
      With dynamic playlists, &amarok; lets you either play tracks from your
      collection in a random order or lets you create biased playlists
      according to probability-driven criteria (<quote>biases</quote>). You
      can create weighted random playlists that adhere to certain criteria
      exactly (<guimenu>Proportional Bias</guimenu>) and to certain criteria
      approximately (<guimenu>Fuzzy Bias</guimenu>). It is possible to mix
      both types of biases when configuring a dynamic playlist.
     </para>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click the <guimenu>Playlists</guimenu> tab at the left side of the
       &amarok; main window and select <guimenu>Dynamic Playlist</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To create a random playlist without matching any criteria, set the
       <guimenu>Playlist</guimenu> drop-down list to
       <literal>Random</literal> (which is the default value) and activate
       the <guimenu>On</guimenu> check-box. A randomly created list of
       tracks appears in the playlist pane.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To add a criterion that should be matched exactly:
      </para>
      <substeps>
       <step>
        <para>
         Click the <guimenu>Add</guimenu> icon in the <guimenu>Proportional
         Bias</guimenu> category.
        </para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>
         Select the desired criterion from the <guimenu>Match</guimenu>
         drop-down list.
        </para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>
         From the <guimenu>With</guimenu> drop-down list, select the value
         that you want to set for this criterion.
        </para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>
         With the <guimenu>Proportion</guimenu> slider, define which portion
         of the playlist should match this criterion.
        </para>
       </step>
      </substeps>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To add a criterion that should be matched approximately:
      </para>
      <substeps>
       <step>
        <para>
         Click the <guimenu>Add</guimenu> icon in the <guimenu>Fuzzy
         Bias</guimenu> category.
        </para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>
         Select the desired criterion from the <guimenu>Match</guimenu>
         drop-down list.
        </para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>
         From the <guimenu>With</guimenu> drop-down list, select the value
         that you want to set for this criterion.
        </para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>
         With the <guimenu>Strictness</guimenu> slider, define how strictly
         to match this criterion.
        </para>
        <informalfigure>
         <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
           <imagedata fileref="amarok_dynamic_playlist.png" width="60%"
            format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
           <imagedata fileref="amarok_dynamic_playlist.png" width="65%"
            format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
         </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
       </step>
      </substeps>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Add further proportional or fuzzy biases as desired.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To remove a bias, click the <guimenu>Remove</guimenu> icon in front
       of this bias.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To save the current configuration for the dynamic playlist, click the
       <guimenu>Save</guimenu> icon at the upper right corner of the
       <guimenu>Dynamic Playlist</guimenu> category and enter a name.
      </para>
      <para>
       The saved dynamic playlist configuration can now be accessed from the
       <guimenu>Playlist</guimenu> drop-down list at any time.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To use the selected dynamic playlist, activate the
       <guimenu>On</guimenu> check-box.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>Repopulate</guimenu> if you want to replace the
       current tracks in the playlist area with the newly generated dynamic
       playlist.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.sound.players.amarok.collection">
    <title>Managing your Music Collection</title>
    <note>
     <title>Many Services Depend on Proper Tagging</title>
     <para>
      When compressing (ripping) your audio data, <literal>tags</literal>
      are stored for each track, containing meta data like information about
      the artist, the track, the album, or the music genre. Usually, the
      tags are automatically assigned during the ripping process but
      sometimes they need to be corrected manually as described in
      <xref linkend="pro.amarok.edit"/>.
     </para>
     <para>
      Many services (like retrieving covers from Amazon, or scrobbling your
      music to <literal>Last.fm</literal>) depend on proper tagging of your
      collection&mdash;otherwise they will fail or transfer incorrect data.
     </para>
    </note>
    <para>
     &amarok; offers a lot of options for managing your personal music
     collection: For example, you can let &amarok; scan for any changes to
     your music collection, edit track information (like tags or ratings and
     statistics) or automatically retrieve the cover artwork for each album.
    </para>
    <para>
     After initial creation and basic configuration of your collection as
     described in
     <xref
      linkend="sec.sound.players.amarok.configure"/>, you can at
     any time trigger an update by selecting <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Update Collection</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>. This reflects any changes done to your collection folder
     on the <guimenu>Collection</guimenu> tab immediately, without waiting
     for &amarok; to update the collection automatically during the next
     check.
    </para>
    <para>
     Tracks of unknown artists or albums are grouped under
     <guimenu>Unknown</guimenu> at the beginning of your collection.
     Compilation albums appear under <guimenu>Various Artists</guimenu>. To
     mark an album as compilation album, right-click the album and select
     <guimenu>Show Under Various Artists</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     To search or filter your collection for a certain track or album, enter
     the title (or part of it) in the search field at the top. Each
     character you enter narrows down the search and the selection in the
     browser is adjusted as you type. To search for specific metadata such
     as <guimenu>Genre</guimenu> or <guimenu>Bitrate</guimenu>, or to
     combine several search options, click the <guimenu>Edit
     Filter</guimenu> button to the right of the search field to open a
     dialog that provides advanced filter options.
    </para>
    <para>
     In the following, find examples for further common tasks you might want
     to execute.
    </para>
    <procedure id="pro.amarok.covers">
     <title>Assigning Album Covers</title>
     <para>
      &amarok;'s <guimenu>Cover Manager</guimenu> lets you comfortably add,
      correct or fetch any missing covers for your music collection. If
      automatic cover retrieval is configured, &amarok; tries to fetch any
      album covers from an Amazon Web server. If &amarok; cannot find an
      album cover (which is sometimes the case if the collection is not
      tagged properly or if the album is only available via a direct sales
      channel), you can also manually assign a cover or custom picture.
     </para>
     <para>
      If not configured otherwise, album covers are displayed on the
      <guimenu>Collection</guimenu> tab, in the context view and on the
      on-screen display (or on external widgets like PlayWolf).
     </para>
     <para>
      Retrieval of covers relies on the tags of your music collection:
      &amarok; uses the <literal>Artist&nbsp;-&nbsp;Album</literal> query to
      search Amazon for covers. The better your collection is tagged, the
      better the hit rate when automatically retrieving covers.
     </para>
     <step>
      <para>
       If you want &amarok; to automatically retrieve cover artwork for each
       album, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Configure &amarok;</guimenu> <guimenu>General</guimenu>
       </menuchoice> and activate the respective option in the configuration
       dialog.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Confirm your changes and close the configuration dialog.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To define from which Amazon Web server &amarok; should get the
       covers, click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Cover
       Manager</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <figure id="fig.sound.amarok.cover">
       <title>&amarok;&mdash;Cover Editor</title>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
         <imagedata fileref="amarok_cover_editor.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
         <imagedata fileref="amarok_cover_editor.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </figure>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       From the <guimenu>Amazon Locale</guimenu> drop-down list choose the
       location of the Web server that suits your needs best.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If &amarok; could not retrieve all covers automatically, you can
       check for any missing covers by setting the <guimenu>View </guimenu>
       to <guimenu>Albums Without Cover</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If necessary, change the <guimenu>Amazon Locale</guimenu>, then click
       <guimenu>Fetch Missing Covers</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If retrieval is still not successful or if you are not satisfied with
       a certain cover, right-click the cover and select <guimenu>Fetch
       Cover</guimenu> to manually refine the search by editing the search
       string.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To remove a cover, right-click the respective cover and select
       <guimenu>Unset Cover</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If you already have your own cover images, you can assign them by
       right-clicking an album cover and choosing <guimenu>Set Custom
       Cover</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <procedure id="pro.amarok.edit">
     <title>Editing Tags, Statistics and Ratings</title>
     <para>
      Although tags are usually created automatically when ripping your
      music, it is sometimes necessary to edit or correct tags. Apart from
      editing tags, &amarok; also lets you manually edit statistics for a
      track like the rating or score. &amarok; automatically assigns a score
      to a song (ranging from <literal>0-100</literal>), based on how many
      times you have played that song and if you have played it completely
      (or skipped it). Every time the song finishes playing, the score is
      changed.
     </para>
     <step>
      <para>
       To edit or set tags for an artist, a complete album or individual
       tracks, right-click the respective entry on the
       <guimenu>Collection</guimenu> tab and select <guimenu>Edit Track
       Details</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       On the <guimenu>Tags</guimenu> tab, add or adjust the information as
       desired.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To set a custom rating for a track or to change the score, switch to
       the <guimenu>Statistics</guimenu> tab.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Move your mouse pointer over the star symbols until they change
       color. The more stars appear in yellow, the higher the rating. Click
       the mouse button to set the rating.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If desired, also adjust the track's <guimenu>Score</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Confirm your changes with <guimenu>Save &amp; Close</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.sound.players.amarok.configure">
    <title>Configuring &amarok;</title>
    <para>
     &amarok; offers a variety of configuration options. At first start-up,
     the most important settings to configure are the folders for your
     personal music collection and which back-end and sound system to use
     for playback. Although you can use &amarok; without a music collection,
     it is recommended to create a collection. Most of the powerful,
     advanced features are only available with an existing collection.
    </para>
    <para>
     Apart from that, &amarok; comes with integrated Internet services that
     you can activate or deactivate, like for example support for
     <literal>Last.fm</literal>, a popular Internet radio and music
     community Web site.
    </para>
<?dbfo-need height="20em"?>
    <procedure id="pro.amarok.config.basic">
     <title>Defining Basic &amarok; Settings</title>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure
       &amarok;</guimenu> </menuchoice> to access the &amarok; configuration
       dialog.
      </para>
      <informalfigure>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
         <imagedata fileref="amarok_configuration.png" width="75%" format="PNG"
         />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
         <imagedata fileref="amarok_configuration.png" width="65%" format="PNG"
         />
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>Collection</guimenu> and in the tree view, select the
       folder (or multiple folders) where &amarok; should scan for your
       music files.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Activate the respective options to make &amarok; scan the folders
       recursively or watch for changes in your music folders.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If you want to import an existing music collection (for example, from
       an older &amarok; version), click <guimenu>Import
       Collection</guimenu> and follow the steps on the screen.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       From the <guimenu>Playback</guimenu> category of the configuration
       dialog, you can also adjust the back-end and the output device for
       playing music, if necessary. To do so, click
       <guimenu>Configure</guimenu> to open the <guimenu>Sound and Video
       Configuration</guimenu> module (also accessible from the KDE
       <guimenu>Personal Settings</guimenu>). For more details about the
       output devices available from the list, hover your mouse pointer over
       the respective entries.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To discover the Web services integrated with &amarok;, click the
       <guimenu>Internet Services</guimenu> category. From there, you can
       activate, deactivate or configure access to several services like
       <guimenu>Ampache</guimenu> Web media server,
       <guimenu>Jamendo</guimenu> legal and free music download,
       <guimenu>Last.fm</guimenu> music community, <guimenu>Magnatune
       Store</guimenu>, <guimenu>MP3tunes</guimenu> music locker or podcasts
       and shoutcasts directories.
      </para>
      <para>
       Some of the services require registration. To sign up for a service
       or to enter your data for an already existing account, click the
       wrench icon next to the service.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To use and customize the appearance of an <guimenu>On Screen
       Display</guimenu> showing information like cover and artist of the
       currently played track, activate <guimenu>Use On-Screen
       Display</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Set the appearance options as desired and drag the preview to the
       desired place to define the position where the on-screen display
       should appear.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Confirm your changes with <guimenu>Apply </guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <tip>
     <title>Using &amarok; Widgets</title>
     <para>
      Instead of using the on-screen display to show information about the
      current track, you can also add external widgets to your desktop for
      displaying information or controlling &amarok;, for example, the
      <guimenu>PlayWolf</guimenu> widget. For details on how to add or
      download widgets, refer to
      <xref linkend="proc.kde.cust.desk.add.widgets"/>.
     </para>
    </tip>
    <para>
     Apart from configuring basic settings, &amarok; also allows you to
     customize most of the panels in the main window: you can define the way
     your collection is displayed, which information to see in the context
     view and how the tracks in the playlist on the right are shown.
    </para>
    <procedure id="pro.amarok.custom.collection">
     <title>Customizing the <guimenu>Collection</guimenu> Tab</title>
     <step>
      <para>
       To change the criteria according to which your collection is sorted
       and displayed, click the <guimenu>Sort Options</guimenu> icon at the
       upper right corner of the <guimenu>Collection</guimenu> tab.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select one of the predefined criteria that are displayed at the top
       of the menu.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Alternatively, create your own sort options by using <guimenu>First
       Level</guimenu>, <guimenu>Second Level</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Third
       Level</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Define if you want publication year and cover art of the albums to be
       displayed in the collection.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <procedure id="pro.amarok.custom.context">
     <title>Customizing the Context View</title>
     <para>
      You can choose from a number of applets to be displayed in the context
      view. These allow you to access different types of information about
      the currently played track by clicking the respective applet. For
      example, the <guimenu>Wikipedia</guimenu> applet searches for the
      artist's name and displays the corresponding Wikipedia article in the
      context browser. <guimenu>Current Track </guimenu> shows the album
      cover (if available) and the listening statistics related to the
      current track. To automatically search for the
      <guimenu>Lyrics</guimenu> of a track and display them in the context
      view, add the <guimenu>Lyrics</guimenu> applet. This applet depends on
      one or more lyrics scripts configured for &amarok;. To add any
      scripts, use the <guimenu>Script Manager</guimenu> that is available
      from the <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> menu in the &amarok; main window.
     </para>
     <step>
      <para>
       To configure which applets should be displayed, click the wrench icon
       at the bottom right corner of the context view. The panel at the
       bottom of the context view changes and shows its configurations
       options.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To add an applet, click any of the <guimenu>Add</guimenu> icons.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Use the arrow icons to scroll through the list of available applets.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click an entry to add the respective applet.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To move applets to a different place within the panel, hover the
       mouse pointer over the respective applet until the cursor turns into
       a crosslines-like form. Move the cursor to the desired position in
       the panel, then click again to insert the applet.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To remove an applet, click the applet's <guimenu>Remove</guimenu>
       icon.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To leave the configuration mode and to lock the applets in their
       position, click the wrench icon.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <procedure id="pro.amarok.custom.playlist">
     <title>Customizing the Playlist</title>
     <para>
      &amarok; comes with several predefined layout settings for the
      playlist pane on the right, but you can also choose to create your own
      layout from scratch (or based on one of the default layouts).
     </para>
     <para>
<!--tracks are differently displayed if they are single or part of an album. -->
     </para>
     <step>
      <para>
       To select one of the predefined layouts, click the wrench icon at the
       bottom of the playlist and select <guimenu>Default</guimenu>,
       <guimenu>No Grouping</guimenu> or <guimenu>Verbose</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To create your own layout, click the wrench icon and select
       <guimenu>Configure Playlist Layouts</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click the default layouts in <guimenu>Available Layouts</guimenu> to
       see the options configured for each layout on the
       <guimenu>Head</guimenu>, <guimenu>Body</guimenu> and
       <guimenu>Single</guimenu> tabs on the right side.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Use the icons below <guimenu>Available Layouts</guimenu> to create a
       new playlist layout from scratch or to copy an existing layout as a
       basis for a new layout. Enter a name for the new layout.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       On each of the tabs on the right, configure the elements &amarok;
       should display by dragging and dropping the desired elements from the
       top row onto the respective tab.
      </para>
      <informalfigure>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
         <imagedata fileref="amarok_configure_playlist.png" width="75%"
          format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
         <imagedata fileref="amarok_configure_playlist.png" width="65%"
          format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Change the position of an element on a tab by clicking it and moving
       it around.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To set format options like <guimenu>Italic</guimenu> or
       <guimenu>Bold</guimenu> or <guimenu>Left</guimenu>,
       <guimenu>Center</guimenu>, or <guimenu>Right</guimenu>, right-click
       an element and select the respective option.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To remove an element from a tab, drag it back to the top row.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If all options are set according to your wishes, leave the
       <guimenu>Playlist Layout Editor</guimenu> with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>
       to save the newly defined layout.
      </para>
      <para>
       You can now switch to the new playlist layout at any time by clicking
       the wrench icon and selecting the layout's name from the context
       menu.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.sound.players.amarok.tray">
    <title>The &amarok; Tray Icon</title>
    <para>
     Like other KDE applications, &amarok; adds an icon to the KDE system
     tray. You can use this icon to control a large number of &amarok;'s
     features. Hovering the mouse pointer over the icon displays information
     about the track currently played. By scrolling the mouse wheel
     simultaneously you can reduce or increase the playback volume. A single
     left-click closes the application window without affecting playback.
     Click again to reopen the window. Clicking with the middle mouse button
     pauses playback&mdash;middle-click again to resume playback.
     Right-clicking opens a context menu where you have access to the player
     controls and can exit &amarok;.
    </para>
    <para>
     Using the <keycap function="shift"/> and <keycap function="control"/>
     keys together with the mouse gives you access to more advanced
     features. Holding <keycap function="shift"/> while scrolling the mouse
     wheel seeks through the current track. Holding
     <keycap function="control"/> while scrolling the mouse wheel skips
     through tracks in the playlist.
    </para>
    <para>
     You may also drag items and drop them on the tray icon to add them to
     the current playlist. A pop-up menu opens, asking whether to append the
     track to the playlist, append and play it, or queue it after the
     current track.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.sound.players.amarok.more">
    <title>For More Information</title>
    <para>
     For more information about &amarok; 2.x, refer to the following Web
     sites:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="http://amarok.kde.org/"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="http://userbase.kde.org/Amarok"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
<!--taroth 2013-02-19: FAQs no longer available at that place-->
<!-- <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="http://amarok.kde.org/wiki/FAQ"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>-->
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="http://introducingkde4.blogspot.com/2009/01/blog-post.html"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.sound.players.juk" os="osuse">
<!--taroth 2011-08-04: juk not on the SLE 11 SP2 media, perhaps osuse only? check for
    next osuse release-->
   <title>JuK Jukebox</title>
   <para>
    JuK is a jukebox application that lets you manage your music file
    collection and playlists. JuK maintains a list of all files it knows
    about. This is called the collection list. The list is specific to JuK
    and is not shared with other applications. Independent of the collection
    list are playlists. You can have as many playlists as you want and you
    can share your JuK playlists with other media players. You can also edit
    the tags of your music files.
   </para>
   <para>
    JuK is included in the
    <systemitem class="resource"
     >juk</systemitem> package. If JuK is
    installed, start it from the main menu or press <keycombo>
    <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter
    <command>juk</command>. On initial start-up you are prompted for the
    folders Juk should scan for your music collection. Find more information
    about JuK in the online help.
   </para>
  </sect2>

<?dbfo-need height="15em"?>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.sound.cd">
  <title>Handling Audio CDs</title><indexterm id="idx.cds.playing" class="startofrange">

  <primary>CDs</primary>

  <secondary>playing</secondary></indexterm><indexterm id="idx.cds.ripping" class="startofrange">

  <primary>CDs</primary>

  <secondary>ripping</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   There are many ways to listen to your favorite music tracks. Either play
   a CD or play digitized versions of them. The following section features
   CD player applications as well as some applications that can be used for
   digitizing audio CDs.
  </para>

  <para>
   For information about how to create your own CDs, refer to
   <xref linkend="cha.k3b"/>.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>CDDA and Analog CD Playback</title>
   <para>
    There are two different ways of playing audio CDs. CD and DVD drives
    capable of analog CD playback read the audio data and send it to the
    sound output device. Some external drives connected via PCMCIA,
    FireWire, or USB need to use CDDA (Compact Disk Digital Audio) to
    extract the audio data first then play it as digital PCM. The players
    featured in the following sections do not support CDDA. Use XMMS if you
    need CDDA support.
   </para>
  </important>

<?dbfo-need height="15em"?>

  <sect2 id="sec.sound.players.kscd">
   <title>KsCD&mdash;Audio CD Player</title><indexterm>
   <primary>sound</primary>
   <secondary>players</secondary>
   <tertiary>KsCD</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>CDs</primary>
   <secondary>players</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>KsCD</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>applications</primary>
   <secondary>multimedia</secondary>
   <tertiary>KsCD</tertiary></indexterm>
   <para>
    KsCD is an easy-to-use audio CD player included in the
    <systemitem class="resource"
     >kscd</systemitem> package. If it is
    installed, press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap>
    </keycombo> and enter <command>kscd</command> to start the application.
<!--taroth 091018: couldn't verfiy the following with
    11.2 RC1: -->
<!--KsCD integrates into your KDE panel and can be
    configured to start playing automatically after a CD has been inserted.
    To access the configuration menu, select <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Extras</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure KsCD</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>. Reteieve album and track information from a CDDB server
    on the Internet if KsCD is configured accordingly. You can also upload
    CDDB information to share it with others. Use the
    <guimenu>CDDB</guimenu> dialog for information retrieval and upload.-->
   </para>
   <figure
    id="fig.sound.kscd">
    <title>KsCD User Interface</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="kscd_main.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="kscd_main.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.sound.oggsect">
   <title>Compressing Audio Data: Ripping</title>
   <para>
    Audio compression can be handled by various tools. The following
    sections feature a command line approach to encoding and playing audio
    data as well as some graphical applications capable of audio
    compression.
   </para>
<!--taroth 091027: commenting as kaudiocreator is no longer available with KDE4 and 
        audex is unfortunately not shipped with 11.2-->
<!--<sect3 id="sec.sound.cd.rip.kaudiocreator">
    <title>Compressing Audio Data Using KAudioCreator</title>
    <para>
     <indexterm>
      <primary>sound</primary>
      <secondary>data compression</secondary>
      <tertiary>KAudioCreator</tertiary>
     </indexterm>
     <indexterm>
      <primary>KAudioCreator</primary>
     </indexterm>
     KAudioCreator is a lean CD ripper application (see
     <xref linkend="fig.sound.kaudiocreator"></xref>). Once started, it
     lists all the tracks of your CD in the <guimenu>CD Tracks</guimenu>
     tab. Select the tracks to rip and encode. To edit the track
     information, use the <guimenu>Album Editor</guimenu> under <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Edit Album</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     Otherwise just start the ripping and encoding with <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Rip Selection</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     Watch the progress of these jobs using the <guimenu>Jobs</guimenu> tab.
     If configured accordingly, KAudioCreator also generates playlist files
     for your selection that can be used by players like &amarok;, XMMS, or
     &musicplayer;.
    </para>
    <figure id="fig.sound.kaudiocreator">
     <title>Ripping Audio CDs with KAudioCreator</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="sound_kaudiocreator.png" width="75%"
                format="PNG"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="sound_kaudiocreator.png" width="75%"
                format="PNG"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </sect3>-->
   <sect3 id="sec.sound.cd.rip.konqui">
    <title>Compressing Audio CDs with Konqueror or Dolphin</title><indexterm>
    <primary>sound</primary>
    <secondary>data compression</secondary>
    <tertiary>Konqueror</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm>
    <primary>sound</primary>
    <secondary>data compression</secondary>
    <tertiary>Dolphin</tertiary></indexterm>
    <para>
     Both Konqueror and Dolphin allow you to rip audio CDs. Before you start
     the actual ripping process with Konqueror or Dolphin, configure the
     handling of audio CDs and the Ogg Vorbis encoder in the
     <guimenu>Personal Settings</guimenu>. From the main menu select
     <guimenu>Configure Desktop</guimenu>, then click <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> <guimenu>Audio CDs</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     The configuration module is divided into three tabs:
     <guimenu>General</guimenu>, <guimenu>Names</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Ogg
     Vorbis Encoder</guimenu>. Normally, a suitable CD device is detected
     automatically. Do not change this default setting unless the
     autodetection fails and you need to set the CD device manually. Error
     correction and encoder priority can also be set here. The <guimenu>Ogg
     Vorbis Encoder</guimenu> tab determines the quality of the encoding. To
     configure online lookup of album, track, and artist information for
     your ripped audio data, select <guimenu>Add Track
     Information</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     To start Konqueror or Dolphin, press <keycombo>
     <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter
     <command>konqueror</command> or <command>dolphin</command>. Insert the
     CD into the CD-ROM drive and enter <literal>audiocd:/</literal> in the
     <guimenu>Location</guimenu> bar. Konqueror or Dolphin then lists the
     tracks of the CD, and some folders.
    </para>
    <para>
     To keep uncompressed audio data on your disk, just select the
     <filename>.wav</filename> files and drag them into another Konqueror or
     Dolphin window to copy them to their final destination. To start the
     Ogg Vorbis encoding, drag the <filename>Ogg Vorbis</filename> folder or
     files from this folder to another Konqueror or Dolphin window. The
     encoding starts as soon as you drop the Ogg Vorbis folder at its
     destination.
    </para>
    <figure
     id="fig.sound.konqui">
     <title>Ripping Audio CDs with Konqueror</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="konqueror_ripping_cd.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="konqueror_ripping_cd.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure><indexterm startref="idx.cds.playing" class="endofrange"/><indexterm startref="idx.cds.ripping" class="endofrange"/>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.sound.oggsect.cmdl">
    <title>Command Line Tools for Encoding and Playback of Audio Data</title><indexterm>
    <primary>sound</primary>
    <secondary>data compression</secondary>
    <tertiary>Ogg Vorbis</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm>
    <primary>Ogg Vorbis</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
     Ogg Vorbis is a free audio compression format that is now supported by
     the majority of audio players and even portable MP3 players. The Web
     page of the project is <ulink url="http://www.xiph.org/vorbis"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     <indexterm>
     <primary>sound</primary>
     <secondary>data compression</secondary>
     <tertiary>oggenc</tertiary>
     </indexterm> <indexterm>
     <primary>oggenc</primary>
     </indexterm> Your system comes with several tools supporting Ogg Vorbis
     (all included in the <systemitem>vorbis-tools</systemitem> package).
     <command>oggenc</command> is a command line tool used for encoding WAV
     files to Ogg. Just run <command>oggenc
     <option>&nbsp;<replaceable>myfile.wav</replaceable></option></command>
     to transform a given <filename>.wav</filename> file into Ogg Vorbis.
     The <option>-h</option> option displays an overview of the other
     parameters. Oggenc supports encoding with a variable bit rate. In this
     way, an even higher degree of compression can be achieved. Instead of
     the bit rate, specify the desired quality with the parameter
     <option>-q</option>. <option>-b</option> determines the average bit
     rate. <option>-m</option> and <option>-M</option> specify the minimum
     and maximum bit rate.
    </para>
    <para>
     ogg123 is a command line Ogg player. Start it with a command like
     <command>ogg123&nbsp;<replaceable>mysong.ogg</replaceable></command>.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
<?dbfo-need height="15em"?>
 <sect1 id="sec.sound.movie">
  <title>Playing Movie Files</title>

  <para>
   You can choose between several movie players shipped with your
   &productname;. Kaffeine, for example, can be run with several back-ends,
   such as Xine and MPlayer.
  </para>

  <para>
   To start Kaffeine, press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
   <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter <command>kaffeine</command>.
  </para>

  <para>
   The formats you can view with Kaffeine depends on the back-end (by
   default, Xine is used). Xine interprets many of the most common
   multimedia formats available. For more information, refer to
   <ulink url="http://www.xine-project.org/"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   In case the format is not supported by the player's engine, &productname;
   offers to search for a suitable codec which you can then install with
   &yast;.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.sound.kaffeine">
   <title>Kaffeine Main Window</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kaffeine_main.png" width="60%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kaffeine_main.png" width="60%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   Kaffeine can also play multimedia streamed over the Internet, and can be
   used as a plug-in for Konqueror. It provides the usual options for
   playing files in full screen mode, navigating through files, and more.
   You can also take a snapshot of the video and save it as an image.
  </para>

<!--taroth 2011-08-04: dragonplayer not on the SLED 11 SP2 media, perhaps osuse only? check for
   next osuse release-->

  <para os="osuse">
   KDE 4 also ships with Dragon Player, included in the
   <systemitem
    class="resource">dragonplayer</systemitem>) package.
   Dragon Player uses the Phonon, which is a multimedia API that connects to
   any of several multimedia frameworks. If Dragon Player is installed,
   start it by pressing <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
   <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and entering <command>dragon</command>.
   For more information on using Dragon Player, refer to the online help.
  </para>
 </sect1>
<!--user comment #11715-->
 <sect1 id="sec.sound.record" os="osuse">
  <title>Recording Audio Data</title>

  <para>
   For recording and editing audio data, <guimenu>Audacity</guimenu>
   provides comprehensive options. The software is also suitable for
   post-processing of all types of audio data. Find detailed information at
   <ulink url=" audacity.sourceforge.net"/>, including a user guide, FAQs
   and troubleshooting.
  </para>

  <para>
   To make audacity work with PulseAudio, open Audacity and set the
   recording and playback devices to <literal>Pulse</literal>. Open
   <guimenu>PulseAudio Volume Control</guimenu> and while playing a test
   sound with Audacity and doing a test recording, make sure Audacity is
   shown on the <guimenu>Recording</guimenu> tab of <guimenu>PulseAudio
   Volume Control</guimenu>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.sound.trouble">
  <title>Troubleshooting</title>

  <para>
   In case you do not get any audio output, check the following:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Sound Card Configured?</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Check if your sound card is properly configured with &yast;. For more
      information, see <xref
       linkend="sec.y2.hw.sound"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Volume Control in Mixer Application?</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Check the volume control of the master channel and the other channels
      available in a mixer application. For more information, see
      <xref linkend="sec.sound.mixers"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Volume Control via Keyboard?</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Many keyboards also have keys for controlling the volume. Check the
      volume control keys of your keyboard.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Volume Control of the Application?</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Most multimedia applications also provide volume controls. Check the
      volume control in the application that you use to play music or movie
      files.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Sound Configuration in <guimenu>Personal Settings</guimenu>?</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Check the defaults for the sound system configuration in the
      <guimenu>Personal Settings</guimenu>. Access them from the main menu
      by selecting <guimenu>Configure Desktop</guimenu>. In the
      <guimenu>Personal Settings</guimenu>, click
      <guimenu>Multimedia</guimenu> to open the <guimenu>Sound and Video
      Configuration</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>External Devices Plugged In Properly?</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      In case you have external devices like loudspeaker or headphones
      connected to your machine, check that they are plugged in properly and
      that they are connected to the right ports.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para os="osuse">
   For more information, also refer to
   <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/SDB:Audio_troubleshooting"> which
   provides an overview of many common problems and possible
   solutions.</ulink>
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
