<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!-- 
 Version information:
 * SLE11 SP1: 0.6.1
 * SLE11 SP2: 0.8.2
 * SLE11 SP3: 0.8.2 (as by 2013-02-28)
-->
<chapter id="cha.gnome.fspot">
 <title>F-Spot: Managing Your Digital Image Collection</title>
 <para>
  F-Spot is a management tool for your collection of digital images tailored
  for the GNOME desktop. It allows you to assign different tags to your
  images in order to categorize them and offers various image editing
  options. For example, you can remove red-eye, crop, and adjust brightness
  and colors. F-Spot supports sixteen common file types, including JPEG,
  BMP, GIF, TIFF, and RAW.
 </para>
 <para>
  You can import photos from your hard drive, your digital camera, or your
  iPod. You can also use F-Spot to view slide shows, create photo CDs,
  generate a Website gallery, or export your photos to your Flickr, 23,
  Picasa Web, or SmugMug account.
 </para>
 <para>
  To access F-Spot, click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Computer</guimenu>
  <guimenu>F-Spot Photo Browser</guimenu> </menuchoice>. The first time you
  run F-Spot, you can tell it where to find the images you want to import
  into your collection. If you already have a collection of images stored on
  your hard drive, enter the path to the relevant directory and optionally
  include subfolders. F-Spot imports these images into its database.
 </para>
 <figure>
  <title>F-Spot Main Window</title>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="fspot_main.png" width="72%" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="fspot_main.png" width="72%" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>
 <para>
  Thumbnails of your images are displayed in the right part of the window,
  and detailed information for a selected image is displayed in a sidebar to
  the left. By default, your photos are displayed in reverse-chronological
  order, so your newest photos are always at the top. You can sort your
  photos in chronological order by clicking <menuchoice>
  <guimenu>View</guimenu> <guimenu>Reverse Order</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
 </para>
 <tip>
  <title>Contents of the Sidebar</title>
  <para>
   At the top of the sidebar, change its contents from
   <guimenu>Tags</guimenu> to <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>, or
   <guimenu>Folders</guimenu>. If the sidebar is not visible at all, press
   <keycap>F9</keycap> or click <menuchoice> <guimenu>View</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Components</guimenu> <guimenu>Sidebar</guimenu> </menuchoice> to
   make the sidebar visible.
  </para>
 </tip>
 <para>
  A menu bar at the top of the window allows you to access the main menus. A
  toolbar below the menu bar offers the following options (move the mouse
  over the icons to see the tooltip, if there is an icon without descriptive
  text):
 </para>
 <table>
  <title>F-Spot Toolbar</title>
  <tgroup cols="2">
   <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="1*"/>
   <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="4.0*"/>
   <thead>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Icon
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Description
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Import
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Import new images from various media such as a folder on your hard
       drive or your digital camera.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Rotate (Left or Right)
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Use this shortcut to change an image's orientation.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Browse
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       The Browse mode allows you to view and search your entire collection
       or tagged subsets of it. You can also use the time line to search
       images by creation date.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Edit Image
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       This mode allows you to select one image and do some basic image
       processing. Details are available in
       <xref linkend="sec.gnome.fspot.edit" xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage"/>.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Fullscreen
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Switch to fullscreen display mode.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Slideshow
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Start a slide show.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
   </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </table>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.fspot.import">
  <title>Importing Photos</title>

  <para>
   You can import photos from your hard drive or from your digital camera
   (see <xref linkend="sec.gnome.fspot.camera"/> for more information).
   F-Spot automatically makes copies of photos imported from your hard
   drive. If you do not want to copy images, uncheck <guimenu>Copy files to
   the Photos folder</guimenu> on the Import dialog box, or press
   <keycap>Shift</keycap> when dragging photos into F-Spot.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Importing Images into F-Spot</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="fspot_import.png" width="74%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="fspot_import.png" width="74%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   By default, F-Spot copies your photos to the <filename>Photos</filename>
   directory in your home directory. You can change the directory F-Spot
   uses by clicking <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <para>
   If all the photos you are importing are from a particular event, or if
   they have some other characteristic in common, you can create a tag for
   them so you can easily find them at a later time. Enter the tags that you
   want to associate on the import of all new photos (separated by commas)
   in the <guimenu>Attach Tags</guimenu> field.
  </para>

  <para>
   To import photos:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Photo</guimenu> <guimenu>Import</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>. The files will be copied to the target directory
     specified via <guimenu>Copy files to</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select an <guimenu>Import Source</guimenu>, then click
     <guimenu>Open</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After the photos are finished loading, click <guimenu>Import</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The photos are added to your catalog.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.fspot.camera">
  <title>Downloading Pictures from Your Camera</title>

  <para>
   You can import new images from your digital camera by connecting it to
   the USB port of your computer. The camera type is detected automatically.
   When you import photos from your camera, F-Spot makes copies of them so
   that you can clear your camera's memory.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Photo</guimenu> <guimenu>Import</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select your camera as the <guimenu>Import Source</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     F-Spot launches a preview window displaying all the images that are
     available for download from your camera. Tagging can be done on import,
     if you enter the appropriate tags in the <guimenu>Attach Tags</guimenu>
     field. If you do not want to import all the images on your camera to
     your database, just deselect the unwanted ones in the preview window.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <textobject role="description"><phrase>F-Spot Import from Camera</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="fspot_import_camera_a.png" width="58%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="fspot_import_camera_a.png" width="58%" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Copy</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     When the photo transfer is complete, click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   The photos are added to your catalog.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.fspot.exif">
  <title>Getting Photo Information</title>

  <para>
   When you select an image, the histogram and some basic statistical
   information is displayed in the lower left part of the window. This
   includes the filename, its version (copy or original image), the date of
   creation, size, and the exposure used in creating this particular photo.
  </para>

  <para>
<!--
  <figure pgwide="0">
   <title>F-Spot Metadata Browser</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="fspot_metadata_a.png" width="49%"
        format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="fspot_metadata_a.png" width="49%"
        format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  -->
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.fspot.tags">
  <title>Managing Tags</title>

  <para>
   Use tags to categorize any of your photos to create manageable subsets of
   your collection. F-Spot comes with default tags, but you can change them
   and add new ones. If, for example, you want to organize your collection
   of portrait shots of your loved ones, do the following:
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Creating Tags in F-Spot</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="fspot_tag_create.png" width="74%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="fspot_tag_create.png" width="74%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the <guimenu>Browse</guimenu> mode of F-Spot.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Activate the <guimenu>Tags</guimenu> view in the sidebar to the left.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the sidebar, right-click the <guimenu>People</guimenu> category,
     then select <guimenu>Create New Tag</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       Create a new tag called <command>Friends</command>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Create a new tag called <filename>Family</filename>.
      </para>
      <para>
       The new tags appear as subcategories below the
       <guimenu>People</guimenu> category.
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Attach tags to images or groups of selected images. You can also use
     the following methods to tag photos:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Drag and drop a photo onto a tag.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Drag and drop a tag onto a photo.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use the options on the <guimenu>Tags</guimenu> menu.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Select a photo, then press <keycap>t</keycap> to display the
       <guimenu>Tags</guimenu> entry bar.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   The first photo you associate with a tag is used for that tag's icon. To
   edit a tag's name, parent tag, or icon, right-click the tag, then select
   <guimenu>Edit Selected Tag</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can change a tag's parent by dragging and dropping it where you want.
   You can also edit the name of a tag by selecting it and pressing
   <keycap>F2</keycap>.
  </para>

  <para>
   After your photos have been tagged, you can browse your collection by
   tags. Using our earlier example, double-clicking <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>People</guimenu> <guimenu>Family</guimenu> </menuchoice> limits
   the displayed collection to the photos tagged <command>Family</command>.
   Searching your collection by tag is also possible through <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Find</guimenu> <guimenu>Find Selected Tag</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>. The result of your search is displayed in the thumbnail
   overview window.
  </para>

  <para>
   Removing tags from single images or groups of images works similarly to
   attaching them. The tag editing functions are also accessible on the
   <guimenu>Tags</guimenu> menu in the top menu bar.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.fspot.search">
  <title>Searching and Finding Photos</title>

  <para>
   As mentioned in <xref linkend="sec.gnome.fspot.tags" />, tags can be used
   as a means to find certain images. Another way to find images is to use
   the <guimenu>Timeline</guimenu> below the toolbar. By dragging the little
   frame along this time line, you can limit the images displayed in the
   thumbnail overview to those taken in a selected time frame. F-Spot starts
   with a default time line, but you can edit the time span by moving the
   sliders to the right and left of the time line.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can also start a search by clicking <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Find</guimenu> <guimenu>Show Find Bar</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
   With the find bar displayed, you can drag tags from the tag view to the
   find bar.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Show Find Bar in F-Spot</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="fspot_searching_a.png" width="66%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="fspot_searching_a.png" width="66%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   To find photos that are tagged with more than one tag, select the first
   tag in the tag view (or drag the tag onto the Find bar), then drag the
   second tag and drop it on top of the first. You can also right-click the
   second tag in the tag view, or click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Find</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Find Selected Tag With</guimenu> </menuchoice>, then select the
   first tag (or group of tags).
  </para>

  <para>
   You can search for photos that do not have a particular tag by
   double-clicking a tag in the Find bar. Photos that do not have that tag
   (or any tag at all) are displayed. You can also right-click a tag in the
   Find bar, then select <guimenu>Exclude</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   To remove a tag from the search, drag it away from the Find bar, or
   right-click the tag and select <guimenu>Remove</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   By default, photos tagged Hidden will not be shown. You must explicitly
   include the Hidden tag in your search to show such photos.
  </para>

  <para>
   There is also a type-to-find entry. Press the forward slash (/) to open
   it. It cannot be used at the same time as the Find bar. You can type
   queries such as <quote>TagA and (TagB or (TagC and TagD))</quote>. At any
   point, if F-Spot recognizes what you have typed as a valid query, it will
   update your search. The <emphasis>not</emphasis> operator is not yet
   supported.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Type-to-find Search</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="fspot_find_a.png" width="93%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="fspot_find_a.png" width="93%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.fspot.export">
  <title>Exporting Image Collections</title>

  <para>
   F-Spot offers a range of export functions for your photo collections:
   <xref
    linkend="sec.gnome.fspot.export.html"/>,
   <xref linkend="sec.gnome.fspot.export.cd"/>,
   <xref
    linkend="sec.gnome.fspot.export.folder"/>, and
   <xref linkend="sec.gnome.fspot.export.online"/>.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnome.fspot.export.html">
   <title>Generating a Website Gallery</title>
<!-- FIXME: check this -->
   <para>
    If you use the PHP software known as Gallery (see
    <ulink url="http://gallery.sourceforge.net"/>), you can post your photos
    to your existing album. Ensure that the Remote module in your Gallery
    installation is enabled (<menuchoice> <guimenu>Site Admin</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Plugins (Get More Plugins)</guimenu> <guimenu>Remote</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>).
   </para>
<!-- FIXME: check this -->
   <para>
    <ulink url="http://pennave.sourceforge.net/">PennAve</ulink> is another
    dynamic photo gallery application. It is designed to be used in
    conjunction with F-Spot to organize and manage your photos.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select the photos you want to export.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Photo</guimenu> <guimenu>Export
      to</guimenu> <guimenu>Web Gallery.</guimenu> </menuchoice>
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <textobject role="description"><phrase>Export to Web Gallery dialog box</phrase>
       </textobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="fspot_export_gallery.png" width="63%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="fspot_export_gallery.png" width="63%" format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select the gallery you want to export your images to, or click
      <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to add a new gallery.
     </para>
     <para>
      F-Spot establishes a connection to the Web location entered for your
      Web gallery.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select the album you want to export the images to, then specify
      whether to resize and rotate the images automatically and export
      titles and comments.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Export</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnome.fspot.export.cd">
   <title>Exporting Photos to CD</title>
   <procedure>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select the photos you want to burn to CD.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Photo</guimenu> <guimenu>Export
      to</guimenu> <guimenu>CD</guimenu> </menuchoice>, then click
      <guimenu>Export</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <para>
      F-Spot copies the files and opens the <guimenu>Write to Disc</guimenu>
      dialog&mdash;in case of trouble it just tries to write an ISO file via
      the <guimenu>Location for Image File</guimenu> dialog. Click
      <guimenu>Burn</guimenu> to confirm the operation.
     </para>
     <informalfigure pgwide="0">
      <mediaobject>
       <textobject role="description"><phrase>Write to Disc dialog box</phrase>
       </textobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="fspot_write_cd.png" width="48%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="fspot_write_cd.png" width="48%" format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Assign a name to your image disk, then select the writing speed.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Write</guimenu> to start the CD writing process.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnome.fspot.export.folder">
   <title>Exporting Photos to a Folder</title>
   <procedure>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select the photos you want to export.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Photo</guimenu> <guimenu>Export
      to</guimenu> <guimenu>Folder</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
     <informalfigure pgwide="0">
      <mediaobject>
       <textobject role="description"><phrase>Folder Export dialog box</phrase>
       </textobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="fspot_export_folder_a.png" width="49%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="fspot_export_folder_a.png" width="49%" format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Choose from the following export methods:
     </para>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Create stand-alone Web gallery:</title>
      <para>
       Export your photos to an interactive Website, ready for you to
       upload.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Save the files only:</title>
      <para>
       Export your photos as files within directories, without putting them
       into a gallery.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Create gallery using <quote>Original</quote>:</title>
      <para>
       Export your photos ready for use with Jakub Steiner's
       <ulink
        url="http://jimmac.musichall.cz/original.php">Original
       Photo Gallery</ulink> software.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Export</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnome.fspot.export.online">
   <title>Posting to a SmugMug, Flickr, 23hq, Zooomr, or Picasa Web Albums Account</title>
   <para>
    If you use <ulink url="http://www.23hq.com/">23hq</ulink>,
    <ulink url="http://www.flickr.com/">Flickr</ulink>,
    <ulink url="http://picasaweb.google.com/">Picasa Web Albums</ulink>,
    <ulink url="http://www.smugmug.com/">SmugMug</ulink>, or
    <ulink url="http://www.zooomr.com/">Zooomr</ulink>, you can post your
    files directly from F-Spot to your account.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select the photos you want to export.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Photo</guimenu> <guimenu>Export
      to</guimenu> </menuchoice> and choose your preferred account.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select or unselect the options you want in the Export dialog box.
     </para>
     <para>
      The options displayed on the Export dialog box depend on the type of
      account you are exporting to. For example, Flickr and 23hq exports
      require authorization in order to upload photos. To do this, click
      <guimenu>Authorize</guimenu> to open a Web browser, then log in to
      your account.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Export</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.fspot.edit">
  <title>Basic Photo Editing</title>

  <para>
   F-Spot offers several basic image editing functions, such as the ability
   to crop, remove red-eye, and adjust color and brightness.
  </para>

  <para>
   When you edit a photo, a new copy (called a version) is created, so your
   original photo is never altered. After your first edit to a photo,
   subsequent edits modify the same version. If you want to create multiple
   versions of a photo (for example, with different cropping or coloring),
   click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Photo</guimenu> <guimenu>Create New
   Version</guimenu> </menuchoice>. To access a photo's original version,
   click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Photo</guimenu> <guimenu>Version</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Original</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Select the photo you want to edit.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     To enter edit mode, click the <guimenu>Edit Image</guimenu> icon in the
     toolbar, double-click the image, or press Enter.
    </para>
    <informalfigure pgwide="0">
     <mediaobject>
      <textobject role="description"><phrase>F-Sport Photo Edit Mode</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="fspot_edit_a.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="fspot_edit_a.png" width="70%" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Choose from the following edit functions, using the buttons of the
     sidebar to the left or the entries from the <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
     menu:
    </para>
    <informaltable frame="topbot" rowsep="0" pgwide="0">
     <tgroup cols="2">
      <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="35*"/>
      <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="65*"/>
      <thead>
       <row>
        <entry colname="1">
         <para>
          Function
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry colname="2">
         <para>
          Description
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
       <row>
        <entry colname="1">
         <para>
<!-- <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
           <imagedata fileref="fspot_crop.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
           <imagedata fileref="fspot_crop.png" format="png"/>
          </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> -->
          Crop
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry colname="2">
         <para>
          Cropping an image is a great way to improve the quality of a
          photograph by improving how it is framed. You crop a photo by
          selecting the part of the photo you want to keep. If you want your
          photo to be the exact dimensions necessary for a certain print
          size, you can constrain the kind of selection F-Spot will allow
          you to draw by choosing the appropriate size from the
          <guimenu>Constraint</guimenu> drop-down list. See the description
          of the Remove Red-Eye function for details on making a selection
          on your photo.
         </para>
         <para>
          After you make your crop selection, click the
          <guimenu>Crop</guimenu> icon beneath the photo to finalize the
          crop. If you are working with the original photo, cropping creates
          a new version of your photo.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry colname="1">
         <para>
<!-- <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
           <imagedata fileref="fspot_redeye.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
           <imagedata fileref="fspot_redeye.png" format="png"/>
          </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> -->
          Red-Eye Reduction
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry colname="2">
         <para>
          To remove red-eye from a photo, select a zone containing the eyes.
          You might want to zoom in on the image to accurately select the
          eyes in the photo. You should be able to correct both eyes on the
          same person at once, or even the eyes from multiple people at
          once. If this does not work, or if the selected zone contains some
          vivid red parts (such as lips), you will probably have to correct
          one red eye at a time.
         </para>
         <para>
          To make your selection, click one corner of the rectangle that
          will be your selection, then drag your mouse to the diagonal
          corner and release it. You can resize your selection by dragging
          its edges, and you can move it by clicking in the middle of it and
          dragging it to where you want it.
         </para>
         <para>
          After you have selected a zone, remove the red by clicking the
          <guimenu>Red-eye</guimenu> icon beneath the photo.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry colname="1">
         <para>
<!-- <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
           <imagedata fileref="fspot_blackandwhite.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
           <imagedata fileref="fspot_blackandwhite.png" format="png"/>
          </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> -->
          Desaturate
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry colname="2">
         <para>
          Converts the photo to black and white.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry colname="1">
         <para>
<!-- <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
           <imagedata fileref="fspot_sepia.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
           <imagedata fileref="fspot_sepia.png" format="png"/>
          </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> -->
          Sepia Tone
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry colname="2">
         <para>
          Converts the photo to sepia tones.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry colname="1">
         <para>
<!-- <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
           <imagedata fileref="fspot_horizon.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
           <imagedata fileref="fspot_horizon.png" format="png"/>
          </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> -->
          Straighten
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry colname="2">
         <para>
          The Straighten effect helps you level a photo and is useful when
          editing landscapes taken without a tripod (when the imaginary line
          of horizon is not at 0°). This tool rotates a photo by a
          specified angle and automagically crops the resulted image so that
          you always see a perfect rectangle.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry colname="1">
         <para>
<!-- <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
           <imagedata fileref="fspot_softfocus.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
           <imagedata fileref="fspot_softfocus.png" format="png"/>
          </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> -->
          Soft Focus
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry colname="2">
         <para>
          Sharpening one region of a picture while blurring all the rest is
          a way to emphasize a particular area and grab attention. The soft
          focus effect is a way to emulate a lens that allows shooting with
          a short distance in front of and beyond the subject that appears
          to be in focus.
         </para>
         <para>
          Choose the central point of the area you want to be in focus, then
          click the <guimenu>Soft Focus</guimenu> icon beneath the photo.
          Adjust the amount of blurring, then click
          <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry colname="1">
         <para>
<!-- <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
           <imagedata fileref="fspot_autocolor.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
           <imagedata fileref="fspot_autocolor.png" format="png"/>
          </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> -->
          Auto Color
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry colname="2">
         <para>
          This effect automatically adjusts color levels to make a
          color-balanced picture. It works best for pictures taken with
          automatic white balance. Click the <guimenu>Automatically adjust
          the colors</guimenu> icon to access this feature.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry colname="1">
         <para>
<!-- <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
           <imagedata fileref="fspot_adjustcolors.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
           <imagedata fileref="fspot_adjustcolors.png" format="png"/>
          </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> -->
          Adjust Colors
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry colname="2">
         <para>
          To adjust the brightness, contrast, and colors of a photo, click
          the <guimenu>Adjust the photo colors</guimenu> icon to open the
          adjustment dialog box. Change the settings you want, then click
          <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry colname="1">
         <para>
          Adjust Time
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry colname="2">
         <para>
          Access this function by clicking <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> <guimenu>Adjust Time</guimenu>
          </menuchoice>. Adjust date and time, then click
          <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry colname="1">
         <para>
          Sharpen
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry colname="2">
         <para>
          Access this function by clicking <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> <guimenu>Sharpen</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
          Adjust the values for <guimenu>Amount</guimenu>,
          <guimenu>Radius</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Threshold</guimenu> to
          your needs, then click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry colname="1">
         <para>
          Comment
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry colname="2">
         <para>
          You can add a description or a comment to a photo by clicking the
          text entry box below the photo and entering text.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     (Optional) If you want to edit another photo, use the arrow keys on the
     toolbar at the right to switch to a new photo.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     To exit the edit mode, click <guimenu>Browse</guimenu> on the toolbar.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <tip>
   <para>
    Professional image editing can also be done with GIMP. For more
    information, see
    <xref
     linkend="cha.gimp" xrefstyle="ChapTitleOnPage"/>.
   </para>
  </tip>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.fspot.share">
  <title>Sharing Photos</title>

  <para>
   You can use either of the following methods to share your photos using
   F-Spot. Both methods share only the photos you have selected when you run
   them.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <xref linkend="sec.gnome.fspot.share.email" xrefstyle="RefWPage"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <xref linkend="sec.gnome.fspot.share.print" xrefstyle="RefWPage"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnome.fspot.share.email">
   <title>E-mailing Photos</title>
   <para>
    You can e-mail your photos directly from F-Spot, sending them as-is
    (original size) or resizing them.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select the photos you want to e-mail.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Photo</guimenu> <guimenu>Send by
      Mail</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
     <informalfigure pgwide="0">
      <mediaobject>
       <textobject role="description"><phrase>F-Spot Create Mail dialog box</phrase>
       </textobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="fspot_email_a.png" width="52%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="fspot_email_a.png" width="52%" format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select a size for your photos.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Create Mail</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <para>
      Your default e-mail program opens, with your photos attached to a new
      mail message.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnome.fspot.share.print">
   <title>Printing Photos</title>
   <procedure>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select the photos you want to print.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Photo</guimenu> <guimenu>Print</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>.
     </para>
     <informalfigure pgwide="0">
      <mediaobject>
       <textobject role="description"><phrase>F-Spot Print Photos dialog box</phrase>
       </textobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="fspot_print_a.png" width="66%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="fspot_print_a.png" width="66%" format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select the print options you want, such as the printer you want to use
      or the page orientation, then click <guimenu>Print</guimenu> to print
      your photos.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.fspot.prefs">
  <title>The Preferences Dialog</title>

  <para>
   Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Photo</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu> </menuchoice> to open the <guimenu>F-Spot
   Preferences</guimenu> dialog.
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description"><phrase>F-Spot Preferences</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="fspot_prefs.png" width="66%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="fspot_prefs.png" width="66%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para>
   In the preferences dialog you can configure where to store your imported
   photos, where to store the tags, color profiles and the F-Spot
   appearance.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.fspot.moreinfo">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   See F-Spot's homepage at <ulink url="http://f-spot.org/"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
