<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.linwin">
 <title>Getting to Know Linux Software</title><indexterm>
 <primary>applications</primary></indexterm>
 <para>
  Linux* comes with a wealth of applications, often offering more than one
  solution to specific needs. The difficulty is finding the application that
  suits your needs best. The next few sections introduce some of the most
  powerful Linux counterparts of common Windows software. Each section is
  dedicated to one particular field of application and presents an overview
  of the Windows applications and Linux equivalents for several tasks. Below
  each table, find further information about the Linux applications with
  links to more information. This list is by no means complete, because
  software development is an evolutionary process and new applications are
  constantly being created.
 </para>
 <tip>
  <title>Applications not Installed by Default</title>
  <para>
   Not all applications mentioned below are installed on your system by
   default and some may not be shipped with your product. If the application
   you want to use is missing, ask your system administrator. If the
   application is provided by your product, you can install it with &yast;.
   Use the search function of the &yast; software management tool to find
   the name of the wanted package.
  </para>
 </tip>
<?dbfo-need height="15em"?>
 <sect1 id="sec.linwin.office">
  <title>Office Applications</title>

  <para>
   This section features the most popular and powerful Linux office and
   business software solutions. These include office suites, databases,
   accounting software, and project management software.
  </para>

  <table>
   <title>Office Software for Windows and Linux</title>
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Task
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Windows Application
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Linux Application
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Office Suite
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Microsoft* Office
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        &ooo;, OpenOffice, KOffice
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Word Processor
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Microsoft Word, WordPerfect
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        &ooo;, OpenOffice Writer, KWord
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Spreadsheet
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Microsoft Excel
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        &ooo;, OpenOffice Calc, Gnumeric, KSpread
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Presentation
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Microsoft PowerPoint
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        &ooo;, OpenOffice Impress, KPresenter
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Data Plotting
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Microsoft Excel
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        &ooo;, Calc, Kst, Gnuplot, Grace (Xmgr), LabPlot
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Local Database
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Microsoft Access
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        &ooo;, Base, Rekall, kexi, Mergeant, PostgreSQL
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Financial Accounting
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Microsoft Money, Quicken
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        GnuCash, KMyMoney
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Project Management
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Microsoft Project
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Planner, Taskjuggler
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Mind Mapping
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        MindManager, Free Mind
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        VYM (View Your Mind), Free Mind<phrase os="osuse">,
        KDissert</phrase>
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.office.suites">
   <title>Office Suites</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry id="vle.linwin.off.ooo">
     <term>&ooo;</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       &ooo; is a stable open source equivalent to Microsoft Office
       including a word processor (Writer), a spreadsheet (Calc), a database
       manager (Base), a presentation manager (Impress), a drawing program
       (Draw), and a formula editor for generating mathematical equations
       and formulas (Math). The user interface is similar to the Microsoft
       Office suite. For more details, see
       <ulink url="http://www.libreoffice.org/"/> or read
       <xref linkend="cha.oo.oview"
       />.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>OpenOffice (formerly known as StarOffice)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       OpenOffice, an office suite software developed by Sun, but now owned
       by <trademark 
                class="registered">Oracle</trademark>,
       is similar to &ooo;. It is available on multiple platforms like
       Linux, Windows and Solaris. It contains the same modules as the &ooo;
       suite. It also includes certain advanced features not available with
       the open source version. For more details, see
       <ulink
                url="http://www.openoffice.org"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry os="osuse">
     <term>KOffice/Caligra</term>
     <listitem>
      <para> 
       Caligra (formerly known as KOffice) is the fully integrated office
       suite designed for the KDE desktop. It comes with various modules, like
       word processing (Words), spreadsheets (Sheets), presentations (Stage),
       several image processing applications (Karbon14, Krita), a database
       front-end (Kexi) and many other applications. For more details, see
       <ulink url="http://www.caligra-suite.org"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.word.process">
   <title>Word Processing</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Writer</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Writer is the stable word-processing and desktop publishing module of
       the &ooo; and OpenOffice. For more details, see
       <ulink url="http://www.libreoffice.org/features/writer/"/> and
       <ulink url="http://www.openoffice.org/product/writer.html"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry os="osuse">
     <term>Words (formerly known as KWord)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Words is the stable frame-based word-processing module of the KOffice
       Suite. Words' can handle large amounts of texts and its easy-to-use
       features help you to create professional looking documents. For more
       details, see <ulink url="http://www.calligra-suite.org/words/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.spreadsheets">
   <title>Spreadsheets</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry id="calc.spread">
     <term>Calc</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Calc is the spreadsheet and data plotting module of the &ooo; and
       OpenOffice suites. It is easy to learn and offers a wide range of
       features. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://www.libreoffice.org/features/calc/"/> and
       <ulink
        url="http://www.openoffice.org/product/calc.html"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry os="osuse">
     <term>Sheets (formerly known as KCells)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Sheets is the spreadsheet module of the Caligra Suite. It is a
       scriptable spreadsheet program which provides both table-oriented
       sheets and support for complex mathematical formulas and statistics.
       For more details see <ulink url="http://www.calligra-suite.org/sheets/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Gnumeric</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Gnumeric is a spreadsheet solution for the GNOME desktop environment
       that can also read files created with other spreadsheets. Its
       built-in functions and tools are extremely accurate. For more
       details, see <ulink url="http://www.gnumeric.org"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.pres">
   <title>Presentations</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Impress</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Impress is the presentation module of the &ooo; and OpenOffice
       suites. Impress lets you create multimedia presentations with 2D and
       3D clip art, special effects, animation, and drawing tools. Impress
       can create PDF files from your presentations, and it is able to view,
       edit and save files in several file formats, including the *.ppt
       format, which is used by Microsoft PowerPoint. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://www.libreoffice.org/features/impress/"/>.
       and
       <ulink
        url="http://www.openoffice.org/product/impress.html"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry os="osuse">
     <term>Stage (formerly known as KPresenter)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>Stage is the presentation module of the Caligra Suite. It
       can prepare complete sets of slides containing text and graphics in a
       variety of formats, and embed all sorts of objects. It is also able
       to load presentations from Microsoft PowerPoint, MagicPoint and &ooo;
       Impress documents. For more details see
       <ulink url="http://www.calligra-suite.org/stage/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.dataplotting">
   <title>Data Plotting</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Calc</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       See <xref linkend="calc.spread"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Gnuplot</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Gnuplot is a very powerful and portable command line controlled data
       plotting software. It is also available for MacOS and Windows
       platforms. Plots created by Gnuplot can be exported to various
       formats, such as PostScript, PDF, and SVG, allowing you to process
       these plots easily. For more details see
       <ulink url="http://www.gnuplot.info/index.html"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Grace</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Grace is a 2D plotting tool for many platforms including Linux. It
       can create and edit plots with a graphical user interface. Grace
       supports an unlimited number of graphs per plot. For more details,
       see <ulink url="http://plasma-gate.weizmann.ac.il/Grace/"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Kst</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Kst is the data plotting module for the KOffice suite. It allows for
       real-time data viewing and plotting with basic data analysis. For
       more details, see <ulink
        url="http://kst.kde.org/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>LabPlot</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       LabPlot is a plotting tool for creating and managing 2D or 3D data
       plots and was written for KDE. Graphs can be produced both from data
       and functions and one plot may include multiple graphs. It also
       offers various data analysis methods. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://labplot.sourceforge.net/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.local.databases">
   <title>Local Databases</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Base</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Base is the database module of the &ooo; and OpenOffice suites. It
       can be used to create <quote>self-contained</quote> database
       documents with all relevant data, table definitions, reports, and
       forms. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://www.libreoffice.org/features/base/"/> and
       <ulink
        url="http://www.openoffice.org/product/base.html"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Gnome-DB</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       GNOME-DB provides a unified data access architecture to GNOME. It is
       useful for any application that accesses persistent data. It consists
       of a data abstraction layer (Libgda), a database widget library and a
       database front-end (Mergeant). For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://www.gnome-db.org/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry os="osuse">
     <term>Kexi</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Kexi is an integrated data management application. It can be used for
       creating databases, inserting data, performing queries, and
       processing data. Forms can be created to provide a custom interface
       to your data. For more details, see
       <ulink url="http://www.calligra-suite.org/kexi/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>PostgreSQL</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       PostgreSQL is an object-relational database management system that
       supports an extended subset of the SQL standard, including
       transactions, foreign keys, subqueries, triggers, and user-defined
       types and functions. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://www.postgresql.org/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
<!--<varlistentry>
     <term>Rekall</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Rekall is a database management tool that supports many database
       applications like MySQL,PostgreSQL and Xbase. Rekall can be used for
       many tasks such as reports, forms, queries and others. For more
       details, see
       <ulink url="http://www.thekompany.com/products/rekall/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>-->
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.fin.account">
   <title>Financial Accounting</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>KmyMoney</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       KmyMoney is a personal financial manager for the KDE desktop. It
       enables users of open source operating systems to keep track of their
       personal finances and offers a broad array of financial features and
       tools. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://kmymoney2.sourceforge.net"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>GnuCash</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       GnuCash is a software tool to control personal and business finances.
       It enables users to keep track of income and expenses and it is also
       used to manage bank accounts, and stock portfolios. For more details,
       see <ulink url="http://www.gnucash.org/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.project.manager">
   <title>Project Management</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Planner</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Planner is a project management tool for the GNOME desktop aiming to
       provide functionality similar to the project management tools used
       under Windows. Amongst its features are Gantt charting and different
       display types for tasks and resources. For more details see
       <ulink url="http://live.gnome.org/Planner"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Taskjuggler</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Taskjuggler is a project management tool that enables the user to
       control projects using Gantt charting features. It can also be used
       to generate reports in different formats (XML, HTML or CSV).
       Taskjuggler can be controlled from the command line but also offers a
       graphical front-end. For more details see
       <ulink url="http://www.taskjuggler.org"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <!--<varlistentry os="osuse">
       <term>Plan</term>
       <listitem>
         <para>Plan is the planning module of the Caligra Suite.
         Add more text.
         </para>
       </listitem>
     </varlistentry>-->
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.mind.map">
   <title>Mind Mapping</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>FreeMind</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       FreeMind is a mind-mapping like tool for structuring ideas, thoughts
       and concepts. It can copy nodes (or the style of nodes) and paste
       texts from sources such as HTML, RTF, and mails. The mind maps can be
       exported into various formats, such as HTML and XML. For more
       details, see
       <ulink url="http://freemind.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/Main_Page"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>VYM</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       VYM (View Your Mind) is a mind-mapping like tool for structuring
       ideas, thoughts and concepts. VYM mind maps are created in XML which
       can be exported to HTML. For more details see
       <ulink url="http://insilmaril.de/vym"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Semantik</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Semantik (previously KDissert) is a mindmapping-like tool for
       structuring idea. Users can generate various outputs from the mind
       map, such as PDF files, text documents and HTML files. For more
       details see <ulink url="http://freehackers.org/~tnagy/kdissert/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.linwin.net">
  <title>Network</title><indexterm>

  <primary>applications</primary>

  <secondary>network</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   The following section features various Linux applications for networking
   purposes. Get to know the most popular Linux browsers and e-mail and chat
   clients.
  </para>

  <table>
<?dbsuse-latex tablehead="p{.20\linewidth}p{.34\linewidth}p{.34\linewidth}" ?>
   <title>Network Software for Windows and Linux</title>
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Task
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Windows Application
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Linux Application
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Web Browser
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Internet Explorer, Firefox*, Opera
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Konqueror, Firefox, Opera, Chromium
<!--Epiphany-->
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        E-Mail Client/Personal Information Management
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Microsoft Outlook*, Lotus Notes, Mozilla Thunderbird*
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Evolution, Kontact, Mozilla Thunderbird
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Instant Messaging/IRC Clients
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        MSN, AIM*, Yahoo!* Messenger, XChat, Gaim
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Gaim, Empathy, Kopete, Konversation, XChat
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Conferencing (Video and Audio)
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        NetMeeting, LifeMeeting
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Ekiga
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Voice over IP
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        X-Lite
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Ekiga, Skype
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        FTP Clients
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        leechftp, wsftp
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        gftp, lukemftp
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.web.brows">
   <title>Browsers</title>
   <variablelist>
    <!-- taroth 2011-10-20: fix bnc#727354-->
    <!--<varlistentry>
     <term>Epiphany</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Epiphany is a lean, but powerful Web browser for the GNOME desktop.
       Many of its features and extensions are similar to Firefox. For more
       details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://projects.gnome.org/epiphany/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>-->
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Firefox</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Firefox is a Web browser that runs on various platforms, including
       Linux, MacOS, and Windows. Its main features include customizable
       searches, pop-up blocking, RSS news feeds, password management,
       tabbed browsing, and some advanced security and privacy options. For
       more details, see
       <ulink url="http://www.mozilla.org/products/firefox/"/> or read
       <xref
        linkend="cha.firefox"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Konqueror</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Konqueror is a multiple application created for the KDE desktop. It
       acts as Web browser, file manager and document viewer. It supports
       most common Web standards, such as CSS(2), Java applets, JavaScript
       and Netscape plug-ins, DOM, and SSL. For more details, see
       <ulink url="http://www.konqueror.org/"/> or read
       <xref linkend="cha.konqueror"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Opera</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Opera is a powerful Web browser with an optional e-mail client and a
       chat module. Opera offers pop-up blocking, RSS feeds, built-in and
       customizable searches, a password manager, and tabbed browsing. For
       more details see <ulink url="http://www.opera.com/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Chromium</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Chromium is an open source Web browser from the <ulink
       url="http://chromium.org">Google Chrom</ulink> project. It's main
       features include speed and a lightweight look, tabbed browsing, lots of
       extensions, and more. For more details, see its Web site.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.mail.client">
   <title>E-Mail Client / Personal Information Management</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Evolution</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Evolution is a personal information management application for the
       GNOME desktop. It includes e-mail, calendar, and address book
       functionalities. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://projects.gnome.org/evolution/"/> or read
       <xref linkend="cha.gnome.evolution"
       />.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Kontact</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Kontact is the personal information management suite for the KDE
       desktop. It includes e-mail, calendar, address book and Palm sync
       functionalities. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://www.kontact.org/"/> or read
       <xref linkend="cha.kontact"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Mozilla Thunderbird</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Mozilla Thunderbird is the e-mail client of the Mozilla suite. It is
       also available for Microsoft Windows and MacOS. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://www.mozilla.com/en-US/thunderbird/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.inst.mess">
   <title>Instant Messaging / IRC Clients</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Empathy</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Empathy is an instant messenger tool for the GNOME desktop. It
       consists of a rich set of reusable instant messaging widgets, and a
       GNOME client. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://live.gnome.org/Empathy"/>
       <remark>taroth 081217: excluding empathy chapter and link to it because software doesn't work
       (crashes, connection problems), e.g. bnc#436314</remark>
       <remark>toms 2011-08-24: Still the same for SLED11 SP2. :-( </remark>
<!-- or read <xref linkend="cha.gnome.empathy"/>-->
       .
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Konversation</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Konversation is the IRC client of the KDE desktop with many
       functionalities. For more details, see
       <ulink url="http://konversation.kde.org"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Kopete</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Kopete is an easy-to-use instant messenger tool supporting many
       protocols. For more details, see
       <ulink url="http://kopete.kde.org/"/> or read
       <xref linkend="cha.kopete"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Pidgin</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Pidgin (previously Gaim) is a multi-platform instant messaging client
       supporting many commonly used instant messaging protocols, allowing
       the user to log into various different services from a single
       application. For more details, see <ulink url="http://pidgin.im/"/>
       or read <xref linkend="cha.gnome.pidgin"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.conferencing">
   <title>VoIP, Video and Audio Conferencing</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Ekiga</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Ekiga (previously GNOMEMeeting) is a free and open source video
       conferencing and VoIP application. Ekiga supports both the SIP and
       H.323 protocols, and is fully interoperable with Microsoft NetMeeting
       and LifeMeeting. For more details see
       <ulink url="http://www.ekiga.org/"
       /> or read
       <xref linkend="cha.ekiga"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Skype</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Skype is an application for several platforms (Linux, Windows, Mac Os
       X) that can be used for phone calls over the Internet with a good
       sound quality and with end-to-end encryption. When using Skype,
       configuring the firewall or router is not necessary. For more
       details, see <ulink url="http://www.skype.com/"/>.
<!--Information on Skype and openSUSE is avaiable from
       <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/Skype_HOWTO"/>.-->
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.ftp">
   <title>FTP Clients</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>gftp</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       gftp is an FTP client using the GTK toolkit. Its features include
       simultaneous downloads, resume of interrupted file transfers, file
       transfer queues, download of entire directories, FTP proxy support,
       remote directory caching, passive and nonpassive file transfers, and
       drag and drop support. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://gftp.seul.org/"/> or read
       <xref linkend="cha.gnome.gftp"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
<!-- toms 2011-08-24: No KBear anymore for SLE11 SP2 -->
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.linwin.mm">
  <title>Multimedia</title>

  <para>
   The following section introduces the most popular multimedia applications
   for Linux. Get to know media players, sound editing solutions, and video
   editing tools.
  </para>

  <table>
<?dbsuse-latex tablehead="p{.20\linewidth}p{.34\linewidth}p{.34\linewidth}" ?>
   <title>Multimedia Software for Windows and Linux</title>
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Task
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Windows Application
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Linux Application
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Audio CD Player
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        CD Player, Winamp, Windows Media Player
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        KsCD, &amarok;, Grip, &musicplayer;
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        CD Burner
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Nero, Roxio Easy CD Creator
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        K3b
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        CD Ripper
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        WMPlayer
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        KAudioCreator, Sound Juicer
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Audio Player
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Winamp, Windows Media Player, iTunes
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        &amarok;, XMMS, Rhythmbox
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Video Player
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Winamp, Windows Media Player
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Kaffeine, MPlayer, Xine, XMMS, Totem, RealPlayer
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Audio Editor
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        SoundForge, Cooledit, Audacity
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Audacity
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Sound Mixer
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        sndvol32
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        alsamixer, Kmix
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Music Notation
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Finale, SmartScore, Sibelius
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        LilyPond, MusE, Noteedit, Rosegarden
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Video Creator and Editor
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Windows Movie Maker, Adobe Premiere, Media Studio Pro
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Kino
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        TV Viewer
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        AVerTV, PowerVCR 3.0, CinePlayer DVR
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        xawtv, motv (analog), tvtime, kdetv, zapping, Kaffeine
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.audioplay">
   <title>Media Players</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>&amarok;</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       &amarok; is a powerful media player for the KDE desktop. It handles
       various audio formats and plays streaming audio broadcasts of radio
       stations on the Internet. For more details, see
       <ulink url="http://amarok.kde.org/"/> or read
       <xref linkend="sec.sound.players.amarok"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry id="Banshee">
     <term>&musicplayer;</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       &musicplayer; is a media player that can encode and decode various
       media formats. &musicplayer; can play, import, and burn audio CDs.
       For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://banshee-project.org/"/> or read
       <xref linkend="cha.banshee"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry id="grip">
     <term>Grip</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Grip is a CD-player and ripper for the GNOME desktop. It has the
       ripping capabilities of cdparanoia built in, but can also use
       external rippers. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://www.nostatic.org/grip/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Kaffeine</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Kaffeine is a multimedia application that supports many audio and
       video formats. For more details, see
       <ulink url="http://kaffeine.kde.org/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>KsCD</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       KsCD is a CD player application for the KDE desktop. Its user
       interface is very similar to that of a normal hardware CD player. 
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>MPlayer</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       MPlayer supports many media formats and can also save all streamed
       content to a file. For more details, see
       <ulink url="http://www.mplayerhq.hu/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>RealPlayer</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       RealPlayer is a proprietary cross-platform media player by
       RealNetworks that plays a number of multimedia formats. For more
       details, see <ulink url="http://www.real.com/player/"
       />.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Totem</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Totem is the default multimedia player for the GNOME computer desktop
       environment. Totem is fully integrated with GNOME Nautilus. For more
       details, see <ulink
        url="http://projects.gnome.org/totem/"/>
       or read <xref linkend="cha.gnome.totem"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Xine</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Xine is a multimedia player for Linux that supports different
       front-end player applications. Another important feature is the
       ability to manually correct the synchronization of audio and video
       streams. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://www.xine-project.org/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>XMMS</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The X Multimedia System 2 (XMMS2) is an audio player for Linux
       systems that supports audio and video formats. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://wiki.xmms2.xmms.se/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.cd.burn">
   <title>CD Burners</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term> &musicplayer;</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       See above for <xref linkend="Banshee"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Brasero</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Brasero is a disc-burning program for the GNOME Desktop allowing
       users to burn audio and data CD/DVDs on the fly. For more details,
       see <ulink
        url="http://projects.gnome.org/brasero/"/> or read
       <xref linkend="cha.gnome.burn"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>K3b</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       K3b is a CD and DID authoring application for the KDE desktop
       environment for Unix-like computer operating systems. It provides a
       graphical user interface to perform most CD/DVD burning tasks and
       contains a built-in DID ripper. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://www.k3b.org/"/> or read
       <xref linkend="cha.k3b"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.cd.rip">
   <title>CD Rippers</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Grip</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       See above for <xref linkend="grip"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>KAudioCreator</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       KAudioCreator is a front-end tool for ripping audio CDs and encoding
       WAVE files. For more details, see
       <ulink url="http://www.icefox.net/programs/?program=KAudioCreator"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Sound Juicer</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Sound Juicer is a front-end application to the cdparanoia CD ripping
       library. It allows the user to extract audio output from CDs and
       convert it into audio files that a personal computer or digital audio
       player can understand and play. It supports ripping to many audio
       codecs. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://www.burtonini.com/blog/computers/sound-juicer"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.audio.edit">
   <title>Audio Editors</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Audacity</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Audacity is a digital audio editor application. Its cross-platform
       allows users to mix tracks, apply effects to them, and export the
       results to WAV or Ogg Vorbis. For more details, see
       <ulink url="http://audacity.sourceforge.net/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.sound.mix">
   <title>Sound Mixers</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>ALSA mixer</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       ALSA mixer is the mixer program for the Advanced Linux Sound
       Architecture (ALSA). It is used to configure sound settings and to
       adjust the volume. It has an ncurses user interface and does not
       require the X Window System. It supports multiple sound cards with
       multiple devices. For more details, see
       <ulink
        url="http://www.alsa-project.org/main/index.php/Main_Page"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.music.not">
   <title>Music Notation</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>LilyPond</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       LilyPond is a music sheet editor. Because the input format is text-
       based, the user can work with any text editor to create note sheets.
       Users do not need to tackle any formatting or notation issues, like
       spacing, line-breaking, or polyphonic collisions. For more details,
       see <ulink url="http://lilypond.org/web/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>MusE</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       MusE is at the moment a MIDI/Audio sequencer with recording and
       editing capabilities. The project works on a complete multitrack
       virtual studio for Linux. For more details, see
       <ulink url="http://www.muse-sequencer.org/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Noteedit</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Noteedit is a powerful score editor for Linux. It creates sheets of
       notes and exports and imports scores to and from many formats. It
       features a graphical user interface. For more details,
       see<ulink url=" http://noteedit.berlios.de/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term> Rosegarden</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Rosegarden is a free music composition and editing environment. It
       features an audio and MIDI sequencer and a score editor. For more
       details, see <ulink
        url="http://rosegardenmusic.com/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.video.creat">
   <title>Video Creators and Editors</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Kino</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Kino is an easy and reliable digital video editor with export to many
       formats. The program supports many basic video editing and assembling
       tasks. It captures video to disk in Raw DIV, AVI, and Quicktime
       formats. For more details, see
       <ulink url="http://www.kinodv.org"
       />.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.linwin.tv.view">
   <title>TV Viewers and Editors</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry id="vle.linwin.xawtv">
     <term>xawtv</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       xawtv is a TV viewer and recorder suite. It supports both analog and
       digital audio and video broadcasts using either a TV tuner or a
       Satellite receiver card DB-S. For more details, see
       <ulink url="http://linux.bytesex.org/xawtv/"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>kdetv</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       kdetv is a TV viewer and recorder application for the KDE desktop
       supporting TV using a tuner card. For more details, see
       <ulink url="http://www.kdetv.org"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.linwin.graph">
  <title>Graphics</title><indexterm>

  <primary>applications</primary>

  <secondary>graphics</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   The following section presents some of the Linux software solutions for
   graphics work. These include simple drawing applications as well as
   fully-fledged image editing tools and powerful rendering and animation
   programs.
  </para>

  <table>
   <title>Graphics Software for Windows and Linux</title>
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Task
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Windows Application
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Linux Application
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Simple Graphic Editing
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Microsoft Paint
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        KolourPaint
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Professional Graphic Editing
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Adobe Photoshop, Paint Shop Pro, Corel PhotoPaint, GIMP
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        GIMP, Krita
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Creating Vector Graphics
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Adobe Illustrator, CorelDraw, Freehand
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        &ooo; Draw, Inkscape, Dia
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        SVG Editing
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        WebDraw, Freehand, Adobe Illustrator
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Inkscape, Dia, Kivio
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Creating 3D Graphics
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        3D Studio MAX, Maya, POV-Ray, Blender
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        POV-Ray, Blender, KPovmodeler
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Managing Digital Photographs
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Software provided by the camera manufacturer
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        DigiKam, f-spot
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Scanning
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Vuescan
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Vuescan, GIMP
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Image Viewing
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        ACDSee
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        gwenview, gThumb, Eye of Gnome, f-spot
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Blender<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>graphics</secondary>
     <tertiary>Blender</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Blender is a powerful rendering and animation tool available on many
      platforms, including Windows, MacOS, and Linux. For more details see
      <ulink url="http://www.blender.org/"
      />.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Dia<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>graphics</secondary>
     <tertiary>Dia</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Dia is the Linux equivalent of Visio. It supports many types of
      special diagrams, such as network or UML charts. Export formats
      include SVG, PNG, and EPS. To support your own custom diagram types,
      provide the new shapes in a special XML format. For more details see
      <ulink
       url="http://projects.gnome.org/dia/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>digiKam<indexterm>
     <primary>digiKam</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>graphics</secondary>
     <tertiary>digiKam</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      digiKam is a smart digital photo management tool for the KDE desktop.
      Create albums, add tags to spare you from copying images around
      different subdirectories, and eventually export your images to your
      own Web site. For more details see
      <ulink url="http://www.digikam.org/"/> or read
      <xref linkend="cha.digicam"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Eye of Gnome (eog)<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>graphics</secondary>
     <tertiary>Eye of Gnome</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Eye of Gnome is an image viewer application for the GNOME desktop. For
      more details, see <ulink url="http://projects.gnome.org/eog/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>f-spot<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>graphics</secondary>
     <tertiary>f-spot</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      f-spot is a flexible digital photograph management tool for the GNOME
      desktop. It lets you create and manage albums and supports various
      export options like HTML pages or the burning of image archives to CD.
      You can also use it as an image viewer on the command line. For more
      details, see <ulink url="http://f-spot.org/Main_Page"/> or read
      <xref
       linkend="cha.gnome.fspot"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>gThumb<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>graphics</secondary>
     <tertiary>gThumb</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      gThumb is an image viewer, browser and organizer for the GNOME
      desktop. It supports the import of your digital images via gphoto2,
      allows you to carry out basic transformation and modifications, and
      lets you tag your images to create albums matching certain categories.
      For more details, see <ulink url="http://gthumb.sourceforge.net/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Gwenview<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>graphics</secondary>
     <tertiary>Gwenview</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Gwenview is a simple image viewer for KDE. It features a folder tree
      window and a file list window that provides the easy navigation of
      your file hierarchy. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://gwenview.sourceforge.net/home/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Inkscape<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>graphics</secondary>
     <tertiary>Inkscape</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Inkscape is a free SVG editor. Users of Adobe Illustrator, Corel Draw,
      and Visio can find a similar range of features and a familiar user
      interface in Inkscape. Among its features, find SVG-to-PNG export,
      layering, transforms, gradients, and grouping of objects. For more
      details, see <ulink url="http://www.inkscape.org/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Kivio<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>graphics</secondary>
     <tertiary>Kivio</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Kivio is a flow-charting application that integrates into the KOffice
      suite. Former users of Visio find a familiar look and feel in Kivio.
      For more details, see
      <ulink
       url="http://www.koffice.org/kivio/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>KolourPaint<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>graphics</secondary>
     <tertiary>KolourPaint</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      KolourPaint is an easy-to-use paint program for the KDE desktop. You
      can use it for tasks such as painting or drawing diagrams and editing
      screen shots, photos, and icons. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://kolourpaint.sourceforge.net/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>KPovmodeler<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>graphics</secondary>
     <tertiary>KPovmodeler</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      KPovmodeler is a POV-Ray front-end that integrates with the KDE
      desktop. KPovmodeler does not require a detailed knowledge of POV-Ray
      scripting because it translates the POV-Ray language into an
      easy-to-understand tree view. Native POV-Ray scripts can be imported
      to KPovmodeler as well. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://www.kpovmodeler.org"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Krita</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Krita is KOffice's answer to Adobe Photoshop and GIMP. It can be used
      for pixel-based image creation and editing. Its features include many
      of the advanced image editing capabilities you would normally expect
      with Adobe Photoshop or GIMP. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://www.koffice.org"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>&ooo; Draw </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      See <xref linkend="vle.linwin.off.ooo"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>POV-Ray<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>graphics</secondary>
     <tertiary>POV-Ray</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      POV-Ray (Persistence of Vision Raytracer) creates three-dimensional,
      photo-realistic images using a rendering technique called ray tracing.
      Because there is a Windows version of POV-Ray, it does not take much
      for Windows users to switch to the Linux version of this application.
      For more details, see <ulink url="http://www.povray.org/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>GIMP<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>graphics</secondary>
     <tertiary>GIMP</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm>
     <primary>GIMP</primary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      GIMP (GNU Image Manipulation Program) is an open source equivalent to
      Adobe Photoshop. It is a raster graphics editor used to process
      digital graphics and photographs. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://www.gimp.org/"/> or read
      <xref linkend="cha.gimp"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>VueScan<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>graphics</secondary>
     <tertiary>VueScan</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      VueScan is a scanning software available for several platforms. You
      can install it parallel to your vendor's scanner software. It supports
      the scanner's special hardware, like batch scanning, autofocus,
      infrared channels for dust and scratch suppression, and multiscan to
      reduce scanner noise in the dark areas of slides. It features simple
      and accurate color correction. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://www.hamrick.com/vsm.html"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.linwin.sys">
  <title>System and File Management</title>

  <para>
   The following section provides an overview of Linux tools for system and
   file management. Get to know text and source code editors, backup
   solutions, and archiving tools.
  </para>

  <table>
   <title>System and File Management Software for Windows and Linux</title>
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Task
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Windows Application
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Linux Application
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        File Manager
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Windows Explorer
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Dolphin, Nautilus, Konqueror
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Text Editor
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        NotePad, WordPad, (X)Emacs
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        kate, GEdit, (X)Emacs, vim
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        PDF Creator
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Adobe Distiller
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Scribus
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        PDF Viewer
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Adobe Reader
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Adobe Reader, Evince, Okular, Xpdf
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Text Recognition
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Recognita, FineReader
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        GOCR
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Command Line Pack Programs
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        zip, rar, arj, lha, etc.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        zip, tar, gzip, bzip2, etc.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        GUI Based Pack Programs
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        WinZip
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Ark, File Roller
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Hard Disk Partitioner
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        PowerQuest, Acronis, Partition Commander
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        &yast;, GNU Parted
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Backup Software
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        ntbackup, Veritas
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        KDar, taper, dump
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Adobe Reader<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>PDF viewers</secondary>
     <tertiary>Adobe Reader</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Adobe Reader for Linux is the exact counterpart of the Windows and Mac
      versions of this application. The look and feel on Linux are the same
      as on other platforms. The other parts of the Adobe Acrobat suite have
      not been ported to Linux. For more details, see
      <ulink
       url="http://www.adobe.com/products/acrobat/readermain.html"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Ark<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>file packers</secondary>
     <tertiary>Ark</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Ark is a GUI-based pack program for the KDE desktop and supports
      common formats. You can view, select, pack, and unpack single files
      within an archive. For more details, read
      <xref
       linkend="sec.kde.use.ark"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Dolphin</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Dolphin is the default file manager for KDE 4. Dolphin offers several
      view modes, file previews and split views. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://dolphin.kde.org/"/> or read
      <xref linkend="sec.kde.dolphin"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>dump</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The dump package contains both dump and restore. dump examines files
      in a file system, determines which ones need to be backed up, and
      copies those files to a specified disk, tape, or other storage medium.
      The restore command performs the inverse function of dump&mdash;it can
      restore a full backup of a file system. For more details, see
      <ulink
       url="http://dump.sourceforge.net/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Evince<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>PDF viewers</secondary>
     <tertiary>Evince</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Evince is a document viewer for PDF and PostScript formats for the
      GNOME desktop. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://www.gnome.org/projects/evince/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>File Roller<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>file packers</secondary>
     <tertiary>File Roller</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      File Roller is a GUI-based pack program for the GNOME desktop. It
      provides features similar to Ark's. For more details, see
      <ulink
       url="http://fileroller.sourceforge.net/home.html"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>GEdit<indexterm>
     <primary>editors</primary>
     <secondary>GEdit</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      GEdit is the official text editor of the GNOME desktop. It provides
      features similar to Kate's. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://www.gnome.org/projects/gedit/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>GNU Parted<indexterm>
     <primary>partitions</primary>
     <secondary>GNU Parted</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      GNU Parted is a command line tool for creating, deleting, resizing,
      checking, and copying partitions and the file systems on them. If you
      need to create space for new operating systems, use this tool to
      reorganize disk usage and copy data between different hard disks. For
      more details, see <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/parted/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>GOCR<indexterm>
     <primary>scanning</primary>
     <secondary>GOCR</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      GOCR is an OCR (optical character recognition) tool. It converts
      scanned images of text into text files. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://jocr.sourceforge.net/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>gzip, tar, bzip2<indexterm>
     <primary>commands</primary>
     <secondary>gzip</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
     <primary>commands</primary>
     <secondary>tar</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
     <primary>commands</primary>
     <secondary>bzip2</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      There are plenty of packaging programs for reducing disk usage. In
      general, they differ only in their pack algorithm. Linux can also
      handle the packaging formats used on Windows. <command>bzip2</command>
      is a bit more efficient than <command>gzip</command>, but needs more
      time, depending on the pack algorithm.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Kate</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Kate is a module of the KDE suite. It has the ability to open several
      files at once either locally or remotely. With syntax highlighting,
      project file creation, and external scripts execution, it is a perfect
      tool for a programmer. For more details, see
      <ulink
       url="http://www.kate-editor.org/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>KDar<indexterm>
     <primary>commands</primary>
     <secondary>KDar</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      KDar stands for KDE disk archiver and is a hardware-independent backup
      solution. KDar uses catalogs (unlike tar), so it is possible to
      extract a single file without reading the whole archive and it is also
      possible to create incremental backups. KDar can split an archive into
      multiple slices and trigger the burning of a data CD or DVD for each
      slice. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://kdar.sourceforge.net/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Konqueror<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>file managers</secondary>
     <tertiary>Konqueror</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Konqueror is a file manager that can also be used as a Web browser,
      document and image viewer, and CD ripper. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://www.konqueror.org/"/> or read
      <xref linkend="cha.konqueror"/> to learn about Konqueror's Web
      browsing functions.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Nautilus</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Nautilus is the default file manager of the GNOME desktop. It can be
      used to create folders and documents, display and manage your files
      and folders, run scripts, write data to a CD, and open URI locations.
      For more details, see
      <ulink
       url="http://www.gnome.org/projects/nautilus/"/> or read
      <xref
       linkend="sec.gnomeuser.start.nautilus"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Okular</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Okular is the document viewer for KDE 4 which replaces KPDF. Apart
      from PDF files, Okular allows you to view a great number of file
      formats. Its functionality can be easily embedded in other
      applications. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://okular.kde.org/"/> or read
      <xref linkend="cha.okular"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>taper<indexterm>
     <primary>commands</primary>
     <secondary>taper</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Taper is a backup and restore program that provides a friendly user
      interface to allow backup and restoration of files to and from a tape
      drive. Conversely, files can be backed up to archive files.
      Recursively selected directories are supported. For more details, see
      at <ulink url="http://taper.sourceforge.net/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>vim<indexterm>
     <primary>editors</primary>
     <secondary>vim</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      vim (vi improved) is a program similar to the text editor vi. Users
      may need time to adjust to vim, because it distinguishes between
      command mode and insert mode. The basic features are the same as in
      all text editors. vim offers some unique options, like macro
      recording, file format detection and conversion, and multiple buffers
      in a screen. For more details, see <ulink url="http://www.vim.org/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>GNU Emacs and XEmacs</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      GNU Emacs is an extensible, customizable, self-documenting, real-time
      display editor. XEmacs is based on GNU Emacs. Both offer nearly the
      same functionality with minor differences. Used by experienced
      developers, they are highly extensible through the Emacs Lisp
      language. They support many languages, like Russian, Greek, Japanese,
      Chinese, and Korean. For more details see
      <ulink url="http://www.xemacs.org/"/> and
      <ulink
       url="http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/emacs.html"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Xpdf<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>PDF viewers</secondary>
     <tertiary>Xpdf</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Xpdf is lean PDF viewing suite for Linux and Unix-like platforms. It
      includes a viewer application and some export plug-ins for PostScript
      or text formats. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://www.foolabs.com/xpdf/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.linwin.swd">
  <title>Software Development</title><indexterm>

  <primary>applications</primary>

  <secondary>development</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   This section introduces Linux IDEs, toolkits, development tools, and
   versioning systems for professional software development.
  </para>

  <table>
<?dbsuse-latex tablehead="p{.20\linewidth}p{.34\linewidth}p{.34\linewidth}" ?>
   <title>Development Software for Windows and Linux</title>
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Task
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Windows Application
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Linux Application
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Integrated Development Environments
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Borland C++, Delphi, Visual Studio, .NET
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        KDevelop, Eric, Eclipse, MonoDevelop, Anjuta
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Toolkits
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        MFC, Qt, GTK+
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Qt, GTK+
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Compilers
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        VisualStudio
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        GCC
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Debugging Tools
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Visual Studio Debugger
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        GDB, Valgrind
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        GUI Design
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Visual Basic, Visual C++
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Glade, Qt Designer
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Versioning Systems
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Clearcase, Perforce, SourceSafe
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        CVS, Subversion
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Anjuta<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>development</secondary>
     <tertiary>Anjuta</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Anjuta is an IDE for GNOME/GTK+ application development. It includes
      an editor with automated formatting, code completion, and
      highlighting. As well as GTK+, it supports Perl, Pascal, and Java
      development. A GDB-based debugger is also included. For more details
      see <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/anjuta/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>CVS<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>development</secondary>
     <tertiary>CVS</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      CVS (Concurrent Versions System) is one of the most important version
      control systems for open source. It is a front-end to the Revision
      Control System (RCS) included in the standard Linux distributions. For
      more details, see <ulink url="http://ximbiot.com/cvs/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Eclipse<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>development</secondary>
     <tertiary>Eclipse</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The Eclipse Platform is designed for building integrated development
      environments that can be extended with custom plug-ins. The base
      distribution also contains a full-featured Java development
      environment. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Eric<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>development</secondary>
     <tertiary>Eric</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Eric is an IDE optimized for Python and Python-Qt development. For
      more details, see
      <ulink url="http://www.die-offenbachs.de/eric/index.html"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>GCC<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>development</secondary>
     <tertiary>GCC</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      GCC is a compiler collection with front-ends for various programming
      languages. Check out a complete list of features and find extensive
      documentation at <ulink
       url="http://gcc.gnu.org"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>GDB<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>development</secondary>
     <tertiary>GDB</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      GDB is a debugging tool for programs written in various programming
      languages. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/gdb/gdb.html"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Glade<indexterm>
     <primary>applications</primary>
     <secondary>development</secondary>
     <tertiary>Glade</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Glade is a user interface builder for GTK+ and GNOME development. As
      well as GTK+ support, it offers support for C, C++, C#, Perl, Python,
      Java, and others. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://glade.gnome.org/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>GTK+</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      GTK+ is a multi platform toolkit for creating graphical user
      interfaces. It is used for all GNOME applications, GIMP, and several
      others. GTK+ has been designed to support a range of languages, not
      only C/C++. Originally it was written for GIMP, hence the name
      <quote>GIMP Toolkit.</quote> For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://www.gtk.org"/>. Language bindings for GTK+ are
      summarized under
      <ulink
       url="http://gtk.org/language-bindings.php"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>KDevelop</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      KDevelop allows you to write programs for different languages (C/C++,
      Python, Perl, etc.). It includes a documentation browser, a source
      code editor with syntax highlighting, a GUI for the compiler, and much
      more. For more details, see
      <ulink
       url="http://www.kdevelop.org"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>MonoDevelop</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      MonoDevelop is an open source integrated development environment for
      the Linux platform, primarily targeted for the development of software
      that uses both Mono and Microsoft .NET framework. MonoDevelop
      integrates features similar to that of Eclipse and Microsoft's Visual
      Studio such as Intellisense, source control integration, and an
      integrated GUI and Web designer. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://www.monodevelop.com/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Qt</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Qt is a program library for developing applications with graphical
      user interfaces. It allows you to develop professional programs
      rapidly. For more details, see
      <ulink
       url="http://trolltech.com"/>. Language bindings for Qt
      development are summarized under
      <ulink url="http://developer.kde.org/language-bindings/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Qt Designer</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Qt Designer is a user interface and form builder for Qt and KDE
      development. It can run as part of the KDevelop IDE or in stand-alone
      mode. QtDesigner can be run under Windows and even integrates into the
      Visual Studio development suite. For more details see
      <ulink
       url="http://trolltech.com/products/qt/designer.html"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Subversion</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Subversion does the same thing CVS does but has major enhancements,
      like moving, renaming, and attaching meta information to files and
      directories. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Valgrind</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Valgrind is a suite of programs for debugging and profiling x86
      applications. For more details, see
      <ulink url="http://valgrind.org/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
