<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.oo.writer">
 <title>&libo; Writer</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    &libo; Writer is a full-featured word processor with page and text
    formatting capabilities. Its interface is similar to interfaces of other
    major word processors, and it includes some features that are usually found
    only in desktop publishing applications.
   </para>

   <para>
    This chapter highlights a few key features of Writer. For more information
    about these features and for complete instructions for using Writer, look
    at the &libo; help or at the sources listed in
    <xref linkend="sec.oo.oview.help"/>.
   </para>

   <para>
    Much of the information in this chapter can also be applied to other &libo;
    modules. For example, other modules use styles similarly to how they are
    used in Writer.
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.oo.writer.createnew">
  <title>Creating a New Document</title>

  <para>
   There are multiple ways to create a new Writer document:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>From Scratch</title>
     <para>
      To create a document from scratch, click <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>New</guimenu> <guimenu>Text
      Document</guimenu> </menuchoice> and a new empty Writer document is
      created.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Using a Wizard</title>
     <para>
      To use a standard format and predefined elements for your own documents,
      use a wizard. Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Wizards</guimenu> <guimenu>Letter</guimenu> </menuchoice> and
      follow the steps.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>From a Template</title>
     <para>
      To use a template, click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guimenu>New</guimenu> <guimenu>Templates</guimenu> </menuchoice> and
      choose one of the directories (for example, <filename>Business
      Correspondence</filename>) and a template within the directory.
      A new document based on the style of your selected template is created.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   For example, to create a business letter, click <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Wizards</guimenu> <guimenu>Letter</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>. Using the wizard, you can easily create a basic
   document using a standard format. A sample wizard dialog is shown in
   <xref linkend="fig.oo.writer.createnew.wizard" xrefstyle="select:label nopage"/>.
  </para>

  <figure xml:id="fig.oo.writer.createnew.wizard">
   <title>A &libo; Wizard</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="oo-wizard.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="oo-wizard.png" width="75%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   Enter text in the document window as desired. Use the tools for applying and
   changing styles or the tools for direct formatting to adjust the appearance
   of the document. Use the <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu or the relevant
   buttons in the toolbar to print and save your document. With the options
   under <guimenu>Insert</guimenu>, add extra items to your document, such as a
   table, picture, or chart.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.oo.writer.styles">
  <title>Formatting with Styles</title>

  <para>
   The traditional way of formatting office documents is direct formatting.
   That means, you use a button, such as <guimenu>Bold</guimenu>, which sets a
   certain property (in this case, a bold typeface). With styles, you can
   bundle a set of properties (for example, font size and font weight) and give
   them a speaking name, such as <emphasis>Headline, first level</emphasis>.
   Using styles, rather than direct formatting has the following advantages:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Gives your pages, paragraphs, texts, and lists a consistent look.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Makes it easy to consistently change formatting later.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Allows reuse and import of styles from another document.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Change one style and its properties are passed on to its descendants.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <example xml:id="ex.oo.usestyle">
   <title>Use of Styles</title>
   <para>
    Imagine that you emphasize text by selecting it and clicking the button
    <guimenu>Bold</guimenu>. Later, you decide you want the emphasized text to
    be italicized. Now, without styles, you need to find all bold text and
    manually change it to italics.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you had used a character style from the beginning, however, you would
    only need to change the style from bold to italics once. All text that
    formatted with a style changes as the style is changed.
   </para>
  </example>
  <para>
   &libo; can use styles for applying consistent formatting to various elements
   in a document. The following types of styles are available in Writer:
  </para>

  <table xml:id="tab.oo.writer.styles">
   <title>Types of Styles</title>
   <tgroup cols="2">
    <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="28*"/>
    <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="72*"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Type of Style
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Function
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>Paragraph</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Applies standardized formatting to the various types of paragraphs in
        your document. For example, apply a paragraph style to a first-level
        heading to set the font and font size, spacing above and below the
        heading, location of the heading, and other formatting specifications.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>Character</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Applies standardized formatting for types of text. For example, if you
        want emphasized text to appear in italics, you can create an emphasis
        style that italicizes selected text when you apply the style to it.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>Frame</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Applies standardized formatting to frames. For example, if your
        document uses marginal notes, you can create frames with specified
        borders, location, and other formatting, so that all of your marginal
        notes have a consistent appearance.
       </para>
       <para>
        Frames are also used for captioning images: A frame can keep the
        caption and the image together. Here, you can use frame style make sure
        that all your images have the same size and background color, for
        example.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>Page</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Applies standardized formatting to a specified type of page. For
        example, if every page of your document contains a header and footer
        except for the first page, you can use a first page style that disables
        headers and footers. You can also use different page styles for left
        and right pages so that you have bigger margins on the insides of pages
        and your page numbers appear on an outside corner.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>List</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Applies standardized formatting to specified list types. For example,
        you can define a checklist with square check boxes and a bullet list
        with round bullets, then easily apply the correct style when creating
        your lists.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>

  <para>
   Direct formatting overrides any styles you have applied. For example, format
   a piece of text both with a character style and using the button
   <guimenu>Bold</guimenu> button. Now, the text will be bold, no matter what
   is set in the style.
  </para>

  <para>
   To remove all direct formatting, first select the appropriate text, then
   right-click it and choose <guimenu>Clear Direct Formatting</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Likewise, if you manually format paragraphs using <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Format</guimenu> <guimenu>Paragraph</guimenu> </menuchoice>, you
   can end up with inconsistent paragraph formatting. This is especially
   true if you copy and paste paragraphs from other documents with different
   formatting. However, if you apply paragraph styles, formatting remains
   consistent. If you change a style, the change is automatically applied to
   all paragraphs formatted with that style.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.oo.writer.styles.window">
   <title>The Side Bar Panel <guimenu>Styles and Formatting</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    The side bar panel <guimenu>Styles and Formatting</guimenu> is a versatile
    formatting tool for applying styles to text, paragraphs, pages, frames, and
    lists. To open this panel, click
    <menuchoice> <guimenu>Styles</guimenu> <guimenu>Styles and
    Formatting</guimenu> </menuchoice>, click the button <guimenu>Styles and
    Formatting</guimenu> (a <literal>T</literal>) in the side bar or press
    <keycap>F11</keycap>.
   </para>
   <!-- FIXME: Screenshot needs update for 12 SP2. - sknorr, 2016-07-14 -->
   <figure xml:id="fig.oo.writer.stylist">
    <title>Styles and Formatting Window</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="oo-stylist.png" width="30%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="oo-stylist.png" width="30%" format="png"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    &libo; comes with several predefined styles. You can use these styles as
    they are, modify them, or create new styles. Use the icons at the top of
    the panel to display formatting styles for the most common elements such as
    paragraphs, frames, pages or lists. To learn more about styles, continue
    with the instructions below.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.oo.writer.styles.apply">
   <title>Applying a Style</title>
   <para>
    To apply a style, select the element you want to apply the style to, and
    double-click the style in the panel <guimenu>Styles and
    Formatting</guimenu>. For example, to apply a style to a paragraph, place
    the cursor anywhere in that paragraph and double-click the desired
    paragraph style.
   </para>
   <para>
    Alternatively, use the paragraph style selector in the toolbar
    <guimenu>Formatting</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.oo.writer.styles.change">
   <title>Changing a Style</title>
   <para>
    By changing styles, you can change formatting throughout a document, rather
    than applying the change separately everywhere you want to apply the new
    formatting.
   </para>
   <para>
    To change an existing style, proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the panel <guimenu>Styles and Formatting</guimenu>, right-click the
      style you want to change.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Modify</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Change the settings for the selected style.
     </para>
     <para>
      For information about the available settings, refer to the &libo; online
      help.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> or <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.oo.writer.styles.create">
   <title>Creating a Style</title>
   <para>
    &libo; comes with a collection of styles to suit many needs of most users.
    However, if you need a style that does not yet exist and want to create an
    own style, follow the procedure below:
   </para>
   <procedure xml:id="pro.oo.writer.styles.create">
    <title>Creating a New Style</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Open the panel <guimenu>Styles and Formatting</guimenu> with
      <menuchoice> <guimenu>Styles</guimenu> <guimenu>Styles and
      Formatting</guimenu> </menuchoice>, or pressing <keycap>F11</keycap>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Make sure you are in the list of styles for the type of style you want to
      create.
     </para>
     <para>
      For example, if you are creating a character style, make sure you are in
      the character style list by clicking the corresponding icon in the
      panel <guimenu>Styles and Formatting</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Right-click anywhere in the list of styles in the panel
      <guimenu>Styles and Formatting</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To open the style dialog, click <guimenu>New</guimenu>. The
      <guimenu>Organizer</guimenu> tab is preselected.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Configure three basic properties of the new style:
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>Name</guimenu>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         The name of your style. Choose any name you like.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>Next Style</guimenu>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         The style that follows your style. The style selected here is used when
         starting a new paragraph by pressing <keycap function="enter"/>. This
         is useful, for example, for headlines, after which you usually want to
         start a normal paragraph of text.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>Inherit From</guimenu>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         A style that your style depends on. If the selected style is changed,
         your style changes as well. For example, to make headers consistent,
         create a <quote>parent</quote> header style and have subsequent
         headers depend on it. This is useful when you only want to change the
         properties that need to be different.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
     <para>
      For details about the style options available in any tab, click the
      <guimenu>Help</guimenu> button of the dialog.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
     Confirm with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. This closes the window.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.oo.writer.style.exa.note">
    <title>Example: Defining a Note Style</title>
    <para>
     Let us assume, you need a note with a different background and borders. To
     create such a style, proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <procedure>
     <title>Creating a Note Style</title>
     <step>
      <para>
       Press <keycap>F11</keycap>. The panel <guimenu>Styles and
       Formatting</guimenu> opens.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Make sure you are in the <guimenu>Paragraph Style</guimenu> list by
       checking that the pilcrow icon (¶) is selected.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Right-click anywhere in the list of styles in the panel
       <guimenu>Styles and Formatting</guimenu> and select
       <guimenu>New</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Specify the following parameters in the tab <guimenu>Organizer</guimenu>:
      </para>
      <informaltable>
       <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            <guimenu>Name</guimenu>
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            Note
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            <guimenu>Next Style</guimenu>
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            Note
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            <guimenu>Inherit from</guimenu>
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            - None -
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            <guimenu>Category</guimenu>
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            Custom Styles
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
        </tbody>
       </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Change the indentation in the tab <guimenu>Indents &amp;
       Spacing</guimenu>, using the text field
       <guimenu>Before Text</guimenu>. If you also want more space above and
       below individual paragraphs, change the values in the
       <guimenu>Above paragraph</guimenu> and
       <guimenu>Below paragraph</guimenu> accordingly.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Switch to the tab <guimenu>Background</guimenu> and choose a color for
       the background.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Switch to the tab <guimenu>Borders</guimenu> and determine your line
       arrangements, line style, color and other parameters.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
      Confirm with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. This closes the window.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select your text in your document and double-click the style
       <guimenu>Note</guimenu>. Your style parameters are applied to the
       text.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.oo.writer.style.exa.page">
    <title>Example: Defining an Even-Odd Page Style</title>
    <para>
     If you want to create double-sided printouts of your documents, especially
     if they are supposed to be bound, use templates for even and odd pages. To
     create page styles for this, proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <procedure xml:id="pro.oo.writer.style.exa.page.even">
     <title>Create an Even (Left) Page Style</title>
     <step>
      <para>
       Press <keycap>F11</keycap>. The panel <guimenu>Styles and
       Formatting</guimenu> opens.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Make sure you are in the list <guimenu>Page Style</guimenu> by checking
       that the paper sheet icon is selected.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Right-click anywhere in the list of styles in the panel
       <guimenu>Styles and Formatting</guimenu> and select
       <guimenu>New</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Enter the following parameters in the tab <guimenu>Organizer</guimenu>:
      </para>
      <informaltable>
       <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            <guimenu>Name</guimenu>
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <remark>Previously, the proposed name was "Left Page," but LibO ships
            with that style, so you would need to edit it instead of being able
            to create it anew. -- sknorr, 2015-09-17
           </remark>
           <para>
            Left Content Page
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            <guimenu>Next Style</guimenu>
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            Leave empty, will be changed later
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            <guimenu>Inherit from</guimenu>
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            not applicable
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            <guimenu>Category</guimenu>
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            not applicable
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
        </tbody>
       </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Change additional parameters as you like in the other tabs. You can also
       adapt the page format and margins (tab <guimenu>Page</guimenu>) or any
       headers and footers.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Confirm with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. This closes the window.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <procedure xml:id="pro.oo.writer.style.exa.page.odd">
     <title>Create an Odd (Right) Page Style</title>
     <step>
      <para>
       Follow the instruction in
       <xref linkend="pro.oo.writer.style.exa.page.even"/> but use the string
       <literal>Right Content Page</literal> in the
       <guimenu>Organizer</guimenu> tab.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select the entry <guimenu>Left Content Page</guimenu> from the
       drop-down box <guimenu>Next Style</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Choose the same parameters as you did for the left page style. If you
       used different sizes for the left and right margin of your even page,
       mirror these values in your odd pages.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Confirm with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. This closes the window.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <para>
     Then connect the left page style with the right page style:
    </para>
    <procedure xml:id="pro.oo.writer.style.exa.page.connect">
     <title>Connect the Right Page Style with the Left Page Style</title>
     <step>
      <para>
       Right-click the entry <guimenu>Left Content Page</guimenu> and choose
       <guimenu>Modify</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Choose <guimenu>Right Content Page</guimenu> from the drop-down
       box <guimenu>Next Style</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Confirm with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. This closes the window.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <para>
     To attach your style, make sure your page is a left (even) page and
     double-click <guimenu>Left Content Page</guimenu>. Whenever your text
     exceeds the length of a page, the following page automatically receives
     the alternative page style.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.oo.writer.largedocs">
  <title>Working with Large Documents</title>

  <para>
   You can use Writer to work on large documents. Large documents can be either
   a single file or a collection of files assembled into a single document.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.oo.writer.largedocs.navig">
   <title>Navigating in Large Documents</title>
   <para>
    The Navigator tool displays information about the contents of a document.
    It also lets you quickly jump to different elements. For example,
    use the Navigator to get a quick overview of all images included in a
    document.
   </para>
   <para>
    To open the Navigator, click <menuchoice> <guimenu>View</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Navigator</guimenu> </menuchoice> or press <keycap>F5</keycap>.
    The elements listed in the Navigator vary with the document loaded
    in Writer.
   </para>
   <para>
    The Navigator is also an element of the side bar: there, it can be opened
    using the button <guimenu>Navigator</guimenu> (a compass).
   </para>
   <para>
    Double-click an item in the Navigator to jump to that item in the document.
   </para>
   <figure xml:id="fig.ooo.navigator">
    <title>Navigator Tool in Writer</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="oo_navigator.png" width="55%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="oo_navigator.png" width="45%" format="png"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.oo.createmaster">
   <title>Using Master Documents</title>
   <para>
    If you are working with a very large document, such as a book, it can be
    easier to manage the book with a master document, rather than
    keeping the book in a single file. A master document enables you to quickly
    apply formatting changes to a large document or to jump to each subdocument
    for editing.
   </para>
   <para>
    A master document is a Writer document that serves as a container for
    multiple Writer files. You can maintain chapters or other subdocuments as
    individual files collected in the master document. Master documents are
    also useful if multiple users are working on a single document. You can
    separate each user’s section of the document into subdocuments collected
    in a master document, allowing multiple writers to work on their
    subdocuments at the same time without fear of overwriting the work of
    others.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Creating a Master Document</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>New</guimenu> <guimenu>Master
      Document</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
     <para>
      or
     </para>
     <para>
      Open an existing document and click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Send</guimenu> <guimenu>Create Master Document</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <remark>Can't describe what the Insert icon looks like... at least, it is
      not simple: a segment of a document, with a line on it and below it a
      newly inserted block marked with an arrowhead. (And all that on 16*16px.)
      -- sknorr, 2015-09-17
     </remark>
     <para>
      The <guimenu>Navigator</guimenu> window will open. In it, select
      <guimenu>Insert</guimenu> (<inlinemediaobject>
      <textobject role="description"><phrase>Insert</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="libreoffice-writer-master-insert.png" width="0.8em" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="libreoffice-writer-master-insert.png" width="1em" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>), then choose <guimenu>File</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select a file to add an existing file to the master document.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure xml:id="pro.oo.master.addnewdocument">
    <title>Adding a New Document to a Master Document</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the window or panel <guimenu>Navigator</guimenu>, choose
      <guimenu>Insert</guimenu> (<inlinemediaobject>
      <textobject role="description"><phrase>Insert</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="libreoffice-writer-master-insert.png" width="0.8em" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="libreoffice-writer-master-insert.png" width="1em" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>), then select <guimenu>New Document</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      A file chooser opens, to allow saving the new document. Specify a name,
      then click <guimenu>Save</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      When you are done editing the new document, save it. Then switch back to
      the master document.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Update the master document with the contents of the new document. To do
      so, right-click the entry of your new document in the
      <guimenu>Navigator</guimenu>, then click
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Update</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Selection</guimenu></menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    To enter some text directly into the master document, select
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Insert</guimenu><guimenu>Text</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The &libo; help files contain more complete information about working with
    master documents. Look for the topic named <citetitle>Using Master
    Documents and Subdocuments</citetitle>.
   </para>
   <tip>
    <title>Styles and Templates in Master Documents</title>
    <para>
     The styles from all of your subdocuments are imported into the master
     document. To ensure that formatting is consistent throughout your master
     document, use the same template for each subdocument. Doing so is not
     mandatory.
    </para>
    <para>
     However, if subdocuments are formatted differently, you might need to do
     some reformatting to successfully bring subdocuments into the master
     document without creating inconsistencies. For example, if two documents
     within a master document include styles with the same name, the master
     document will use the formatting specified for the style in the document
     imported first.
    </para>
   </tip>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.oo.writer.html">
  <title>Using Writer as an HTML Editor</title>

  <para>
   In addition to being a full-featured word processor, Writer also functions
   as an HTML editor. You can style HTML pages like any other document, but
   there are specific <guimenu>HTML Styles</guimenu> that help with creating
   good HTML. You can view the document as it will appear online, or you can
   directly edit the HTML code.
  </para>

  <procedure xml:id="pro.oo.writer.html.create">
   <title>Creating an HTML Page</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>New</guimenu>
     <guimenu>HTML Document</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Press <keycap>F11</keycap> to open the panel <guimenu>Styles and
     Formatting</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     At the bottom of the panel <guimenu>Styles and Formatting</guimenu>,
     click the drop-down box to open it.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>HTML Styles</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create your HTML page, using the styles to tag your text.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Save As</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the location where you want to save your file and name the file.
     Make sure that in the bottom drop-down box, <guimenu>HTML
     Document</guimenu> is selected.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   To edit HTML code directly or to see the HTML code created when you edit the
   HTML file as a Writer document, click
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>View</guimenu> <guimenu>HTML Source</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>. In HTML Source mode, the <guimenu>Formatting and
   Styles</guimenu> list is not available.
  </para>

  <para>
   The first time you switch to <guimenu>HTML Source</guimenu> mode, you are
   prompted to save the file as HTML, if you have not already done so.
  </para>

  <para>
   To switch back from <guimenu>HTML Source</guimenu> mode to Web Layout, click
   <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenu>HTML
   source</guimenu></menuchoice> again.
   <remark>I added this, because it is a bit of a bug/illogical, since
   there is a separate menu entry Web Layout which is the layout are switching
   to. -- sknorr, 2015-09-17</remark>
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
