<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.digicam">
 <title>DigiKam: Managing Your Digital Image Collection</title><indexterm id="idx.digital_cameras" class="startofrange">
 <primary>digital cameras</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>graphics</primary>
 <secondary>digital cameras</secondary></indexterm>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   Managing digital photographs in Linux is very straightforward. KDE's
   digiKam downloads your images directly from your camera. It helps you
   organize and manipulate your images to get the best possible results. The
   application includes several useful plug-ins that can convert your images
   to various different formats. Image improvement plug-ins also include red
   eye reduction, speck removal and hot pixel removal. Various filter and
   effect plug-ins help create little works of art from your digital images.
  </para>
 </abstract><indexterm>
 <primary>digiKam</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>digital cameras</primary>
 <secondary>digiKam</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>applications</primary>
 <secondary>graphics</secondary>
 <tertiary>digiKam</tertiary></indexterm>
 <sect1 id="sec.digikam.intro">
  <title>About DigiKam</title>

  <para>
   Start digiKam from the main menu or by pressing <keycombo>
   <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and entering
   <command>digikam</command>. digiKam will ask you to choose a location to
   store your images and albums. On start-up, digiKam shows a window with
   two main areas: a list of your albums to the left and the images in the
   current album to the right. See
   <xref
    linkend="fig.digikam.mainwin"/>. The far right edge of the
   window has a number of tabs attached which can be used to display
   important information about your images, or to manipulate certain
   image-related data:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Properties</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use this tab to access properties assigned to your images, such as
      file properties (permissions, ownership, modification date, etc.),
      image properties (dimensions, file format, etc.), and photograph
      properties (basic model, exposure and aperture information).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Metadata</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use this tab to access the various kinds of metadata associated with
      your images, such as EXIF, IPTC and XMP data..
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Colors</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use this tab to access color management-related data and to analyze
      the histograms associated with your images.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Geolocation</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use this tab to search for the location stored in the picture.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Caption/Tags</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use this tab to assign comments, tags or ratings to your images.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Tag Filters</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use <guimenu>Tag Filter</guimenu> to filter the amount of images
      displayed in the main view, using tagging information. For details
      about tagging in digiKam, refer to
      <xref
       linkend="sec.digikam.tags"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <figure id="fig.digikam.mainwin">
   <title>The Main Window of digiKam</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="digikam_mainwin.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="digikam_mainwin.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.digikam.config">
  <title>Configuring Your Camera</title><indexterm>

  <primary>digital cameras</primary>

  <secondary>accessing</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>digital cameras</primary>

  <secondary>PTP protocol</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>PTP protocol</primary></indexterm>

  <para>
   To download images from your digital camera, simply connect the camera to
   the USB port of your computer using the USB cable provided by the camera
   manufacturer. Depending on your camera model, you may need to switch your
   camera to a special data transfer mode. Consult the camera's manual about
   this.
  </para>

  <para>
   There are four possibilities for accessing the pictures on the camera:
  </para>

  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>USB Mass Devices</title>
     <para>
      If your camera can be switched to a USB mass storage device, select
      this option. After you connect the camera to the USB port of your
      computer and turn the camera on, the new USB device is automatically
      detected and mounted. KDE lets you select the action to take in the
      event of any such device being mounted. You can choose to start
      digiKam or any other image viewing or processing application whenever
      a device of this type is mounted.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>PTP (Picture Transfer Protocol, also Known as PictBridge)</title>
     <para>
      If your camera can be switched to PTP, select this option. Normally
      your camera is not automatically mounted in PTP mode, but can be
      accessed through digiKam.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Special Drivers and Gphoto2</title>
     <para>
      If your camera supports neither USB mass storage nor PTP, try the
      special drivers provided by gphoto2, see
      <xref linkend="sec.digicam.trouble"/>.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Card Readers</title>
     <para>
      Nowadays cameras can use different non-volatile memory cards. For
      example, SD memory cards, compact flash (CF), memory sticks, to name a
      few. Some new computers have a card reader on board with different
      slots, to support all these formats. If you do not want to deal with
      cables, protocols, or drivers, select this option, as it simplifies a
      lot. Normally, card readers are detected as removable devices and are
      automatically mounted in KDE.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>
   To set up a camera in digiKam, select <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Import</guimenu> <guimenu>Cameras</guimenu> <guimenu>Add
   Camera</guimenu> </menuchoice>. First, try to detect the camera
   automatically with <guimenu>Auto-Detect</guimenu>. If this fails, browse
   the list of supported cameras for your model with <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
   If your camera model is not included in the list, try an older model or
   use USB/IEEE mass storage camera and confirm with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.digikam.download">
  <title>Downloading Pictures from the Camera</title>

  <para>
   To download images from a camera that has been properly configured,
   attach the camera to your computer and select the camera from the
   <guimenu>Camera</guimenu> menu. digiKam opens a window and begins to
   download thumbnails and display them as in
   <xref
    linkend="fig.digikam.picdownload"/>. Right-click an image to
   open a pop-up menu with the options to <guimenu>View</guimenu> the image,
   to <guimenu>Download</guimenu>, or <guimenu>Delete</guimenu> the image.
   Select the <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> tab to the right of the download
   window to rename the image files using <guimenu>Renaming
   Options</guimenu>. Review the EXIF data associated with the selected
   image using the <guimenu>Metadata</guimenu> tab.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.digikam.picdownload">
   <title>Downloading Pictures from a Camera</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="digikam_downloadpics.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="digikam_downloadpics.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <tip>
   <title>Renaming Images</title>
   <para>
    Mass renaming of your images comes in handy if your camera's filenames
    are not meaningful enough for your purpose. Provide a unique prefix, add
    an optional date, and let digiKam provide a sequence number.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
   Select all images to download from the camera by pressing the left mouse
   button or by clicking individual images with
   <keycap function="control">Ctrl</keycap> pressed, or by using one of the
   select modes provided by the <guimenu>Images</guimenu> menu at the bottom
   of the download window. Click <guimenu>Download</guimenu> and select the
   destination from the list, or create a new album with <guimenu>New
   Album</guimenu> (which automatically suggests a filename with the current
   date). Confirm with <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to start the download process.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>Downloading Images from the Storage Medium</title>
   <para>
    To save your camera's battery power, you can also attach a USB hub to
    your computer (providing an appropriate slot for your storage medium)
    and download the files from there. Once the USB hub is connected to your
    computer, the KDE media handler dialog opens and offers to download the
    images from the medium you attached.
   </para>
  </tip>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.digikam.albums">
  <title>Managing Albums</title><indexterm>

  <primary>graphics</primary>

  <secondary>albums</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   By default, digiKam creates a folder called <guimenu>My Albums</guimenu>
   to hold all root albums, called collections. Collections can store
   albums, while albums store sub albums and images. The first collection
   was created on first start with the First-run Wizard dialogue.
  </para>

  <para>
   The albums can be sorted by directory layout, by collection name set in
   the album properties, or by the date that the albums were first created
   (this date can also be changed in the properties of each album).
  </para>

  <para>
   To create a new album, use one of these methods:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Upload new images from the camera and create the target album during
     the download.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Create a new album by selecting a collection folder first and then
     <menuchoice> <guimenu>Album</guimenu> <guimenu>New Album</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> from the main menu or via right-click.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Import an existing folder of images from your hard disk (select
     <menuchoice> <guimenu>Import</guimenu> <guimenu>Add
     Folders...</guimenu> </menuchoice>).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Right-click a collection folder and select <guimenu>New
     Album</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   To create a new collection, go to <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure
   digiKam</guimenu></menuchoice>, <guimenu>Collections </guimenu> menu and
   choose <guimenu>Add Collection</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Once you have chosen to create a new album, provide some basic
   administrative information about the new album, such as an album title.
   Optionally, choose a category, insert some comments, and select an album
   date. Categories are a way of organizing your albums by a common label.
   This label is used when you select <menuchoice> <guimenu>View</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Sort Albums</guimenu> <guimenu>By Category</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>. The comment is shown in the banner at the top of the main
   window. The album date is used when you select <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>View</guimenu> <guimenu>Sort Albums</guimenu> <guimenu>By
   Date</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <para>
   digiKam uses the first photograph in the album as the preview icon in the
   <guimenu>My Albums</guimenu> list. To select a different one, right-click
   the respective photograph and select <guimenu>Set as Album
   Thumbnail</guimenu> from the context menu.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.digikam.tags">
  <title>Managing Tags</title>

  <para>
   Managing a high number of different images across various albums can be
   very difficult. To manage your images by custom categories and across
   albums, digiKam provides the <guimenu>My Tags</guimenu> system. Tags
   categorize images, and more than one tag can be assigned to an image.
  </para>

  <para>
   For example, assume that you took several pictures of animals and
   distributed them across various albums. Now you are looking for an easy
   way to generate an overview of all pictures ever taken of animals. Using
   digiKam's tags, proceed as follows for this scenario:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tag</guimenu> <guimenu>New Tag</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> in the upper menu bar and enter a name for the new tag,
     in this case <literal>animals</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The dialog box allows you to create hierarchical tags, too. For
     example, to have a <literal>bear</literal> tag which is underneath a
     <literal>animals</literal> tag, insert <literal>animals/bear</literal>
     into the text field. Provide an optional icon and leave this dialog
     with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Go to each album and tag all images showing some animals by
     right-clicking the image and selecting <menuchoice> <guimenu>Assign
     Tag</guimenu> <guimenu>animals</guimenu><guimenu>Assign this
     Tag</guimenu> </menuchoice>. To tag more then one picture at once, use
     the <keycap function="control"/> key.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   If you need to process a huge number of images, an easier way to do the
   tagging would be using the <guimenu>Captions/Tags</guimenu> tab from the
   tab bar at the right edge of the main window. This interface allows you
   to assign tags to this image, enter an optional descriptive comment, and
   rate this image. When you are done with the first image, stay in this
   dialog, click the right arrow button, and click <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>
   when finished to apply your settings. Do it with all your images of this
   album. Proceed similarly with all other albums and images.
  </para>

  <para>
   To retrieve all images in your entire collection that carry a certain tag
   (in this case <literal>animals</literal>), proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open the <guimenu>Tags</guimenu> tab in the left tab bar.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Unfold the <guimenu>My Tag</guimenu> item.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the <guimenu>animals</guimenu> tag.
    </para>
    <para>
     As a result, all images in your entire collection carrying this tag are
     displayed.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <figure id="fig.digikam.tabs">
   <title>Display Tagged Images Only</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="digikam_tabs.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="digikam_tabs.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   The <guimenu>Tag Filter</guimenu> in the far right edge of the main
   window limits the number of images displayed for the current album to
   those marked by the tag or tags selected here.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.digikam.search">
  <title>Creating Powerful Search Filters</title>

  <para>
   Any image collection soon becomes unmanageable if you do not find a means
   to easily search for the images you need and find them. To help you
   organize your collection, digiKam offers you two search options:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Simple Search</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A basic search. Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Search</guimenu> </menuchoice> and enter a text string that
      might be associated with your image (image or tag name or comment) and
      hit <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. You can save this search for future use,
      and edit other existing searches listed under
      <guimenu>Searches</guimenu> on the left edge of your digiKam window.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Advanced Search</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Complex search filter. Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Advanced Search</guimenu> </menuchoice>, provides a wide
      spectrum of search criteriums, which are:
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>File, Album, Tags</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Search for names of albums, tags or the filenames of pictures.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Picture Properties</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Search for image properties like date, rating, file size, color depth
      and a lot more.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Caption, Comment, Title</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Search for comments, author and IPTC information.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Photograph Information</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Search for photograph information like focal length, sensitivity and
      so on..
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   With the <guimenu>Add Search Group</guimenu> button it is possible to
   combine several search criteria. <guimenu>Searches</guimenu>.
  </para>

<?dbfo-need height="15em"?>

  <para>
   The following example illustrates how to create an <guimenu>Advanced
   Search</guimenu> using rating or tag information to search for images:
  </para>

  <procedure id="proc.digikam.search">
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Advanced
     Search</guimenu> </menuchoice> from the main menu.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Picture Properties</guimenu> criterion. Now select
     <guimenu>Rating</guimenu> from 2 to 5 stars.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the <guimenu>Add Search Group</guimenu> button. Another search
     board appears. It is possible to combine search parameters with
     <guimenu>And</guimenu> or <guimenu>Or</guimenu> and the four options.
     Click on <guimenu>Meet any of the following conditions</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the <guimenu>File, Album, Tags</guimenu> criterion and choose a
     tag from the tags list.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the <guimenu>Picture Properties</guimenu> criterion. Choose JPEG
     as file format and press the <guimenu>Ok</guimenu> button. The results
     of your search are displayed in the digiKam window.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To save the search for future use, click on <guimenu>Searches</guimenu>
     tab on the left side. Specify a name for this search and <guimenu>Save
     Current Search</guimenu> by clicking the save button. Leave the
     <guimenu>Advanced Search</guimenu> dialog with another click on the
     <guimenu>Searches</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <figure id="fig.digikam.search">
   <title>Creating an Advanced Search Filter</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="digikam_search.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="digikam_search.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.digikam.export">
  <title>Exporting Image Collections</title>

  <para>
   digiKam provides several export options that help archive and publish
   your personal image collections. It offers archiving to iPod, HTML
   export, and export to a remote gallery.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <para>
    digiKam comes with some customized export functions for the most known
    online archives and the general export function <menuchoice> <guimenu>
    Export</guimenu> <guimenu>HTML Gallery</guimenu> </menuchoice>. To
    create an HTML export of your image collection, proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Export</guimenu> <guimenu>HTML
     Gallery</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Determine which part of your collection should be archived by selecting
     albums or tags in <guimenu>Collection</guimenu> and click
     <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Use <guimenu>Theme</guimenu> dialog to set the appearance of your HTML
     gallery and click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Specify size, compression and file type for the thumbnails used for
     gallery navigation in <guimenu>Image Settings</guimenu> and click
     <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Determine the location of the gallery on disk with
     <guimenu>Output</guimenu> and click <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure>
   <para>
    To export your collection to an external image gallery on the Internet,
    proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Get an account for an external Web site to host your gallery.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Export</guimenu> <guimenu>Export to
     Gallery </guimenu> </menuchoice> and provide the URL, username, and
     password for the external site when asked. digiKam establishes a
     connection to the site specified and opens a new window called
     <guimenu>Gallery Export</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Determine the location of your new album in the gallery.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>New Album</guimenu> and provide the information
     requested by digiKam.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Upload the images to the new album with <guimenu>Add Photos</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.digicam.digikam.loc">
  <title>Managing Geolocation</title>

  <para>
   Some cameras store GPS (Global Positioning System) coordinates within the
   photographs when they take a picture. With this information digiKam is
   able to illustrate and search photographs by their location and display
   them on a globe. To make use of Geolocation, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Search the Map</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Click on the <guimenu>Map Searches</guimenu> tab on the left side.
      Press <keycap
       function="shift"/> ctrl and the left mouse button
      to choose an area on the map. Use the mouse wheel to zoom in and out.
      Every image matching the coordinates of the area will be displayed
      inside the main window.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Show Geolocation</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Click on the <guimenu>Geolocation</guimenu> tab on the right side to
      open the globe. Select one or more pictures with the left mouse
      button. Every picture containing GPS information will be displayed on
      the map. To zoom in/out use the mouse wheel.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Adding Geolocation</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Choose a picture in the main window and select
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Image
      </guimenu><guimenu>Geolocation</guimenu><guimenu>Edit Coordinates
      </guimenu></menuchoice>. Choose the location on the map or enter the
      coordinates manually and press <guimenu>Ok</guimenu>. The coordinates
      are now stored in the image’s EXIF tags. To edit several pictures at
      once press the <keycap function="control"/> key while choosing the
      desired pictures.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <figure id="fig.digikam.loc">
   <title>Watching picture locations on the map</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="digikam_location.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="digikam_location.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.digicam.digikam.edit">
  <title>Viewing and Editing Images</title><indexterm>

  <primary>graphics</primary>

  <secondary>editing</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>image editing</primary>

  <secondary>digiKam</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>digiKam</primary>

  <secondary>image editing</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   digiKam comes with a comprehensive image viewing and editing suite
   consisting of various plug-ins. To enter digiKam's viewing or editing
   mode, right-click an image thumbnail and select <guimenu>View</guimenu>
   or <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> from the context menu. To use the plug-ins,
   install the <systemitem class="resource">digikamimageplugins</systemitem>
   package.
  </para>

  <para>
   To view one or more images you have the following options:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To view a single image, browse to your album or collection and click on
     your image to display it. Another click brings you back to the previous
     view.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To start a slide show with all images, use <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>View</guimenu> <guimenu>Slideshow</guimenu>
     <guimenu>All</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To start a slide show with selected images only, hold down the
     <keycap function="control"
     /> key, select your images, and choose
     <menuchoice> <guimenu>View</guimenu> <guimenu>Slideshow</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Selection</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   To edit a selected image, use <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> from the main menu.
   This opens a window which contains some of the most frequently used basic
   editing options:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Use the back/forward buttons to browse your album without having to go
     back to the full album view.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Use the undo/redo menus to selectively undo or redo certain operations.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Use the zooming options to zoom in or out, or to fit the image view to
     the window size you are using. Use the looking glass icon to
     selectively zoom into a particular area of the image.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Flip the image clockwise or counter-clockwise.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Activate a slide show or full screen view of the selected image.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <sect2 id="sec.digikam.decorate">
   <title>Applying Image Decorations</title>
   <para>
    The editing mode contains more useful features. Use the
    <guimenu>Decorate</guimenu> menu to superimpose various kinds of
    graphics and text effects onto your images without having to bother
    about filters and their fine-tuning:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Apply Texture</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Select the type of texture you want to apply to your image and
       determine how prominent this texture should be
       (<guimenu>Relief</guimenu>). digiKam applies the texture and saves
       the changes to the original copy of your image.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Add Border</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Select the type of border. Depending on the type of border you have
       selected, choose one or two colors to be used for the border and set
       the width of the border around your image. digiKam creates the border
       and saves the changes to the original copy of your image.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Insert Text</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Enter the text you want to superimpose on the image. Choose font,
       font style and size. Select the text justification and decide whether
       the text should be rotated (and to what degree). Add an optional
       border and semi-transparency. digiKam adds your text layer to the
       original image.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Template Superimpose</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Just as you can superimpose any text on your image, you can also
       apply ready-made templates to create funny greeting cards, posters
       and the like.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.digikam.color">
   <title>Manipulating Color Settings</title>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>Color</guimenu> menu allows you to manage all kinds of
    different color-related settings. Its capabilities range from simple
    auto correction mechanisms to full-blown color management via color
    profiles:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Auto Color Correction</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If aiming for a straightforward color and exposure correction of your
       image, try this option. Choose from various preset modes and apply
       the one that matches best. Use the histograms to determine whether
       the result matches your needs.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Brightness/Contrast/Gamma</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This tool offers a simple way of fixing over or underexposed images.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Hue/Saturation/Lightness</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This tool helps you to optimize images that have been taken under
       very bright lighting conditions and appear somewhat washed out. Bring
       color saturation back to these images by manipulating the hue and
       saturation sliders. Depending on the level of color, you might also
       want to adjust the lightness to prevent the image from registering
       too dark. Of course, you can also use this tool to achieve the
       opposite effect if you need to brighten up an image that has been
       taken at low light conditions and contains far too much color
       saturation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Color Balance</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Depending on the lighting conditions under which an image was taken
       or the quality of an image scan, the colors may appear somehow out of
       balance. Using the color balance tool, you can try to shift the
       balance towards another end of the color spectrum.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Invert</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Invert the color values.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Black &amp; White</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Transform your color image into black and white. Use the
       <guimenu>Film</guimenu>, <guimenu>Lens Filters</guimenu>,
       <guimenu>Tone</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Lightness</guimenu> to tweak
       the end product. The <guimenu>Film</guimenu> tab offers you to
       emulate the effects various black and white films. To emulate color
       filters used with the camera lens, use the <guimenu>Lens
       Filters</guimenu> tab. Note that you can only apply one filter at a
       time. Using the <guimenu>Tone</guimenu> tab you can have your black
       and white image tinted in a particular way (sepia, for example).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Depth</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Determine the color depth (in bits). Transform 8-bit into 16-bit
       images and vice versa.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Color Management</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Color management via ICC color profiles helps you maintain color
       fidelity across multiple output devices (camera, display, printer).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Levels Adjust</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use this option to control multiple levels and to check the resulting
       image in just one tool. It lets you save the chosen level settings
       and thus enables you to apply the same corrections to multiple
       images, if needed. This comes in handy if you know that your camera
       tends to use the same faulty color settings all the time, and you
       would like to be able to correct them with just a single click.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Color Effects</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This tool offers a selection of color effects like edge finding,
       solarizing, etc.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>White Balance</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Every source of light registers differently on your digital camera's
       chip. Depending on the light source, the color temperature tends to
       register either warmer (towards the red end of the spectrum) or
       cooler (towards the blue end of the spectrum) than standard daylight.
       Most cameras ship with preset white balance schemes that try to
       compensate these effects. If the resulting images registers faulty,
       use the white balance adjustment provided by digiKam. Either
       manipulate the color temperature directly by using the Kelvin slider,
       or choose one of the preset white balance schemes.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Curves Adjust</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This tool allows you to basically perform any operation available
       through the <guimenu>Brightness/Contrast/Gamma</guimenu> and the
       <guimenu>Levels Adjust</guimenu> tools, but in one tool and using
       free-function mapping. Therefore this tool is more powerful and
       flexible than the other two, but it may take some time to get used
       to.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Channel Mixer</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The channel mixer tool provides an alternative way of converting
       colored images to black and white. Using the
       <guimenu>Monochrome</guimenu> option and the channel sliders, you can
       selectively determine how much each of the color channels contributes
       to the overall image. The channel mixer option is much more flexible
       than the standard conversion to black and white, because you can
       manage each color channel separately.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.digikam.fix">
   <title>Fixing and Tweaking Your Images</title>
   <para>
    Use the <guimenu>Enhance</guimenu> menu to address a number of common
    defects related to digital imagery:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Blur</guimenu>, <guimenu>Sharpen</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Tweak the sharpness of your image or smooth it.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Red Eyes</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Reduce or eliminate red eyes caused by use of a flash.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Inpainting</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <quote>Heal</quote> defective areas of your image.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Noise Reduction</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Remove artifacts, such as those caused by dust on your lens or
       sensor. Compensate for pixel noise caused by high ISO settings of
       your digital camera and reduce noise and artifacts in low quality
       scans.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Hot Pixels</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Detect and erase problem pixels of your image caused by defective
       pixels of your camera's sensor.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><menuchoice><guimenu>Lens</guimenu><guimenu>Distortion</guimenu></menuchoice>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Compensate for barrel and pincushion distortion of your images caused
       by the use of strong wide-angle or telephoto lenses.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><menuchoice><guimenu>Lens</guimenu><guimenu>Vignetting Correction</guimenu></menuchoice>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Compensates circular shades (<emphasis>vignettes</emphasis>) at the
       edges or in the center of your image that were caused by the use of
       strong wide-angle or telephoto lenses.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><menuchoice><guimenu>Lens</guimenu><guimenu>Vignetting Correction</guimenu></menuchoice>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Compensates circular shades (<emphasis>vignettes</emphasis>) at the
       edges or in the center of your image that were caused by the use of
       strong wide-angle or telephoto lenses.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Restoration</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Provides an all-inclusive treatment to images exhibiting various
       digital defects, such as noise and scratches.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    To observe the functionality of the <guimenu>Fix</guimenu> options, look
    at <guimenu>Inpainting</guimenu>, for example. Assume some dust or
    scratch on your lens ruined an image. To remove this kind of blemish,
    proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <procedure id="proc.dk.tf">
    <step id="st.dk.tf1">
     <para>
      Open your image.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step id="st.dk.tf2">
     <para>
      Use the mouse cursor to select the area to which to apply the fix.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step id="st.dk.tf3">
     <para>
      Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Enhance</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Inpainting</guimenu> </menuchoice> or press <keycombo>
      <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>E</keycap> </keycombo>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step id="st.dk.tf4">
     <para>
      Determine the method to use to remove the blemish:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Choose one of the <guimenu>Preset</guimenu> options (<guimenu>Remove
        Small Artifact</guimenu>, <guimenu>Remove Medium Artifact</guimenu>,
        or <guimenu>Remove Large Artifact</guimenu>) and proceed with
        <xref linkend="st.dk.tf6" xrefstyle="select: nopage"
        />.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Set the filter parameters on your own. Proceed with
        <xref linkend="st.dk.tf5"
         xrefstyle="select: nopage"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </step>
    <step id="st.dk.tf5">
     <para>
      If you opted against using any of the preset filters (in the
      <guimenu>Preset</guimenu> tab), open the <guimenu>General</guimenu>
      and <guimenu>Advanced Settings</guimenu> tabs and adjust the settings
      to your needs.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step id="st.dk.tf6">
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to apply your settings and modify the
      image accordingly.
     </para>
     <tip>
      <title>Creating and Reusing Your Own Filter Settings</title>
      <para>
       If you need to use the same set of settings more than once (for
       example, if a scratch on the lens ruined an entire series of images),
       create your set of filter settings. Save them for later use by
       clicking <guimenu>Save As</guimenu> and saving them to a text file.
       For subsequent images, open the <guimenu>Image Inpainting</guimenu>
       dialog, click <guimenu>Load</guimenu>, then select the text file and
       apply the filter settings with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </tip>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <figure id="fig.digikam.inpaint">
    <title>Using <guimenu>Inpainting</guimenu> to Remove Artifacts</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="digikam_inpaint.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="digikam_inpaint.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.digikam.transform">
   <title>Applying Image Transformations</title>
   <para>
    To scale or rotate an image, use the <guimenu>Transform</guimenu> menu:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Rotate, Flip, Free Rotation</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Rotate your image to a certain degree. <guimenu>Rotate</guimenu>
       rotates by multiples of 90 degrees. With <guimenu>Free
       Rotation</guimenu>, specify any angle you want.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Crop, Aspect Ratio Crop</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Crop your image. <guimenu>Crop</guimenu> cuts to any rectangular
       selection on top of your image. <guimenu>Aspect Ratio Crop</guimenu>
       crops the image following various sophisticated design principles.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Perspective Adjustment</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Adjust the perspective of an image. For example, if you notice some
       odd angles in shots containing vertical or horizontal lines, use this
       tool to correct them. Grab any of the four handles to the corners of
       your image and move them as needed. Use the <guimenu>Crop</guimenu>
       tool to remove the resulting black edges of your image, and to trim
       it down.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Shear</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Shift one part of your image to one direction and the other to the
       opposite direction, either horizontally or vertically. Specify the
       angles for vertical and horizontal shear and use
       <guimenu>Crop</guimenu> to trim the resulting image.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Resize</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Scale your image. <guimenu>Resize</guimenu> offers a simple interface
       allowing you to manipulate your image size by pixel or percentage.
       Select whether to keep the aspect ratio. If you select
       <guimenu>Restore photograph</guimenu>, you can fine-tune the
       algorithms used on your resized image and improve the quality of the
       end product. Note that this option might be considerably slower than
       a simple resize operation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    Assuming you have an image that is otherwise perfect, but you are not
    entirely satisfied with the composition yet or need to crop your image
    to match a certain paper format for reproduction. Use <guimenu>Aspect
    Ratio Crop</guimenu> and proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Open your image.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Transform</guimenu> <guimenu>Aspect Ratio
      Crop</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Determine the orientation and aspect ratio to use:
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>None</guimenu>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Specify a free crop of the image using the <guimenu>X</guimenu>,
         <guimenu>Width</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Y</guimenu>,
         <guimenu>Height</guimenu> sliders.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>Custom</guimenu>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Select a custom ration of width versus height instead of using one
         of the preset values.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>X:Y Ratio</guimenu>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         These ratios match most of the common paper sizes used to print
         photographs. Pick the one that suits your purpose best.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>Golden Ratio</guimenu>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         A ratio (1:1.618) that is traditionally used by artists and
         architects to create harmonious results.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
     <para>
      Use the <guimenu>Max. Aspect</guimenu> button to set the crop area to
      the maximum possible size of the specified ratio.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      After determining the size of your crop selection, optionally apply
      compositional rules to it. The <guimenu>Composition Guide</guimenu>
      helps to create a crop selection that results in a visually pleasing
      image. Dotted lines are displayed that guide you to a better
      composition of your image.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      If the position of your crop does not follow the compositional rule to
      your satisfaction, move it.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to apply your crop selection and trim your
      image.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <figure id="fig.digikam.acrop">
    <title>Creating a Custom Crop Using Aspect Ratio Crop</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="digikam_acrop.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="digikam_acrop.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.digikam.filters">
   <title>Applying Filters and Effects</title>
   <para>
    You can select from a variety of basic effects and filters to apply to
    your images, giving them a more artistic or over-the-top look:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Raindrops</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Apply raindrop effects to your image. Determine the size and number
       of the drops and specify the degree of distortion caused by the drops
       (<guimenu>Fish eyes</guimenu>).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Infrared Film</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Simulate the use of infrared film to achieve a slightly surreal
       effect. The result is strikingly different from the original image.
       Add additional film grain and tweak the sensitivity (ISO) to achieve
       a more artistic feel.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Oil Paint</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Simulate an oil painting. Determine the brush size and the degree of
       smoothing to apply to your image.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Emboss</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Pretend your image had been embossed to a sheet of paper. Choose an
       appropriate depth.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Distortion Effects</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Apply various strange distortion effects, such as fish eyes, to your
       image. Determine type, level, and repetition.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Add Film Grain</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Add film grain to your image to give it a rough look.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Blur Effects</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Blur your image to simulate the image being out of focus or to mimic
       any kind of movement that was not there when you took the image.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Charcoal Drawing</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Transform your image into a black and white charcoal drawing. Choose
       an appropriate pencil size and determine the degree of smoothing to
       apply to the image.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <figure id="fig.digikam.ir">
    <title>Simulating IR Photography</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="digikam_ir.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="digikam_ir.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.digikam.tools">
  <title>Useful Tools</title>

  <para>
   digiKam offers several little helpers for organizing your image
   collection and for processing your images. Find them in the
   <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> menu. Some highlights:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Find Duplicates</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you suspect that your collection contains a number of duplicates,
      use this option to find and delete them. First, determine which album
      or tag to include in the scope of your search. Click
      <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to initiate the search. If your collection
      contains any duplicates, you get a split screen showing both images
      and can select one of them for deletion.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Create Calendar</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Create a simple calendar using a standard layout by selecting the
      images to use and by selecting paper size and fonts.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.digikam.batch">
  <title>Batch Processing</title>

  <para>
   If you need to perform certain actions on a large number of files at
   once, use batch processing. Add borders, edit colors, apply various
   effects and filters, rename and resize images, recompress them, or
   perform a RAW conversion.
  </para>

  <para>
   To find out whether your camera's RAW format is supported by the digiKam
   converter plug-in, check <menuchoice><guimenu>Help</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Supported RAW Cameras</guimenu></menuchoice>. Use
   <menuchoice><guimenu>Batch</guimenu> <guimenu>Convert
   Images</guimenu></menuchoice> to convert images from one format to
   another, for example from jpg to png.
  </para>

  <para>
   An example of batch processing of images could involve applying a
   solarizing effect to a number of images. To queue images for batch
   processing and perform the actual processing, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Batch</guimenu> <guimenu>Image
     Effects</guimenu> </menuchoice> or right-click the album's name and
     select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Batch Processes</guimenu> <guimenu>Image
     Effects</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Set the effect to <guimenu>Solarize</guimenu> and click
     <guimenu>Options</guimenu> to determine the degree of the effect to be
     applied and display an optional preview.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Decide whether to rename or overwrite the original images, or even have
     them removed after the transformation has taken place.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Set the target folder to hold the resulting images. If you do not want
     the new images to be written to the original folder, select
     <guimenu>New</guimenu> and add a new folder or subfolder. Select the
     new folder with your mouse pointer.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Accept or modify the list of images queued for the transformation.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Start</guimenu> to initiate the transformation.
    </para>
    <para>
     digiKam informs you about the progress and the success of the
     transformation.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <figure id="fig.digikam.batch">
   <title>Batch Processing: Solarizing Images</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="digikam_batch.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="digikam_batch.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.digicam.trouble">
  <title>Troubleshooting</title>

  <para>
   Although &productname; and digiKam support a broad range of cameras, you
   might occasionally hit one of the following problems when using your
   digital camera with &productname;:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Downloading Images from Your Camera Fails</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <indexterm>
      <primary>gphoto2</primary>
      </indexterm> If downloading your images fails no matter which protocol
      you have chosen (PTP or USB), try using the command line instead of
      digiKam. The <command>gphoto2 <option>--P</option></command> command
      initializes the camera and downloads the images if gphoto2 supports
      this camera.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Your Camera is not Officially Supported by digiKam</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Try <command>gphoto2 <option>--list-cameras</option></command> and the
      information at <ulink url="http://www.gphoto.org/"/> to obtain more
      information about the status of your camera's support by Linux.
     </para>
     <para>
      If the camera is not listed there, remove the storage medium from the
      camera and use a card reader device (either an external or internal
      one). As soon as the medium is detected, it is mounted automatically
      and you can import the images to your digiKam collection with
      <menuchoice> <guimenu>Import</guimenu> <guimenu>Add Images</guimenu>
      </menuchoice> or <menuchoice> <guimenu>Import</guimenu> <guimenu>Add
      Folders</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.digicam.info">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   For more information about using digital cameras with Linux, refer to the
   following Web sites:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://www.digikam.org"/>>&mdash;The official homepage of
     digiKam
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://www.digikam.org/drupal/docs"/>&mdash;The official
     digiKam Handbook
    </para>
   </listitem>
<!-- doesn't work anymore 
   <listitem>
    <para><ulink
      url="http://docs.kde.org/development/en/extragear-graphics/digikamimageplugins/index.html"/>&mdash;digiKam Plug-in Documentation</para>
   </listitem>
-->
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://www.gphoto.org"/>&mdash;Information about gPhoto2
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://www.gphoto.org/proj/libgphoto2/support.php"/>&mdash;A
     comprehensive list of supported cameras
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.digital_cameras"/>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
