<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!--
  Version information:
  * SLE11 SP1: 3.3.1.2
  * SLE11 SP2: 3.4.2.3
  * SLE11 SP3: 3.6.3.2.4 (2013-02-28)
  * SLE12 SP1 [beta 3]: 4.3.5.2.0+
  * SLE12 SP2 [beta 4]: 5.1.1.3
-->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.oo.oview">
 <title>&libo;: The Office Suite</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    &libo; is an open source office suite that provides tools for all
    types of office tasks such as writing texts, working with spreadsheets,
    or creating graphics and presentations. With &libo;, you can use the
    same data across different computing platforms. You can also open and
    edit files in other formats, including Microsoft Office formats, then save
    them back to this format, if needed. This chapter contains information that
    applies to all &libo; modules.
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.oo.oview.modules">
  <title>&libo; Modules</title>

  <para>
   &libo; consists of several application modules (subprograms) which are
   designed to integrate with each other. They are listed in
   <xref linkend="tab.oo.oview.modules" xrefstyle="select:label nopage"/>. A
   full description of each module is available in the online help, described
   in <xref linkend="sec.oo.oview.help"/>.
  </para>

  <table xml:id="tab.oo.oview.modules">
   <title>The &libo; Application Modules</title>
   <tgroup cols="2">
    <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="19*"/>
    <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="81*"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Module
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Purpose
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Writer
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Word processor module
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Calc
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Spreadsheet module
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Impress
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Presentation module
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Base
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Database module
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Draw
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Module for drawing vector graphics
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Math
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Module for generating mathematical formulas
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>

  <para>
   The following chapters cover individual &libo; modules:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><xref linkend="cha.oo.writer"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Introduces &libo; Writer.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><xref linkend="cha.oo.calc"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Introduces &libo; Calc.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><xref linkend="cha.oo.various"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Introduces &libo; Impress, Base, Draw, and Math.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.oo.oview.start">
  <title>Starting &libo;</title>

  <para>
   To start &libo;, click
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> <guimenu>Office</guimenu>
   <guimenu>LibreOffice</guimenu></menuchoice>. In the &libo; start center,
   choose the type of document you want to create.
  </para>

  <para>
   There are multiple methods to directly start one of the &libo; modules:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If any &libo; module is open, you can start any of the other
     modules by clicking
     <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>New</guimenu></menuchoice>
     and then selecting the type of document you want to create.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You can also start individual &libo; modules from the menu
     <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     As an alternative, use the command <command>libreoffice</command> and one
     of the options
     <option>--writer</option>, <option>--calc</option>,
     <option>--impress</option>, <option>--draw</option>, or
     <option>--base</option> to start the respective module. 
    </para>
    <para>
     &libo; has many command line options, especially for allowing document
     conversions. To learn more about the command line options of &libo;, see
     <command>libreoffice --help</command> or the man page of &libo;
     (<command>man libreoffice(1)</command>).
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   Before you start working with &libo;, you may be interested in changing
   some options from the preferences dialog. Click <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Options</guimenu> </menuchoice> to open
   it. The most important ones are:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><menuchoice><guimenu>&libo;</guimenu><guimenu>User Data</guimenu></menuchoice>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Specify your user data such as company, first and last name, street,
      city, and other useful information. This data has many uses: It is used
      in the comment functions of Writer and Calc, for authorship information
      in PDF documents, and for serial letters in Writer.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><menuchoice><guimenu>&libo;</guimenu><guimenu>Fonts</guimenu></menuchoice>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Map font names to installed fonts. This can be useful if you exchange
      documents with others and the document you received contains fonts that
      are not available on your system.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><menuchoice><guimenu>Load/Save</guimenu><guimenu>General</guimenu></menuchoice>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Contains loading and saving specific options.
      For example, you can choose whether to always create a backup copy
      and which file format &libo; should use by default.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   To learn more about configuring &libo;, see
   <xref linkend="sec.oo.oview.global"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.oo.interface">
  <title>The &libo; User Interface</title>

  <para>
   The user interface of most &libo; is very similar across its modules:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Menu Bar</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      At the top of the application, there is the menu bar which gives
      access to almost all functionality of &libo;. They can be customized to
      include more or fewer functions. You can also add and remove menus.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Toolbars</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      By default, the toolbars are positioned directly below the menu bar. The
      toolbars comprise the most used and most important items of the
      module.
     </para>
     <para>
      The toolbars can be dragged to any side of the window or can be dragged
      into the middle of the window, to make them float. They can be customized
      to include more or fewer functions. You can also add and remove toolbars.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Side Bar</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      By default, the side bar is positioned at the right side of the &libo;
      window. On the first start of &libo;, it is only visible as several icons
      stacked vertically. Clicking one of the icons opens a panel with more
      elements. Click the icon again to close the panel. Similarly to the
      toolbars, the sidebar comprises the most important functions.
     </para>
     <para>
      The sidebar can be dragged to the left or right side of the window or can
      be dragged into the middle of the window, to make it float. You can hide
      or show side bar panels but cannot customize their functionality.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Statusbar</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The statusbar is displayed at the bottom of the window. It mainly shows
      information about the document, such as the number of words (in Writer)
      or the sum of values of selected cells (in Calc). However, it can also be
      used to change the zoom or language settings. Many elements open
      additional menus or dialogs on left click, right click, or double click.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
   For more information on customizing &libo;, see
   <xref linkend="sec.oo.oview.cust"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.oo.oview.migration">
  <title>Compatibility with Other Office Applications</title>

  <para>
   The native file format of &libo; is the OpenDocument format. OpenDocument is
   an ISO-standardized format for office documents that is based on XML.
   However, &libo; can also work with documents, spreadsheets, presentations,
   and databases in many other formats, including Microsoft&thrdmrk;
   Office&thrdmrk; formats. Files in Microsoft Office formats can be opened and
   saved back normally.
  </para>

  <para>
   In case there should ever be issues with opening documents, you can try the
   following strategies:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Text Documents</title>
     <para>
      Consider opening text documents in the original application and saving
      them as RTF.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Spreadsheets</title>
     <para>
      Consider opening spreadsheets in the original application and saving them
      as Excel files. If this does not work, try the CSV format. However,
      saving as CSV means that all formatting, cell type definitions, formulas,
      and macros will be lost.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.oo.oview.migration.convert">
   <title>Converting Documents to the OpenDocument Format</title>
   <para>
    &libo; can read, edit, and save documents in several formats. It is not
    necessary to convert files from those formats to the OpenDocument format
    used by LibreOffice to use those files. However, if you want to convert the
    files, you can do so. To convert several documents, such as when first
    switching to &libo;, do the following:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Wizards</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Document Converter</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose the file format from which to convert.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Specify where &libo; should look for templates and documents to
      convert and in which directory the converted files should be placed.
     </para>
     <para>
      Documents retrieved from a Windows partition are usually in a
      subdirectory of <filename>/windows</filename>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Make sure that all other settings are correct, then click
      <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Review the summary of the actions to perform, then start the
      conversion by clicking <guimenu>Convert</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <para>
      The amount of time needed for the conversion depends on the number of
      files and their complexity. For most documents, conversion does not take
      very long.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      When everything is done, close the Wizard by clicking
      <guimenu>Close</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.oo.oview.migration.share">
   <title>Sharing Files with Users of Other Office Suites</title>
   <para>
    &libo; is available for several operating systems. This makes it
    an excellent tool when a group of users frequently need to share files
    and do not use the same system on their computers.
   </para>
   <para>
    When sharing documents with others, you have several options:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>If the recipient needs to be able to edit the file</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Save the document in the format the other user needs. For example, to
       save as a Microsoft Word file, click <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Save As</guimenu> </menuchoice>, then
       select the Microsoft Word file type for the version of Word the other
       user needs.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>If the recipient only needs to read the document</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Export the document to a PDF file with <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Export as PDF</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
       PDF files can be read on any platform using a PDF viewer.
      </para>
      <remark>
       LibreOffice has a nice functionality that allows adding an OpenDocument
       into a PDF file. This way, you can share it with anyone with a PDF
       reader. If the person additionally uses LibO/AOO, they can also edit.
       File > Export as PDF > Embed OpenDocument File -- sknorr, 2015-09-17
      </remark>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>If you want to share a document for editing</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Agree on a common exchange format that works for everyone. TXT and RTF
       formats, although limited in formatting, can be a good option for text
       documents.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>If you want to e-mail a document as a PDF</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Send</guimenu>
       <guimenu>E-mail as PDF</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Your default e-mail
       program opens with the file attached.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>If you want to e-mail a document to a Microsoft Word user</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Send</guimenu>
       <guimenu>E-mail as Microsoft Word</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Your default
       e-mail program opens with the file attached.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.oo.oview.passwd">
  <title>Saving Files with a Password</title>

  <para>
   You can save files, no matter in which &libo; format, with a password. Unlike
   older versions of &libo;, the encryption applied to the document with recent
   versions of &libo; is very strong. However, this encryption does not protect
   file names and file sizes of encrypted files. If that is important to you,
   see the alternate encryption methods described in
   <xref linkend="cha.security.cryptofs"/>.
  </para>
  <procedure xml:id="pro.oo.encrypt">
   <title></title>
   <step>
    <para>
     To save a file with a password,
     select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Save</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> or <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Save
     As</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the dialog that opens, activate the check box <guimenu>Save with
     password</guimenu> at the bottom and click <guimenu>Save</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Type and confirm your password, then click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   The next time you open the file, you will be prompted for the password.
  </para>

  <para>
   To change the password, do either of the following:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Overwrite the same file by selecting
     <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenu>Save As</guimenu></menuchoice>.
     Make sure <guimenu>Save with Password</guimenu> is deactivated.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Select
     <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Properties</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> and click <guimenu>Change Password</guimenu> to access the
     password dialog.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 os="sled;osuse" arch="x86_64" xml:id="sec.oo.oview.certstore">
  <title>Signing Documents</title>

  <remark>
   taroth 081201: is this the correct place where the cert
   store comes in? - taroth 081218: still no answer, so going to locdrop
   now anyway
  </remark>

  <remark>
   This is really only a third of the story, there are a few interesting
   questions here, such as:
   ? How do I get a certificate?
   ! From a CA or self-signed:
     + StartSSL (free/cheap, recognized in most browsers),
     + CAcert (free, recognized only on Debian)
     + Let's Encrypt (free, simple with some command line experience, not sure
       if they provide certificates for signing documents)
     + Tiny CA tool to self-sign (not recognized on the receiving end)

   ? How do I get the certificate to be displayed in LibreOffice?
   ! Add it to your Firefox profile... Yes! You can probably also configure
     other Firefox or Thunderbird profiles. However, apparently, Seahorse would
     not work. Need to find out later.

   ? More information?
   ! Try:
     + https://help.libreoffice.org/Common/About_Digital_Signatures
     + http://www.techrepublic.com/blog/diy-it-guy/diy-add-digital-signatures-to-libreoffice-documents/
     + https://ask.libreoffice.org/en/question/4141/digitally-signing-the-document-issue-what-is-nss-certificate-db/

   - sknorr, 2015-09-17
  </remark>

  <remark>
   Make this a procedure later. -- sknorr, 2015-09-17
  </remark>

  <para>
   You can digitally sign documents to protect them.
   For this, you need a personal certificate, similar to an HTTPS certificate.
   You can either create a self-signed certificate or choose to obtain one from
   a Certificate Authority.
  </para>

  <para>
   When applying a digital signature to a document, a kind of checksum is
   created from the document's content and your personal key. The checksum is
   stored together with the document.
  </para>

  <para>
   When another person opens the document, the checksum will be generated again.
   The new checksum is then compared to the original checksum.
   If both are equal, the application will signal that the document has not
   been changed in the meantime.
  </para>

  <para>
   To add a certificate to &libo;, you need to use Firefox:
  </para>
  <procedure xml:id="pro.oo.importcertificate">
   <title></title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start Firefox by selecting
     <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guimenu>Internet</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Firefox</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Go to the certificates preferences by opening the menu
     (<inlinemediaobject>
      <textobject role="description"><phrase>Three-lines button</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="hamburger_button.svg" width="0.8em" format="svg"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="hamburger_button-fallback.png" width="1em" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>), then select
     <menuchoice><guimenu>Preferences</guimenu><guimenu>Advanced</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Certificates</guimenu><guimenu>View Certificates</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Add your certificate by selecting <guimenu>Your Certificates</guimenu>
     and clicking <guimenu>Import</guimenu> and then locate your certificate.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   To sign a document, first open it in &libo;. Then select
   <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenu>Digital Signatures</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Sign Document</guimenu></menuchoice>. Select the certificate you
   want to use for signing, then click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   &productname; allows you to access certificates from the certificate store.
   For more information, refer to <xref linkend="cha.certstore"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.oo.oview.cust">
  <title>Customizing &libo;</title>

  <para>
   You can customize &libo; to best suit your needs and working style.
   Toolbars, menus, and key combinations can all be reconfigured to help you
   more quickly access the features you use the most.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can also assign macros to application events if you want specific
   actions to occur when those events take place. For example, if you always
   work with a specific spreadsheet, you can create a macro that opens the
   spreadsheet and assign the macro to the
   <guimenu>Start Application</guimenu> event.
  </para>

  <para>
   This section contains simple, generic instructions for customizing your
   environment. The changes you make are effective immediately. This means, you
   can see if the changes are what you wanted and go back and modify them if
   they are not. See the &libo; help files for detailed instructions.
  </para>

  <para>
   To access the customization dialog in any open &libo; module, select
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Customize</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <figure xml:id="fig.oo.oview.custom">
   <title>Customization Dialog in Writer</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="oo_customize_main.png" width="50%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="oo_customize_main.png" width="50%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <note>
   <title>Further Information</title>
   <para>
    Click <guimenu>Help</guimenu> for more information about the options in the
    <guimenu>Customize</guimenu> dialog.
   </para>
  </note>

  <procedure>
   <title>Customizing Toolbars</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the customization dialog, click the tab <guimenu>Toolbar</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     From the drop-down box <guimenu>Toolbar</guimenu>, select the toolbar
     you want to customize.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Activate the check boxes next to the commands you want to appear on the
     toolbar, and deactivate the check boxes next to the commands you do not
     want to appear. A short description for each command is shown at the
     bottom of the dialog.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     With <guimenu>Save In</guimenu>, select whether to save your customized
     toolbar in the current &libo; module or in the current document. If
     you decide to save it in the &libo; module, the customized toolbar is
     used whenever you open that module. If you decide to save it together
     with the current document, the customized toolbar is used whenever you
     open that document.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Repeat to customize additional toolbars.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   If you want to switch back to the original settings again, open the
   customization dialog, click the <guimenu>Toolbar</guimenu> drop-down box and
   select <guimenu>Restore Default Settings</guimenu>. Click
   <guimenu>Yes</guimenu> and <guimenu>Reset</guimenu> to proceed.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Showing or Hiding Buttons in the Toolbar</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the arrow icon at the right edge of the toolbar you want to change.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Visible Buttons</guimenu> to display a list of buttons.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the buttons in the list to enable (check) or disable (uncheck)
     them.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure>
   <title>Customizing Menus</title>
   <para>
    You can add or delete items from current menus, reorganize menus, and even
    create new menus.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Customize</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Menus</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the menu you want to change, or click <guimenu>New</guimenu> to
     create a new menu.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Modify, add, or delete menu items as desired.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure>
   <title>Customizing Key Combinations</title>
   <para>
    You can reassign currently assigned key combinations and assign new ones to
    frequently used functions.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Customize</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Keyboard</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the keys you want to assign to a combination.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select a <guimenu>Category</guimenu> and an appropriate
     <guimenu>function</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Modify</guimenu> to assign the function to the key or
     <guimenu>Delete</guimenu> to remove an existing assignment.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure>
   <title>Customizing Events</title>
   <para>
    &libo; also provides ways to assign macros to events such as
    application start-up or the saving of a document. The assigned macro
    runs automatically whenever the selected event occurs.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Customize</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Events</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the event you want to change.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Assign or remove macros for the selected event.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.oo.oview.global">
  <title>Changing the Global Settings</title>

  <para>
   Global settings can be changed in any &libo; module by clicking
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Options</guimenu>
   </menuchoice> on the menu bar. This opens the window shown in the figure
   below. A tree structure is used to display categories of settings.
  </para>

  <figure xml:id="fig.ooo.cust.globalsettings">
   <title>The Options Window</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="oo_options.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="oo_options.png" width="75%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   The settings categories that appear depend on the module you are working
   in. For example, if you are in Writer, the &libo; Writer category
   appears in the list, but the &libo; Calc category does not. The
   &libo; Base category appears in both Calc and Writer. The Module
   column in the table shows where each setting category is available.
  </para>

  <para>
   The following table lists the settings categories along with a brief
   description of each category:
  </para>

  <table xml:id="tab.ooo.globalcategory">
   <title>Global Setting Categories</title>
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="25*"/>
    <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="55*"/>
    <colspec align="center" colnum="3" colname="3" colwidth="20*"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Settings Category
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Description
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Module
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>&libo;</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Basic settings, including your user data (such as your
        address and e-mail), important paths, and settings for printers and
        external programs.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        All
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>Load/Save</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Settings related to the opening and saving of several
        file types. There is a dialog for general settings and several
        special dialogs to define how external formats should be handled.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        All
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>Language Settings</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Settings related to languages and writing aids, such as
        your locale and spell checker settings. This is also the place to
        enable support for Asian languages.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        All
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu> &libo; Writer</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Settings related to word processing, such as the basic units, fonts and
        layout that Writer should use.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Writer
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>&libo; Writer/Web</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Settings related to the HTML authoring features of &libo;.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Writer
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>&libo; Calc</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Settings related to spreadsheets, such as spreadsheet appearance,
        Microsoft Excel compatibility options, and calculation options.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Calc
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>&libo; Impress</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Settings related to presentations, such as enabling the smartphone
        remote control and the grid of the page to use.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Impress
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>&libo; Draw</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Settings related to drawings, such as the grid of the page to use.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Draw
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>&libo; Base</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Allows setting and editing database connections and registered
        databases.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Base
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>Charts</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Allows defining the default colors used for newly created charts.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        All
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>Internet</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Allows configuring a proxy and the e-mail software to use.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        All
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>

  <important>
   <title>Settings Apply Globally</title>
   <para>
    All settings listed in the table apply <emphasis>globally</emphasis> for
    the specified modules. That means, they are used as defaults for every
    new document you create.
   </para>
  </important>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.oo.oview.templates">
  <title>Using Templates</title>

  <para>
   A template is a document containing only the styles&mdash;and
   content&mdash; that you want to appear in every document of that type.
   When a document is created or opened with the template, the styles are
   automatically applied to that document. Templates greatly enhance the use
   of &libo; by simplifying formatting tasks for a variety of different
   types of documents.
  </para>

  <para>
   For example, in a word processor, you can write letters, memos, and reports,
   all of which look different and require different styles. Or, for example,
   for spreadsheets, you could use different cell styles or headings for
   certain types of spreadsheets. If you use templates for each of your
   document types, the styles you need for each document are always readily
   available.
  </para>

  <para>
   &libo; comes with a set of predefined templates. You can also find
   additional templates on the Internet, for example at
   <link xlink:href="http://templates.libreoffice.org"/>. For details, see
   <xref linkend="sec.oo.oview.help"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   Creating own templates requires some planning. You need to determine how you
   want the document to look, so you can create the styles you need in that
   template.
  </para>

  <para>
   A detailed explanation of templates is beyond the scope of this section.
   <xref linkend="pro.oo.oview.templates"/> only shows how to generate a
   template from an existing document.
  </para>

  <procedure xml:id="pro.oo.oview.templates">
   <title>Creating &libo; Templates</title>
   <para>
    For text documents, spreadsheets, presentations, and drawings, you can
    create a template from an existing document as follows:
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start &libo; and open or create a document that contains the styles
     and content that you want to re-use for other documents of that type.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Templates</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Save as Template</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Choose a directory to save the image in by double-clicking one of the
     directory icons.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you are in a subdirectory and want to go up again, use the path bar
     displayed above the directories.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     From the toolbar, choose <guimenu>Save</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Specify a name for the template.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <note>
   <title>Converting Microsoft Word Templates</title>
   <para>
    You can convert Microsoft Word templates like you would convert any other
    Word document. For more information, see
    <xref linkend="sec.oo.oview.migration.convert"/>.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.oo.overview.properties">
  <title>Setting Metadata and Properties</title>

  <para>
   When exchanging documents with other people, it is sometimes useful to
   store metadata like the owner of the file, who it was received from, and a
   URL.
   &libo; lets you attach such metadata to the file.
   This helps you track metadata which you do not want to or cannot save in
   the content of the file.
   This feature is also the basis for later sorting, searching and retrieving
   your documents based on metadata.
   <remark>toms 2010-03-04: Maybe remove the last sentence as the "How?"
   should be explained too (which might be difficult)</remark>
   <remark>In general, SLED contains rather rudimentary document management
    software. If you want to make the most use of metadata, you will need an
    external system -- sknorr, 2015-09-17</remark>
  </para>

  <para>
   As an example, we assume you want to set these properties to your file:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A title, subject, and some keywords
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The owner of the file
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Who sent you the file
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   To attach such metadata to your document, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Setting Properties</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Properties</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>. A dialog opens. It has, among others, the following tabs:
    </para>
<!-- Commented out all the tabs: led too far away from the procedure.
- sknorr, 2016-07-13-->
<!--<variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>General</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        This is an overview tab where you can see the type, its
        location, size, when it was created and modified and other useful
        information. If you have a digital signature, it is also possible to
        digitally sign your document.
        <remark>toms 2010-03-03 How?
         Where?</remark>
        <remark>Could explain use of Apply User Data/Reset -> clean PDF output
         without author information. E.g. people won't see that the secretary
         writes the boss's speeches etc. Needs to be done in another procedure.
         - sknorr, 2015-09-17</remark>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Description</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Insert your title, subject, keywords and comments as you like.
        <remark>How are keywords separated? Commas? - sknorr, 2015-09-17
        </remark>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Custom Properties</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Custom properties specify the editor, owner, publisher, received from,
        and other useful metadata.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>CMIS Properties</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Allows managing documents from CMIS repositories, such as Alfresco*.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Security</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Allows setting a password needed to change the document.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Font</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Allows embedding all used fonts in the document.
        This will make the document larger
        It has the advantage that anyone receiving the document will be able
        see the document with the original fonts.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Statistics</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Contains an overview of your documents.
        It lists the number of pages, tables, graphics, and others depending on
        the type of your document.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>-->
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Change to the <guimenu>Description</guimenu> tab and insert title,
     subject, and your keywords.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Switch to the <guimenu>Custom Properties</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step xml:id="st.oo.property.add">
    <para>
     To add a row for a property, click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Name</guimenu> row, click the drop-down box the entry. A
     list of properties appears, from it, choose <guimenu>Owner</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Insert the name of the owner in the <guimenu>Value</guimenu> row.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Repeat from <xref linkend="st.oo.property.add"/> but as the name of the
     property, choose <guimenu>Received from</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Optionally, repeat from <xref linkend="st.oo.property.add"/> for more
     properties.
    </para>
    <para>
     To remove a property, click the red icon at the end of the corresponding
     row.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Leave the dialog with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Save the file.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.oo.oview.help">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   &libo; contains extensive online help. In addition, a large community
   of users and developers support it. The following list shows some
   places where you can go for additional information.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     &libo; Application Help (<menuchoice><guimenu>Help</guimenu>
     <guimenu>LibreOffice Help</guimenu></menuchoice>)
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Extensive help on performing any task in &libo;.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><link xlink:href="https://www.libreoffice.org"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Home page of &libo;
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><link xlink:href="https://ask.libreoffice.org"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Official question and answer page for &libo;.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><link xlink:href="http://www.taming-libreoffice.com/"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Taming &libo;: books, news, tips and tricks.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><link xlink:href="http://www.pitonyak.org/oo.php"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Extensive information about creating and using macros.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><link xlink:href="http://extensions.libreoffice.org/"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Extension and template directory for &libo;.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><link xlink:href="https://www.worldlabel.com/Pages/openoffice-template.htm"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Templates for creating labels with &libo;.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
