<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!--
 Version information:
 * SLE11 SP1: 4.3.5
 * SLE11 SP2: 4.3.5
 * SLE11 SP3: 4.3.5 (2013-02-28)
-->
<chapter id="cha.kontact">
 <title>Kontact: E-Mailing and Calendaring</title><indexterm
  id="idx.kontact" class="startofrange">
 <primary>Kontact</primary></indexterm><indexterm id="idx.e-mail_programs_Kontact"
  class="startofrange">
 <primary>email applications</primary>
 <secondary>Kontact</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>applications</primary>
 <secondary>network</secondary>
 <tertiary>Kontact</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>applications</primary>
 <secondary>office</secondary>
 <tertiary>Kontact</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>KMail</primary>
 <see>Kontact</see></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>KOrganizer</primary>
 <see>Kontact</see></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>KAddressBook</primary>
 <see>Kontact</see></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>KNotes</primary>
 <see>Kontact</see></indexterm>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   Kontact combines the functionality of a number of KDE applications into a
   convenient, single interface for personal information management. These
   applications include KMail for e-mail, KOrganizer for the calendar,
   KAddressBook for contacts, KNode for newsgroups, and KNotes for notes.
   <remark>toms: KPilot seems not ready for oS 11.1, so I've disabled the following
    phrase:</remark>
   <phrase os="osuse12">It is also possible to sync data with external
   devices, such as handheld device.</phrase> Kontact integrates easily with
   the rest of the KDE desktop and connects to a variety of groupware
   servers. It includes extra features such as journal entries, Spam and
   virus filtering, and an RSS reader.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <para>
  Start Kontact from the main menu. Alternatively, press <keycombo>
  <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter
  <command>kontact</command> . You can also open the individual components
  instead of the combined application if you only need partial
  functionality.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.kontact.window">
  <title>Kontact Overview</title>

  <para>
   The default window view is shown in <xref linkend="fig.kontact.open"/>.
   Use the icons in the left section to access the different components.
   <indexterm>
   <primary>Kontact</primary>
   <secondary>summary</secondary>
   </indexterm> The <guimenu>Summary</guimenu> provides basic information,
   including upcoming birthdays, to-dos and the number of new mail messages.
   The news section can access RSS feeds to provide updated news of interest
   to you. Use <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure
   Summary View</guimenu> </menuchoice> to configure the information
   displayed.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.kontact.open">
   <title>The Kontact Summary View</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kontact-main.png" width="90%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kontact-main.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Mail</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The folder area to the left contains a list of your mail folders (mail
      boxes) indicating the total number of messages and the number of
      unread messages. To select a folder, simply click it. The messages in
      that folder appear in the top right frame. The number of messages in
      that folder is also shown in the status bar at the bottom of the
      application window.
     </para>
     <para>
      The subject, sender, and time of receipt of each message are listed in
      the header area to the right. Click a message to select it and display
      it in the message window. Sort the messages by clicking one of the
      column headers (subject, sender, date, etc.). The contents of the
      currently selected message are displayed in the message frame of the
      window. Attachments are depicted as icons at the end of the message,
      based on the MIME type of the attachment, or they can be displayed
      inline.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Contacts<indexterm>
     <primary>Kontact</primary>
     <secondary>contacts</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The upper left frame of this component shows all addresses in the
      currently-activated address books. The lower left frame lists your
      address books and shows whether they are currently active. The right
      frame shows the currently-selected contact. Use the search bar at the
      top to find a particular contact.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Calendar<indexterm>
     <primary>calendars</primary>
     <secondary>Kontact</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
     <primary>Kontact</primary>
     <secondary>calendar</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The calendar view is divided into a number of frames. By default, view
      a small calendar of this month and a week view of the current week.
      Also find a list of to-dos, a detailed view of the current event or
      to-do, and a list of calendars with the status of each. Select a
      different view from the toolbar or the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>To-Do List<indexterm>
     <primary>Kontact</primary>
     <secondary>to-do lists</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <guimenu>To-do List</guimenu> shows your list of tasks. Click the
      field at the top to add a new item to the list. Right-click in the
      column of an existing item to make changes to the value in that
      column. An item can be broken into several subitems. Right-click and
      select <guimenu>New Sub-to-do</guimenu> to create a subitem. You can
      also assign to-dos to other people.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Journal<indexterm>
     <primary>Kontact</primary>
     <secondary>journal</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The <guimenu>Journal</guimenu> provides a place for your reflections,
      occurrences, or experiences. Choose a date in the calendar frame and
      click <guimenu>Add Journal Entry</guimenu> to add a new entry. If a
      journal entry already exists for the chosen date, edit it in the right
      frame.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Notes<indexterm>
     <primary>Kontact</primary>
     <secondary>notes</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use the Notes component to keep sticky notes to yourself. If you are
      using KDE, use the KNotes icon in the system tray to make your notes
      visible on the desktop.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Feeds<indexterm>
     <primary>Kontact</primary>
     <secondary>feeds</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
     <primary>Kontact</primary>
     <secondary>RSS</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The <guimenu>Feeds</guimenu> window is divided into three
      frames&mdash;a tree view with RSS feeds on the left, an article list
      on the top right, and the article view on the bottom right side. Click
      a feed in the tree view to display it. Right-click a feed to update,
      edit, or delete it. Right-click a folder in the tree view to open a
      menu where you can add a new feed or manipulate existing feeds within.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kontact.mail">
  <title>Mail</title>

  <para>
   Kontact uses KMail as its e-mail component. You can also start it
   separately with the command <command>kmail</command>. To configure it,
   open the mail component then select <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure KMail</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>. KMail is a fully-featured e-mail client that supports a
   number of protocols.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.kontact.mail">
   <title>The Kontact Mail Component</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kontact-mail.png" width="90%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kontact-mail.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect2 id="sec.kontact.mail.conf">
   <title>Configuring Identities</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Kontact</primary>
   <secondary>identities</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Kontact</primary>
   <secondary>accounts</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    KMail can manage multiple e-mail accounts (private or business).
    Creating separate identities for your different e-mail accounts allows
    you to associate different sender addresses, cryptography settings and
    signatures with each of them. To create an identity, select <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure KMail</guimenu>
    </menuchoice> and choose <menuchoice> <guimenu>Identities</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Add</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Determine whether to create a new
    identity from scratch, use the control center settings
    <remark>toms 2009-08-17: It seems the menu entries doesn't exist anymore. No
     replacement found. :( </remark>
<!--from <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Personal Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Password &amp; User
    Account</guimenu> </menuchoice>-->
    , or whether to duplicate an existing identity.
   </para>
   <para>
    To create a new identity from scratch, enter the name of the new
    identity and enter your name, organization and e-mail address in the
    <guimenu>General</guimenu> tab. You can also configure one or several of
    the following options:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Cryptography</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Set the keys to use for signing and encrypting messages. For the
       encryption to work, first create a key with KGpg, as described in
       <xref linkend="cha.crypto"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Advanced</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Enter a default reply-to and a default blind carbon-copy address,
       (usually empty), choose a dictionary, select the folders for draft,
       sent messages, and templates, and define by which sending account the
       messages should be sent.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Templates</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Define custom templates to use for new messages, for default replies
       to senders and lists, and for forwarded messages. To use templates,
       activate <guimenu>Use Custom Message Templates</guimenu>, first.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Signature</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>Enable Signature</guimenu> first to use it. Decide how
       your messages should be signed. Use the input field below to
       configure your signature or obtain it from a file or the output of a
       command.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Picture</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use this tab to include a picture in the X-Face format in your
       messages. X-Face can only hold black and white images with a
       dimension of 48 &times; 48 pixels. You can obtain the picture from
       the input field below or from an external source.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kontact.accounts">
   <title>Creating Accounts</title>
   <para>
    Before you can send or receive e-mails, create one or several accounts.
    KMail allows both remote accounts and local mailboxes. The settings
    under <guimenu>Accounts</guimenu> determine how Kontact receives and
    sends e-mail. Many of these settings vary depending on the system and
    network in which your mail server is located. If you are not sure about
    the settings or items to select, consult your ISP or system
    administrator.
   </para>
   <para>
    To configure a remote account, proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start Kontact and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Configure KMail</guimenu> <guimenu>Accounts</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Create an incoming account by clicking on the
      <guimenu>Receiving</guimenu> tab:
     </para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>
        Click <guimenu>Add</guimenu> and choose the account type. Usually it
        is POP3, IMAP, or disconnected IMAP.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Enter your account name (can be freely chosen), the incoming mail
        server, login and password.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Decide, if the following options are useful to your setup:
       </para>
       <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
         <term><menuchoice><guimenu>General</guimenu><guimenu>Store POP
           password</guimenu></menuchoice>
         </term>
         <listitem>
          <para>
           If you use KWallet, check <guimenu>Store POP password</guimenu>.
           This makes it a bit more convenient as you do not have to type in
           your passwords (it is taken once from KWallet, see
           <xref linkend="cha.kde.kwallet"/>.)
          </para>
         </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
         <term><menuchoice><guimenu>General</guimenu><guimenu>Enable interval mail
            checking</guimenu></menuchoice>
         </term>
         <listitem>
          <para>
           If you need to be up-to-date with your mails, check this option
           and enter the interval.
          </para>
         </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
         <term><menuchoice><guimenu>Advanced</guimenu><guimenu>Leave fetched messages on the
            server</guimenu></menuchoice> (POP3 only)</term>
         <listitem>
          <para>
           KMail can leave the original message on the server and receive a
           copy. Especially for POP3 accounts, this could be useful, if you
           need the mail on a different computer.
          </para>
         </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
         <term><menuchoice><guimenu>Advanced</guimenu><guimenu>Use default
           identity</guimenu></menuchoice> (IMAP/disconnected IMAP only)</term>
         <listitem>
          <para>
           This option lets you choose your identity.
          </para>
         </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
         <term/>
         <listitem>
          <para/>
         </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
       </variablelist>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Proceed with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step id="st.kontact.outgoingaccount">
     <para>
      Create an outgoing account by clicking on the
      <guimenu>Sending</guimenu> tab and click <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to
      choose either <guimenu>SMTP</guimenu> or <guimenu>Sendmail</guimenu>:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If you select SMTP (the default), enter an account name and the host
        name of the SMTP server. Should the server require login and
        password, also check <guimenu>Server requires
        authentication</guimenu> and enter the required credentials.
        Configure additional security settings using the
        <guimenu>Security</guimenu> tab.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If you select Sendmail, no further configuration is required.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Apply your settings and leave the account configuration dialog with
      <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    To configure a local mailbox, proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start Kontact and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Configure KMail</guimenu> <guimenu>Accounts</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Create an incoming account by clicking on the
      <guimenu>Receiving</guimenu> tab:
     </para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>
        Click <guimenu>Add</guimenu> and choose <guimenu>Local
        mailbox</guimenu> or <guimenu>Maildir mailbox</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Enter your account name. Choose any name you like.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Decide which locking method you want. Usually you can leave it on
        <guimenu>Procmail lockfile</guimenu>
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Proceed with <guimenu>Ok</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Create an outgoing account as described in
      <xref linkend="st.kontact.outgoingaccount"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kontact.mail.create">
   <title>Composing Messages</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Kontact</primary>
   <secondary>creating messages</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    To compose new messages, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Message</guimenu>
    <guimenu>New Message</guimenu> </menuchoice> or click the corresponding
    icon in the toolbar. To send messages from different e-mail accounts,
    select one of the identities as described in
    <xref
     linkend="sec.kontact.mail.conf"/>. Select <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>View</guimenu> <guimenu>Identity</guimenu> </menuchoice> to
    show a pop-up menu. In <guimenu>To</guimenu>, enter an e-mail address or
    part of a name or address in your address book. If Kontact can match
    what you enter to something in the address book, a selection list opens.
    Click the desired contact or complete your input if none matches. To
    select directly from the address book, click the
    <guimenu>Select...</guimenu> button next to the
    <guimenu>Address</guimenu> field.
   </para><indexterm>
   <primary>Kontact</primary>
   <secondary>attachments</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    To attach files to your message, click the paper clip icon and select
    the file to attach. Conversely, drag a file from the desktop or another
    folder to the <guimenu>New Message</guimenu> window or select one of the
    options in the <guimenu>Attach</guimenu> menu. Normally, the format of a
    file is recognized correctly. If the format is not recognized,
    right-click the icon. From the menu that appears, select
    <guimenu>Properties</guimenu>. Set the format and filename in the next
    dialog and add a description. In addition, decide whether the attached
    file should be signed or encrypted.
   </para>
   <para>
    When you are finished composing your message, send it immediately with
    <menuchoice> <guimenu>Message</guimenu> <guimenu>Send</guimenu>
    </menuchoice> or move it to the outbox with <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Message</guimenu> <guimenu>Send Later</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    If you send the e-mail, the message is copied to
    <filename>sent-mail</filename> after having been sent successfully.
    Messages moved to the <filename>outbox</filename> can be edited or
    deleted.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kontact.mail.folder">
   <title>Managing Folders</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Kontact</primary>
   <secondary>folders</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Message folders help organize your messages. By default, they are
    located in the <filename>~/.kde4/share/apps/kmail/mail</filename>
    directory. When starting KMail for the first time, the program creates
    several folders. If you are using IMAP, the IMAP folders are listed
    below the local folders. Each incoming mail server has its folders in
    the Folder list.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you want to organize your messages in additional folders, select from
    your list your parent folder and create new folders by selecting
    <menuchoice> <guimenu>Folder</guimenu> <guimenu>New Folder</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>. This opens a window in which to specify the name and
    format of the new folder.
   </para>
   <para>
    Right-click the folder for a context menu offering several folder
    operations. Click <guimenu>Expire</guimenu> to specify the expiration
    date for read and unread messages, what should happen with them after
    expiration, and whether expired messages should be deleted or moved to a
    folder. If you intend to use the folder to store messages from a mailing
    list, set the necessary options under <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Folder</guimenu> <guimenu>Mailing List Management</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>.
   </para>
   <para>
    To move one or several messages from one folder to another, drag them
    from the upper window and drop them into the appropriate folder in the
    left window. Messages can also be moved by highlighting the messages
    then pressing <keycap>M</keycap> or selecting <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Message</guimenu> <guimenu>Move to</guimenu> </menuchoice>. In
    the list of folders that appears, select the folder to which to move
    your messages.
   </para>
   <para>
    Additionally, you can add folders to the <guimenu>Favorite
    Folders</guimenu> pane. This enables you to go quickly to your
    frequently used mail folders, especially if your folders are deeply
    structured. Choose the relevant folder and select <guimenu>Add to
    Favorite Folders</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kontact.mail.crypto">
   <title>Signing and Encrypting e-mails</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Kontact</primary>
   <secondary>encryption</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>encryption</primary>
   <secondary>Kontact</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Kontact</primary>
   <secondary>signing</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    E-mail is an insecure medium, as anyone could theoretically read your
    e-mails or send some in your name. By signing your e-mails you enable
    the recipient of your e-mails to verify the sender of the messages as
    the key used to sign is only available to you. By encrypting the
    contents of your e-mails you ensure that they can only be read by the
    recipient. KMail supports both the signing and encryption of e-mails.
   </para>
   <para>
    Prepare KMail for signing and encrypting e-mails:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Generate a key pair as described in
      <xref linkend="sec.crypto.kgpg.keygen"/> and export your public key as
      described in <xref linkend="sec.crypto.kgpg.mng.export"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Configure the details of the encryption procedure in KMail:
     </para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>
        Start KMail and go to <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>
        <guimenu>Configure KMail</guimenu> <guimenu>Identities</guimenu>
        </menuchoice>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Select the identity under which to send encrypted and signed
        messages. Click <guimenu>Modify...</guimenu> and proceed to
        <guimenu>Cryptography</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Change the <guimenu>OpenPGP signing key</guimenu> by clicking on
        <guimenu>Change...</guimenu> and selecting your key from the dialog
        box.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Change the <guimenu>OpenPGP encryption key</guimenu> by clicking on
        <guimenu>Change...</guimenu> and selecting your key from the dialog
        box.
       </para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Change to <menuchoice> <guimenu>Security</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Composing</guimenu> </menuchoice> and check <guimenu>When
      encrypting e-mails, always also encrypt to the certificate of my own
      identify</guimenu>. With this option you can decrypt the message or
      file at any time.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Apply your settings and leave the configuration dialog with
      <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <sect3 id="sec.kontact.crypto.signing">
    <title>Sending Signed Mails</title>
    <para>
     Sign your e-mails to allow the recipient to verify whether these have
     really been sent by you. KMail uses your private key to sign your
     messages and the recipient can verify the signature using your public
     key available on key servers. To sign an e-mail, proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <procedure>
     <step>
      <para>
       Compose your e-mail as usual.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Options</guimenu> <guimenu>Sign
       Message</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If you know the recipient can download your public key from a key
       server, you can omit this step. For convenience reasons, select
       <menuchoice> <guimenu>Attach</guimenu> <guimenu>Attach My Public
       Key</guimenu> </menuchoice> to create an attachment to your e-mail
       containing your public key.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Send your message as usual via <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Message</guimenu> <guimenu>Send Mail</guimenu> </menuchoice>
       and enter your key's passphrase when prompted. KMail signs your
       message using your private key and the recipient can verify the
       signature by the public key attached to your message.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.kontact.crypto.encrypting">
    <title>Sending Encrypted Mails</title>
    <para>
     Use encryption on your e-mails whenever you want to make sure that only
     the recipient can read the contents. To be able to exchange encrypted
     e-mails with another party, get the appropriate public key and use it
     to encrypt your message. At the other end, the private key is then used
     to decrypt the contents of your message. Of course, you can use both
     signatures and encryption on your messages.
    </para>
    <para>
     To send an encrypted e-mail, proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <procedure>
     <step>
      <para>
       Start KGpg with <keycombo> <keycap function="alt">Alt</keycap>
       <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and entering <command>kgpg</command>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Get the recipient's public key:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         If you get it directly from the recipient, import the key with KGpg
         via <menuchoice> <guimenu>Keys</guimenu> <guimenu>Import
         Key</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Access a public key server and import it from there. Select in KGpg
         <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Key Server
         Dialog</guimenu> </menuchoice>, and search for the key. Select the
         respective key and import it into your keyring.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Compose a new message in KMail.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Options</guimenu> <guimenu>Encrypt
       Message</guimenu> </menuchoice>. In the mail window a blue line
       <guimenu>Message will be encrypted</guimenu> is displayed.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Send the mail. A dialog window opens and asks you for the correct
       key.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Check whether all keys are correct.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Enter your passphrase.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kontact.import">
   <title>Importing E-Mail from Other Mail Programs</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Kontact</primary>
   <secondary>importing mail</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    To import e-mail from other applications, select <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Import Messages</guimenu> </menuchoice>
    from the mail view in Kontact. It currently features import filters for
    Outlook Express, the Mbox format, e-mail text format, Pegasus Mail,
    Opera, Evolution, and more. The import utility can also be started
    separately with the command <command>kmailcvt</command>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Select the corresponding application and confirm with
    <guimenu>Continue</guimenu>. A file or a folder must be provided,
    depending on the selected type. KMail then completes the process.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kontact.mail.filter">
   <title>Filters</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Kontact</primary>
   <secondary>filters</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Filters are a convenient method of automatically processing incoming
    mail. They use aspects of the mail such as sender or size, to move mail
    to certain folders, delete unwanted mails, bounce mails back to the
    sender, or perform a number of other actions.
   </para>
   <sect3
    id="sec.kontact.mail.filter.create">
    <title>Setting Up a Filter</title>
    <para>
     To create a filter based on an existing message, right-click the
     desired message then select <guimenu>Create Filter</guimenu> and the
     desired filter criteria. To create a filter from scratch, select
     <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure
     Filters</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Select the match method for filter criteria (all or any). Then select
     criteria that applies only to the desired messages. In <guimenu>Filter
     Actions</guimenu>, set what the filter should do to the messages that
     meet the criteria. The <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> tab provides control
     over whether the filter is applied for specific accounts only.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.kontact.mail.filter.use">
    <title>Applying Filters</title>
    <para>
     Filters are applied in the order listed in the dialog accessed with
     <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure
     Filters</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Change the order by selecting a filter
     and clicking the arrow buttons. Filters are only applied to new
     incoming messages or sent messages as specified in the filter's
     advanced options. To apply filters to existing messages, right-click
     the desired messages and choose <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Messages</guimenu> <guimenu>Apply Filter</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> and the desired filter.
    </para>
    <para>
     If your filters do not act as expected, monitor them with <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Filter Log Viewer</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>. When logging is enabled in this dialog, it shows how
     messages are processed by your filters and can help locate the problem.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kontact.contact">
  <title>Contacts</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Kontact</primary>

  <secondary>contacts</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>Kontact</primary>

  <secondary>address books</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   The contacts component uses KAddressBook. You can also start it
   separately with the command <command>kaddressbook</command>. Configure it
   with <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure
   KAddressBook</guimenu> </menuchoice>. To search for a particular contact,
   use the search bar. With <guimenu>Filter</guimenu>, select to display
   only contacts in a certain category. Right-click a contact to open a menu
   in which to select from a variety of options, such as sending the contact
   information in an e-mail.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.kontact.cont">
   <title>The Kontact Address Book</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kontact-cont.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kontact-cont.png" width="50%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect2 id="sec.kontact.contact.add">
   <title>Adding Contacts</title>
   <para>
    To add a contact with the name and e-mail address from an e-mail,
    right-click the address in the mail component and select <guimenu>Open
    in Address Book</guimenu>. To add a new contact without using an e-mail,
    select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>New
    Contact</guimenu> </menuchoice> in the address component. Both methods
    open a dialog in which to enter information about the contact.
   </para>
   <para>
    In the <guimenu>General</guimenu> tab, enter basic contact information,
    such as name, e-mail addresses, and telephone numbers. Categories can be
    used to sort addresses. <guimenu>Details</guimenu> contains more
    specific information, such as birthday and spouse's name.
   </para>
   <para>
    If your contact uses an instant messenger, you can add these identities
    in <guimenu>IM Addresses</guimenu>. If you do this and have Kopete or
    another KDE chat program running at the same time as Kontact, view
    status information about these identities in Kontact. In <guimenu>Crypto
    Settings</guimenu>, enter the contact's encryption data, such as public
    key.
   </para>
   <para>
    <guimenu>Misc</guimenu> has additional information, such as a photograph
    and the location of the user's Free/Busy information. Use
    <guimenu>Custom Fields</guimenu> to add your own information to the
    contact or address book.
   </para>
   <para>
    Contacts can also be imported in a variety of formats. Use <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Import</guimenu> </menuchoice> and
    select the desired format. Then select the file to import.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kontact.contact.list">
   <title>Creating a Distribution List</title>
   <para>
    If you frequently send e-mail messages to the same group of people, a
    distribution list enables you to store multiple e-mail addresses as a
    single contact item so that you do not need to enter each name
    individually in every e-mail you send to that group. To create a
    distribution list, proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Show Extension
      Bar</guimenu> <guimenu>Distribution List Editor</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>. A new section appears.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>New List</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Enter a name for the list and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Add contacts to the list by dragging them from the address list and
      dropping them in the distribution list window.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use this list like you would an individual contact when creating an
      e-mail.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kontact.contact.books">
   <title>Adding Address Books</title>
   <important>
    <title>Groupware Address Books</title>
    <para>
     <indexterm>
     <primary>Kontact</primary>
     <secondary>GroupWise</secondary>
     </indexterm> <indexterm>
     <primary>Kontact</primary>
     <secondary>Exchange</secondary>
     </indexterm> The best way to add groupware resources is with the
     Groupware Wizard, a separate tool. To use it, close Kontact then run
     <command>groupwarewizard</command> in a command line or from the Office
     group of the KDE menu. Select the server type (such as SLOX, GroupWise,
     or Exchange) from the list offered, then enter the address and
     authentication data. The wizard then adds the available resources to
     Kontact.
    </para>
   </important>
   <para>
    Kontact can access multiple address books, such as shared ones offered
    by Novell GroupWise or an LDAP server. Select <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>View</guimenu> <guimenu>Address Books</guimenu> </menuchoice>
    to view the current address books. Press <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to add
    one then select the type and enter the required information.
   </para>
   <para>
    The check boxes in front of the address books show the activation status
    of each address book. To prevent the display of a book without deleting
    it, uncheck it. <guimenu>Remove</guimenu> deletes the selected book from
    the list.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kontact.cal">
  <title>Calendar</title><indexterm>

  <primary>calendars</primary>

  <secondary>Kontact</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>Kontact</primary>

  <secondary>calendar</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Kontact uses KOrganizer as its calendar component. You can also start it
   separately with the command <command>korganizer</command>. To configure
   it, use <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure
   Calendar</guimenu> </menuchoice>. With the calendar, enter appointments
   and schedule meetings with others. If desired, you can be reminded of
   upcoming events. You can also import, export, and archive calendars with
   the options from the <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.kontact.cal">
   <title>The Kontact Calendar</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kontact-cal.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kontact-cal.png" width="50%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect2 id="sec.kontact.cal.event">
   <title>Scheduling an Event</title>
   <para>
    Add a new event or meeting with <menuchoice> <guimenu>Actions</guimenu>
    <guimenu>New Event</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Enter the desired details.
    Under <guimenu>Reminder</guimenu>, specify the exact time (minutes,
    hours, or days in advance) that the attendees should be reminded of the
    event. If an event recurs, specify the appropriate interval. Another way
    to create an event at a specific point in the calendar is to
    double-click the corresponding field in one of the program's calendar
    views. This opens the same dialog window as that available from the
    menu. Alternatively, select a time range in the Calendar view and
    right-click.
   </para>
   <para>
    Specify the attendees of an event by entering their data manually in the
    dialog or by inserting data from the address book. To enter data
    manually, select <guimenu>New</guimenu>. To import data from the address
    book, click <guimenu>Select Addressee</guimenu> then select the
    corresponding entries from the dialog. To schedule the event based on
    the participants' availability, go to <guimenu>Free/Busy</guimenu> and
    click <guimenu>Pick Date</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Use the <guimenu>Recurrence</guimenu> tab to configure an event that
    happens on a regular basis. <guimenu>Attachments</guimenu> can be
    convenient for linking other information with the event, such as an
    agenda for a meeting.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kontact.cal.cals">
   <title>Adding Calendars</title>
   <important>
    <title>Groupware Calendars</title>
    <para>
     <indexterm>
     <primary>Kontact</primary>
     <secondary>GroupWise</secondary>
     </indexterm> <indexterm>
     <primary>Kontact</primary>
     <secondary>Exchange</secondary>
     </indexterm> The best way to add groupware resources is with Groupware
     Wizard, a separate tool. To use it, close Kontact then run
     <command>groupwarewizard</command> in a command line or from the Office
     group of the KDE menu. Select the server type (such as SLOX, GroupWise,
     or Exchange) from the list offered then enter the address and
     authentication data. The wizard adds the available resources to
     Kontact.
    </para>
   </important>
   <para>
    The calendar module can connect to multiple calendars simultaneously.
    This is useful for combining a personal calendar with an organizational
    one. To add a new calendar, click <guimenu>Add</guimenu> then select the
    calendar type. Complete the necessary fields.
   </para>
   <para>
    The check boxes in front of the calendars show the activation status of
    each. To prevent the display of a calendar without deleting it, uncheck
    it. <guimenu>Remove</guimenu> deletes the selected calendar from the
    list.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
<!-- disabling for 10.3 as we do not have a clue which sync application will -->
<!-- be used in the end -->
<!--
 <sect1 id="sec.kontact.pilot">
  <title>Syncing Data with a Handheld</title>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Kontact</primary>
   <secondary>PDAs and</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>PDAs</primary>
   <secondary>Kontact</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para> Kontact is designed so its data can be synced with handheld devices,
   such as a Palm. View information about the status of KPilot in the summary.
   Refer to FIX ME<xref linkend="cha.kpilot"/> for information about
   configuring and using KPilot.
  </para>
 </sect1>
-->
 <xi:include os="sled" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="apps_kontact_gw_i.xml"
  />
 <sect1 id="sec.kontact.more">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   Kontact includes help for itself and its various components. Access it
   with <menuchoice> <guimenu>Help</guimenu> <guimenu>Kontact
   Handbook</guimenu> </menuchoice>. The project's Web page,
   <ulink url="http://www.kontact.org"/>, is also informative.
  </para><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.e-mail_programs_Kontact"
   /><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.kontact"/>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
