<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.firefox">
 <title>Firefox: Browsing the Web</title>
 <info>
      <abstract>
        <para>
    Included with your &productnamereg; is the Mozilla Firefox Web
    browser. With features like tabbed browsing, pop-up window blocking and
    download and image management, Firefox combines the latest browsing and
    security technologies with an easy-to-use interface. Using tabs, you can
    view more than one Web page in a single window. You can suppress
    annoying advertisements and disable images for faster browsing.
    Firefox's easy access to different search engines helps you find the
    information you need.
   </para>
        <para>
    Start Firefox from the main menu or by entering the command
    <command>firefox</command>. The main program features are described in
    the following sections.
   </para>
      </abstract>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
        </dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="idx.firefox">
 <primary>Firefox</primary></indexterm><indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="idx.browsers.firefox">
 <primary>Web browsers</primary>
 <secondary>Firefox</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>applications</primary>
 <secondary>network</secondary>
 <tertiary>Firefox</tertiary></indexterm>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.firefox.navigating">
  <title>Navigating Web Sites</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Firefox</primary>

  <secondary>navigating</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Firefox has much of the same look and feel as other browsers. It is shown
   in <xref linkend="fig.firefox.main"/>. The navigation toolbar includes
   <guimenu>Forward</guimenu> and <guimenu>Back</guimenu>, the smart
   location bar for a Web address, and the search bar. Bookmarks are also
   available for quick access from the bookmarks toolbar. For more
   information about the various Firefox features, use the
   <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu.
  </para>

  <figure xml:id="fig.firefox.main">
   <title>The Browser Window of Firefox</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="firefox_main.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="firefox_main.png" width="55%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.locationbar">
   <title>The Smart Location Bar</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>location bar</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    When typing into the location bar, an auto-completion drop-down box
    opens, showing the addresses matching what you have typed. The phrase
    that is matched is highlighted with bold letters. The drop-down box
    shows all matching addresses, bookmarks, page titles and tag names from
    your browsing history and your bookmarks list. Matching even works
    across word boundaries. Entries visited most frequently and recently are
    listed first.
   </para>
   <para>
    List entries from the bookmark list are marked with a star. Bookmarks
    with tags are marked with an additional label followed by the tag names.
    List entries from the browsing history are not marked.
   </para>
   <para>
    Use <keycap function="up"/> and <keycap function="down"/> or the mouse
    wheel to scroll through the list. Press <keycap function="enter"/> or
    click an entry to go to the selected page. <keycap function="delete"/>
    removes an entry from the list if it is an entry from the history.
    Bookmarked entries can only be removed by deleting the associated
    bookmark.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.zoom">
   <title>Zooming</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>zoom</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Firefox offers two zooming options: page zoom, the default, and text
    zoom. Page view zooms the entire page as is, with all elements of a
    page, including graphics, expanding equally while text zoom only changes
    the text size.
   </para>
   <para>
    To toggle between page and text zoom, choose <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>View</guimenu> <guimenu>Zoom</guimenu> <guimenu>Zoom Text
    Only</guimenu></menuchoice>. To zoom in or out either use the mouse
    wheel while holding the <keycap function="control"/> key, or use
    <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>+</keycap> </keycombo>
    and <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/>
    <keycap>-</keycap></keycombo>. Reset the zoom factor with <keycombo>
    <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>0</keycap> </keycombo>
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.tabbedbrowsing">
   <title>Tabbed Browsing</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>tabs</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>tabbed browsing</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    If you often use more than one Web page at a time, tabbed browsing makes
    it easier to switch between pages. It allows you to load Web sites in
    separate tabs within one window.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Opening tabs</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To open a new tab, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
       <guimenu>New Tab</guimenu> </menuchoice> or press <keycombo>
       <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>T</keycap> </keycombo>. This
       opens an empty tab in the Firefox window. To open a link on a Web
       page or a bookmark in a tab, middle-click it. Alternatively,
       right-click a link and select <guimenu>Open Link in New
       Tab</guimenu>. You may also open an address in the location bar in a
       new tab with a middle-click or by pressing <keycombo>
       <keycap function="control"/> <keycap function="enter"/> </keycombo>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Closing Tabs</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Right-click a tab to open a context menu, giving you access to tab
       managing options such as closing, reloading, or bookmarking. To close
       a tab, you may also use <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/>
       <keycap>W</keycap> </keycombo> or click the close button. Any closed
       tab can be restored by choosing from <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>History</guimenu> <guimenu>Recently Closed Tabs</guimenu>
       </menuchoice>. In order to reopen the last closed tab either choose
       <guimenu>Undo Close Tab</guimenu> from the context menu or press
       <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/> <keycap function="shift"/>
       <keycap>T</keycap></keycombo>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Sorting Tabs</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       By default, tabs are sorted in the order you opened them. Rearrange
       the tab order by dragging and dropping a tab to the desired position.
       If you have opened a large number of tabs, they will not all be
       displayed in the tab bar. Use the arrows at the ends of the bar to
       move left or right-click the down arrow at the right end of the tab
       bar to get a list of all tabs.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Dragging and Dropping</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Drag and drop also works with tabs. Drag a link onto an existing tab
       to open it in that tab or drag and drop a link on an empty space in
       the tab bar to open a new tab. Drag and drop a tab to the desktop to
       open it in a new browser window.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.sidebar">
   <title>Using the Sidebar</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>sidebar</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Use the left side of your browser window for viewing bookmarks or
    browsing history. Extensions may add new ways to use the sidebar as
    well. To display the sidebar, select <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>View</guimenu> <guimenu>Sidebar</guimenu> </menuchoice> and
    select the desired contents.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.firefox.findinfo">
  <title>Finding Information</title>

  <para>
   There are two ways to find information in Firefox: use the search bar to
   search the Internet with a search engine or the find bar to search the
   page currently displayed.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.searchengine">
   <title>Finding Information on the Web</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>searching with</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>search bar</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>web search</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Firefox has a search bar that can access different engines like Google,
    Yahoo, or Amazon. For example, if you want to find information about
    &suse; using the current engine, click in the search bar, type
    <literal>&suse;</literal>, and hit <keycap function="enter"/>. The
    results appear in your window. To choose your search engine, click the
    icon to the left of the search bar. A menu opens with a list of
    available search engines.
   </para>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.firefox.searchengine.add">
    <title>Customizing the Search Bar</title>
    <para>
     If you want to change the order, add, or delete a search engine,
     establish an Internet connection and proceed as follows.
    </para>
    <procedure>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click the icon to the left of the search bar.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select <guimenu>Manage Search Engines</guimenu> from the menu.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>Remove</guimenu> to delete an entry and <guimenu>Move
       Up/Down</guimenu> to change the order.
      </para>
      <para>
       To add a search engine, click <guimenu>Get More Search
       Engines</guimenu>. Firefox displays a Web page with available
       plug-ins. You can choose from Wikipedia, IMDB, Flickr, and numerous
       others. Click <guimenu>Download Now</guimenu> to install it.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <figure xml:id="fig.firefox.manage_search">
     <title>Manage Search Engines</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="firefox_manage_searchengines.png" width="70%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="firefox_manage_searchengines.png" width="70%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
     Some Web sites offer search engines that you can add directly to the
     search bar. Whenever you enter such a Web site, the icon to the left of
     the search bar turns blue. Click the icon and select the
     <quote>Add</quote> entry from the menu.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.firefox.searchengine.smartkeywords">
    <title>Adding Smart Keywords to Your Online Searches</title><indexterm>
    <primary>Firefox</primary>
    <secondary>smart keywords</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     Firefox lets you define your own <emphasis>smart keywords</emphasis>:
     abbreviations to use as a URL shortcut for a particular search engine.
     If you define <literal>ws</literal> as a smart keyword for the
     Wikipedia search for example, you can now type <literal>ws
     <replaceable>SEARCHTERM</replaceable></literal> into the location bar
     to search Wikipedia for <replaceable>SEARCHTERM</replaceable>.
    </para>
    <para>
     To assign a shortcut for a search engine from the search bar, click the
     icon to the left of the search bar and open the <guimenu>Manage Search
     Engines</guimenu> dialog. Mark a search engine and open the
     <guimenu>Edit Keyword</guimenu> dialog.
    </para>
    <para>
     It is also possible to define a smart keyword for any search field on a
     Web site. Proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <procedure>
     <step>
      <para>
       Right-click the search field and choose <guimenu>Add a Keyword for
       this Search</guimenu> from the menu that opens. The <guimenu>Add
       Bookmark</guimenu> dialog appears.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       In <guimenu>Name</guimenu>, enter a descriptive name for this smart
       keyword.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Enter your <guimenu>Keyword</guimenu> for this search.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Choose the location where to save this smart keyword with
       <guimenu>Create In</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Finalize with <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <tip>
     <title>Smart Keywords for Regular Web sites</title>
     <para>
      Using smart keywords is not restricted to search engines. You can also
      add a smart keyword to a bookmark (via the bookmark's properties). For
      example, if you assign <literal>suse</literal> to the &suse; home
      page bookmark, you can open it by typing <literal>suse</literal> into
      the location bar.
     </para>
    </tip>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.findinfo.page">
   <title>Searching in the Current Page</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>finding on page</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    To search inside a Web page, click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Find in This Page</guimenu> </menuchoice> or press <keycombo>
    <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>F</keycap> </keycombo>. The find
    bar opens. It is usually displayed at the bottom of a window. Type your
    query in the text box. Firefox finds the first occurrence of this phrase
    as you type. You can find other occurrences of the phrase by pressing
    <keycap>F3</keycap> or the <guimenu>Next</guimenu> button in the find
    bar. Clicking the <guimenu>Highlight All</guimenu> button will highlight
    all occurrences of the phrase. Checking the <guimenu>Match
    Case</guimenu> option makes the query case-sensitive.
   </para><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>quickfind</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Firefox also offers two quick-find options. Click anywhere you like to
    start a search on a Web page, type the key <keycap>/</keycap>
    immediately followed by the search term. The first occurrence of the
    search term will be highlighted as you type. Use <keycap>F3</keycap> to
    find the next occurrence. It is also possible to limit quick-find to
    links only. This search option is available by typing the key
    <keycap>'</keycap>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.firefox.bookmarks">
  <title>Managing Bookmarks</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Firefox</primary>

  <secondary>bookmarks</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Bookmarks offer a convenient way of saving links to your favorite Web
   sites. Firefox not only makes it very easy to add new bookmarks with just
   one mouse click, it also offers multiple ways to manage large bookmark
   collections.
   You can sort bookmarks into folders, classify them with tags, or filter them
   with smart bookmarks.
  </para>

  <para>
   Add a bookmark by clicking the star in the location bar. The star will
   turn yellow to indicate the page is bookmarked. Clicking once will save
   the bookmark in the <guimenu>Unsorted Bookmarks</guimenu> folder under
   the page title. Double click the star to open a menu which lets you
   choose a location where to save the bookmark and lets you enter a name
   and tags. Bookmarking all open tabs is done via the context menu.
   Right-click in a tab and choose <guimenu>Bookmark All Tabs</guimenu>.
   Firefox asks you to create a new folder for the tab links. To remove or
   edit a bookmark, open it and click the star in the location bar.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.bookmarks.organise">
   <title>Organizing Bookmarks</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>bookmarks</secondary>
   <tertiary>managing</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>bookmarks</secondary>
   <tertiary>Library</tertiary></indexterm>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>Library</guimenu> can be used to manage the properties
    (name and address location) for each bookmark and organize the bookmarks
    into folders and sections. It resembles
    <xref linkend="fig.firefox.library"/>.
   </para>
   <figure xml:id="fig.firefox.library">
    <title>The Firefox Bookmark Library</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="firefox_library.png" width="95%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="firefox_library.png" width="95%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    To open the <guimenu>Library</guimenu>, click <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu> <guimenu>Show All Bookmarks</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>. The library window is split into two parts: the left pane
    shows the folder tree view, the right pane the subfolders and bookmarks
    of the selected folder. Use <guimenu>Views</guimenu> to customize the
    right pane. The left pane contains three main folders:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>History</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Contains your complete browsing history. You cannot alter this list
       other than by deleting entries from it.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Tags</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Lists bookmarks for each tag you have specified. See
       <xref linkend="sec.firefox.bookmarks.tags"/> for more information on
       tags.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>All Bookmarks</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This category contains the three main bookmark folders:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>Bookmarks Toolbar</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Contains the bookmarks and folders displayed beneath the location
          bar. See <xref linkend="sec.firefox.bookmarks.toolbar"/> for more
          information.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>Bookmarks Menu</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Holds the bookmarks and folder accessible via the
          <guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu> entry in the main menu or the
          bookmarks side menu.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>Unsorted Bookmarks</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Contains all bookmarks created with a single click the star in the
          location bar. This folder is only visible in the library and the
          bookmarks sidebar.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    Organize your bookmarks using the right pane. Choose actions for folders
    or bookmarks either from the context menu that opens when you
    right-click an item or from the <guimenu>Organize</guimenu> menu. The
    properties of a chosen folder or bookmark can be edited in the bottom
    part of the right pane. By default, only <guimenu>Name</guimenu>,
    <guimenu>Location</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Tags</guimenu> are displayed
    for a bookmark. Click <guimenu>More</guimenu> to gain access to all
    properties.
   </para>
   <para>
    Use drag and drop to rearrange your bookmarks. Left-click a bookmark and
    drag it to a new position while holding the mouse button pressed. Drop
    it by releasing the mouse button. You can use this technique to move a
    bookmark or a folder to a different folder, or to change the order of
    bookmarks in a folder.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.bookmarks.tags">
   <title>Tags</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>bookmarks</secondary>
   <tertiary>tags</tertiary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Tags offer a convenient way to file a bookmark under several categories.
    You can tag a bookmark with as much terms as you want. For example, to
    access all sites tagged with <literal>suse</literal> enter
    <literal>suse</literal> into the location bar. What's more, a smart
    bookmark folder for each tag is automatically created in the tags folder
    of the library. Drag and drop a smart bookmark for a tag onto your
    bookmark toolbar or into a folder of your bookmarks menu to easily
    access it.
   </para>
   <para>
    To add tags to a bookmark, open the bookmark in Firefox and click the
    yellow star in the location bar. The <guimenu>Edit This
    Bookmark</guimenu> dialog opens where you can add a comma separated list
    of tags. It is also possible to add tags via the bookmark's properties
    dialog which you can open in the library or by right-clicking a bookmark
    in the menu or the toolbar.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.bookmarks.imexport">
   <title>Importing and Exporting Bookmarks</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>bookmarks</secondary>
   <tertiary>importing</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>bookmarks</secondary>
   <tertiary>exporting</tertiary></indexterm>
   <para>
    If you used a different browser in the past, you probably want to use
    your old bookmarks in Firefox, too. Firefox can automatically import
    bookmarks from other browsers installed on your system, such as Netscape
    or Opera. You also can import bookmarks from a file exported from a
    browser on a different computer or from a backup.
   </para>
   <para>
    To import bookmarks from another browser or from a file in HTML format,
    open the library by choosing <menuchoice> <guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Show All Bookmarks</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Start the Import
    Wizard by choosing <menuchoice> <guimenu>Import and Backup</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Import Bookmarks from HTML</guimenu> </menuchoice> and choose
    an import location. Start the import by clicking
    <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. Bookmarks from another browser are imported to
    a separate folder under the bookmarks menu named <filename>From
    <replaceable>Browser Name</replaceable> </filename>. Imports from an
    HTML file are imported as is.
   </para>
   <para>
    Exporting bookmarks is also done via the <guimenu>Import and
    Backup</guimenu> dialog in the library window. To save your bookmarks as
    an HTML file, choose <guimenu>Export Boomarks to HTML</guimenu>. In
    order to create or restore a backup of your bookmarks, choose
    <guimenu>Backup</guimenu> or <guimenu>Restore</guimenu>. Firefox uses
    the JavaScript Object Notation file format (<filename>.json</filename>)
    for backups.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.bookmarks.live">
   <title>Live Bookmarks</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>bookmarks</secondary>
   <tertiary>live bookmarks</tertiary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Live bookmarks display headlines in your bookmark menu and keep you up
    to date with the latest news. This enables you to save time with one
    glance at your favorite sites. Live bookmarks update automatically.
   </para>
   <para>
    Many sites and blogs support this format. A Web site indicates this by
    showing an orange icon in the right part of the location bar. Click the
    icon and choose <guimenu>Subscribe Now</guimenu> in the page that opens.
    A dialog opens in which to select the name and location of your live
    bookmark. Confirm with <guimenu>Add</guimenu>. This page also lets you
    choose alternative applications to subscribe to, such as
    <guimenu>Bloglines</guimenu>, or <guimenu>My Yahoo</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.bookmarks.smart">
   <title>Smart Bookmarks</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>bookmarks</secondary>
   <tertiary>smart bookmarks</tertiary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Smart bookmarks are virtual bookmark folders that are dynamically
    updated. By default, three smart bookmark folders are already
    predefined: the <guimenu>Most Visited</guimenu> links are available from
    your bookmarks toolbar, <guimenu>Recently Bookmarked</guimenu> links and
    <guimenu>Recent Tags</guimenu> are located in the bookmarks menu.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.bookmarks.toolbar">
   <title>The Bookmarks Toolbar</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>bookmarks</secondary>
   <tertiary>toolbar</tertiary></indexterm>
   <para>
    The <literal>Bookmarks Toolbar</literal> is displayed beneath the
    location bar and lets you quickly access bookmarks. You can also add,
    organize, and edit bookmarks directly. By default, the
    <literal>Bookmarks Toolbar</literal> is populated with a predefined set
    of bookmarks organized into several folders (see
    <xref linkend="fig.firefox.main"/>).
   </para>
   <para>
    To manage the <literal>Bookmarks Toolbar</literal> you can use the
    library as described in
    <xref linkend="sec.firefox.bookmarks.organise"/>. Its content is located
    in the <guimenu>Bookmarks Toolbar Folder</guimenu>. It is also possible
    to manage the toolbar directly. To add a folder, bookmark, or separator,
    right-click an empty space in the toolbar and select the appropriate
    entry from the pop-up menu. To add the current page to the bar use drag
    and drop: left-click the Web page's icon in the location bar and drag it
    to the desired position on the bookmarks toolbar while pressing the
    mouse button. Hovering over an existing bookmark folder will
    automatically open it, enabling you to place the bookmark within this
    folder.
   </para>
   <para>
    To manage a certain folder or bookmark, right-click it. A pop-up menu
    opens which lets you <guimenu>Delete</guimenu> it or change its
    <guimenu>Properties</guimenu>. To move or copy an entry, choose
    <guimenu>Cut</guimenu>, or <guimenu>Copy</guimenu> and
    <guimenu>Paste</guimenu> it to the desired position.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.firefox.downloadmanager">
  <title>Using the Download Manager</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Firefox</primary>

  <secondary>download manager</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>download managers</primary>

  <secondary>Firefox</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Keep track of your current and past downloads with the help of the
   download manager. It automatically opens every time you download a file.
   To manually start the download manager, click <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Downloads</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
   While downloading a file, a progress bar indicates the download status.
   If necessary, pause the download and resume it later. To open a
   downloaded file with the associated application, click
   <guimenu>Open</guimenu>. To open the location to which the file was
   saved, choose <guimenu>Open Containing Folder</guimenu>. <guimenu>Remove
   From List</guimenu> only deletes the entry from the download manager, it
   does not delete the file from the hard disk.
  </para>

  <para>
<!-- is this still true ? -->
   By default, all files are downloaded to your desktop. To change this
   behavior, open the download manager's configuration window from
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu>
   </menuchoice> and go to the <guimenu>General</guimenu> tab. In the
   <guimenu>Download</guimenu> area, either choose another location or
   <guimenu>Always Ask Me Where to Save Files</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>Resuming Downloads</title>
   <para>
    If your browser crashes or is closed while downloading, all pending
    downloads will automatically be resumed in the background when starting
    Firefox the next time. A download that was paused before the browser was
    closed can manually be resumed via the download manager.
   </para>
  </tip>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.firefox.security">
  <title>Security</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Firefox</primary>

  <secondary>security</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Since browsing the Internet has become more risky, Firefox offers various
   measures to make browsing safer. It automatically checks whether you are
   trying to access a site known to contain harmful software (malware) or a
   site known to steal sensitive data (phishing) and stops you from entering
   these sites. The Instant Web Site ID lets you easily check a site's
   legitimacy, and a password manager and the pop-up blocker offer
   additional security. With Private Browsing you can surf the Internet
   without Firefox recording any data on your computer.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.security.instant_id">
   <title>Instant Web Site ID</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>site identity</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Firefox allows you to check the identity of a Web page with a single
    glance. The color of the Web site's icon (also called favicon) in the
    location bar to the left of the address indicates which identity
    information is available and whether communication is encrypted or not:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Gray</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The site does not provide any identity information and communication
       between Web server and browser is not encrypted. This is fine as long
       as you do not exchange sensitive information with this site. Most Web
       sites will be <quote>gray</quote>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Blue</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This site is from a domain that has been verified by a certificate,
       so you can be sure that you are really connected to the very site it
       claims to be. Communication with a <quote>blue</quote> server is
       always encrypted.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Green</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This site completely identifies itself by a certificate that ensures
       a site is owned by the person or organization it claims to be. This
       is especially important when exchanging very sensitive data (for
       example when doing money transactions over the Internet). In this
       case you can be sure to be on your bank's Web site when it sends
       complete identity information. Communication with a
       <quote>green</quote> server is always encrypted.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    To view detailed identity information, click the Web site's icon in the
    location bar. In the opening pop-up click <guimenu>More
    Information</guimenu> to open the Page Info Window. Here, you can view
    the site's certificate and the encryption level, as well as information
    about stored passwords and cookies.
   </para>
   <para>
    With the <guimenu>Permissions</guimenu> view you can set per-site
    permissions for image loading, pop-ups, cookies and installation
    permissions. The <guimenu>Media</guimenu> view lists all images,
    background graphics and embedded objects from a site and displays
    further information on each item together with a preview. It also lets
    you save each individual item.
   </para>
   <figure xml:id="fig.firefox.pageinfo">
    <title>The Firefox Page Info Window</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="firefox_page_info.png" width="70%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="firefox_page_info.png" width="70%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.firefox.security.instant_id.cert_import">
    <title>Importing Certificates</title>
    <para>
     Firefox comes with a certificate store for identifying certification
     authorities (CA). Using these certificates enables the browser to
     automatically verify certificates issued by Web sites. If a Web site
     issues a certificate that has not been signed by one of the CAs from
     the certificate store, it is not trusted. This ensures that no spoofed
     certificates are accepted.
    </para>
    <para>
     Large organizations usually use their own certification authorities
     in-house and distribute the respective certificates via the system-wide
     certification store located at <filename>/etc/pki/nssdb</filename>. To
     configure Firefox (and all other Mozilla tools such as Thunderbird) to
     use this system-wide CA store in addition to its own, you need to
     export the <envar>NSS_USE_SHARED_DB</envar> variable, for example by
     adding the following line to <filename>~/.bashrc</filename>:
    </para>
<screen>export NSS_USE_SHARED_DB=1</screen>
    <para>
     Alternatively or additionally you can manually import certificates via
     <menuchoice><guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> <guimenu>Encryption</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Your Certificates</guimenu></menuchoice> in the
     <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu> dialog. Make sure to only import
     certificates you can absolutely trust!
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.security.passwords">
   <title>Password Management</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>passwords</secondary></indexterm><indexterm os="sled">
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>CASA</secondary></indexterm><indexterm os="sled">
   <primary>CASA</primary>
   <secondary>Firefox</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Each time you enter a user name and a password on a Web site, Firefox
    offers to store this data. A new toolbar on top of the page opens,
    asking you whether you want Firefox to remember the password. If you
    accept by clicking <guimenu>Remember</guimenu>, the password will be
    stored on your hard disk in an encrypted format. The next time you
    access this site, Firefox will automatically fill in the login data.
   </para>
   <para>
    To review or manage your passwords, open the password manager by
    clicking <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu> <guimenu>Security</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Saved Passwords</guimenu> </menuchoice>. The password manager
    opens with a list of sites and their corresponding user names. By
    default, the passwords are not displayed. You can click <guimenu>Show
    Passwords</guimenu> to display them. Delete single or all entries from
    the list using <guimenu>Remove</guimenu> or <guimenu>Remove
    All</guimenu>, respectively.
   </para>
   <para>
    To protect your passwords from unauthorized access, you can set a master
    password that is required when managing or adding passwords. Open the
    <guimenu>Security</guimenu> tab on the <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu>
    dialog and check <guimenu>Use a Master Password</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.security.private_browsing">
   <title>Private Browsing</title>
   <para>
    By default, Firefox keeps track of your browsing history by storing
    content and links of visited Web sites, cookies, downloads, passwords,
    search terms and formula data. Collecting and storing this data makes
    browsing faster and more convenient. However, when you use a public
    terminal or a friend's computer, for example, you might want to turn it
    off. In Private Browsing mode Firefox will not keep track of your
    browsing history nor will it cache the content of pages you have
    visited.
   </para>
   <para>
    Enable the Private Browsing mode by either clicking <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>New Private
    Window</guimenu></menuchoice> or by pressing <keycombo>
    <keycap function="control"/> <keycap function="shift"/>
    <keycap>P</keycap></keycombo>. The current Web site and all open tabs
    will be replaced by the Private Browsing information screen. As long as
    you will browse in private mode, the string <literal>(Private
    Browsing)</literal> will be displayed in the window's titlebar.
   </para>
   <para>
    Disable Private Browsing by closing the private window.
<!--either clicking <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Stop Private
    Browsing</guimenu></menuchoice> or by pressing <keycombo>
    <keycap function="control"/> <keycap function="shift"/>
    <keycap>P</keycap> </keycombo>. Your previous session will be restored.-->
   </para>
   <para>
    To make Private Browsing the default mode, open the
    <guimenu>Privacy</guimenu> tab in the Preference window as described in
    <xref linkend="sec.firefox.preferences"/>, set <guimenu>Firefox
    will:</guimenu> to <guimenu>Use custom settings for history</guimenu>
    and then choose <guimenu>Always use private browsing mode</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <warning>
    <title>Bookmarks and Downloads</title>
    <para>
     Downloads and bookmarks you made during Private Browsing mode will be
     kept.
    </para>
   </warning>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.firefox.customizing">
  <title>Customizing Firefox</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Firefox</primary>

  <secondary>configuring</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Firefox can be customized extensively. You can not only change the way
   Firefox behaves (by altering its preferences), but also add additional
   functionality (by installing extensions) or change the look and feel (by
   installing new themes). With the Add-ons manager, Firefox offers a
   convenient way to manage extensions, themes and plug-ins.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.preferences">
   <title>Preferences</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>preferences</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Firefox offers a wide range of configuration options available via
    <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>, see <xref linkend="fig.firefox.preferences"/>. Each
    option is described in detail in the online help, which can be accessed
    by clicking the <guimenu>Help</guimenu> button.
   </para>
   <figure xml:id="fig.firefox.preferences">
    <title>The Preferences Window</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="firefox_preferences.png" width="70%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="firefox_preferences.png" width="70%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.firefox.preferences.sessions">
    <title>Session management</title><indexterm>
    <primary>Firefox</primary>
    <secondary>session management</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     By default, Firefox automatically restores your
     session&mdash;windows and tabs&mdash; only after it has crashed,
     or after a restart when having installed an extension. However, it can
     be configured to restore a session every time it is started: Open the
     Preferences dialog as described in
     <xref linkend="sec.firefox.preferences"/> and go to the
     <guimenu>General</guimenu> tab. Set <guimenu>When Firefox
     Starts:</guimenu> to <guimenu>Show My Windows and Tabs from Last
     Time</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     When you have multiple windows open they will only be restored the next
     time when you close all of them at once with <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Quit</guimenu> </menuchoice> or with
     <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>Q</keycap> </keycombo>.
     If you close the windows one by one, only the last window will be
     restored.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.firefox.preferences.language">
    <title>Language Preferences for Web Sites</title><indexterm>
    <primary>Firefox</primary>
    <secondary>language</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     When sending a request to a Web server, the browser always sends the
     information about which language is preferred by the user. Web sites
     that are available in more than one language (and are configured to
     evaluate this language parameter) will display their pages in the
     language the browser requests. On &productname;, the preferred
     language is preconfigured to use the same language as the desktop. To
     change this setting, open the <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu> window as
     described in <xref linkend="sec.firefox.preferences"/>, go to the
     <guimenu>Content</guimenu> tab and <guimenu>Choose</guimenu> your
     preferred language.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.firefox.preferences.spelling">
    <title>Spell Checking</title><indexterm>
    <primary>Firefox</primary>
    <secondary>spell-checking</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     When typing into multiple-line text boxes, Firefox, by default,
     spell-checks what you type. Misspelled words are underlined in red. To
     correct a word, right-click it and select the correct spelling from the
     context menu. You may also add the word to the dictionary, if it is
     correct.
    </para>
    <para>
     To change or add a dictionary, right-click anywhere in a multi-line
     text box and select the appropriate option from the context menu. Here
     you may also disable spell-checking for this text box. If you want to
     globally disable spell checking, open the
     <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu> window as described in
     <xref linkend="sec.firefox.preferences"/> and go to the
     <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> tab. Uncheck <guimenu>Check My Spelling As
     I Type</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.firefox.extensions">
   <title>Add-ons</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>add-ons</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>extensions</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>themes</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Extensions let you personalize Firefox to exactly fit your needs. With
    the help of extensions you can change Firefox's look and feel, enhance
    existing functionality (such as the download manager or tabbed
    browsing), and add functions (such as a blog editor, Bit Torrent support
    or even a music player). Certain extensions also assist Web developers,
    while others increase security by dynamically blocking active content.
    More than 5000 extensions are available for Firefox. With the add-ons
    manager you cannot only install new extensions, but also disable,
    enable, or delete them. It also finds updates for installed extensions.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you do not like the standard look and feel of Firefox, install a new
    <emphasis>theme</emphasis>. Themes do not change the functionality, only
    the appearance of the browser.
   </para>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.firefox.extensions.install">
    <title>Installing Add-ons</title><indexterm>
    <primary>Firefox</primary>
    <secondary>add-ons</secondary>
    <tertiary>installing</tertiary></indexterm>
    <para>
     To add an extension or theme, start the add-ons manager with
     <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Add-Ons</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>. It opens with the <guimenu>Get Add-Ons</guimenu> tab
     either displaying a choice of recommended add-ons or the results of
     your last search. Use the <guimenu>Search All Add-Ons</guimenu> field
     to search for specific add-ons. Click an entry in the list to view a
     short description and a screenshot. Install the add-on by clicking
     <guimenu>Add to Firefox</guimenu> or open a Web page with detailed
     information by clicking the <guimenu>Learn More</guimenu> link.
    </para>
    <figure xml:id="fig.firefox.extensions">
     <title>Installing Firefox Extensions</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="firefox_addon_manager.png" width="70%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="firefox_addon_manager.png" width="70%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
     If you want to browse all available add-ons or want to use advanced
     search options, click <guimenu>Browse All Add-Ons</guimenu>. This opens
     the Firefox add-ons Web page. To install an extension, click on the
     <guimenu>Add to Firefox</guimenu> button on the page describing the
     add-on.
    </para>
    <para>
     In order to activate freshly installed extensions or themes, Firefox
     needs to be restarted via the <guimenu>Restart Firefox</guimenu> button
     in the add-ons manager. Restarting the browser with this button ensures
     that the complete session will be restored.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.firefox.extensions.manage">
    <title>Managing Add-ons</title><indexterm>
    <primary>Firefox</primary>
    <secondary>add-ons</secondary>
    <tertiary>managing</tertiary></indexterm>
    <para>
     The Add-ons Manager also offers a convenient interface to manage
     extensions, themes, and plug-ins. <guimenu>Extensions</guimenu> can be
     enabled, disabled or uninstalled. If an extension is configurable, its
     configuration options can be accessed via the
     <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu> button. In the <guimenu>Themes</guimenu>
     tab you may <guimenu>Uninstall</guimenu> a theme, or activate a
     different theme by clicking <guimenu>Use Theme</guimenu>. Pending
     extension and theme installations are also listed. Select
     <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu> to stop the installation. Although you cannot
     install <guimenu>Plug-Ins</guimenu> as a user, you may disable or
     enable them with the Add-ons manager.
    </para>
    <para>
     Actions like uninstalling or disabling an add-on require a browser
     restart. Each time you perform such an action, the <guimenu>Restart
     Browser</guimenu> button is displayed in the add-ons manager.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

<!--  <sect2 id="sec.firefox.lockdown"
   os="sled">
   <title>Disabling Features</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Firefox</primary>
   <secondary>lockdown</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    <remark condition="generic"> 2008-02-29 - fs: Fate #302023 and #300976 </remark>
    For special-use cases (for instance when using &productname; as an
    Internet terminal) it is recommended to disable (lockdown) certain
    features, such as saving or printing a page, viewing the page source or
    disabling the cache. This can be achieved by using the GConf system. See
    <xref linkend="sec.gnome.gconf.lockdown"/> for detailed information.
   </para>
  </sect2>-->
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.firefox.printing">
  <title>Printing from Firefox</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Firefox</primary>

  <secondary>printing</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>printing</primary>

  <secondary>Firefox</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Before you actually print a Web page, you can use the print preview
   function to control how the printed page will look like. Choose
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Print Preview</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>. Configure paper size and orientation per printer with
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Page Setup</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <para>
   To print a Web page either choose <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Print</guimenu> </menuchoice> or press
   <keycombo><keycap function="control"/><keycap>P</keycap></keycombo>. The
   Printer dialog opens. To print with the default options click
   <guimenu>Print</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   The Printer dialog also offers extensive configuration options to
   fine-tune the printout. On the <guimenu>General</guimenu> tab, choose a
   printer, the range to print, the number of copies and the order.
   <guimenu>Page Setup</guimenu> lets you specify the number of pages per
   side, the scaling factor as well as paper source and type. You can also
   activate double-sided printing here if the printer supports it. Control
   how frames, backgrounds, header and footer are printed on the
   <guimenu>Options</guimenu> tab. You may also specify
   <guimenu>Job</guimenu> options, such as printing at a specific time, and
   the <guimenu>Image Quality</guimenu> in this dialog.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <!--
   We used to have section here that explained how to open/create MHTML files.
   However, the firefox-mhtml package is not maintained anymore. Should we still
   need this functionality, there is this add-on:
   https://addons.mozilla.org/en-GB/firefox/addon/mozilla-archive-format
   Relevant old FATE: FATE#302866. - sknorr, 2015-09-23
 -->

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.firefox.flashplayer.props">
  <title>Controlling Adobe Flash Player Settings</title>

  <para>
   <remark condition="generic">taroth 2013-02-20 - Fate #313848</remark>
   You can control the settings of the Adobe Flash Player plug-in with a
   local settings manager. Start the <guimenu>Adobe Flash Player
   Settings</guimenu> from the main menu or run
   <command>flash-player-properties</command> from a command line. The
   dialog allows you to define your preferences with regard to
   <guimenu>Storage</guimenu>, <guimenu>Camera and Mic</guimenu>,
   <guimenu>Playback</guimenu> and to change some advanced settings. For
   more information, refer to
   <link xlink:href="http://www.macromedia.com/support/documentation/en/flashplayer/help/settings_manager.html"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.firefox.moreinfo">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   Get more information about Firefox from the official knowledge base
   available via <keycap>F1</keycap>. More useful information is available
   from the following links:
  </para>

  <simplelist>
   <member><emphasis>Support forum</emphasis>: <link xlink:href="http://support.mozilla.com/forum"/>
   </member>
   <member><emphasis>Main Menu reference</emphasis>: <link xlink:href="http://support.mozilla.com/kb/Menu+reference"/>
   </member>
   <member><emphasis>Preferences reference</emphasis>: <link xlink:href="http://support.mozilla.com/kb/Options+window"/>
   </member>
   <member><emphasis>Keyboard shortcuts</emphasis>: <link xlink:href="http://support.mozilla.com/kb/Keyboard+shortcuts"/>
   </member>
  </simplelist><indexterm startref="idx.firefox" class="endofrange"/><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.browsers.firefox"/>
 </sect1>
</chapter>