<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!--taroth 2013-02-18: SLED 11 SP3 contains pidgin 2.6.6-->
<!-- SLE 12 ships with Empathy, Pidgin needs to be installed later ... We should
probably replace the Pidgin & Ekiga chapters with an Empathy chapter at some point.
- sknorr, 2015-09-22 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.gnome.empathy">
 <title>Empathy: Instant Messaging</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
   </dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  Empathy is an instant messaging (IM) client that
  allows you to connect to multiple accounts simultaneously. Chat live with
  your contacts in one tabbed interface, regardless of which IM system they
  use. Empathy uses Telepathy for protocol support.
 </para>
 <para> Empathy supports the following instant messaging protocols: Google Talk 
  (Jabber/XMPP), MSN, IRC, Salut, AIM, Facebook, Yahoo!, Gadu Gadu, Groupwise&reg;, 
  ICQ and QQ. (The supported protocols depend on installed Telepathy Connection 
  Manager components.)
 </para>
 <para>
  In the following, learn how to set up Empathy and how to communicate with
  your contacts.
 </para>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.empathy.start">
  <title>Starting Empathy</title>

  <para>
   To start Empathy, select
   <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guimenu>Internet</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Empathy</guimenu></menuchoice>.
  </para>

 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.empathy.configure">
  <title>Configuring Accounts</title>

  <para>
   To use Empathy, you must already have an account for the messaging service
   you want to use. For example, to use Empathy to chat via AIM, you must
   first have an AIM account.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Adding and Editing Accounts in Empathy</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     To start Empathy, select
     <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guimenu>Internet</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Empathy</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you start Empathy for the first time, a message appears, prompting
     you to configure an account.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter your account data. The <guimenu>Messaging
     and VoIP Accounts</guimenu> dialog shows the accounts that have been 
     configured so far.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To add another account:</para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>In the <guimenu>Messaging and VoIP Accounts</guimenu> dialog, 
       click the plus icon.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para> Choose the type of account you want to configure, enter your user
       ID and password for the account and click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>. The
       dialog to add or modify accounts differs for each type of account,
       depending on what setup options are available for that account.</para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
    </step>
   <step>
    <para>To enter or modify connection data for an account:</para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>Select the account and click <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Edit Connection Parameters</guimenu>
        <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu>
       </menuchoice>.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Enter a server name and a port to use for the connection. Specify additional parameters,
       such as encryption options, if necessary. If you are unsure which parameters to use, refer to
       your <phrase os="sled;sles">system administrator or</phrase> messaging service. </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Click <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> to confirm your changes.</para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   To go online with your account, turn the account switch on. When prompted for
   your password, enter it.
  </para>
  <para>
  To disable the account, turn the switch off. If you are finished with the
  configuration of your accounts, close the <guimenu>Messaging
   and VoIP Accounts</guimenu> dialog.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.empathy.buddy_list">
  <title>Managing Contacts</title>

  <para>
   Use the <guimenu>Contact List</guimenu> to manage your contacts.
   You can add and remove contacts and organize them in groups,
   so they are easy to find.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Adding Contacts</title>
   <step>
    <para>To add a contact, click <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Contacts</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Add Contacts</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Select the <guimenu>Account</guimenu> for which you want to add a contact.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>As <guimenu>Identifier</guimenu>, enter the name or user ID of the person you want to
     add.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>By default, <guimenu>Alias</guimenu> will show the same entry, but you can enter a
     different name or nickname for the contact person here.</para>
    <para>As soon as you start typing into the <guimenu>Identifier</guimenu> text box, the dialog
     will also show any groups that you have already defined.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>To add the new contact to a group, activate the respective group's check box.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>To create a new group, type a group name into the text box next to <guimenu>Add
      Group</guimenu> and click <guimenu>Add Group</guimenu>.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Click <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to confirm your changes and to close the dialog.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>In case the groups or the newly added contacts are not displayed in the
   <guimenu>Contact List</guimenu>, check the Empathy preferences by clicking
   <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu>
    <guimenu>General</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>. Activate <guimenu>Show offline contacts</guimenu> and
   <guimenu>Show groups</guimenu> to make all contacts and groups appear in
   the <guimenu>Contact List</guimenu>.
  </para>
   <para> To remove a contact from the list, right-click the name of that contact,
    select <guimenu>Remove</guimenu> and confirm your choice. </para>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.empathy.chat">
  <title>Chatting with Friends</title>

  <para>
   It is necessary to be connected to the Internet to be able to chat with
   other participants. After a successful login, you are usually marked as
   <guimenu>Available</guimenu> in the <guimenu>Contact List</guimenu>, and thus
   visible to others. To change your status, click the drop-down box at the top of
   the <guimenu>Contact List</guimenu> and select another option.
  </para>

  <para>
   To open a chat session, double-click a contact name in the
   <guimenu>Contact List</guimenu>. The
   chat screen opens. Type your message, then press <keycap function="enter"/>
   to send.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you open more than one chat session, the new session appears as a tab
   in the existing chat window.
   To see all messages of a session and to be able to write a reply, click the
   tab of that session.
   To see multiple session side by side, use the mouse to drag a tab out of the
   window.
   A second window will open.
  </para>
  <para>
   To close a chat session, close the tab or window for it.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.empathy.more">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   This chapter explained the Empathy options you need to know about to set
   up Empathy and communicate with your contacts. It does not explain all of
   features and options available.
   For more information, open Empathy, then click
  <guimenu>Help</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   For updates about new features and for the latest information, refer to
   the home page of the project at 
   <link xlink:href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Apps/Empathy"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
