<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.gimp">
 <title>GIMP: Manipulating Graphics</title><indexterm id="idx.gimp"
  class="startofrange">
 <primary>GIMP</primary></indexterm><indexterm id="idx.graphics.editing" class="startofrange">
 <primary>graphics</primary>
 <secondary>editing</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>applications</primary>
 <secondary>graphics</secondary>
 <tertiary>GIMP</tertiary></indexterm>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   GIMP (<emphasis>the GNU Image Manipulation Program</emphasis>) is a
   program for creating and editing raster graphics. In most aspects, its
   features are comparable to those of Adobe Photoshop and other commercial
   programs. Use it to resize and retouch photographs, design graphics for
   Web pages, create covers for your custom CDs, or almost any other
   graphics project. It meets the needs of both amateurs and professionals.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <para>
  Like many other Linux programs, GIMP is developed as a cooperative effort
  of developers worldwide who volunteer their time and code to the project.
  The program is under constant development, so the version included in your
  system may vary slightly from the version discussed here. The layout of
  the individual windows and window sections is especially likely to vary.
 </para>
 <para>
  GIMP is an extremely complex program. Only a small range of features,
  tools, and menu items are discussed in this chapter. See
  <xref linkend="sec.gimp.moreinfo"/> for ideas of where to find more
  information about the program.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.gimp.graphics"
   >
  <title>Graphics Formats</title><indexterm>

  <primary>graphics</primary>

  <secondary>pixel</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>graphics</primary>

  <secondary>vector</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   There are two main types of graphics&mdash;raster and vector. GIMP is
   intended for working with raster graphics, which is the normal format for
   digital photographs or scanned images. Raster image is a collection of
   pixels&mdash;small blocks of color that together create the entire image.
   High resolution images contain large number of pixels and image files can
   easily become quite large because of this. It is also not possible to
   increase the size of a pixel image without losing quality. GIMP supports
   all the common formats of raster graphics, like JPEG, PNG, GIF, BMP,
   TIFF, and more.
<!--FIXME LATER raw-->
  </para>

  <para>
   Unlike raster graphics, vector graphics do not store information for all
   individual pixels. Instead, it uses geometrical primitives such as
   points, lines, curves, and polygons. Vector images can be scaled very
   easily and image files can be smaller. The disadvantage of vector
   graphics is that it is not good at representing complex images with many
   different colors such as photographs. There are many specialized
   applications for vector graphics, for example Inkscape. GIMP has only a
   very limited support for vector graphics. For example, GIMP can open and
   rasterize vector graphics in SVG format or work with vector paths.
  </para>

  <para>
   GIMP 2.6 still supports only limited selection of color spaces. It
   supports indexed images and grayscale or RGB images with 8 bits per
   channel (24 bits per pixel in RGB images without alpha channel). Many
   high-end digital cameras can produce image files with higher color
   depths. If you import such an image to GIMP, you will lose some color
   information.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gimp.starting"
   >
  <title>Starting GIMP</title><indexterm>

  <primary>GIMP</primary>

  <secondary>starting</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   To start GIMP, select <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Graphics</guimenu><guimenu>GIMP</guimenu></menuchoice>. Alternatively, enter <command>gimp
   &amp;</command> in a command line.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.gimp.starting.defaultwin">
   <title>The Default Windows</title>
   <para>
    Three windows appear by default. The toolbox, an empty image window with
    the main GIMP menu, and a window containing several docked dialogs. They
    can be arranged on the screen and, except the toolbox and the last image
    window, closed if no longer needed. Closing the toolbox or the last
    image window quits the application. In the default configuration, GIMP
    saves your window layout when you quit. Dialogs left open reappear when
    you next start the program.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.gimp.getstart.imagewin">
    <title>The Image Window</title>
    <para>
     Every new, opened, or scanned image appears in its own window. If there
     is more than one open image, each image has its own image window. There
     is always at least one image window open. If there is currently no
     image open, the image window is empty, containing only the main GIMP
     menu and drop area, which can be used to open any file by dragging and
     dropping it there. Closing the last image window quits the application.
    </para>
    <para>
     The menu bar in the top of the window provides access to all image
     functions. Conversely, access the menu by right-clicking the image or
     clicking the small arrow button in the left corner of the rulers.
    </para>
    <para>
     The <guimenu>File</guimenu> menu offers the standard file operations,
     such as <guimenu>New</guimenu>, <guimenu>Open</guimenu>,
     <guimenu>Save</guimenu>, <guimenu>Print</guimenu> and
     <guimenu>Close</guimenu>. <guimenu>Quit</guimenu> quits the
     application.
    </para>
    <para>
     <indexterm>
     <primary>GIMP</primary>
     <secondary>views</secondary>
     </indexterm> With the items in the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu,
     control the display of the image and the image window. <guimenu>New
     View</guimenu> opens a second display window of the current image.
     Changes made in one view are reflected in all other views of that
     image. Alternate views are useful for magnifying a part of an image for
     manipulation while seeing the complete image in another view. Adjust
     the magnification level of the current window with
     <guimenu>Zoom</guimenu>. When <guimenu>Fit Image in Window</guimenu> is
     selected, the image window is resized to fit the current image display
     exactly.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.gimp.starting.defaultwin.toolbox">
    <title>The Toolbox</title>
    <para>
     The toolbox contains important controls of the application. Closing it
     quits the application. At the very top, there is a drop area which can
     be used to open any image file by simply dragging and dropping it
     there. Below that, find icons for the various tools. Hover the mouse
     over an icon to display information about it.
    </para>
    <figure id="fig.gimp.toolbox">
     <title>The Toolbox</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="gimp-toolbox.png" width="25%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="gimp-toolbox.png" width="20%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
     The current foreground and background color are shown in two overlapping
     boxes. The default colors are black for the foreground and white for the
     background. Click the box to open a color selection dialog. Swap the
     foreground and background color with the bent arrow symbol to the upper
     right of the boxes. Use the black and white symbol to the lower left to
     reset the colors to the default.
    </para>
    <para>
     Under the toolbox, a dialog shows options for the currently selected
     tool. If it is not visible, open it by double-clicking the tool's icon
     in the toolbox.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.gimp.starting.defaultwin.lcpu">
    <title>Layers, Channels, Paths, Undo</title>
    <para>
     In the first section, use the drop-down box to select the image to
     which the tabs refer. By clicking <guimenu>Auto</guimenu>, control
     whether the active image is chosen automatically. By default,
     <guimenu>Auto</guimenu> is enabled.
    </para>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Layers</guimenu> shows the different layers in the current
     images and can be used to manipulate the layers. Information is
     available in <xref linkend="sec.gimp.advanced.layers"/>.
     <guimenu>Channels</guimenu> shows and can manipulate the color channels
     of the image.
    </para>
    <para>
     Paths are a vector-based method of selecting parts of an image. They
     can also be used for drawing. <guimenu>Paths</guimenu> shows the paths
     available for an image and provides access to path functions.
     <guimenu>Undo</guimenu> shows a limited history of modifications made
     to the current image. Its use is described in
     <xref linkend="sec.gimp.basics.undo"/>.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gimp.getstart">
  <title>Getting Started</title>

  <para>
   Although GIMP can be a bit overwhelming for new users, most quickly find
   it easy to use after they work out a few basics. Crucial basic functions
   are creating, opening, and saving images.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.gimp.getstart.creating">
   <title>Creating a New Image</title><indexterm>
   <primary>GIMP</primary>
   <secondary>creating images</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    To create a new image, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
    <guimenu>New</guimenu></menuchoice> or press <keycombo>
    <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>N</keycap></keycombo>. This opens a dialog
    in which to make settings for the new image. If desired, select a
    predefined setting called a <guimenu>Template</guimenu>. <indexterm>
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>templates</secondary>
    </indexterm> To create a custom template, select <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Windows</guimenu> <guimenu>Dockable Dialogs</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Templates</guimenu> </menuchoice> and use the controls offered
    by the window that opens.
   </para>
   <para>
    In the <guimenu>Image Size</guimenu> section, set the size of the image
    to create in pixels or another unit. Click the unit to select another
    unit from the list of available units. The ratio between pixels and a
    unit is set in <guimenu>Resolution</guimenu>, which appears when the
    <guimenu>Advanced Options</guimenu> section is opened. A resolution of
    72 pixels per inch corresponds to common screen display. It is
    sufficient for Web page graphics. A higher resolution should be used for
    print images. For most printers, a resolution of 300 pixels per inch
    results in an acceptable quality.
   </para>
   <para>
    In <guimenu>Color space</guimenu>, select whether the image should be in
    color (<guimenu>RGB</guimenu>) or <guimenu>Grayscale</guimenu>. For
    detailed information about image types, see
    <xref linkend="sec.gimp.advanced.modes"/>. In <guimenu>Fill
    With</guimenu> select the color the image is filled with. You can choose
    between <guimenu>Foreground Color</guimenu> and <guimenu>Background
    Color</guimenu> set in the toolbox, <guimenu>White</guimenu> or
    <guimenu>Transparency</guimenu> for a transparent image. Transparency is
    represented by a gray checkerboard pattern. You can enter a comment for
    the new image in <guimenu>Comment</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    When the settings meet your needs, press <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. To
    restore the default settings, press <guimenu>Reset</guimenu>. Pressing
    <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu> aborts creation of a new image.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gimp.getstart.open">
   <title>Opening an Existing Image</title><indexterm>
   <primary>GIMP</primary>
   <secondary>opening images</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    To open an existing image, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Open</guimenu></menuchoice> or press <keycombo>
    <keycap function="control"/><keycap>O</keycap></keycombo>. In the dialog that
    opens, select the desired file. You can also press <keycombo>
    <keycap function="control"/><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo> and type directly the
    path to the desired image. Then click <guimenu>Open</guimenu> to open
    the selected image or press <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu> to skip opening an
    image.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <!-- seems not supported anymore-->
  <!--<sect2 id="sec.gimp.getstart.scan">
   <title>Scanning an Image</title><indexterm>
   <primary>GIMP</primary>
   <secondary>scanning</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Instead of opening an existing image or creating a new one, you can scan
    one. To scan directly from GIMP, make sure that the package
    <systemitem>xsane</systemitem> is installed. To open the scanning
    dialog, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Create</guimenu> <guimenu>XSane: Device dialog</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Create a preview when the object to scan is smaller than the total
    scanning area. Press <guimenu>Acquire preview</guimenu> in the
    <guimenu>Preview</guimenu> dialog to create a preview. If you want to
    scan only part of the area, select the desired rectangular part with the
    mouse.
   </para>
   <para>
    In the <guimenu>xsane</guimenu> dialog, select whether to scan a binary
    (black and white without shades of gray), grayscale, or color image and
    the required scan resolution. The higher the resolution you choose, the
    better is the quality of the scanned image. However, this also results
    in a correspondingly larger file and the scanning process can take a
    very long time at higher resolutions. The size of the final image (both
    in pixels and bytes) is shown in the lower part of the dialog.
   </para>
   <para>
    In the <guimenu>xsane</guimenu> dialog, use the sliders to set desired
    gamma, brightness, and contrast values. These sliders are not available
    in binary mode. Changes are visible in the preview immediately. Once all
    settings have been made, click <guimenu>Scan</guimenu> to scan the
    image.
   </para>
  </sect2>-->
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gimp.saving">
  <title>Saving Images</title><indexterm>

  <primary>GIMP</primary>

  <secondary>saving images</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   No image function is as important as <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Save</guimenu></menuchoice>. It is better to save too often than
   too rarely. Use <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenu>Save
   as</guimenu></menuchoice> to save the image with a new file name. It is a
   good idea to save image stages under different names or make backups in
   another directory so you can easily restore a previous state.
  </para>

  <para>
   When saving for the first time or using <guimenu>Save as</guimenu>, a
   dialog opens in which to specify the file name and type. Enter the
   file name in the field at the top. For <guimenu>Save in folder</guimenu>,
   select the directory in which to save the file from a list of commonly
   used directories. To use a different directory or create a new one, open
   <guimenu>Browse for other folders</guimenu>. It is recommended to leave
   <guimenu>Select File Type</guimenu> set to <guimenu>By
   Extension</guimenu>. With that setting, GIMP determines the file type
   based on the extension appended to the file name. The following file types
   are frequently useful:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>XCF<indexterm>
     <primary>graphics</primary>
     <secondary>file formats</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
     <primary>files</primary>
     <secondary>formats</secondary>
     <tertiary>XCF</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This is the native format of the application. It saves all layer and
      path information along with the image itself. Even if you need an
      image in another format, it is usually a good idea to save a copy as
      XCF to simplify future modifications. Information about layers is
      available in <xref linkend="sec.gimp.advanced.layers"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
<!--   <varlistentry>
    <term>PAT<indexterm>
      <primary>files</primary>
      <secondary>formats</secondary>
      <tertiary>PAT</tertiary>
     </indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This is the format used for GIMP patterns. Saving an image in this
      format enables using the image as a fill pattern in GIMP.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>-->
   <varlistentry>
    <term>JPEG<indexterm>
     <primary>files</primary>
     <secondary>formats</secondary>
     <tertiary>JPG</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      JPG or JPEG is a common format for photographs and Web page graphics
      without transparency. Its compression method enables reduction of file
      sizes, but information is lost when compressing. It may be a good idea
      to use the preview option when adjusting the compression level. Levels
      of 85% to 75% often result in an acceptable image quality with
      reasonable compression. Saving a backup in a lossless format, like
      XCF, is also recommended. If editing an image, save only the finished
      image as JPG. Repeatedly loading a JPG then saving can quickly result
      in poor image quality.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>GIF<indexterm>
     <primary>files</primary>
     <secondary>formats</secondary>
     <tertiary>GIF</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Although very popular in the past for graphics with transparency, GIF
      is less often used now because of license issues. GIF is also used for
      animated images. The format can only save <emphasis>indexed</emphasis>
      images. See <xref linkend="sec.gimp.advanced.modes"/> for information
      about indexed images. The file size can often be quite small if only a
      few colors are used.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>PNG<indexterm>
     <primary>files</primary>
     <secondary>formats</secondary>
     <tertiary>PNG</tertiary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      With its support for transparency, lossless compression, free
      availability, and increasing browser support, PNG is replacing GIF as
      the preferred format for Web graphics with transparency. An added
      advantage is that PNG offers partial transparency, which is not
      offered by GIF. This enables smoother transitions from colored areas
      to transparent areas (<emphasis>antialiasing</emphasis>).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   To save an image in the chosen format, press <guimenu>Save</guimenu>. To
   abort, press <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu>. If the image has features that
   cannot be saved in the chosen format, a dialog appears with choices for
   resolving the situation. Choosing <guimenu>Export</guimenu>, if offered,
   normally gives the desired results. A window then opens with the options
   of the format. Reasonable default values are provided.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1
  id="sec.gimp.basics">
  <title>Editing Images</title><indexterm id="idx.gimp.editing_images"
   class="startofrange">

  <primary>GIMP</primary>

  <secondary>editing images</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   GIMP provides a number of tools for making changes to images. The
   functions described here are those most interesting for home users.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.gimp.basics.size"
    >
   <title>Changing the Image Size</title><indexterm id="idx.graphics.resizing"
    class="startofrange">
   <primary>graphics</primary>
   <secondary>resizing</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    After an image is scanned or a digital photograph is loaded from the
    camera, it is often necessary to modify the size for display on a Web
    page or for printing. Images can easily be made smaller either by
    scaling them down or by cutting off parts of them. Enlarging an image is
    much more problematic. Because of the nature of raster graphics, quality
    is lost when an image is enlarged. It is recommended to keep a copy of
    your original image before scaling or cropping.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.gimp.basics.size.cropping">
    <title>Cropping an Image</title><indexterm>
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>cropping</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     Cropping an image works like cutting the edges off a piece of paper.
     Select the crop tool from the toolbox (it resembles a scalpel) or with
     <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Transform
     Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Crop</guimenu></menuchoice>. Click a starting
     corner and drag to outline the area to keep.
    </para>
    <para>
     A rectangle showing the crop area will appear. To adjust the size of
     the rectangle, move your mouse pointer above any of the rectangle's
     sides or corners, click and drag to resize as desired. If you want to
     adjust both width and height of the rectangle, use a corner. To adjust
     only one dimension, use a side. To move the whole rectangle to a
     different position without resizing, click anywhere near its center and
     drag to the desired position.
    </para>
    <para>
     When you are satisfied with the crop area, click anywhere inside to
     crop the image or press <keycap function="enter"/>. To cancel the cropping,
     click anywhere outside the crop area.
    </para>
    <para>
     Advanced options for the crop tool are available in the <guimenu>Tool
     Options</guimenu> dialog.
    </para>
<!--The results of
     <guimenu>Resize</guimenu> are identical to those of <guimenu>Change
     Canvas Size</guimenu>, described in
     <xref
      linkend="sec.gimp.basics.size.canvas"/>.-->
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.gimp.basics.size.scaling">
    <title>Scaling an Image</title><indexterm>
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>scaling images</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Image</guimenu><guimenu>Scale
     Image</guimenu></menuchoice> to change the overall size of an image.
     Select the new size by entering it in <guimenu>Width</guimenu> or
     <guimenu>Height</guimenu>. To change the proportions of the image when
     scaling (this distorts the image), click the chain icon to the right of
     the fields to break the link between them. When those fields are
     linked, all values are changed proportionately. Adjust the resolution
     with <guimenu>X resolution</guimenu> and <guimenu>Y
     resolution</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The <guimenu>Interpolation</guimenu> option controls the quality of the
     resulting image. The default <guimenu>Cubic</guimenu> interpolation
     method is a good standard to use in most cases.
    </para>
    <para>
     When finished adjusting the size, press <guimenu>Scale</guimenu> to
     scale the image. <guimenu>Reset</guimenu> restores the original values.
     <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu> aborts the procedure.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.gimp.basics.size.canvas">
    <title>Changing the Canvas Size</title>
    <para>
     Changing the canvas size is like putting a mat around an image. Even if
     the mat is smaller, the rest of the image is there, but you can only
     see part of it. If the mat is larger, you see the original image with
     extra space around it. To do this, select <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Image</guimenu> <guimenu>Canvas Size</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para>
     In the dialog that opens, enter the new size. By default, the width and
     height maintain the same proportions as the current image. To change
     this, click the chain icon.
    </para>
    <para>
     After adjusting the size, determine how the existing image should be
     positioned in comparison to the new size. Use the
     <guimenu>Offset</guimenu> values or drag the box inside the frame at
     the bottom. When satisfied with the changes, click
     <guimenu>Resize</guimenu> to change the canvas size. Click
     <guimenu>Reset</guimenu> to restore the original values or
     <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu> to cancel the canvas resize.
    </para><indexterm startref="idx.graphics.resizing" class="endofrange"/>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gimp.basics.select">
   <title>Selecting Parts of Images</title><indexterm id="idx.gimp.selecting" class="startofrange">
   <primary>GIMP</primary>
   <secondary>selecting</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    It is often useful to perform an image operation on only part of an
    image. To do this, the part of the image with which to work must be
    selected. Areas can be selected using the select tools available in the
    toolbox, using the quick mask, or combining different options.
    Selections can also be modified with the items under
    <guimenu>Select</guimenu>. The selection is outlined with a dashed line,
    called <emphasis>marching ants</emphasis>.
   </para>
   <sect3
    id="sec.gimp.basics.select.tools">
    <title>Using the Selection Tools</title>
    <para>
     The main selection tools are rather easy to use. The paths tool, which
     can also be used for more than selecting, is more complicated so is not
     described here. In the tool options for the other selection tools, use
     one of the icons in the <guimenu>Mode</guimenu> row to determine
     whether the selection should replace, be added to, be subtracted from,
     or intersect with an existing selection.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Rect Select</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        This tool can be used to select rectangular or square areas. To
        select an area with a fixed aspect ratio, width, height or size,
        activate the <guimenu>Fixed</guimenu> option and choose the relevant
        mode in the <guimenu>Tool Options</guimenu> dialog. To create a
        square, hold <keycap function="shift"/> while selecting a region.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Ellipse Select</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Use this to select elliptical or circular areas. The same options
        are available as with the rectangular selection. To create a circle,
        hold <keycap function="shift"/> while selecting a region.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Free Select (Lasso)</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        With this tool, you can create a selection based on a combination of
        freehand drawing and polygonal segments. To draw a freehand line,
        drag the mouse over the image with the left mouse button pressed. To
        create a polygonal segment, release the mouse button where the
        segment should start and press it again where the segment should
        end. To complete the selection, hover the pointer above the starting
        point and click inside the circle.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Fuzzy Select (Magic Wand)</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        This tools selects a continuous region based on color similarities.
        Set the maximum difference between colors in the tool options dialog
        in <guimenu>Threshold</guimenu>. By default, the selection is based
        only on the active layer. To base the selection on all visible
        layers, check <guimenu>Sample merged</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Select by Color</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        With this, select all the pixels in the image with the same or
        similar color as the clicked pixel. The maximum difference between
        colors can be set in the tool options dialog in
        <guimenu>Threshold</guimenu>. The important difference between this
        tool and Fuzzy Select is that Fuzzy Select works on continuous color
        areas while Select by Color selects all pixels with similar colors
        in the whole image regardless of their position.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Intelligent Scissors</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Click a series of points in the image. As you click, the points are
        connected based on color differences. Click the first point to
        close the area. Convert it to a regular selection by clicking inside
        it.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Foreground Selection Tool</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The Foreground Selection tool lets you semi-automatically select an
        object in a photograph with minimal manual effort.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
     If you want to use the Foreground Selection tool, follow these steps:
    </para>
    <procedure id="sec.gimp.basics.select.fs">
     <step>
      <para>
       Activate the Foreground Selection tool by clicking its icon in the
       Toolbox or choosing <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Selection Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Foreground
       Select</guimenu> </menuchoice> from the menu.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Roughly select the foreground object you want to extract. Select as
       little as possible from the background but include the whole object.
       At this point, the tool works like the Fuzzy Select tool.
      </para>
      <para>
       When you release the mouse button, the non selected part of the image
       is covered with dark blue mask.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Draw a continuous line through the foreground object going over
       colors which will be kept for the extraction. Do not paint over
       background pixels.
      </para>
      <para>
       When you release the mouse button, all background is covered with
       dark blue mask. If parts of the object are also masked, paint over
       them. The mask will adapt.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       When you are satisfied with the mask, press
       <keycap function="enter">Enter</keycap>. The mask will be converted
       to a new selection.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.gimp.basics.select.quickmask">
    <title>Using the Quick Mask</title><indexterm>
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>quick mask</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     The quick mask is a way of selecting parts of an image using the paint
     tools. A good way to use it is to make a rough selection using the
     intelligent scissors or the lasso (the free selection tool). Then
     activate the quick mask by pressing the small icon with the dashed box
     in the lower left corner.
    </para>
    <para>
     The quick mask displays the selection using an overlay of red. Areas
     shaded with red are not selected. Areas appearing as they did before
     the mask was activated are selected. To modify the selection, use the
     paint tools. Painting with white selects the painted pixels. Painting
     with black deselects pixels. Shades of gray (colors are treated as
     shades of gray) are a partial selection. Partial selection allow a
     smooth transitions between selected and unselected areas.
    </para>
    <para>
     To use a different color for displaying the quick mask, right-click the
     quick mask button then select <guimenu>Configure Color and
     Opacity</guimenu> from the menu. Click the colored box in the dialog
     that opens in order to select a new color.
    </para>
    <para>
     After using the paint tools to adjust the selection as desired, convert
     from the quick mask view back to the normal selection view by clicking
     the icon in the lower left corner of the image window (currently
     displaying a red box). The selection is again displayed with the
     marching ants.
    </para><indexterm
     startref="idx.gimp.selecting" class="endofrange"/>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gimp.basics.color">
   <title>Applying and Removing Color</title>
   <para>
    Most image editing involves applying or removing color. By selecting a
    part of the image, limit where color can be applied or removed. When you
    select a tool and move the cursor onto an image, the cursor's appearance
    changes to reflect the chosen tool. With many tools, an icon of the
    current tool is shown along with the arrow. For paint tools, an outline
    of the current brush is shown, allowing you to see exactly where you
    will be painting in the image and how large of an area will be painted.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.gimp.basics.color.selecting">
    <title>Selecting Colors</title><indexterm>
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>colors</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     Paint tools use the foreground color. To select the color, first click
     the display box of the foreground color in the Toolbox. A dialog with
     five tabs opens. These tabs provide different color selection methods.
     Only the first tab, shown in
     <xref
      linkend="fig.gimp.colorselector"/>, is described here. The
     new color is shown in <guimenu>Current</guimenu>. The previous color is
     shown in <guimenu>Old</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <figure id="fig.gimp.colorselector">
     <title>The Basic Color Selector Dialog</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="gimp-color.png" width="60%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="gimp-color.png" width="50%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
     The easiest way to select a color is by using the colored areas in the
     boxes to the left. In the narrow vertical bar, click a color similar to
     the desired color. The larger box to the left then shows available
     nuances. Click the desired color. It is then shown in
     <guimenu>Current</guimenu>. If that color is not what you want, try
     again.
    </para>
    <para>
     The arrow button to the right of <guimenu>Current</guimenu> enables the
     saving of a number of possible colors. Click the arrow to copy the
     current color to the history. A color can then be selected by clicking
     it in the history. A color can also be selected by directly entering
     its hexadecimal color code in <guimenu>HTML Notation</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The color selector defaults to selecting a color by hue, which is
     usually easiest for a new user. To select by saturation, value, red,
     green, or blue, select the corresponding radio button to the right. The
     sliders and number fields can also be used to modify the currently
     selected color. Experiment a bit to find out what works best for you.
    </para>
    <para>
     When the desired color is shown in <guimenu>Current</guimenu>, click
     <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. To restore the original values shown when the
     dialog was opened, click <guimenu>Reset</guimenu>. To abort changing
     the color, click <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     To select a color that already exists in your image, use the eye
     dropper tool. With the tool options, set whether the foreground or
     background color should be selected. Then click a point in the image
     that shows the desired color. When the color is right, click
     <guimenu>Close</guimenu> to close the tool's dialog.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.gimp.basics.color.painting">
    <title>Painting and Erasing</title>
    <para>
     To paint and erase, use the tools from the toolbox. There are a number
     of options available to fine-tune each tool. Pressure sensitivity
     options apply only when a pressure-sensitive graphics tablet is used.
    </para>
    <para>
     The pencil, brush, airbrush, and eraser work much like their real-life
     equivalents. The ink tool works like a calligraphy pen. Paint by
     clicking and dragging. The bucket fill is a method of coloring areas of
     an image. It fills based on color boundaries in the image. Adjusting
     the threshold modifies its sensitivity to color changes.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.gimp.basics.color.text">
    <title>Adding Text</title><indexterm>
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>text</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     With the text tool, easily add text to an image. With the tool options,
     select the desired font, font size, color, justification, indent, and
     line spacing. Then click a starting point in the image. A small dialog
     opens in which to enter your text. Enter single or multiple lines of
     text then press <guimenu>Close</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The text tool creates text in a special layer. To work with the image
     after adding text, read
     <xref
      linkend="sec.gimp.advanced.layers"/>. When the text layer
     is active, it is possible to modify the text by clicking in the image
     to reopen the entry dialog. Change the settings by modifying the tool
     options.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.gimp.basics.color.clone">
    <title>Retouching Images&mdash;The Clone Tool</title><indexterm>
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>retouching images</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     The clone tool is ideal for retouching images. It enables you to paint
     in an image using information from another part of the image. If
     desired, it can instead take information from a pattern.
    </para>
    <para>
     When retouching, it is usually a good idea to use a small brush with
     soft edges. In this way, the modifications can blend better with the
     original image.
    </para>
    <para>
     To select the source point in the image, press and hold
     <keycap function="control"/> while clicking the desired source point. Then
     paint with the tool, as usual. When you move the cursor while painting,
     the source point, marked by a cross, moves as well. If the
     <guimenu>Alignment</guimenu> is set to <guimenu>None</guimenu> (the
     default setting), the source resets to the original when you release
     the left mouse button.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gimp.basics.levels">
   <title>Adjusting Color Levels</title><indexterm>
   <primary>GIMP</primary>
   <secondary>levels</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Images often need a little adjusting to get ideal print or display
    results. In many programs designed for inexperienced users, the
    brightness and contrast levels are modified. This can work and is also
    available in GIMP, but better results can be obtained by adjusting the
    color levels.
   </para>
   <para>
    To do this, select <menuchoice><guimenu>Colors</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Levels</guimenu></menuchoice>. A dialog opens for controlling
    the levels in the image. Good results can usually be obtained by
    clicking <guimenu>Auto</guimenu>. To make manual adjustments to all
    channels, use the dropper tools in <guimenu>All Channels</guimenu> to
    pick areas in the image that should be black, neutral gray, and white.
   </para>
   <para>
    To modify a channel individually, select the desired channel in
    <guimenu>Channel</guimenu>. Then drag the black, white, and middle
    markers in the slider in <guimenu>Input Levels</guimenu>. Conversely,
    use the dropper tools to select points in the image that should serve as
    the white, black, and gray points for that channel.
   </para>
   <para>
    If <guimenu>Preview</guimenu> is checked, the image window shows a
    preview of the image with the modifications applied. When the desired
    result is achieved, press <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to apply the changes.
    With <guimenu>Reset</guimenu>, restore the original settings.
    <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu> aborts level adjustment.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gimp.basics.undo">
   <title>Undoing Mistakes</title><indexterm>
   <primary>GIMP</primary>
   <secondary>undo</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Most modifications made in GIMP can be undone. To view a history of
    modifications, use the undo dialog included in the default window layout
    or open one from the image window menu with <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Windows</guimenu> <guimenu>Dockable Dialogs</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Undo History</guimenu></menuchoice>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The dialog shows a base image and a series of editing changes that can
    be undone. Use the buttons to undo and redo changes. In this way, you
    can work back to the base image. If you undo a modification then make a
    new one, the undone modification cannot be redone.
   </para>
   <para>
    Changes can also be undone and redone with the <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
    menu. Alternatively, use the shortcuts <keycombo>
    <keycap function="control"/><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo> and <keycombo>
    <keycap function="control"/><keycap>Y</keycap></keycombo>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2
   id="sec.gimp.advanced.layers">
   <title>Layers</title><indexterm>
   <primary>GIMP</primary>
   <secondary>layers</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Layers are a very important aspect of GIMP. By drawing parts of your
    image on separate layers, you can change, move, or delete those parts
    without damaging the rest of the image. To understand how layers work,
    imagine an image created from a stack of transparent sheets. Different
    parts of the image are drawn on different sheets. The stack can be
    rearranged, changing which parts are on top. Individual layers or groups
    of layers can shift position, moving sections of the image to other
    locations. New sheets can be added and others set aside.
   </para>
   <para>
    Use the <guimenu>Layers</guimenu> dialog to view the available layers of
    an image. The text tool automatically creates special text layers when
    used. The active layer is highlighted. The buttons at the bottom of the
    dialog offer a number of functions. More are available in the menu
    opened when a layer is right-clicked in the dialog. The two icon spaces
    before the image name are used for toggling image visibility (eye icon
    when visible) and for linking layers. Linked layers are marked with the
    chain icon and moved as a group.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gimp.advanced.modes">
   <title>Image Modes</title><indexterm>
   <primary>GIMP</primary>
   <secondary>image modes</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    GIMP has three image modes&mdash;RGB, Grayscale, and Indexed. RGB is a
    normal color mode and is the best mode for editing most images.
    Grayscale is used for black-and-white images. Indexed limits the colors
    in the image to a set number. It is mainly used for GIF images. If you
    need an indexed image, it is normally best to edit the image in RGB then
    convert to indexed right before saving. If you save to a format that
    requires an indexed image, GIMP offers to index the image when saving.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gimp.advanced.effects">
   <title>Special Effects</title><indexterm>
   <primary>GIMP</primary>
   <secondary>effects</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    GIMP includes a wide range of filters and scripts for enhancing images,
    adding special effects to them or making artistic manipulations. They
    are available in <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>. Experimenting is the best
    way to find out what is available.
   </para><indexterm startref="idx.gimp.editing_images" class="endofrange"/>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gimp.printing">
  <title>Printing Images</title><indexterm>

  <primary>GIMP</primary>

  <secondary>printing</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>printing</primary>

  <secondary>GIMP</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   To print an image, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Print</guimenu></menuchoice> from the image menu. If your
   printer is configured in the system, it should appear in the list. You
   can configure printing options on <guimenu>Page Setup</guimenu> and
   <guimenu>Image Settings</guimenu> tabs.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.gimp.print">
   <title>The Print Dialog</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="gimp-print.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="gimp-print.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

<!--  <para>
   In the bottom portion of the window, adjust the image size. Press
   <guimenu>Use Original Image Size</guimenu> to take these settings from
   the image itself. This is recommended if you set an appropriate print
   size and resolution in the image. Adjust the image's position on the page
   with the fields in <guimenu>Position</guimenu> or by dragging the image
   in <guimenu>Preview</guimenu>.
  </para>-->

  <para>
   When satisfied with the settings, press <guimenu>Print</guimenu>.
<!--To save
   the settings for future use, instead use <guimenu>Print and Save
    Settings</guimenu>.-->
   <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu> aborts printing.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gimp.moreinfo"
   >
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   The following resources are very useful for users of GIMP. They contain
   much more information about GIMP than this chapter. If you want to use
   GIMP for more advanced tasks, you should not miss these resources.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://www.gimp.org"/> is the official home page of The
     GIMP. News about GIMP and related software are regularly posted on the
     frontpage.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Help</guimenu> provides access to the internal help system
     including extensive GIMP User Manual. The package
     <systemitem class="resource">gimp-help</systemitem> needs to be
     installed. This documentation is also available online in HTML and PDF
     formats at <ulink
      url="http://docs.gimp.org"/>. Translations into
     many languages are available.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A collection of many interesting GIMP tutorials is maintained at
     <ulink
      url="http://gimp.org/tutorials/"/>. It contains basic
     tutorials for complete beginners as well as tutorials for advanced or
     expert users.
    </para>
   </listitem>
<!--  <listitem>
    <para>
     Various interesting information about GIMP can be found on the Wilber's
     Wiki at <ulink
      url="http://wiki.gimp.org/gimp/"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>-->
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Printed books about GIMP are published regularly. You will find a
     selection of the best ones with short annotations at
     <ulink url="http://gimp.org/books/"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     GIMP functionality can be extended with scripts and plug-ins. Many such
     scripts and plug-ins are distributed in the GIMP package, but others
     can be downloaded from the Internet. At
     <ulink
     url="http://registry.gimp.org/"/>, you will find a database
     of GIMP scripts and plug-ins.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   You can also use mailing lists or IRC channels to ask questions about
   GIMP. Always try to find answers in the documentation mentioned
   above or in mailing list archives before asking your question. The time
   of experienced users present on GIMP lists and channels is limited. Be
   polite and patient. It may take some time before your question is
   answered.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     There are a number of mailing lists about GIMP. You will find them at
     <ulink url="http://gimp.org/mail_lists.html"/>. GIMP User list is the
     most appropriate place to ask user questions.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     There is a whole IRC network dedicated to GIMP and GNOME desktop
     environment&mdash;GIMPNet. You can connect to GIMPNet with your
     favorite IRC client by pointing it at the irc.gimp.org server. The
     #gimp-users channel is the right place to ask question about using
     GIMP. If you want to listen to developer's discussions, join the #gimp
     channel.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.gimp"/><indexterm class="endofrange"
   startref="idx.graphics.editing"/>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
