<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC 
  "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN"
  "novdocx.dtd"
[
 <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entities;
]>
<!-- 
  Version information:
  * SLE11 SP1: 3.3.1.2
  * SLE11 SP2: 3.4.2.3
  * SLE11 SP3: 3.6.3.2.4 (2013-02-28)
-->
<chapter id="cha.oo.oview">
 <title>&ooo;: The Office Suite</title>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   &ooo; is an open-source office suite that provides tools for all types of
   office tasks such as writing texts, working with spreadsheets, or
   creating graphics and presentations. With &ooo;, you can use the same
   data across different computing platforms. You can also open and edit
   files in other formats, including Microsoft Office, then save them back
   to this format, if needed. This chapter contains information that applies
   to all of the &ooo; modules.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <sect1 id="sec.oo.oview.modules">
  <title>&ooo; Modules</title>

<!--<informalfigure pgwide="0">
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="oo-wizard-impress.png" width="75%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="oo-wizard-impress.png" width="75%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>-->

  <para>
   &ooo; consists of several application modules (subprograms), which are
   designed to interact with each other. They are listed in
   <xref linkend="tab.oo.oview.modules"
    xrefstyle="select:label nopage"/>.
   A full description of each module is available in the online help,
   described in <xref linkend="sec.oo.oview.help"/>.
  </para>

  <table id="tab.oo.oview.modules">
   <title>The &ooo; Application Modules</title>
   <tgroup cols="2">
    <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="19*"/>
    <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="81*"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Module
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Purpose
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Writer
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Word processor application module
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Calc
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Spreadsheet application module
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Impress
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Presentation application module
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Base
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Database application module
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Draw
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Application module for drawing vector graphics
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Math
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Application module for generating mathematical formulas
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.oo.oview.start">
  <title>Starting &ooo;</title>

  <para>
   To start the &ooo; suite, press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
    <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter <command>libreoffice</command>.
   You can also use
   <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Office</guimenu>
    <guimenu>LibreOffice</guimenu></menuchoice>
   The &ooo; window opens. The following chapters cover individual &ooo;
   modules:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><xref linkend="cha.oo.writer"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Introduces &ooo; Writer.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><xref linkend="cha.oo.calc"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Introduces &ooo; Calc.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><xref linkend="cha.oo.various"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Introduces &ooo; Impress, Base, Draw, and Math.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   In the selection dialog, choose the module you want to open or which file
   type you want to create. If any &ooo; application is open, you can start
   any of the other applications by clicking <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>New</guimenu><guimenu>Name of
   Application</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can also start individual &ooo; modules from your main menu. As an
   alternative, use the command <command>libreoffice</command> and one of
   the options <option>--writer</option>, <option>--calc</option>,
   <option>--impress</option>, <option>--draw</option> or
   <option>--base</option> to start the respective module. Find more useful
   options with <option>--help</option>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Before you start working with &ooo;, you may be interested in changing
   some options from the preferences dialog. Click <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Options</guimenu> </menuchoice> to
   open it. The most important ones are:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><menuchoice><guimenu>&ooo;</guimenu><guimenu>User Data</guimenu></menuchoice>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Insert your user data like company, first and last name, street, city,
      and other useful information. This data is used in &ooo; Writer for
      annotations, for example.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><menuchoice><guimenu>&ooo;</guimenu><guimenu>Fonts</guimenu></menuchoice>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Offers mappings from one font name to another. This could be useful,
      if you exchange documents with others and the document you received
      contains fonts that are not available on your system.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><menuchoice><guimenu>Load/Save</guimenu><guimenu>General</guimenu></menuchoice>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Contains load and save specific options. For example, here select the
      option to always create a backup copy or decide which default file
      format &ooo; should use.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.oo.oview.migration">
  <title>Compatibility with Other Office Applications</title>

  <para>
   &ooo; can work with documents, spreadsheets, presentations, and databases
   in many other formats, including Microsoft Office. They can be easily
   opened like other files and saved back to the original format. If you
   have problems with your documents, consider opening them in the original
   application and resaving them in an open format such as RTF for text
   documents. In case of migration issues with spreadsheets however, it is
   advisable to re-save them as Excel files and use this as intermediate
   format (with CSV format you would lose all cell formatting and CSV
   sometimes leads to incorrect cell type detection for spreadsheets).
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.oo.oview.migration.convert">
   <title>Converting Documents to the &ooo; Format</title>
   <para>
    &ooo; can read, edit, and save documents in a number of formats. It is
    not necessary to convert files from those formats to the &ooo; format to
    use those files. However, if you want to convert the files, you can do
    so. To convert a number of documents, such as when first switching to
    &ooo;, do the following:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Wizards</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Document Converter</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose the document type (StarOffice* or Microsoft Office).
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose the file format from which to convert.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Specify where &ooo; should look for templates and documents to convert
      and in which directory the converted files should be placed.
     </para>
     <para>
      Documents retrieved from a Windows partition are usually in a
      subdirectory of <filename>/windows</filename>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Make sure that all other settings are correct, then click
      <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Review the summary of the actions to perform, then start the
      conversion by clicking <guimenu>Convert</guimenu>. When everything is
      done, close the Wizard by clicking <guimenu>Close</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <para>
      The amount of time needed for the conversion depends on the number of
      files and their complexity. For most documents, conversion does not
      take very long.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.oo.oview.migration.share">
   <title>Sharing Files with Users of Other Office Suites</title>
   <para>
    &ooo; is available for a number of operating systems. This makes it an
    excellent tool when a group of users frequently need to share files and
    do not use the same system on their computers.
   </para>
   <para>
    When sharing documents with others, you have several options.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>If the recipient needs to be able to edit the file</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Save the document in the format the other user needs. For example, to
       save as a Microsoft Word file, click <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Save As</guimenu> </menuchoice>,
       then select the Microsoft Word file type for the version of Word the
       other user needs.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>If the recipient only needs to read the document</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Export the document to a PDF file with <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Export as PDF</guimenu>
       </menuchoice>. PDF files can be read on any platform using a PDF
       viewer.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>If you want to share a document for editing</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Agree on a common exchange format that works for everyone. TXT and
       RTF formats, although limited in formatting, might be a good option
       for text documents.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>If you want to e-mail a document as a PDF</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Send</guimenu>
       <guimenu>E-mail as PDF</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Your default e-mail
       program opens with the file attached.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>If you want to e-mail a document to a Microsoft Word user</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Send</guimenu>
       <guimenu>E-mail as Microsoft Word</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Your
       default e-mail program opens with the file attached.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Send a document as the body of an e-mail</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Send</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Document as E-mail</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Your default
       e-mail program opens with the contents of the document as the e-mail
       body.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.oo.oview.passwd">
  <title>Saving &ooo; Files with a Password</title>

  <para>
   You can save files, no matter in which &ooo; format, with a password.
   Note that this offers limited protection only. For stronger protection,
   use encryption methods as described in
   <xref
    linkend="cha.security.cryptofs"/>. To save a file with a
   password, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Save</guimenu> </menuchoice> or <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Save As</guimenu> </menuchoice>. In the
   dialog that opens, activate the <guimenu>Save with password</guimenu>
   check box and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. After you have typed and
   confirmed your password, your file will be saved. The next time a user
   opens the file, he will be prompted for the password.
  </para>

  <para>
   To change the password, either overwrite the same file by selecting
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Save As</guimenu>
   </menuchoice> or select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> </menuchoice> and click <guimenu>Change
   Password</guimenu> to access the password dialog.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 os="sled" id="sec.oo.oview.certstore">
  <title>Signing Documents</title>

  <para>
   <remark>taroth 081201: is this the correct place where the cert
   store comes in? - taroth 081218: still no answer, so going to locdrop
   now anyway</remark>
   You can digitally sign documents to protect them. For this you need a
   personal key (certificate). When applying a digital signature to a
   document, a kind of checksum is created from the document's content and
   your personal key. The checksum is stored together with the document.
   When another person opens the document, the recent checksum will be
   compared to the original checksum and if both are equal, the application
   will signal that the document has not been changed in the meantime. To
   sign a document, select <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenu>Digital Signature</guimenu> </menuchoice>
   and click <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to add the certificate you want to use
   for signing.
  </para>

  <para>
   &productname; allows you to access certificates from the certificate
   store. For more information, refer to <xref linkend="cha.certstore"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.oo.oview.cust">
  <title>Customizing &ooo;</title>

  <para>
   You can customize &ooo; to best suit your needs and working style.
   Toolbars, menus, and key combinations can all be reconfigured to help
   you more quickly access the features you use the most. You can also
   assign macros to application events if you want specific actions to occur
   when those events take place. For example, if you always work with a
   specific spreadsheet, you can create a macro that opens the spreadsheet
   and assign the macro to the Start Application event.
  </para>

  <para>
   This section contains simple, generic instructions for customizing your
   environment. The changes you make are effective immediately, so you can
   see if the changes are what you wanted and go back and modify them if
   they are not. See the &ooo; help files for detailed instructions.
  </para>

  <para>
   To access the customization dialog in any open &ooo; module, select
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Customize</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.oo.oview.custom">
   <title>Customization Dialog in Writer</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="oo_customize_main.png" width="50%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="oo_customize_main.png" width="50%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <procedure>
   <title>Customizing Toolbars</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the customization dialog, click the <guimenu>Toolbar</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     From the <guimenu>Toolbar</guimenu> drop-down box, select the toolbar
     you want to customize.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the check boxes next to the commands you want to appear on the
     toolbar, and deselect the check boxes next to the commands you do not
     want to appear. A short description for each command is shown at the
     bottom of the dialog.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     With <guimenu>Save In</guimenu>, select whether to save your customized
     toolbar in the current &ooo; module or in the current document. If you
     decide to save it in the &ooo; module, the customized toolbar is used
     whenever you open that module. If you decide to save it together with
     the current document, the customized toolbar is used whenever you open
     that document.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Repeat to customize additional toolbars.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   If you want to switch back to the original settings again, open the
   customization dialog, click the <guimenu>Toolbar</guimenu> drop-down box
   and select <guimenu>Restore Default Settings</guimenu>. Click
   <guimenu>Yes</guimenu> and <guimenu>Reset</guimenu> to proceed.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Showing or Hiding Buttons in the Toolbar</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the arrow icon at the right edge of the toolbar you want to
     change.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Visible Buttons</guimenu> to display a list of buttons.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the buttons in the list to enable (check) or disable (uncheck)
     them.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure>
   <title>Customizing Menus</title>
   <para>
    You can add or delete items from current menus, reorganize menus, and
    even create new menus.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Customize</guimenu> <guimenu>Menus</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the menu you want to change, or click <guimenu>New</guimenu> to
     create a new menu.
    </para>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Help</guimenu> for more information about the options in
     the <guimenu>Customize</guimenu> dialog.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Modify, add, or delete menu items as desired.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure>
   <title>Customizing Key Combinations</title>
   <para>
    You can reassign currently assigned key combinations and assign new
    ones to frequently used functions.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Customize</guimenu> <guimenu>Keyboard</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the keys you want to assign to a combination.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select a <guimenu>Category</guimenu> and an appropriate
     <guimenu>function</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Modify</guimenu> to assign the function to the key or
     <guimenu>Delete</guimenu> to remove an existing assignment.
    </para>
    <note>
     <title>Further Information</title>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Help</guimenu> for more information about the options
      in the <guimenu>Customize</guimenu> dialog.
     </para>
    </note>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure>
   <title>Customizing Events</title>
   <para>
    &ooo; also provides ways to assign macros to events such as application
    start-up or the saving of a document. The assigned macro runs
    automatically whenever the selected event occurs.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Customize</guimenu> <guimenu>Events</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the event you want to change.
    </para>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Help</guimenu> for more information about the options in
     the <guimenu>Customize</guimenu> dialog.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Assign or remove macros for the selected event.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.oo.oview.global">
  <title>Changing the Global Settings</title>

  <para>
   Global settings can be changed in any &ooo; application by clicking
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Options</guimenu>
   </menuchoice> on the menu bar. This opens the window shown in the figure
   below. A tree structure is used to display categories of settings.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.ooo.cust.globalsettings">
   <title>The Options Window</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="oo_options.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="oo_options.png" width="75%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   The settings categories that appear depend on the module you are working
   in. For example, if you are in Writer, the &ooo; Writer category appears
   in the list, but the &ooo; Calc category does not. The &ooo; Base
   category appears in both Calc and Writer. The Application column in the
   table shows where each setting category is available.
  </para>

  <para>
   The following table lists the settings categories along with a brief
   description of each category:
  </para>

  <table id="tab.ooo.globalcategory">
   <title>Global Setting Categories</title>
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="25*"/>
    <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="55*"/>
    <colspec align="center" colnum="3" colname="3" colwidth="20*"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Settings
<?dblinebreak?>
        Category
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Description
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Application
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>&ooo;</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Various basic settings, including your user data (such as your
        address and e-mail), important paths, and settings for printers and
        external programs.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        All
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>Load/Save</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Includes the settings related to the opening and saving of several
        file types. There is a dialog for general settings and several
        special dialogs to define how external formats should be handled.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        All
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>Language
<?dblinebreak?>
        Settings</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Covers the various settings related to languages and writing aids,
        such as your locale and spell checker settings. This is also the
        place to enable support for Asian languages.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        All
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu> &ooo;
<?dblinebreak?>
        Writer</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Configures the global word processing options, such as the basic
        fonts and layout that Writer should use.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Writer
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>&ooo;
<?dblinebreak?>
        Writer/Web</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Changes the settings related to the HTML authoring features of
        &ooo;.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Writer
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>&ooo;
<?dblinebreak?>
        Base</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Provides dialogs to set and edit connections and registered
        databases.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Base
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>Charts</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Defines the default colors used for newly created charts.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        All
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <guimenu>Internet</guimenu>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Includes the dialogs to configure any proxies and to change settings
        related to search engines.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        All
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>

  <important>
   <title>Settings Applied Globally</title>
   <para>
    All settings listed in the table are applied
    <emphasis>globally</emphasis> for the specified applications. They are
    used as defaults for every new document you create.
   </para>
  </important>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.oo.oview.templates">
  <title>Using Templates</title>

  <para>
   A template is a document containing only the styles&mdash;and
   content&mdash; that you want to appear in every document of that type.
   When a document is created or opened with the template, the styles are
   automatically applied to that document. Templates greatly enhance the use
   of &ooo; by simplifying formatting tasks for a variety of different types
   of documents. For example, in a word processor, you might write letters,
   memos, and reports, all of which look different and require different
   styles. Or, for example, for spreadsheets, you might want to use
   different cell styles or headings for certain types of spreadsheets. If
   you use templates for each of your document types, the styles you need
   for each document are always readily available.
  </para>

  <para>
   &ooo; comes with a set of predefined templates, and you can find
   additional templates on the Internet. For details, see
   <xref linkend="sec.oo.oview.help"/>. If you want to create your own
   templates, this requires some up-front planning. You need to determine
   how you want the document to look so you can create the styles you need
   in that template.
  </para>

  <para>
   A detailed explanation of templates is beyond the scope of this section.
   <xref
    linkend="pro.oo.oview.templates"/> only shows how to generate a
   template from an existing document.
  </para>

  <procedure id="pro.oo.oview.templates">
   <title>Creating &ooo; Templates</title>
   <para>
    For text documents, spreadsheets, presentations, and drawings, you can
    easily create a template from an existing document as follows:
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start &ooo; and open or create a document that contains the styles and
     content that you want to re-use for other documents of that type.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Templates</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Save</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Specify a name for the template.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Categories</guimenu> box, click the category you want
     to place the template in. The category is the directory where the template
     is stored.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <note>
   <title>Converting Former Microsoft Word Templates</title>
   <para>
    You can convert Microsoft Word templates like you would create any other
    Word document. See <xref
     linkend="sec.oo.oview.migration.convert"/>
    for information.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.oo.overview.properties">
  <title>Setting Metadata and Properties</title>

  <para>
   When exchanging documents with other people, it is sometimes useful to
   store metadata like the owner of the file, received from, an URL, or other
   useful data. &ooo; lets you save these metadata which can be attached to
   your file. This helps you track metadata which should or cannot be saved in
   your file. It is also useful for sorting, searching and retrieving your
   documents based on the metadata that you have inserted before.
   <remark>toms 2010-03-04: Maybe remove the last sentence as the "How?"
   should be explained too (which might be difficult)</remark>
  </para>

  <para>
   As an example, we assume you want to set these properties to your file:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A title, subject, and some keywords
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     An owner of your file
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     When it was received from
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   To attach these metadata to your document, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Setting Properties</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> </menuchoice>. A dialog opens with
     the following tabs:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>General</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        This is a more overview tab where you can see the type, its
        location, size, when it was created and modified and other useful
        information. If you have a digital signature, it is also possible to
        digitally sign your document.
        <remark>toms 2010-03-03 How?
         Where?</remark>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Description</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Insert your title, subject, keywords and comments as you like.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Custom Properties</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Custom properties specify the editor, owner, publisher, received
        from, and other useful metadata.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Internet</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Determine if your document needs a refresh from the Internet.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Statistics</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Contains an overview about your documents. Usually it lists the
        number of pages, tables, graphics, and others depending on the type
        of your document.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Change to the <guimenu>Description</guimenu> tab and insert title,
     subject, and your keywords.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Switch to the <guimenu>Custom Properties</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>. In the properties list a new entry is
     created.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the pull-down menu of the first entry in the
     <guimenu>Name</guimenu> row. A list of properties appears.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Choose the <guimenu>Owner</guimenu> and insert your text in the
     <guimenu>Value</guimenu> row.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Repeat the previous step with the <guimenu>Received from</guimenu>
     property and a suitable value.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Leave the dialog with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Save your file.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.oo.oview.help">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   &ooo; contains extensive online help. In addition, a large community of
   users and developers support it. The following lists shows some of the
   places where you can go for additional information.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>&ooo; Online Help Menu</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Extensive help on performing any task in &ooo;.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><ulink url="http://www.libreoffice.org"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Home page of &libo;
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><ulink url="http://www.taming-openoffice-org.com/"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Taming &ooo; and Apache OpenOffice: books, news, tips and tricks.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><ulink url="http://www.pitonyak.org/oo.php"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Extensive information about creating and using macros.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><ulink url="http://www.worldlabel.com/Pages/openoffice-template.htm"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Various templates for creating labels with &ooo;.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
