<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!-- 
 Version information:
 * SLE11 SP1: 4.3.5
 * SLE11 SP2: 4.3.5
 * SLE11 SP3: 4.3.5 (2013-02-28)
-->
<chapter id="cha.kopete">
 <title>Kopete: Instant Messaging</title><indexterm>
 <primary>KDE</primary>
 <secondary>Kopete</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>Internet</primary>
 <secondary>chatting</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>applications</primary>
 <secondary>network</secondary>
 <tertiary>Kopete</tertiary></indexterm>
 <para>
  Kopete is an online messenger application allowing multiple partners
  connected to the Internet to chat with each other. Kopete currently
  supports all common messenger protocols, such as AOL* Instant Messenger
  (AIM), GroupWise&reg; Messenger, ICQ, Jabber*, SMS, Skype*, WinPopup and
  Yahoo!*.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.kopete.config">
  <title>Configuring Kopete</title>

  <para>
   Before you can chat with your friends, you need to create an account:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open Kopete by pressing <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
     <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and entering <command>kopete</command>.
     If Kopete does not start, check if the package
     <systemitem class="resource">kopete</systemitem> is installed.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Configure</guimenu> </menuchoice> and click <guimenu>Add
     Accounts...</guimenu>. The configuration wizard appears.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select your messaging service. Generally, this is mostly determined by
     what service your friends are using.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If the messaging services requires registration but you do not have an
     account for this service yet, click <guimenu>Register New
     Account</guimenu>. In the browser window that opens, enter your user
     data to register.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Switch back to Kopete and enter the data received on registration with
     the messaging service. This usually consists of the nickname or e-mail
     address and a password. Complete the configuration of your account by
     clicking <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

<!-- 
    <figure id="fig.kopete.conf">
      <title>Kopete Configuration Panels</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="kopete-conf.png" width="55%" format="PNG"
          ></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="kopete-conf.png" width="55%" format="PNG"
          ></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
-->

  <para>
   After you have configured your account you need to add contacts to chat
   with them. If you have already created an account on another PC, this
   data is imported and automatically added to your contact list after
   login.
   <remark>taroth 0707017: really? but only if you have used and
    configured kopete there as well, I guess</remark>
   <remark>mdejmek:080924: sound strange to me as
    well... please, check</remark>
   <remark>toms: This is correct. If I add a new contact at home, say
    for ICQ, and I move to the office and log in there, I'll get the new contact(s) automatically in
    my contact list.</remark>
   <remark>mdejmek: 080925: okay, added this, to make it clearer</remark>
   To manually create a contact entry, click <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Add Contact</guimenu> </menuchoice>. A
   new assistant appears to help with creation. However, you must be online
   and connect with Kopete to the selected messaging service to add a
   contact to your list.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kopete.chat">
  <title>Chatting with Friends</title>

  <para>
   It is necessary to be connected to the Internet to be able to chat with
   other participants. When this is done, you should set your status by
   clicking <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Set
   Status</guimenu> <guimenu>Online</guimenu> </menuchoice>. This
   establishes a connection between Kopete and the selected messaging
   service. After the successful login, you are visible to others.
  </para>

  <para>
   The main application windows features a list of contacts. You must have
   contacts to chat with others. To add a new contact, click on <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Add Contact</guimenu> </menuchoice> and
   choose your identity. After you have entered the relevant data (which can
   vary depending on your account) you see your new contact. When you
   right-click a contact marked as online, a menu opens with various
   options. Send that person a message or start a chatting session. A chat
   allows the invitation of additional participants for real-time
   discussion. Connection to all participants is closed when the creator of
   the chat session closes it.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.kopete.chat">
   <title>Chat Window</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kopete_chat.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kopete_chat.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   If you want to see your previous chat session, select a contact and go to
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Latest History</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>. This menu item shows your chat sessions with this person.
   Conversely, you can select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
   <guimenu>View History</guimenu> </menuchoice>. This opens a window where
   you can see an overview of all contacts and there saved messages.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can view other options by right-clicking a username. A pop-up menu
   opens. An important option is <guimenu>Start Chat</guimenu> to start a
   chatting session. With <guimenu>Rename Contact</guimenu> and
   <guimenu>Remove Contact</guimenu>, you can run the relevant action. The
   pop-up menu also contains a submenu item with the username where you can
   block the user or get user information.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>Scrolling Through Old Chat Sessions</title>
   <para>
    If you want to know what you wrote during one of the last chat sessions
    with a person, click a contact to open the chat window again and press
    <keycombo> <keycap function="alt">Alt</keycap>
    <keycap function="left">Left</keycap> </keycombo> or <keycombo>
    <keycap function="alt">Alt</keycap>
    <keycap function="right">Right</keycap> </keycombo> to scroll through
    your sessions. Alternatively, use the arrow icons in the toolbar to
    scroll back and forth.
   </para>
  </tip>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kopete.customizing">
  <title>Customizing Kopete</title>

  <para>
   Kopete offers numerous options to customize it according to your needs.
   Find some examples in the following sections.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.kopete.addgroup">
   <title>Adding Groups</title>
   <para>
    Grouping contacts in your list can give a better overview. Click
    <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Create New Group</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>. Name the group and confirm this with
    <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. A new folder appears in the contact list that can
    be used to store the desired contacts. Drag and drop contacts into the
    desired folder.
   </para>
   <figure id="fig.kopete.contact">
    <title>The Main Kopete Window</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="kopete_groups.png" width="55%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="kopete_groups.png" width="28%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    Empty groups can be disabled by activating <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Hide Empty Groups</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>. To customize a special group only, right-click the
    relevant entry and select <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> in the pop-up
    window that opens. Now change the icons or your notifications.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kopete.globalidentity">
   <title>Using an Identity</title>
   <para>
    Kopete can manage several accounts, which is helpful if you have friends
    using different messenger protocols. Each account can be associated with
    a different identity. This is useful for privacy or business reasons. To
    create a new identity, proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      In Kopete, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Configure</guimenu> </menuchoice> and go to the
      <guimenu>Accounts</guimenu> tab. The configuration window appears.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select <guimenu>Add Identity...</guimenu> and enter a name, nickname,
      and other information.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      If you want to use the new identity for different accounts, simply
      move your account into your new identity.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kopete.notifications">
   <title>Configuring Notifications</title>
   <para>
    Kopete allows you to configure notifications for events such as contacts
    coming online or going offline or an incoming message for you. This can
    be done globally, for a specific group or a single contact.
   </para>
   <para>
    To activate the notifications option proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Make sure all your contacts are shown in the Kopete window. If not,
      select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Show Offline
      Users</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Right-click your preferred contact and select
      <guimenu>Properties</guimenu>. The notification dialog appears, see
      <xref linkend="fig.kopete.notifications"
       xrefstyle="select:label nopage"/>
     </para>
     <figure id="fig.kopete.notifications">
      <title>Notification Dialog in Kopete</title>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="kopete_notifications.png" width="80%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="kopete_notifications.png" width="80%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </figure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Go to the <guimenu>Custom Notification</guimenu> tab and select
      <guimenu>Contact Gone Online</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Decide which action should be executed for this event: <guimenu>Play a
      Sound</guimenu>, <guimenu>Show a Message in a Popup</guimenu>,
      <guimenu>Log to a File</guimenu>, <guimenu>Mark Taskbar
      Entry</guimenu>, or <guimenu>Run Command</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to confirm your settings.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    To modify the default notification options, select <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Notifications</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>. Select which event is important for you and change the
    notification settings. For example, if you want to be informed by a
    sound when any of your contacts has come online, select <guimenu>A
    contact has come online</guimenu> and activate <guimenu>Play a
    sound</guimenu>. Select the sound and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to
    close the configuration dialog.
   </para>
  </sect2>

<!--<sect2 id="sec.kopete.usernotifications">
      <title>Contact Defined Settings</title>
     <remark>taroth 070717: can you please move this content to the section before
    (sec.kopete.notification)? apart from the different way to get there, it is
    pretty much the same thing, only related to a certain contact and I don't
    think it needs  a separate sect2 </remark>
      <remark>toms 20070720: done. :)</remark>
    </sect2>-->

  <sect2 id="sec.kopete.plugins">
   <title>Configuring Kopete Plug-ins</title>
   <para>
    Kopete offers some nice extensions for you chat sessions which can be
    accessed from <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Configure Plugins</guimenu> </menuchoice>. For example, you can
    auto replace text, encrypt outgoing messages, highlight text (if the
    message contains some interesting words), render LaTeX formulas, or
    translate messages.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kopete.moreinfo">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   More information about Kopete and chats can be found on the following Web
   sites:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://kopete.kde.org">Kopete Home Page</ulink>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://www.webopedia.com/quick_ref/textmessageabbreviations.asp">Common
     Abbreviations Used in Chat Sessions</ulink>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://www.kde-forum.org">KDE Forum</ulink>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
