<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!--taroth 2013-02-18: SLED 11 SP3 contains pidgin 2.6.6-->
<!-- SLE 12 ships with Empathy, Pidgin needs to be installed later ... We should
probably replace the Pidgin & Ekiga chapters with an Empathy chapter at some point.
- sknorr, 2015-09-22 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.gnome.pidgin">
 <title>Pidgin: Instant Messaging</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
   </dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  Pidgin is an instant messaging (IM) client that
  allows you to connect to multiple accounts simultaneously. Chat live with
  your contacts in one tabbed interface, regardless of which IM system they
  use.
 </para>
 <para>
  Pidgin supports the following instant messaging protocols: AOL&ast;
  Instant Messenger (AIM), Bonjour, Gadu-Gadu, Google&ast; Talk, GroupWise&reg;
  Messenger, ICQ&ast;, IRC, Jabber/XMPP,
  Microsoft Lync&ast;/Office Communicator&ast;, MSN&ast; Messenger, MXit,
  MySpace&ast; IM,
  <remark>Not sure if MySpace IM still works: there still is a
  chat function, but the Windows app has been discontinued - sknorr, 2015-09-22
  </remark>
  QQ, SIMPLE, Yahoo!&ast;, and Zephyr&ast;.
  Pidgin supports many features of the various networks, such as file transfers,
  away messages, and typing notifications.
 </para>
 <para>
  In the following, learn how to set up Pidgin and how to communicate with
  your contacts.
 </para>

 <note>
  <title>Pidgin May Not Be Installed</title>
  <para>
   Before proceeding, make sure that the package <package>pidgin</package> is
   installed.
  </para>
  <para>
   To chat with users of Microsoft Lync and Microsoft Office Communicator,
   make sure that the package <package>pidgin-sipe</package> is installed.
  </para>
 </note>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.pidgin.start">
  <title>Starting Pidgin</title>

  <para>
   To start Pidgin, select
   <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guimenu>Internet</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Pidgin</guimenu></menuchoice>.
  </para>

 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.pidgin.configure">
  <title>Configuring Accounts</title>

  <para>
   To use Pidgin, you must already have accounts on the systems you want to
   use. For example, to use Pidgin for your AIM account, you must first have
   an AIM account. Once you have those accounts, set them up in the Pidgin
   <guimenu>Add Account</guimenu> dialog.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Adding and Editing Accounts</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     To start Pidgin, select
     <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guimenu>Internet</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Pidgin</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you start Pidgin for the first time, a message appears, prompting
     you to configure an account. Otherwise, Pidgin opens the Buddy List
     window, showing your contacts.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="optional">
    <para>
     To add or edit an account from the Buddy List, select <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Accounts</guimenu> <guimenu>Manage Accounts</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Accounts</guimenu> dialog, click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>
     to add a new account or select an existing account and click
     <guimenu>Modify</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Basic</guimenu> tab, select the protocol. The dialog to
     add or modify accounts differs for each protocol, depending on what
     setup options are available for that protocol.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="pidgin_addaccount.png" width="48%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="pidgin_addaccount.png" width="48%" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the data you received when you registered with the messaging service.
     This usually consists of the user name or e-mail address and a
     password.
    </para>
    <para>
     Your protocol might also support additional options, such as a
     buddy icon, alias, login options, or others.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="optional">
    <para>
     In many cases, the correct server data is now already set up.
     However, if you are configuring a Bonjour, Jabber, Groupwise, IRC,
     Microsoft Lync/Office Communicator, SIMPLE, or ZEPHYR account,
     you will have to add server or personal data.
    </para>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> tab, enter the data you got from your
     <phrase os="sled;sles">system administrator or</phrase> messaging service.
     <!-- Each type of account needs a little different data. Which means we
     can't really specify what it is - sknorr, 2015-09-23 -->
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Add</guimenu> (new account) or
     <guimenu>Save</guimenu> (modified account).
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Repeat this procedure to add accounts for each additional protocol you want
     to use.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   After an account is added, you can log in to that account by entering
   your password in the Pidgin login dialog.
  </para>
  <para>
   Use the
   <guimenu>Accounts</guimenu> menu to view and enable or disable accounts
   that you have configured.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.pidgin.buddy_list">
  <title>Managing Contacts</title>

  <remark>Ugh. "Buddy" is a horrible word, especially in enterprise
   documentation. Luckily, in Empathy, this is called the "roster", not the
   "buddy list." - sknorr, 2015-09-22
  </remark>
  <para>
   Use the Buddy List to manage your contacts, also known as buddies.
   You can add and remove buddies from your Buddy List.
   You can also organize your buddies in groups, so they are easy to find.
  </para>

  <para>
   After your accounts are set up, all buddies who are online appear in your
   Buddy List. If you want buddies who are not online to appear in the
   Buddy List, click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Buddies</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Show</guimenu> <guimenu>Offline Buddies</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Pidgin Buddy List</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="pidgin_buddylist.png" width="28%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="pidgin_buddylist.png" width="28%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   To add a buddy to your Buddy List, click <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Buddies</guimenu> <guimenu>Add Buddy</guimenu> </menuchoice>,
   then enter the information about that buddy.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>Adding Contacts for Certain Protocols</title>
   <para>
    <remark>Which protocols? - sknorr, 2015-09-23</remark>
    For some protocols, you cannot add a buddy in the Pidgin interface. You
    must use the official client for those protocols if you want to add to your
    buddy list.
    After you have added a buddy in the protocol’s client, that
    buddy appears in your Buddy List.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   To remove a buddy from the list of contacts, right-click the name of that
   buddy in the Buddy List and click <guimenu>Remove</guimenu>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.pidgin.chat">
  <title>Chatting with Friends</title>

  <para>
   It is necessary to be connected to the Internet to be able to chat with
   other participants. After a successful login, you are usually marked as
   <guimenu>Available</guimenu> in the Buddy List, and thus visible to
   others. To change your status, click the drop-down box at the bottom of
   the Buddy List and select another option.
  </para>

  <para>
   To open a chat session, double-click a buddy name in the Buddy List. The
   Chat screen opens. Type your message, then press <keycap>Enter</keycap>
   to send.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you open more than one chat session, the new session appears as a tab
   in the existing Chat window.
   To see all messages of a session and to be able to write a reply, click the
   tab of that session.
   To see multiple session side by side, use the mouse to drag a tab out of the
   window.
   A second window will open.
  </para>
  <para>
   To close a chat session, close the tab or window for it.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Pidgin Chat Session</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="pidgin_chat.png" width="55%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="pidgin_chat.png" width="55%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.pidgin.more">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   This chapter explained the Pidgin options you need to know about to set
   up Pidgin and communicate with your contacts. It does not explain all of
   features and options of Pidgin.
   For more information, open Pidgin, then click
   <menuchoice><guimenu>Help</guimenu><guimenu>Online Help</guimenu>
  </menuchoice> or press <keycap>F1</keycap>.
  </para>

  <para>
   For updates about new features and for the latest information, refer to
   the home page of the project at <link xlink:href="http://www.pidgin.im"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>