<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!--taroth 2013-02-2013: SLED 11 SP3 contains banshee 2.0.1-->
<chapter id="cha.banshee">
 <title>&musicplayer;: Playing and Managing Your Music</title>
 <para>
  &musicplayerreg; is a GNOME media management and playback application that
  lets you import CDs, sync your music and video collection to a digital
  audio player, play music directly from a digital audio player, create
  playlists with songs from your library, create audio and MP3 CDs from
  subsets of your library, and subscribe to, download, and listen to your
  favorite podcasts. &musicplayer; also supports streaming audio through its
  Internet Radio plug-in.
 </para>
 <para>
  To open &musicplayer;, click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Computer</guimenu>
  <guimenu>&musicplayer; Media Player</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
 </para>
 <para>
  The &musicplayer; displays a list of sources on the left. Select the
  respective entry to import music and videos, or to add Internet radio
  stations.
 </para>
 <figure id="fig.banshee.media.player">
  <title>&musicplayer; Media Player</title>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="banshee_music_library.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="banshee_music_library.png" width="70%" format="png"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>
 <sect1 id="sec.banshee.listen">
  <title>Listening to Music</title>

  <para>
   At first start of &musicplayer;, the music library is empty. To listen to
   music, you need to import music from sources such as files, folders, or a
   CD. You can also listen to music from Internet radio stations, podcasts,
   and your digital audio player. For more information, see
   <xref
    linkend="sec.banshee.audioplayer" xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage"/>.
   Alternatively, you can use &musicplayer;'s CD player function and listen
   to music directly off a CD.
  </para>

  <para>
   &musicplayer; also comes with MP3 support. If your music collection
   consists of both MP3 and Ogg Vorbis files, you do not need to convert any
   files to a different format. Open &musicplayer; and start listening.
  </para>

  <para>
   If the format you are trying to play is not supported by the player's
   engine, &musicplayer; lets you search for a suitable codec which you can
   then install with &yast;.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.banshee.listen.import">
   <title>Importing Music</title>
   <para>
    &musicplayer; can import music from a file, folder, CD, or an
    alternative music source (such as a digital audio player): Click
    <menuchoice> <guimenu>Media</guimenu> <guimenu>Import Media</guimenu>
    </menuchoice> and select where to import the media from.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.banshee.listen.play">
   <title>Playing Your Music</title>
   <para>
    To play a song, select the song in the library and click the play button
    in the upper left corner. Use the other buttons to pause a song or play
    the next or previous song. Use the loudspeaker button on the right to
    adjust the volume. You can also use the items on the
    <guimenu>Playback</guimenu> menu to repeat or shuffle songs.
   </para>
   <para>
    &musicplayer; has an integrated CD player. When you insert a music CD,
    the CD title appears in the left panel. Select the title and click the
    play button to play the CD.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.banshee.listen.play.notification">
    <title>Notification Area Icon</title>
    <para>
     You can keep &musicplayer; hidden in the notification area when you are
     not interacting with it by minimizing the &musicplayer; window. You
     will only see pop-up bubbles identifying the current song when track
     changes happen.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you do not want to see the pop-ups, click <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Extensions</guimenu> <guimenu>Notification Area Icon</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Disable</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.banshee.listen.play.recommend">
    <title>Music Recommendations</title>
    <para>
     You can enable additional panes in &musicplayer; to get more
     information about a song, it's artist or similar artists. Click
     <guimenu>View</guimenu> and enable <guimenu>Context Pane</guimenu> to
     show additional information from Wikipedia, related YouTube videos, or
     to receive recommendations on music that you might like, based on the
     currently playing song. (For information on configuring the context
     pane, refer to <xref linkend="sec.banshee.configure"/>).
    </para>
    <figure id="fig.banshee.listen.play.recommend">
     <title>Context Pane: Music Recommendations</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="banshee_recommendations_a.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="banshee_recommendations_a.png" width="75%" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.banshee.listen.rip">
   <title>Ripping Your Music</title>
   <para>
    &musicplayer; also allows you to rip music from an audio CD into various
    formats: Ogg Vorbis, or FLAC (Free Lossless Audio Codec) for example.
    You can set general preferences for ripping audio CDs as described in
    <xref linkend="sec.banshee.configure"/>. Ripping an audio CD
    automatically adds the tracks to your music library.
   </para>
   <procedure id="pro.banshee.listen.rip">
    <step>
     <para>
      Insert an audio CD into your CD or DVD drive.
     </para>
     <para>
      &musicplayer; automatically lists the CD as a source on the left
      sidebar.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <textobject role="description"><phrase>Ripping Music in &musicplayer;</phrase>
       </textobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="banshee_rip.png" width="90%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="banshee_rip.png" width="90%" format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select the CD entry in the source list on the left, and activate or
      deactivate tracks to rip as desired.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To start the ripping process, click <guimenu>Import CD</guimenu> in
      the upper right corner.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.banshee.listen.radio">
   <title>Listening to Internet Radio</title>
   <para>
    You can use &musicplayer; to listen to Internet radio stations and
    streaming audio.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.banshee.listen.radio.new">
    <title>Adding a New Internet Radio Station</title>
    <procedure id="pro.banshee.listen.radio.new">
     <step>
      <para>
       Right-click <guimenu>Radio</guimenu> in the source list, then click
       <guimenu>Add Station</guimenu>.
      </para>
      <informalfigure pgwide="0">
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
         <imagedata fileref="banshee_addradio_a.png" width="49%" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
         <imagedata fileref="banshee_addradio_a.png" width="49%" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Enter the stream details in the <guimenu>Add New Radio
       Station</guimenu> dialog box, then click <guimenu>Save</guimenu>.
      </para>
      <para>
       The new station is added to your list.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.banshee.listen.radio.web">
    <title>Listening to an Internet Radio Station</title>
    <para>
     To listen to Internet radio stations, select <guimenu>Radio</guimenu>
     in the source list on the left, then double-click the station you want
     to listen to.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.banshee.listen.podcast">
   <title>Listening to Podcasts</title>
   <para>
    &musicplayer; lets you subscribe, download, and listen to your favorite
    Podcasts.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.banshee.listen.podcast.subscribe">
    <title>Subscribing to a Podcast</title>
    <procedure id="pro.banshee.listen.podcast.subscribe">
     <step>
      <para>
       Select <guimenu>Podcast</guimenu> in the source list on the left.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Media</guimenu> <guimenu>Add
       Podcast</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Enter the URL of the podcast you want to subscribe to.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select what you want to happen when new episodes of this podcast are
       available. You can change the selected options later by
       right-clicking on the name of the podcast in the main window.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>Subscribe</guimenu>.
      </para>
      <para>
       The new podcast is added to your list.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.banshee.listen.podcast.listen">
    <title>Listening to a Podcast</title>
    <para>
     To listen to a podcast, select <guimenu>Podcasts</guimenu> in the
     source list, then double-click the podcast you want to listen to.
    </para>
<!--<figure id="fig.banshee.listen.podcast.listen">
     <title>Podcasts in &musicplayer;</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="banshee_podcast_a.png" width="95%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="banshee_podcast_a.png" width="95%" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>-->
    <para>
     To manage a single podcast you are subscribed to, right-click its name
     in the main window, and select one of the offered actions such as
     episode handling, visiting the podcast home page, unsubscribing and
     deleting, and checking or setting properties.
    </para>
    <para>
     To update all podcasts that you are subscribed to, manage podcast
     playlists, or set podcast related preferences, right-click
     <guimenu>Podcasts</guimenu> in the source list.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.banshee.manage">
  <title>Managing Your Music Library</title>

  <para>
   &musicplayer; gives you several ways to organize your music. You can
   create playlists, and sort and rate songs. You can also view a variety of
   information about your music collection, including playback statistics
   (when a song was last played and how many times).
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.banshee.manage.organize">
   <title>Organizing Your Music</title>
   <procedure id="pro.banshee.banshee.manage.organize.newplaylist">
    <title>Managing Playlists</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      To create a new music playlist, select <guimenu>Music</guimenu> in the
      source list on the left side.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Media</guimenu> <guimenu>New
      Playlist</guimenu> </menuchoice> (or press <keycombo>
      <keycap
         function="control"/> <keycap>N</keycap> </keycombo>).
      A new playlist is displayed below <guimenu>Music</guimenu> in the left
      panel. Enter the name you want.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To fill the new playlist, drag songs from the right-hand side of the
      window to the relevant playlist entry and drop them.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use the options on the <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu to remove or
      delete songs and rename or delete playlists.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To sort the current playlist according to a column, click the title of
      the column. Click the column title again to reverse the sort order.
      You can also right-click <guimenu>Music</guimenu>, then click
      <guimenu>Sort Playlists</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure>
    <title>Editing Track Information and Viewing Track Details</title>
    <para>
     You can edit the name of the artist, album, and title, as well as the
     track number and track count:
    </para>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select a song, then click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Edit Track Information</guimenu> </menuchoice>
      (<keycap>E</keycap>). Alternatively, in the main window right-click
      the song and select <guimenu>Edit Track Information</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To rate a song, select the number of stars you want to assign in the
      <guimenu>Rating</guimenu> field. This enables you to play only songs
      with a certain rating.
     </para>
     <figure id="fig.banshee.manage.organize.props">
      <title>Track Editor</title>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="banshee_properties_1.png" width="57%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="banshee_properties_1.png" width="47%" format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </figure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      If you want to set all fields in a group to the same value, select
      multiple songs in a playlist and click <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> <guimenu>Edit Track Information</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>. Make the changes you want, then click <guimenu>Sync All
      Field Values</guimenu>. You can also use the <guimenu>Back</guimenu>
      and <guimenu>Forward</guimenu> buttons to cycle through the selected
      songs.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      The track editor also lets you view detailed information about the
      selected song, including the bit rate, the sample rate, when a song
      was last played, when it was imported, how long the song is, how many
      times the song has been played, and where it is stored in your file
      system. To access the information, click the
      <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> tab.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.banshee.manage.playlist">
   <title>Creating Smart Playlists</title>
   <para>
    You can create playlists that automatically add and remove songs based
    on criteria you specify. For example, a smart playlist can contain songs
    you rated as five stars but that you have not listened to for six
    months. Another smart playlist can contain all songs published in 2010
    that you have labeled with the <guimenu>Classical</guimenu> genre.
   </para>
   <para>
    &musicplayer; automatically updates all smart playlists when a change is
    made to your music library. If you import new songs, &musicplayer;
    checks to see if they match any of your available smart playlists. When
    applicable, &musicplayer; also updates your smart playlists if you just
    listened to a song or updated a song's metadata.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.banshee.manage.playlist.create">
    <title>Creating a Smart Playlist</title>
    <procedure id="banshee.manage.playlist.create">
     <step>
      <para>
       Select <guimenu>Music</guimenu> in the source list on the left side.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       In the menu bar, click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Media</guimenu>
       <guimenu>New Smart Playlist</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Specify a name for the smart playlist, then select the criteria for
       songs in this playlist to match.
      </para>
      <informalfigure>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
         <imagedata fileref="banshee_smartplaylist.png" width="68%" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
         <imagedata fileref="banshee_smartplaylist.png" width="58%" format="png"/>
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      <para>
       Use the plus and minus symbols to add or remove criteria.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To use an already defined smart playlist, click <guimenu>Predefined
       Smart Playlists</guimenu>, select the playlist you want and click
       <guimenu>Open in Editor</guimenu>. Modify the criteria according to
       your wishes.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>Save</guimenu>. The smart playlist is added to your
       music library.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.banshee.audioplayer">
  <title>Using &musicplayer; with Your Digital Audio Player or Smart Phone</title>

  <para>
   &musicplayer; supports several digital audio players, including Apple*
   iPods, Creative* Nomads*, Dell* DJs, Nokia* N810, and almost any other
   generic USB Mass Storage devices (like Android phones, or Nokia* N900).
   Instead of having to use separate applications to get support for your
   audio devices, &musicplayer; gives you integrated support and lets you
   copy your music to or from your device, no matter what format the music
   is in.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.banshee.audioplayer.play">
   <title>Playing Music from your Digital Audio Player or Smart Phone</title>
   <para>
    To play music from your digital audio player, simply plug your device
    into your system. After the system recognizes the device, an icon is
    displayed in the left panel in &musicplayer;.
   </para>
   <para>
    Select the icon to display the music on your device in the right panel.
    Double-click the song you want to listen to.
   </para>
   <figure id="fig.banshee.audioplayer.play">
    <title>&musicplayer; MP3 Playback from a Nokia N810</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="banshee_n810_playback.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="banshee_n810_playback.png" width="72%" format="png"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    To view or change device properties, right-click your device, then
    select <guimenu>Device Properties</guimenu>. From there, you can view
    various pieces of information. For example, if you have an iPod, you can
    update the owner's name.
   </para>
   <figure id="fig.banshee.ipod.dev_props">
    <title>&musicplayer; iPod Device Properties</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="banshee_ipod_device_props.png" width="45%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="banshee_ipod_device_props.png" width="50%" format="png"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.banshee.audioplayer.add">
   <title>Adding Music to Your Digital Audio Player or Smart Phone</title>
   <para>
    To add tracks to your player or phone, simply drag them from your music
    library to your device.
   </para>
   <para>
    &musicplayer; transparently supports the transcoding of your songs for
    any device. You can have your music library in any number of formats
    (including, but not limited to, FLAC, Ogg Vorbis, MP3, and AAC), and it
    will be transparently transcoded before it is sent to your digital audio
    player.
   </para>
   <para>
    To remove tracks, select your device in the list of sources, right-click
    the song you want to delete, then click <guimenu>Delete from
    &lt;device_name&gt;</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.banshee.audioplayer.copy">
   <title>Copying Music from Your Digital Audio Player or Smart Phone to &musicplayer;</title>
   <para>
    &musicplayer; supports the importing of music from a digital audio
    player or smart phone to your music library. Simply drag and drop the
    songs from the device to your music library. You can also import all of
    the music on your device by right-clicking your player in the source
    list and selecting <guimenu>Import to Library</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <figure id="fig.banshee.audioplayer.copy">
    <title>Importing Music from Your Digital Audio Player to &musicplayer;</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="banshee_dap_import.png" width="83%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="banshee_dap_import.png" width="83%" format="png"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.banshee.audioplayer.sync">
   <title>Synchronizing With Digital Audio Players or Smart Phones</title>
   <para>
    &musicplayer; offers several options to keep your external devices up to
    date with your &musicplayer; library: you can either synchronize music,
    audiobooks, videos, or podcasts manually or choose automatic
    synchronization, for example, on first plug-in or after any changes to
    your &musicplayer; library.
   </para>
   <para>
    To set the synchronization options, plug in your device, select the
    device entry in the source list on the left and select the respective
    options on the right.
   </para>
   <para>
    &musicplayer; also synchronizes the ratings and cover art in your tracks
    to your iPod.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.banshee.cd">
  <title>Creating Audio and MP3 CDs</title>

  <procedure id="pro.sec.banshee.cd.create">
   <step>
    <para>
     Insert a blank CD into the CD or DVD drive.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the songs you want to burn.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> <guimenu>Write CD</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Burn</guimenu> to start Brasero where you can set any
     additional options. For more information about Brasero, see
     <xref linkend="cha.gnome.burn"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the burning process. You can track the status of the burn the
     Brasero pop-up window. A message box appears when the burn is complete.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.banshee.share">
  <title>Sharing Your Music</title>

  <para>
   &musicplayer; contains a plug-in for <productname>Last.fm</productname>,
   a popular Internet radio and music community Web site. You can
   automatically update your online <ulink url="http://www.last.fm"/>
   profile with the music you listen to in &musicplayer;. This lets others
   see what you are listening to, and gives you access to charts detailing
   your listening history. If you join groups such as the
   <ulink url="http://www.last.fm/group/Banshee">Banshee Group</ulink>, you
   can also see what other people are listening to.
  </para>

  <para>
   To scrobble your music to Last.fm and to share your music, you need to
   have a Last.fm account. Then you can activate the Last.fm plug-in in
   &musicplayer;, enter your Last.fm credentials, and enable song reporting:
  </para>

  <procedure id="pro.sec.banshee.share">
   <title>Scrobbling Your Music to Last.fm</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     To enable the plug-in, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu> <guimenu>Extensions</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>, activate <guimenu>Last.fm Scrobbling</guimenu> and close
     the dialog.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the source list on the left, select the <literal>Last.fm</literal>
     entry and click <guimenu>Account Settings</guimenu> in the right pane.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If you have already registered with
     <ulink url="http://www.last.fm/"
      >Last.fm</ulink>, enter your
     Last.fm username and click <guimenu>Log in to Last.fm</guimenu> which
     takes you to the Last.fm Web site. Follow the instructions on the
     screen to allow &musicplayer; to connect to your Last.fm account.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you have not previously registered with Last.fm, click <guimenu>Sign
     up for Last.fm</guimenu>. This takes you to the Last.fm Web site where
     you can register. Follow the instructions on the screen.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After having entered your Last.fm credentials, activate <guimenu>Enable
     Song Reporting</guimenu> and confirm your changes. &musicplayer; starts
     reporting with the next song you play.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.banshee.configure">
  <title>Configuring &musicplayer; Preferences</title>

  <procedure id="pro.sec.banshee.configure">
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <textobject role="description"><phrase>&musicplayer; Preferences dialog box</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="banshee_preferences.png" width="49%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="banshee_preferences.png" width="49%" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     For example, choose from the <guimenu>General</guimenu> tab whether to
     write metadata to the imported files or disable features requiring
     Internet access.
    </para>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Copy Files to Music Folder When Importing</guimenu> to
     place a copy of the files you import in your &musicplayer; music
     folder.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Source Specific</guimenu> tab, you can define a number
     of settings for each source that you can select in the source list on
     the left. The available options depend on the entry you select from the
     <guimenu>Source</guimenu> drop-down list:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For example, for the source <literal>Music</literal> you can define
       the following settings: the location that is used when you import
       music (<guimenu>Music Folder</guimenu>), or the folder hierarchy in
       the music library, and how filenames are displayed (<guimenu>File
       Organization)</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For <literal>Videos</literal> and <literal>Podcasts</literal> you can
       also specify the location that is used when you import videos or
       download podcasts.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For <literal>Audio CDs</literal>, define the <guimenu>Import
       Format</guimenu> you want to use for CD ripping. Click
       <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> to configure advanced options for that
       format.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For Last.fm access, enter your Last.fm credentials.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Extensions</guimenu> tab enable or disable features
     such as <guimenu>Cover Art Fetching</guimenu>, <guimenu>Internet
     Radio</guimenu>, <guimenu>Last.fm Scrobbling</guimenu>, or support for
     <guimenu>Amazon MP3 Store</guimenu>. This also defines which entries
     appear in the source list on the left.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Close</guimenu> to save your changes.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.banshee.more">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   For more information about &musicplayer;, including a section with FAQs
   (Frequently Asked Questions) and updates about new features, refer to the
   project's home page at <ulink url="http://banshee.fm"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
