<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC 
  "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN"
  "novdocx.dtd"
[
 <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entities;
]>
<!-- 
 Version information:
 * SLE11 SP1: 4.3.5
 * SLE11 SP2: 4.3.5
-->
<chapter id="cha.okular">
 <title>Viewing PDF Files and Other Documents with Okular</title>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   Apart from PDF files, Okular allows you to view a great number of file
   formats, such as PostScript, several image formats, OpenDocument format
   (ODF), OpenDocument text (ODT), some eBook formats (ePub), and even
   Microsoft* Compiled HTML Help (CHM). Okular also provides support for
   bookmarks, annotations, form fields, multimedia content, and rotation of
   pages.
   <remark>taroth
    080911: new chapter about KDE document viewer (as PM wants to keep doc clear of proprietary
    stuff: don't mention acroread)</remark>
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <sect1 id="sec.okular.viewpdf">
  <title>Viewing PDF Files</title>

  <para>
   Documents that need to be shared or printed across platforms can be saved
   as PDF (Portable Document Format) files, for example, in the
   OpenOffice.org suite. View them with Okular, the default KDE document
   viewer.
  </para>

  <para>
   Start Okular from the main menu or press <keycombo>
   <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter
   <command>okular</command>. To open a document, select <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Open</guimenu> </menuchoice> and choose
   the desired file from the file system. Navigate through the document by
   using the navigation icons at the top or bottom of the window. Depending
   on which icon you click on the navigation panel on the left, the sidebar
   either shows a table of <guimenu>Contents</guimenu>, a
   <guimenu>Thumbnails</guimenu> view of each page, the
   <guimenu>Reviews</guimenu> for this file, or your
   <guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu> for this file. To filter for any text listed
   in the sidebar or the overall document, enter a string into the input
   field at the top of the sidebar. If you want to select and copy text or
   images from the file in Okular, click the <guimenu>Selection</guimenu>
   icon in the toolbar and select one of the options from the context menu.
   Click the <guimenu>Browse</guimenu> icon to switch back to browsing the
   document.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Okular Viewing a PDF File</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kde_okular.png" width="80%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kde_okular.png" width="80%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.okular.annotate">
  <title>Annotating a PDF File</title>

  <para>
   With Okular, you can review a document by highlighting certain text parts
   or adding annotations or bookmarks that Okular then attaches to the file
   in form of metadata. Note that the annotations and markers you add are
   not stored within the document, so you cannot print them or pass them on
   to other users.
  </para>

  <para>
   To create an annotation for a page, press <keycap>F6</keycap> and select
   one of the annotation tools from the toolbar that appears. The annotation
   is added to the list of Reviews and is flagged with the login name of the
   user who created it. Use the icons at the bottom of the sidebar to group
   the annotations by page, by author or to show the annotations for the
   current page only.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Annotating a PDF File</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="okular_annotate.png" width="80%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="okular_annotate.png" width="80%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.okular.moreinfo">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   See the homepage <ulink url="http://okular.kde.org"/> of Okular for more
   information. The supported formats can be viewed at
   <ulink url="http://okular.kde.org/formats.php"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
