<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!-- 
 Version information:
 * SLE11 SP1: 4.3.5
 * SLE11 SP2: 4.3.5
 * SLE11 SP3: 4.3.5 (as by 2013-02-28)
-->
<chapter id="cha.konqueror">
 <title>Konqueror: Browsing the Web</title><indexterm>
 <primary>browsers</primary>
 <see>Web browsers</see></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>applications</primary>
 <secondary>network</secondary>
 <tertiary>Konqueror</tertiary></indexterm>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   Konqueror is a modern Web browser, but can also be used as a file
   manager. However, to manage your files and directories, it is recommended
   to use Dolphin. If you start the browser with the icon in the panel,
   Konqueror opens with the Web browser profile. As a browser, Konqueror
   offers tabbed browsing, the possibility of saving Web pages with
   graphics, Internet keywords, bookmarks, and support for Java and
   JavaScript.
  </para>
 </abstract><indexterm id="idx.Konqueror_Webbrowser" class="startofrange">
 <primary>Konqueror</primary></indexterm><indexterm id="idx.Webbrowser_Konqueror" class="startofrange">
 <primary>Web browsers</primary>
 <secondary>Konqueror</secondary></indexterm>
 <figure id="fig.kde2.konqueror">
  <title>The Browser Window of Konqueror</title>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="konqueror.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="konqueror.png" width="50%" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>
 <para>
  <indexterm>
  <primary>Konqueror</primary>
  <secondary>starting</secondary>
  </indexterm> Start Konqueror from the main menu or by entering the command
  <command>konqueror</command>. If Konqueror does not start, check if the
  package <systemitem class="resource">konqueror</systemitem> is installed.
  To load a Web page, enter its address in the location bar, for example
  <ulink url="http://www.opensuse.org"/>. Konqueror now attempts to reach
  the address and displays the page. Entering the protocol at the beginning
  of the address (<systemitem>http://</systemitem> in this case) is not
  strictly required. The program is able to complete the address
  automatically, but this only works reliably with Web addresses. For an FTP
  address, always enter <literal>ftp://</literal> at the beginning of the
  input field.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.konq.tabbedbrowsing">
  <title>Tabbed Browsing</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Konqueror</primary>

  <secondary>tabs</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   If you often use more than one Web page at a time, tabbed browsing may
   make it easier to switch between them. Load Web sites in separate tabs
   within one window. The advantage is that you keep more control over your
   desktop because you only have one main window. After logout, the KDE
   session management allows you to save your Web session in Konqueror. The
   next time you log in, Konqueror loads the exact URLs visited last time.
  </para>

  <para>
   To open a new tab, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Window</guimenu>
   <guimenu>New Tab</guimenu> </menuchoice> or press <keycombo>
   <keycap function="control">Ctrl</keycap> <keycap>T</keycap> </keycombo>.
   To change the behavior of tabs, go to <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure Konqueror</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>. In the dialog box that opens, select
   <guimenu>General</guimenu> and enable <guimenu>Open links in new tab
   instead of in new window</guimenu>. You can also hide the tab bar with
   <guimenu>Hide the tab bar When only one tab is open</guimenu>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.konq.automaticscrolling">
  <title>Automatic Scrolling</title>

  <para>
   In general, scrolling with the mouse is the normal way to view
   information further down a page. However, there are occasions when it is
   preferable not to use a mouse. It can be very convenient to use key
   combinations instead of removing your hands from the keyboard.
  </para>

  <para>
   To scroll down automatically, use <keycombo>
   <keycap function="shift">Shift</keycap> <keycap function="down"/>
   </keycombo>. This scrolls down the page without further intervention.
   Increase the speed by pressing <keycombo>
   <keycap function="shift">Shift</keycap>
   <keycap function="down">↓</keycap> </keycombo> again. Pressing
   <keycombo> <keycap function="shift">Shift</keycap>
   <keycap function="up">↑</keycap> </keycombo> slows down. To stop
   scrolling, use <keycap
        function="down">↓</keycap>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.konq.profiles">
  <title>Profiles</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Konqueror</primary>

  <secondary>profiles</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   <xref linkend="sec.konq.tabbedbrowsing"/> described how to handle tabs in
   Konqueror. You can save your tabs with URLs and the position of the
   window in a profile. This differs from the session management already
   mentioned. With profiles, your saved tabs are at hand without the
   intensive start-up time of session management.
  </para>

  <para>
   To create a profile, do the following:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Go to <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure View
     Profiles</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the dialog box that appears, insert a name in <guimenu>Profile
     Name</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To save your URLs, select <guimenu>Save URLs in Profile</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Approve with <guimenu>Save</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   The next time you need your tab collection, go to <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Load View Profile</guimenu>
   </menuchoice> and find the name listed in the menu. After you select it,
   Konqueror restores your tabs.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.konq.saving">
  <title>Saving Web Pages and Graphics</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Konqueror</primary>

  <secondary>saving Web pages</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>Web pages</primary>

  <secondary>archiving</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   As in other browsers, you can save Web pages. To do this, select
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Save As</guimenu>
   </menuchoice> and specify a name for your HTML file. However, images are
   not saved. To archive an entire Web page including the images, select
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Archive Web Page</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>. Konqueror suggests a filename that you can usually accept.
   The filename ends with <filename>.war</filename>, the extension for Web
   archives. To view the saved Web archive later, simply click the relevant
   file and the Web page is displayed in Konqueror along with images.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.konq.searching">
  <title>Searching with Konqueror</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Konqueror</primary>

  <secondary>Web shortcuts</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>Konqueror</primary>

  <secondary>keywords</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Searching with Konqueror is very convenient. You can use the search bar
   or Web shortcuts.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.konq.searchbar">
   <title>Using the Search Bar</title>
   <para>
    Konqueror contains a search bar where you can choose from many search
    engines. If you want to search for a specific term, proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Locate the search bar in Konqueror. It is on the right side after the
      location bar.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the icon inside the search bar. Choose a search engine from the
      pop-up menu.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Insert your search term and press
      <keycap function="enter">Enter</keycap>. The result is displayed in
      Konqueror.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    If you need a search engine that is not listed in the pop-up menu, add
    it as follows:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Adding More Search Engines</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      In Konqueror, click the icon in the search bar.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose <guimenu>Select Search Engines...</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Make sure that <guimenu>Enable Web shortcuts</guimenu> is activated.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Enable the relevant search engine and close the dialog with
      <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. You can see your selected search engine when
      you click the icon in the search bar.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.konq.webshortcut">
   <title>Using Web Shortcuts</title>
   <para>
    Each search engine defined is attached to a <emphasis>web
    shortcut</emphasis>. This shortcut can be entered in the location bar.
   </para>
   <para>
    To see which search engines are already defined, go to <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure Konqueror</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Web Browsing</guimenu> <guimenu>Web Shortcuts</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>. You can see the names of the search providers and the
    shortcuts. Konqueror defines many search engines: Google, Yahoo, Lycos,
    and a number of less common resources like an acronym database, the
    Internet movie database, and KDE application searches.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you do not find your preferred search engine here, you are able to
    define a new one very easily. For example, to search our home page for
    some interesting articles, go to
    <ulink
     url="http://en.opensuse.org/"/>, enter your query and look
    for the appropriate results.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Creating New Web Shortcuts</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Go to the search bar, click the icon, and select <guimenu>Select
      Search Engines</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Make sure that <guimenu>Enable Web shortcuts</guimenu> is activated.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>New</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Create a new Web shortcut:
     </para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>
        Assign your Web shortcut a name in <guimenu>Search provider
        name</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Enter the search URI. For example, if you want to search in
        &opensuse;, use
        <ulink
         url="http://en.opensuse.org/Special:Search?search=\{@}"/>.
        The search query is specified as <literal>\{@}</literal>. Get more
        information by clicking in the text field labeled with
        <guimenu>Search URI</guimenu> and pressing <keycombo>
        <keycap function="shift">Shift</keycap> <keycap>F1</keycap>
        </keycombo>.
       </para>
       <remark>Translators: Change the "en" to your language code. -toms</remark>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Enter your abbreviations in <guimenu>URI Shortcuts</guimenu>. There
        you can enter more than one, separated by commas.
       </para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Proceed with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    After creating a new Web shortcut, you can use it in the location bar.
    The result is displayed in the current window.
   </para>
   <tip>
    <title>Using Shortcuts Directly without Opening Konqueror</title>
    <para>
     You do not need to open Konqueror and enter the Web shortcut. You can
     use it directly: select <guimenu>Run Command</guimenu> from the main
     menu or press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt">Alt</keycap>
     <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo>. After the dialog box appears, enter
     your shortcut, a colon (:), and your search term.
    </para>
   </tip>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.konq.bookmarks">
  <title>Bookmarks</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Konqueror</primary>

  <secondary>bookmarks</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Instead of remembering and reentering addresses for sites visited often,
   you can bookmark these URLs using the <guimenu>Bookmark</guimenu> menu.
   As well as Web page addresses, you can also bookmark the directories of
   your local disk in this way.
  </para>

  <para>
   To create a new bookmark in Konqueror, click <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu> <guimenu>Add Bookmark</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>. Any previously added bookmarks are included as items in
   the menu. It is a good idea to arrange the bookmark collection by
   subjects in a hierarchical structure, so that you do not lose track of
   the different items. Create a new subgroup for your bookmarks with
   <guimenu>New Bookmark Folder</guimenu>. Selecting <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu> <guimenu>Edit Bookmarks</guimenu>
   </menuchoice> opens the bookmark editor. Use this program to organize,
   rearrange, add, and delete bookmarks.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you are using Netscape, Mozilla, or Firefox as additional browsers, it
   is not necessary to re-create your bookmarks. <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Import</guimenu> <guimenu>Import
   Netscape Bookmarks</guimenu> </menuchoice> in the bookmark editor enables
   you to integrate your Netscape and Mozilla bookmarks into your most
   current collection. The reverse is also possible via <guimenu>Export as
   Netscape Bookmarks</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Change your bookmarks by right-clicking the entry. A pop-up menu appears
   in which to select the desired action (cut, copy, delete, etc.). When you
   are satisfied with the result, save the bookmarks with <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Save</guimenu> </menuchoice>. If you
   only want to change the name or link, just right-click the entry in the
   bookmark toolbar and select <guimenu>Properties</guimenu>. Change the
   name and location and confirm with <guimenu>Update</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   To save your bookmark list and have instant access to it, make your
   bookmarks visible in Konqueror. Select <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Toolbars</guimenu> <guimenu>Bookmark
   Toolbar (Konqueror)</guimenu> </menuchoice>. A bookmark panel is
   automatically displayed in the current Konqueror window.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.konq.java">
  <title>Java and JavaScript</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Konqueror</primary>

  <secondary>Java</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>Konqueror</primary>

  <secondary>JavaScript</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Do not confuse these two languages. Java <indexterm>
   <primary>Java</primary>
   </indexterm> is an object-oriented, platform-independent programming
   language from Sun Microsystems. It is frequently used for small programs
   (applets), which are executed over the Internet for things like online
   banking, chatting, and shopping. JavaScript <indexterm>
   <primary>JavaScript</primary>
   </indexterm> is an interpreted scripting language mainly used for the
   dynamic structuring of Web pages, for example, for menus and other
   effects.
  </para>

  <para>
   Konqueror allows you to enable or disable these two languages. This can
   even be done in a domain-specific way, which means that you can permit
   access for some hosts and block access for others. Java and JavaScript
   are often disabled for security reasons. Unfortunately, some Web pages
   require JavaScript for correct display.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.konq.adblock">
  <title>Enabling Advertisement Blockers</title>

  <para>
   Some Web pages open annoying advertisements. With the help of Konqueror,
   these windows can be blocked. Proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Blocking Advertisements</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure
     Konqueror</guimenu> <guimenu>Web Browsing</guimenu> <guimenu>AdBlock
     Filters</guimenu> </menuchoice> in Konqueror.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Activate <guimenu>Enable filters</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter an expression for the Web page to filter. For example:
    </para>
<screen>http://www.example.com/*</screen>
    <para>
     This filters everything that comes from that URL.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Insert</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   If you need the entries on another computer, click
   <guimenu>Export</guimenu>, save the file, move it to your other computer
   and import it there into Konqueror using the same dialog box.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.konq.moreinfo">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   For any questions or problems that arise when working with Konqueror,
   refer to the application's handbook, which is available from the
   <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu. Konqueror also has a Web page, located at
   <ulink
    url="http://www.konqueror.org"/>.
  </para><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.Webbrowser_Konqueror"/><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.Konqueror_Webbrowser"/>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
