<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:novdoc-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml" 
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN"
                      "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "IGNORE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<?provo dirname="autoupgrade/"?>
<article id="art.update.auto" lang="en">
<?suse-quickstart columns="no" color="novell" version="2"?>
<!--
    version="1" color="suse" columns="2"
-->
 <title>Automated Upgrade from &sls; 10 SP3 to 11 SP1</title>
 <subtitle>&productname; &productnumber;</subtitle>
 <articleinfo>
  <productnumber>&productnumber;</productnumber><productname>&productname;</productname>
 </articleinfo>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   The following procedure is a way to do a mass upgrade unattended from
   &sls;&nbsp;10 SP3 to &sls;&nbsp;11 SP1. Several preparation steps are
   needed to create a suitable AutoYaST profile. AutoYaST finally will
   execute the upgrade process.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <sect1 id="sec.update.auto.prep">
  <title>Preparing and Applying the Driver Update Disk (DUD)</title>

  <para>
   The <systemitem>unattended_upgrade_dud</systemitem> package contains the
   Driver Update Disk (DUD); when installed, find it at
   <filename>/var/adm/unattended_migration.dud</filename>. This file
   contains all changes, which are needed for the unattended upgrade
   workflow. Install the <systemitem>unattended_upgrade_dud</systemitem>
   package to get access to the DUD. You do not need to install it on all
   the machines, which you intend to upgrade.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can use the DUD as follows, alternatively:
  </para>

  <sect2 id="update.auto.prep.mod">
   <title>Modify Contents of the Installation Source (Repository)</title>
   <para>
    Applicable on: &x86;, x86_64, &zseries;
   </para>
   <para>
    Append the DUD to the end of the installation
    <systemitem>initrd</systemitem>. The installation
    <systemitem>initrd</systemitem> is located at
    <filename>/boot/<replaceable>architecture</replaceable>/loader/initrd</filename>
    on the first DVD. Either use an ISO editor to update the ISO image or
    modify the <systemitem>initrd</systemitem> in your network installation
    environment. To adapt the <systemitem>initrd</systemitem>, run (use the
    correct path for your installation <systemitem>initrd</systemitem>):
   </para>
<screen
           >cat /var/adm/unattended_migration.dud >><replaceable>/path/to/your/installation/initrd</replaceable></screen>
   <warning>
    <title>Modified <systemitem>initrd</systemitem> Runs Unattended Upgrade Automatically</title>
    <para>
     Such an updated installation <systemitem>initrd</systemitem> will
     automatically run the unattended upgrade and will not be capable of
     doing any other method of upgrade or (auto)installation.
    </para>
   </warning>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="update.auto.prep.kpara">
   <title>Provide an Additional Kernel Parameter</title>
   <para>
    Applicable on: &x86;, x86_64, &ppc;, &ipf; &zseries;
   </para>
   <para>
    This way, there is no need to modify the installation source at all. You
    just must add an additional kernel parameter, which will point linuxrc
    to the DUD. At the boot prompt or in PXE boot menu add (replace the URI
    with correct one in your network infrastructure):
   </para>
<screen
>dud=<replaceable>ftp://host/directory/dud.dud</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    On &zseries;, you must add the parameters to the PARM file; proceed the
    same way as you do when performing an &ay;-driven installation.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     You may be asked to confirm the DUD, if it is comming from an unsafe
     installation source (repository). You can add the
     <literal>insecure=1</literal> boot parameter to the installation kernel
     to disable all cryptographical checking normally done by Linuxrc. For
     more information about Linuxrc, see
     <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/SDB:Linuxrc"/>.
    </para>
   </note>
  </sect2>

<!--
     <sect2 id="update.auto.prep.parm">
      <title>Update the PARM File</title>

       <para>Applicable on: &zseries;</para>
       <para>
        Update the PARM file for installation booting in a way that it
        establishes up the network connection and applies the DUD.
       </para>
     </sect2>
-->
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>&grub; Menu Section for Booting into the Upgrade</title>
  <remark condition="clarity">
   2014-02-10 - fs: FIXME: This entry needs to be adjusted to GRUB 2. ATM I
                           have no clue how to do it in GRUB 2.
  </remark>

  <para>
   An alternate way to boot the system is to create an additional section in
   the &grub; menu (similar for other architectures), which starts the
   installation. The following example assumes that there is a separate
   <filename>/boot</filename> partition, which is referred in &grub; as
   <literal>(hd0,0)</literal>:
  </para>

<screen
>title Upgrade
    root (hd0,0)
    kernel /upgrade/vmlinuz install=<replaceable>inst_source_url</replaceable> vga=0x314
    initrd /upgrade/initrd
  </screen>

  <para>
   The above example assumes that the installation kernel and the updated
   <systemitem>initrd</systemitem> (see
   <xref
  linkend="update.auto.prep.mod"/>) are located in the
   <filename>/boot/upgrade</filename> directory. If the
   <systemitem>initrd</systemitem> is not updated, just append the
   <literal>dud=</literal> parameter. On &zseries;, you must add the
   parameters to the PARM file&mdash;proceed the same way as you do when
   performing an &ay;-driven installation.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.update.auto.prep_autoyast">
  <title>Preparing the &ay; Profile</title>

  <para>
   The &ay; profile for the automated upgrade uses the same file format as
   the &ay; installation. <phrase os="sled;sles">For more information about
   &ay;, see the Deployment Guide and the &ay; Guide
<!-- <ulink
url="http://www.suse.de/~ug/autoyast_doc/index.html"/>-->
   .</phrase>
  </para>

  <para>
   However, for obvious reasons, there are some parts of the system (e.g.,
   partitioning) that do not make sense to be configured during the upgrade.
   On the other hand, it is useful to set upgrade-specific options by means
   of the &ay; profile.
  </para>

  <sect2>
   <title>Upgrade</title>
   <para>
    The upgrade options define the behavior of the dependency solver during
    upgrade:
   </para>
<screen><![CDATA[<upgrade>
  <only_installed_packages
    config:type="boolean">false</only_installed_packages>
  <stop_on_solver_conflict
    config:type="boolean">true</stop_on_solver_conflict>
</upgrade>]]></screen>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>only_installed_packages</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Set to <literal>true</literal> for package-based upgrades
       (recommended for upgrading to the next service pack of the same
       product) or <literal>false</literal> for pattern-based upgrades
       (recommended for an upgrade between versions of a product, e.g. from
       SLES10 to SLES11).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>stop_on_solver_conflict</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Defines whether to show the proposal in case of failure to resolve
       package dependencies interactively (recommended to be set to
       <literal>true</literal>, but this could result in an interactive
       process, during which the user must to resolve the conflicts
       manually.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Software Selection</title>
   <para>
    The software selection options define, which components to select or
    deselect in addition to the results of the resolver:
   </para>
<screen><![CDATA[<software>
  <packages config:type="list">
    <package>autoyast2-installation</package>
    <package>apparmor-profile-editor</package>
  </packages>
  <patterns config:type="list">
    <pattern>base</pattern>
  </patterns>
  <remove-packages config:type="list"/>
  <remove-patterns config:type="list"/>
</software>]]></screen>
   <para>
    It is especially important to set packages or patterns for being
    selected or deselected in order to resolve package conflicts and thus to
    avoid the need for interactive intervention. Once the upgrade is done,
    the newly created <filename>autoupg_updated.xml</filename> file contains
    these packages and patterns plus those that were selected or deselected
    for any other reason.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Backup Before Upgrade</title>
   <para>
    The backup before upgrade options match these features in the upgrade
    proposal.
   </para>
<screen><![CDATA[<backup>
  <sysconfig config:type="boolean">true</sysconfig>
  <modified config:type="boolean">true</modified>
  <remove_old config:type="boolean">false</remove_old>
</backup>]]></screen>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>sysconfig</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       defines whether to backup sysconfig before upgrading.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>modified</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       defines whether to backup the modified configuration files before
       upgrading.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>remove_old</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       defines whether to remove old backups from previous upgrades.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Networking</title>
   <para>
    To assure that the network configuration is kept during upgrade, the
    following needs to be added to the &ay; profile:
   </para>
<screen><![CDATA[<networking>
  <keep_install_network
    config:type="boolean">true</keep_install_network>
  <start_immediately
    config:type="boolean">true</start_immediately>
</networking>]]></screen>
   <para>
    If your system contains an add-on, which needs to be upgraded, always
    include the add-on information as in the example. After the upgrade the
    system needs to be registered in order to activate the update
    repositories.
<!-- FIXME: point ty ay docs? -->
    See the example of the registration part in attached autoupg.xml.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Running the Automated Upgrade</title>

  <para>
   To start the automated upgrade, you must boot the installation media with
   the DUD applied and pass the &ay; profile to it. There are two ways to
   pass the profile to the system:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Pass the profile to the kernel command line the same way as for the
     AutoYaST installation (use the
     <literal>autoyast=<replaceable>url</replaceable></literal> parameter.
     For &zseries;, this is the only possibility.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Before you start the upgrade, copy the profile to
     <filename>/root/autoupg.xml</filename>. Then there is no need for any
     additional kernel parameter.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   The latter approach allows you to have a single installation kernel
   command line for even different machines&mdash;just copy the appropriate
   profile into its file system.
  </para>

  <para>
   As long as you have only one &sls; system installed on your machine,
   there are no package conflicts and you did not set the profile to stop on
   the upgrade proposal, the complete process will be non-interactive. In
   case you enter the upgrade proposal, you can modify its settings for the
   upgrade.
  </para>

  <para>
   After the upgrade finishes, &yast; writes the
   <filename>/root/autoupg-updated.xml</filename> file, which contains the
   profile with applied software selection changes done in the proposal.
   This is especially useful in case of mass upgrades of machines with the
   same package selection. This way, conflict resolutions from one machine
   can easily be applied on other machines, which consequently will get
   these conflicts resolved automatically and the upgrade itself will be
   non-interactive.
  </para>

  <para>
   If there are more &sls; systems installed on the machine, you will always
   be asked, which one to upgrade&mdash;there is no way to select it in
   advance.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Second Stage of the Upgrade</title>

  <para>
   The automated upgrade by default does not perform configuration changes
   during the second stage of the upgrade. The only exception is network
   configuration, which needs to be set to be preserved in the AutoYaST
   upgrade profile.
  </para>

  <para>
   If configuration adjustment of some system areas is needed after the
   upgrade (e.g., configuring a new service), add the relevant sections to
   the &ay; profile for the upgrade and the configuration of the selected
   system areas will be saved during the upgrade.
  </para>

  <warning>
   <title>&ay; Supplied Configuration Replaces Exisiting Configuration</title>
   <para>
    Be warned that existing configuration of that system area will be
    replaced and thus destroyed by the &ay; configuration.
   </para>
  </warning>

  <para>
   Normally, the only configuration adjustment, which should be present in
   the &ay; profile, is the registration of the system with Subscription
   Management Tool (SMT) or Novell Customer Center (NCC). If this is
   missing, the system will not get the update repository and updates will
   not be possible&mdash;unless configured later again.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Limitations and Hints</title>

  <para></para>

  <sect2>
   <title>&nm; and Registration</title>
   <para>
    In case of using &nm; for managing network devices and network
    connections, network connection is not available during the second stage
    of the upgrade. This prevents the system from performing the
    registration.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Cleaning Up Upgrade Setting</title>
   <para>
    If you do any changes in your system in order to trigger the upgrade
    process (e.g., adding a new section to the boot loader menu), you
    probably want to remove it after the upgrade is done.
   </para>
   <para>
<!-- was:
    http://www.suse.de/~ug/autoyast_doc/createprofile.scripts.html -->
    You can do it automatically with a post-installation script. Find an
    example in the &ay; documentation at
    <ulink
    url="http://www.suse.com/doc/sles11/book_autoyast/data/createprofile_scripts.html"/>.
    A sample script for cleaning up &grub;'s <filename>menu.lst</filename> is
    included in the sample <filename>autoupg.xml</filename> file. Make sure
    that the script matches your particular setup and that it does not
    remove more than you actually want!
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>For More Information</title>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Update Media How-To:
      <ulink url="http://ftp.suse.com/pub/people/hvogel/Update-Media-HOWTO/index.html"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Linuxrc Documentation:
      <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/SDB:Linuxrc"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</article>
