<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE"> 
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> 
 %entities;
]>
<!-- ********************************* Please see LICENSE.txt for this document's license. ********************************* -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:novdoc-profile.xsl"                  type="text/xml"                   title="Profiling step"?>
<chapter xml:base="art_kde_quick.xml" id="art.kdequick">
 <title>&kdequick;</title>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   &productnamereg; offers all tools which Linux&ast; users require for
   their daily activities. The product is supplied with a user-friendly
   graphical environment (KDE&ast; Desktop) which communicates with the
   basic Linux system in order to access files, folders, and programs and
   manage them. <phrase os="osuse">&productname; offers an integrated suite
   of applications for a broad range of activities (Office, multimedia,
   Internet).</phrase> The &libo; suite is also included. This enables you
   to edit and save files in many formats. As &libo; is available for
   different operating systems, you can use the files you have created with
   it on several computer platforms.
   <remark>OpenDocument is an ISO standard and supported not just by LibreOffice, but also by Lotus Symphony, MSO 2007+, Ooo, Calligra etc. That could be added, too. -- sknorr, Sep 11, 2012</remark>
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.start">
  <title>Getting Started</title>

  <para>
   When you start your system, you are usually prompted to enter your user
   name and password. If you have not installed your system yourself, ask
   your system administrator for the user name and password.
  </para>

  <para>
   The KDE Desktop appears after first logging into KDE. Its appearance
   depends on whether &productnamereg; could activate the 3D functions of
   your graphics card. Optics and functionality in both cases are the same,
   only the operation differs slightly.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.overview">
  <title>The Standard KDE Desktop</title>

  <para>
   When you log into KDE for the first time, the KDE desktop is displayed
   which contains the following basic elements:
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kde_desktop_menus.png" width="80%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kde_desktop_menus.png" width="80%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Desktop folder:</title>
   <para>
    The content of the <filename>~/Desktop</filename> Directory is displayed
    as standard on the milk glass surface on the top left. Any file placed
    in this directory also appears in this view.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Desktop context menu:</title>
   <para>
    Right-click on an empty area on the desktop in order to access the
    Context menu which you can use to change the appearance of the desktop,
    add the desktop control bars or mini programs (widgets), configure
    desktop settings, fix mini programs in the current position (lock), lock
    the screen or terminate the current session.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Toolbox:</title>
   <para>
    Click on the icon at the very top right of the desktop with the mouse to
    access the menu which you can use to add or lock mini programs.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>KDE control bar:</title>
   <para>
    As standard, the control bar on the lower edge of the KDE desktop
    contains the icon for the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> on the left side
    and further mini programs and program icons and the icon for the control
    bar settings on the right side. A short description of the icon is
    displayed when you point the mouse pointer at an icon in the control
    bar.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Main menu:</title>
   <para>
    Click in the lower control bar on the left to open the main menu. The
    <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> consists of the following elements: a
    search function at the top and different tabs below, which offer rapid
    access to the key menu functions. Your registration name and the host
    name of the computer are also displayed in the menu.
   </para>
  </formalpara>
 </sect1>
<?dbfo-need height="20em"?>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.startprogr">
  <title>Starting programs</title>

  <para>
   Start programs in the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu>, in the command line
   with the help of a shell or the <guimenu>Execute a command</guimenu>
   option. Programs can also be launched from the desktop or the control bar
   by clicking once on the program icon with the left mouse button.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.startprogr.menu">
   <title>Using the main menu</title>
   <para>
    To open the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu>, click on the <guimenu>Main
    Menu</guimenu> icon in the control bar or press &altf2;.
   </para>
   <para>
    A standard selection of pre-programmed shortcuts for quick access is
    displayed under <guimenu>Favorites</guimenu> All the applications
    installed in your system can be seen under
    <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>. Click on the relevant entry to navigate
    through the menu structure. You can return via the breadcrumb menu (the
    light gray text directly at the top right above the menu points). You
    only need to click on a previous menu point there. To jump back to
    Start, select <guimenu>All programs</guimenu>. The
    <guimenu>Computer</guimenu> and <guimenu>History</guimenu> tabs provide
    fast access to frequently used storage locations, applications, and
    documents. Under <guimenu>Quit</guimenu> you can find various options
    for ending the session, such as logging off, locking the screen (further
    access is only possible with a password), shutting down and restarting
    the computer. Some computers offer to put your session on RAM or a data
    medium into deep sleep mode.
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="kde_main_menu.png" width="65%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="kde_main_menu.png" width="50%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
   <para>
    If you use a program often and do not want to access it through the menu
    structure every time, you can add its icon to the
    <guimenu>Favorites</guimenu> tab. To do so, right-click on any other tab
    in the program and select <guimenu>Add to Favorites</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.startprogr.krunner">
   <title>Use the “Execute command” dialog box</title>
   <para>
    KRunner is a helper application which lets you quickly start programs.
    It also offers a search function to search for applications or storage
    locations.
   </para>
   <para>
    Press &altf2; to open the <guimenu>Execute command</guimenu> dialog box.
    Enter a command, for example <command>dolphin</command>. Even during
    input, a list of applications or actions is displayed in the dialog box
    which match your entry. Select one of the results, or press
    <keycap function="enter"/> to start the highlighted application or
    action. The command to start is often (but not always) the application
    name written in lower case letters.
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="kde_krunner.png" width="75%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="kde_krunner.png" width="60%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
   <para>
    In the <guimenu>Execute command</guimenu> dialog box you can use
    different functions: Click on the question mark icon to display a list
    of active functions. To edit or retrieve a list of all functions, click
    on the cogwheel icon. You can use so-called <emphasis>web key
    shortcuts</emphasis> which are defined in Konqueror to send search
    enquiries directly to a search engine without needing to open the
    browser beforehand. Another interesting function is the calculation of a
    mathematical expression such as
    <literal>&equals;2&plus;2^4-sin(2)</literal>. The conversion of units,
    such as from miles per hours to kilometers per hour, is also very
    useful. Simply enter the expression <literal>60 mph in km/h</literal> to
    retrieve the converted value.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.startprogr.search">
   <title>Search for Programs</title>
   <para>
    Both the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> and the <guimenu>Execute
    command</guimenu> dialog box offer a search function which enables you
    to start programs quickly, even if you do not know the exact application
    name or command. To search for an application, start from the
    <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> by entering a command or a part of the
    application name in the <guimenu>Search</guimenu> box or in the input
    field in the <guimenu>Execute command</guimenu> dialog box. Every
    character entered restricts the search.
   </para>
   <para>
    Select the application from the list below the input field which
    corresponds to your query.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.mediahandling">
  <title>Handling Media</title>

  <para>
   When you place a CD or DVD into the drive, or connect a USB stick or an
   external hard drive, the widget opens a small window for device
   notification which notifies you of the process. Possible actions for the
   respective type of device are also suggested.
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata width="40%" fileref="kde_devicenotifier.png"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata width="25%" fileref="kde_devicenotifier.png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para>
   For example, if you connect a digital camera, you can download your
   photos with Gwenview (image viewer) or &digikam; (image management
   program). Click on the device entry in the widget to access the available
   actions. To securely remove the device from the computer, click on the
   icon to the right of the device entry (the cable icon or the eject
   button).
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.custom">
  <title>Adapt your desktop</title>

  <para>
   You can tailor the appearance and behavior of your KDE desktop to your
   personal requirements.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.custom.lock">
   <title>Fixing and approving desktop objects</title>
   <para>
    Desktop elements can be fixed in the current position to prevent them
    moving to and from on the desktop. This does not affect the program
    windows, but only elements which are directly on the desktop such as the
    widgets or program icons. When the desktop elements are fixed, no
    objects can be added to the desktop, moved or removed.
   </para>
   <para>
    Click on the Cashew icon (toolbox) in the top right of the desktop to
    fix or release the desktop elements and select <guimenu>Lock
    widgets</guimenu> or <guimenu>Unlock widgets</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Alternatively, right-click on an empty space on the desktop and select
    <guimenu>Lock widgets</guimenu> or <guimenu>Unlock widgets</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.custom.indiv">
   <title>Changing individual desktop elements</title>
   <para>
    In the following sections you will find some examples of how individual
    desktop elements can be changed.
   </para>
   <procedure id="proc.kdequick.conf.icons">
    <title>Adding program icons to the desktop</title>
    <para>
     Proceed as follows to create a link to an application and to place it
     on the desktop or the control bar:
    </para>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click on the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> and search for the desired
      application.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Right-click on the <guimenu>Add to desktop</guimenu> option in the
      displayed context menu to select it. If this menu entry is not
      available, your desktop elements are probably fixed. Release these
      first, as described in <xref linkend="sec.kdequick.custom.lock"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To change the position of icon symbol on the desktop, click on the
      icon with the left mouse button and drag it to the desired location.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    If you want to delete an icon from the desktop, right-click on the
    program icon and select <guimenu>Remove icon</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <procedure id="proc.kdequick.widgets.add">
    <title>Adding widgets on the desktop or on the control bar</title>
    <step performance="required">
     <formalpara>
      <title>To add widgets to your desktop</title>
      <para>
       Right-click on an empty space on your desktop and select <guimenu>Add
       widgets</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>To add a widget to your control bar</title>
      <para>
       Right-click on an empty space on the control bar and select
       <menuchoice><guimenu>Control bar Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Add
       widgets</guimenu></menuchoice>.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <para>
      If these menu entries are not available, your desktop elements are
      probably fixed. In this case, first right-click on the control bar and
      select <guimenu>Unlock widgets</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select a widget from the displayed list. Search through the available
      widgets with the help of the scroll bar. To restrict the selection of
      widgets either input a search term in the input field or select a
      category.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To display the selected widget on the desktop or on the control bar,
      click it with the left mouse button, keep the button depressed and
      drag the symbol to its envisaged position. Then release the left mouse
      button again. The mouse pointer turns into a prohibited symbol in
      locations where it is impossible to place the widget.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To remove a widget from the desktop or the control bar, right-click on
      the widget and select <guimenu>Remove...</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure id="proc.kdequick.widgets.conf">
    <title>Configuring widgets</title>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Hold the mouse pointer over a widget until a translucent frame appears
      around the widget which displays a row of icons:
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_widget_frame.png" width="45%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_widget_frame.png" width="40%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
     <para>
      If the frame does not appear, your widgets are probably fixed. Release
      these first, as described in
      <xref linkend="sec.kdequick.custom.lock"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To change the size of the widget, click on the ruler symbol in the
      frame with the left mouse button and keep the mouse button depressed
      while you slowly move the pointer over the desktop.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To rotate the widget in one direction, click on the curved arrow
      symbol in the frame with the left mouse button and keep the mouse
      button depressed while you drag the mouse pointer in a circular motion
      over the desktop. There is a locking limit on the horizontal and
      vertical positions to which you can <quote>affix</quote> the widget if
      necessary. Of course, you can also place it in any appropriate
      position.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To change the content, the settings or the properties of a widget,
      click on the cogwheel icon in the frame with the left mouse button.
      Determine the options as desired in the configuration dialog box which
      is now displayed.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    panels are available to gain more space for your own programs.
   </para>
   <procedure id="proc.kdequick.panel.add">
    <title>Adding and removing panels</title>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Right-click on an empty space on the desktop, select <guimenu>Add
      panel</guimenu>, and a panel type from the list.
     </para>
     <para>
      If these menu entries are not available, your desktop elements are
      probably fixed. In this case, first right-click and select
      <guimenu>Unlock widgets</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click on the Cashew icon at the end of the new panel to access the
      configuration options and adapt the panel as described in
      <xref linkend="proc.kdequick.panel.conf"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To delete a panel, right-click on an empty space in the panel for
      deletion and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>panel Settings</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Remove "panel”</guimenu> </menuchoice>. At least one panel
      must remain on the desktop in &productname;.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure id="proc.kdequick.panel.conf">
    <title>Configuring panels</title>
    <para>
     Applications and widgets can be added in the main panel or other
     panels. panel elements and other panels can be shifted to different
     positions or removed if necessary.
    </para>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      In order to access options for the current panel, right-click on an
      empty space in the panel and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings for
      panel</guimenu> <guimenu>panel settings</guimenu> </menuchoice>. It is
      quicker if you click on the cashew icon at the very right of the bar.
      In any case, the view of the panel changes and the configuration
      options are displayed.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_move_panel.png" width="85%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_move_panel.png" width="50%" format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
     <para>
      If the menu entry and the icon is not available, your desktop elements
      are probably fixed. To unlock, first right-click on the panel and
      select <guimenu>Unlock widgets</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      In order to move objects in the panel to another position in the
      panel, point to the desired panel object with the mouse cursor (e.g.
      program icon, desktop toggle, task manager, system section for panel).
      The mouse pointer takes the form of a cross. Click on the object and
      drag the element to the desired position in the panel. Click again to
      fix it in this position.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To increase the distance between two widgets, use <guimenu>Add
      spacers</guimenu>. A spacer widget is displayed on the right hand
      side. Drag it to the preferred location and leave it there.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To change the width of the panel, click on the small arrow icon on the
      left and right hand side of the settings panel. With the arrow on the
      left hand side you can determine the position of the panel and with
      the arrows on the right hand side you can determine the maximized and
      minimized size.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To change the height of the panel, left-click on the
      <guimenu>Height</guimenu> button and drag to the desired final
      position.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      With the help of the <guimenu>Screen edge</guimenu> button, position
      the panel on one side of the screen. Drag the panel into the desired
      position using drag and drop.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      If you need additional widgets in your panel, you can add them using
      the <guimenu>Add widgets</guimenu> button as described in
      <xref linkend="proc.kdequick.widgets.add"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To remove program icons or widgets from the panel, right-click on the
      object in question and select the menu entry to remove the icon or
      widget.
     </para>
     <para>
      The icons in the system section of the panel normally belong to
      applications which are executed in the background. You can therefore
      only remove these icons once you have closed these applications (click
      on the icon and select <guimenu>End</guimenu>).
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Further configuration options (e.g. orientation) and further functions
      (e.g. automatic masking) can be found under <guimenu>Advanced
      settings</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      When all panel settings meet your requirements, close the panel
      settings with the red button on the right hand side.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure id="proc.kdequick.conf.deskback">
    <title>Changing the Desktop Background</title>
    <para>
     You can set the desktop background in such a way that images, slide
     shows, samples or colors are displayed. Even a world map or the weather
     forecast can be used as a desktop background.
    </para>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Right-click on an empty space on the desktop and select
      <guimenu>Default desktop settings</guimenu>. A configuration window is
      opened.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      In the <guimenu>View</guimenu> section select a type from the
      <guimenu>Background image</guimenu> dropdown list. Further
      configuration options are dependent on the object you have selected
      for the background.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      In order to use an image as a background, proceed as follows:
     </para>
     <substeps performance="required">
      <step performance="required">
       <para>
        Choose the <guimenu>Image</guimenu> option under <guimenu>Background
        image</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step performance="required">
       <para>
        Define the <guimenu>Positioning</guimenu> of the image.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step performance="required">
       <para>
        Use one of the available background images by selecting the desired
        background in the list, or click on <guimenu>Download new background
        images</guimenu> to obtain further background images from the
        Internet.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step performance="required">
       <para>
        To use a user-defined image, click on <guimenu>Open</guimenu> and
        select an image file from the file system.
       </para>
       <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
         <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="kde_conf_deskback.png" width="75%"/>
         </imageobject>
         <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="kde_conf_deskback.png" width="60%"/>
         </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
       </informalfigure>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Determine the other options in the configuration dialog box according
      to your wishes and click on <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to save your changes
      and close the configuration dialog box.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.custom.kcontrol">
   <title>Modify personal settings</title>
   <para>
    Apart from changing individual desktop elements, you can adapt your
    desktop with KDE to your precise requirements. Options for adapting the
    entire appearance and behavior of your desktop can be found in the
    <guimenu>Configure desktop</guimenu> configuration dialog box.
   </para>
   <para>
    Launch <guimenu>Configure desktop</guimenu> in the <guimenu>Main
    Menu</guimenu> by selecting <menuchoice> <guimenu>Favorites</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Configure desktop</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The settings are sub-divided into different categories. Hover the mouse
    on an icon to see further details. You need system administrator rights
    for some tasks in Configure desktop (&rootuser;).
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="kde_kcontrol_main.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="kde_kcontrol_main.png" width="75%" format="png"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
   <para>
    Change the settings as desired. Changes only become effective when you
    click on <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>. Click on <guimenu>Restore</guimenu>
    to discard changes in the last view which have not yet been applied. In
    order to restore all elements in the last view to standard values, click
    on <guimenu>Default settings</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    To return to the initial display (with all categories), click in the top
    left of the dialog box on <guimenu>Overview</guimenu>. You can also
    input search terms at the top of the window (for example
    <guimenu>Screensaver</guimenu>) to find the category which contains
    options that match the search text. Each character you enter in the
    <guimenu>Search</guimenu> field further restricts the search. The icon
    of the category found is highlighted in a different color.
   </para>
   <para>
    For a more simple overview of all categories, you can change to a tree
    view by clicking on <guimenu>Create</guimenu> and selecting a different
    <guimenu>View design</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.desktopeffects">
  <title>Application of desktop effects</title>

  <para>
   If your computer supports a 3D graphics card, you can use graphic
   effects, such as converting the desktop to a rotating 3D dice, activating
   translucent or transparent windows or maximizing and minimizing the
   desktop screen. You can also use other window effects such as Shadow,
   Blending in and Remodeling. If you do not have a 3D graphics card, some
   effects may be disabled or can slow down your system. If your system is
   too slow, disable the effects for the current session by pressing
   <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap function="shift"/>
   <keycap>F12</keycap> </keycombo>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Configure the effects of your desktop as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Start the <guimenu>Configure desktop</guimenu> as described in
     <xref linkend="sec.kdequick.custom.kcontrol"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Desktop effects</guimenu> from the <guimenu>Desktop
     appearance and behavior</guimenu> category, and select
     <guimenu>Activate desktop effects upon system start</guimenu>. If your
     graphics card does not support the 3D function, you are notified
     accordingly.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Optional: Change some options under <guimenu>General settings</guimenu>
     on the <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Select the effects to be activated on the <guimenu>All
     effects</guimenu> tab. When you click on the information icon, a short
     explanation on the respective effect is superimposed. If an effect is
     activated, you can obtain access to further configuration options with
     the cogwheel icon (right), for example to assign keyboard shortcuts for
     the effect.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     With <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> you can activate the effects permanently.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.virtdesk">
  <title>Use of virtual desktops</title>

  <para>
   The desktop environment enables you to organize your programs and tasks
   on several virtual desktops. If you often run a lot of programs
   simultaneously, this minimizes the number of windows to arrange on your
   screen. For example, you can use a desktop for e-mails and the calendar
   and another desktop for text processing or graphic applications.
  </para>

  <procedure id="proc.kdequick.virtdesk.move">
   <title>Moving an application to another virtual desktop</title>
   <para>
    You can display a currently executed application on one or all virtual
    desktops or move them to other desktops.
   </para>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Open the application.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Right-click on the title bar of the application.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Click on <guimenu>On Desktop</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Select the desktop where the application should be placed.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Click on the desired desktop in the desktop toggle switch in the
     control bar in order to change to a certain desktop. Change to the next
     or previous desktop by placing the mouse pointer in an empty space on
     the desktop and moving the mouse wheel.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure id="proc.kdequick.virtdesk.add">
   <title>Configuring the virtual desktop</title>
   <para>
    You can increase the number of virtual desktops, change standard names,
    assign activities, configure effect animations and assign keyboard
    shortcuts to switch virtual desktops.
   </para>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     To add additional desktops, right-click on the desktop toggle switch in
     the control bar and select <guimenu>Add virtual desktop</guimenu>. A
     new desktop is displayed in the desktop toggle switch.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     If configuration options are available, right-click on the desktop
     toggle switch and select <guimenu>Desktop toggle switch
     settings</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_add_virtdesk.png" width="85%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_add_virtdesk.png" width="60%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     You can configure the appearance of the desktop toggle switch in the
     control bar with the options in the <guimenu>General</guimenu>
     category.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Desktop names, key combinations to change between desktops, and the
     switchover type can be configured in the <guimenu>Virtual
     Desktops</guimenu> category.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Determine the desired options and click on <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. The
     changes are adopted and the configuration dialog box is closed.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.dolphin">
  <title>Management of files and folders</title>

  <para>
   In KDE 4, Konqueror has been replaced by Dolphin as a standard file
   manager. Konqueror will continue to be used as a web browser (information
   regarding this can be found in <xref linkend="sec.kdequick.browser"/>).
   Start Dolphin in the main menu by selecting <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Favorites</guimenu> <guimenu>File manager</guimenu></menuchoice>
   or pressing &altf2; and entering <command>dolphin</command>.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.dolphin.oview">
   <title>Dolphin main window</title>
   <para>
    The Dolphin main window consists of the following elements:
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="dolphin_main.png" width="80%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="dolphin_main.png" width="70%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
   <formalpara>
    <title>Menu bar:</title>
    <para>
     Call the main menu up via the cogwheel icon. All possible functions are
     ready there, such as copying, moving or deletion of files, changing
     view, starting of further tools, changing settings and calling up help.
    </para>
   </formalpara>
   <formalpara>
    <title>Symbol bar:</title>
    <para>
     The symbol bar accelerates the navigation and changing of the display.
     The relevant functions can also be called up via the main menu. If the
     mouse pointer is positioned over an icon for a moment, a short
     description of the icon is displayed.
    </para>
   </formalpara>
   <formalpara>
    <title>Address bar:</title>
    <para>
     The address bar displays the path to the current directory. It is
     available in two versions: one displays the path to the current
     directory with buttons for each superordinate folder. Click on a
     directory name in this view in order to change to this directory. The
     second version of the address bar displays the path to the current
     directory as a text chain which can be edited.
    </para>
   </formalpara>
   <formalpara>
    <title>Fields:</title>
    <para>
     The <guimenu>Places</guimenu> sidebar is displayed in Dolphin as
     standard. It enables rapid access to frequently used places such as
     your home directory, the root directory of the file system
     (<filename>/</filename>), the Recycle Bin, and removable media. You can
     add further different control bars in the main menu under <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>View</guimenu> <guimenu>Side bars</guimenu> </menuchoice> .
    </para>
   </formalpara>
   <formalpara>
    <title>Display field (work area):</title>
    <para>
     The content of the selected directory or the selected file is displayed
     in the display field. Dolphin shows the content of your home directory
     as standard at the start. By clicking on a folder in Dolphin an action
     is started directly as standard: Dolphin loads the file into an
     application or opens the folder for further processing.
    </para>
   </formalpara>
   <formalpara>
    <title>Status bar:</title>
    <para>
     Shows the file type and the size of the currently selected object and
     enables maximization and minimization of the icons or entries in the
     display field via the slider.
    </para>
   </formalpara>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.dolphin.files">
   <title>Management of folders and files in Dolphin</title>
   <para>
    To perform actions such as copying, moving, creating or deleting files,
    you require the relevant rights for the respective folders and files.
   </para>
   <para>
    To copy, move or delete a file or a folder proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To select one or several files and folders in Dolphin move the mouse
      pointer over the file or folder, but do not click on it. A green cross
      appears on the left upper edge. The object is selected when you click
      on it. To clear the selection, click on the red minus sign which is
      displayed when the object is selected.
     </para>
     <para>
      Alternatively, press <keycap function="control"/> and click on the
      objects which should be selected or unselected.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step id="step.dophin.cut" performance="required">
     <para>
      Right-click and select <guimenu>Copy</guimenu> or
      <guimenu>Cut</guimenu> in the context menu.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Navigate to the target folder where you wish to insert the object.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To create a new folder at the current location, right-click in the
      display field and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Create</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Folder</guimenu> </menuchoice> or press <keycap>F10</keycap>.
      Enter a folder name in the new window and press
      <keycap function="enter"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      In order to insert the copied or cut object in
      <xref linkend="step.dophin.cut"/>, right-click on the target folder in
      the main display field and select <guimenu>Insert</guimenu>. The
      object is copied or moved into this folder.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To delete a file or a folder, right-click in the main display field on
      the object and select <guimenu>Send to Recycle Bin</guimenu> in the
      context menu. The object is moved to the bin. You can retrieve it from
      there or permanently delete the object if necessary.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    In order to quickly filter for certain file names in the current
    directory, press <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/>
    <keycap>I</keycap> </keycombo> to add the <guimenu>Filter</guimenu>
    input field at the bottom of the Dolphin main window. Enter any part of
    the file name for which you are searching to see all files in the
    current directory which contain the chain of characters searched for.
    Press <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>F</keycap>
    </keycombo> to use the desktop search for detailed and advanced search.
    You can find further information on this in
    <xref linkend="sec.kdequick.find"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.dolphin.conf">
   <title>Configuration of Dolphin</title>
   <para>
    Dolphin offers many options for changing the view and the options as a
    whole to suit your preferences.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Changing the view</title>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To change from standard view to the editable version of the address
      bar, press <keycap>F6</keycap>. Enter a path to a directory. After
      inputting an address, press <keycap function="enter"/> or click the
      green hook on the right adjacent to the input field.
     </para>
     <para>
      To delete the content in the address bar click on the right on the
      black <literal>X</literal> icon. To change back to the standard view,
      press <keycombo><keycap function="control"/> <keycap>L</keycap>
      </keycombo>.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="dolphin_location_bar.png" width="99%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="dolphin_location_bar.png" width="70%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To change the view of the currently displayed folder click on one of
      the relevant icons in the icon bar (fourth, fifth and sixth from the
      left). Dolphin retains the selected view for each folder. Press
      <keycap>F3</keycap> to display the content of the current folder in
      two separate columns. You can now navigate to a different directory in
      each column and easily drag or position objects or compare the
      contents of directories. Press <keycap>F3</keycap> again to close the
      split pane.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_dolphin_splitview.png" width="90%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_dolphin_splitview.png" width="90%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      If you want Dolphin to display hidden files, click on the cogwheel
      icon to open the main menu and choose <guimenu>Show hidden
      files</guimenu>. (If you have enabled the menu bar, instead use
      <menuchoice> <guimenu>View</guimenu> <guimenu>Show hidden
      files</guimenu> </menuchoice>.)
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To display further details on the files (such as access rights or
      ownership), select <guimenu>Additional Information</guimenu> in the
      main menu behind the cogwheel icon and activate the relevant options.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To add further directories to the <guimenu>Places</guimenu> sidebar,
      drag a folder from the desktop into the <guimenu>Places</guimenu>
      sidebar and position it there Right-click on the context menu and use
      it to hide, edit, or remove entries from <guimenu>Places</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To add further sidebars to the main window, select
      <guimenu>Sidebars</guimenu> behind the cogwheel icon in the main menu
      and then further sidebars such as <guimenu>Folders</guimenu> or
      <guimenu>Terminals</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    Separate the sidebars from Dolphin’s main window by clicking the name
    of the sidebar and then dragging it to another location on the desktop.
    If the sidebar has no title it is locked. In such a case, right-click in
    a free area on the sidebar and then select <guimenu>Unlock
    sidebars</guimenu>. to integrate the sidebar into Dolphin’s main
    window again, double-click on the name of the sidebar again.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Changing the overall behavior of Dolphin</title>
    <para>
     To change the behavior or the view of Dolphin as a whole, select
     <guimenu>Configure dolphin</guimenu> in the main menu behind the
     Cogwheel icon and view the options offered in Dolphin’s configuration
     catalog.
    </para>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      If a certain view mode should apply to all folders, click on
      <guimenu>General</guimenu> in the left sidebar and activate
      <guimenu>Use common properties for all folders</guimenu>. Click on
      <guimenu>Views</guimenu> in the left sidebar and adapt the options for
      the different views. Click on <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> to save the
      changes.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      If Dolphin displays another directory on startup, or if you want to
      use the editable address bar constantly, click on
      <guimenu>Startup</guimenu> in the left sidebar and change the relevant
      options.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To configure the entries and services displayed in Dolphin’s context
      menu, click on <guimenu>General</guimenu>. Activate the entries to be
      displayed on the <guimenu>Context menu</guimenu> tab. Click on
      <guimenu>Services</guimenu> in the left sidebar and activate or
      disable the relevant services to be displayed in the context menu.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click on <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to accept the changes and close the
      Dolphin configuration dialog box.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.browser">
  <title>Browsing on the Internet</title>

  <para>
   Apart from Konqueror (the standard KDE web browser) &productname; also
   contains the Firefox web browser. To start Konqueror or Firefox, press
   &altf2; and enter <command>konqueror</command> or
   <command>firefox</command>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Both browsers offer support for modern web standards, the use of tabs, a
   pop-up blocker, and download and image management. Simple access to
   different search engines helps you in searching for required information.
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="firefox_main.png" width="85%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="firefox_main.png" width="75%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para>
   Enter the URL in the address field to start browsing. Press <keycombo>
   <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>T</keycap> </keycombo> to open a
   new, empty tab. To open a link in a new tab, click on the link with your
   middle mouse button. When you right-click on the tab, a menu with tab
   options is superimposed. This menu allows you to create new tabs, reload
   the content of a certain tab or all available tabs and close tabs. You
   can also change the sequence of the tabs by dragging it to the desired
   position and leaving it there.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.browser.search">
   <title>Finding Information</title>
   <para>
    Firefox offers two different types of search options: You can search for
    information on the web or on the current webpage using certain terms.
   </para>
<?dbfo-need height="20em"?>
   <procedure>
    <title>Searching the web</title>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To start a search on the web, click on the left icon on the right of
      the search bar (adjacent to the places bar) to open a list of search
      engines.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select the desired search engine and enter your search terms into the
      input field.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Press <keycap function="enter"/> to start the search process.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      If you want to search the current webpage with Firefox or Konqueror,
      press
      <keycombo><keycap function="control"/><keycap>F</keycap></keycombo> to
      display a search bar at the bottom of the window. Enter your search
      term there and start the search with the buttons below the search bar
      in different directors or configure the search options, for example
      <guimenu>Upper/Lower case</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    Konqueror offers predefined web key combinations to quickly search the
    web. To search for <literal>yast</literal>, for example, on the web
    using the Google search engine enter <literal>gg:yast</literal> in
    Konqueror’s address bar (or the <guimenu>Execute command</guimenu>
    dialog box) and press <keycap function="enter"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can also define individual Web key combinations in Konqueror and
    Firefox as described in <xref linkend="sec.kdequick.browser.conf"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.browser.download">
   <title>Downloading Files from the Web</title>
   <para>
    When you download a file with Firefox or Konqueror, a dialog box is
    opened in which you are requested whether you want to save the file or
    open it with a certain application. Also specify whether the selected
    action should apply to all files of this type. Firefox saves the file in
    the folder configured in the Firefox settings as standard and shows the
    completed downloads in the <guimenu>Downloads</guimenu> dialog box.
   </para>
   <para>
    To open the downloaded files directly from there, right-click on
    <guimenu>Open</guimenu> to select the option. To clear the history of
    downloaded files, click on <guimenu>Empty list</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.browser.conf">
   <title>Configuring Preferences</title>
   <para>
    Changing the settings in Konqueror or Firefox. Access the configuration
    dialog box in Konqueror by selecting <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure Konqueror</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>. To change the behavior of Konqueror as a web browser,
    select one of the sub-categories in <guimenu>Surfing the
    Internet</guimenu> in the left navigation area to display the options
    for the relevant category. For example, you can <quote>hide</quote> the
    true identity of Konqueror and identify Konqueror as another browser
    (such as, Internet Explorer&ast;) for certain websites you visit. To do
    so, select <guimenu>Browser identification</guimenu> and click on
    <guimenu>New</guimenu> in order to add a new, page-specific
    identification.
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="konqui_pref.png" width="80%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="konqui_pref.png" width="70%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
   <para>
    Perhaps you would also like to configure the web key shortcut you can
    use with Konqueror (and the <guimenu>Execute command</guimenu> dialog
    box). Click on <guimenu>Web shortcut</guimenu> in the configuration
    dialog box of Konqueror to display the currently defined key shortcut.
    Click on <guimenu>New</guimenu> to define new key shortcuts. Press
    <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to close the configuration dialog box of Konqueror
    and apply the changes.
   </para>
   <para>
    Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit </guimenu> <guimenu>Preferences
    </guimenu> </menuchoice> in Firefox to open the <guimenu>Firefox
    settings</guimenu>. Click on the symbols in the upper display field in
    order to access the options for the relevant category. For example,
    change the standard download folder on the <guimenu>General</guimenu>
    page or change the blocking of pop-up windows on the
    <guimenu>Content</guimenu> page. Click on <guimenu>Close</guimenu> to
    accept the changes.
   </para>
   <para>
    Navigate to the website with the desired search field to configure a web
    key combination for a search in Firefox. Right-click on the search field
    and select <guimenu>Add keyword for this search...</guimenu>. Enter a
    <guimenu>Keyword</guimenu> and close the dialog box by pressing
    <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.kwallet">
  <title>Managing Passwords</title>

  <para>
   When you input a password in a KDE application for the first time (for
   example in KMail or in Konqueror), you are asked if you want to save the
   password. If you click on <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>, the KWallet assistant
   starts as standard. KWallet is a password management tool which can
   collect all passwords and save them in one or more encrypted files
   (so-called <quote>Wallets</quote>).
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kwallet_welcome.png" width="70%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kwallet_welcome.png" width="65%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para>
   To activate the KWallet, select <guimenu>Basic set-up</guimenu>, and
   click on <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu>. Select <guimenu>Yes, I want to use
   the KDE digital wallet for my personal information</guimenu>. Then assign
   a master password to the standard wallet (<literal>kdewallet</literal>),
   which is created in the next step.
  </para>

  <warning>
   <title>Protect your password for KWallet</title>
   <para>
    If you forget your master password for a wallet, this password cannot be
    recreated. Also, everyone who knows your password can look inside your
    wallet.
   </para>
  </warning>

  <para>
   Click on <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> to close the assistant. If you
   originally started the KWallet assistant via a different application such
   as Konqueror or KMail, you are requested in KWallet to re-enter the
   password so that the password can be saved in the newly created wallet
   for this application. After the first configuration you can open KWallet
   at any time to display, search for, delete or create entries. Entering
   passwords manually is not usually necessary. KDE recognizes when a
   resource needs to be authenticated and KWallet starts automatically and
   asks you to enter your KWallet password. However, you can also add
   additional data if you wish. To configure the KWallet options, press
   &altf2; and enter <command>kwalletmanager</command>. The <guimenu>Service
   program for digital wallets</guimenu> is opened. If the window does not
   appear, take a look at the system section of the control bar (on the left
   adjacent to the clock). If necessary, expand all hidden applications via
   the small triangle. Then click on the <guimenu>Service program for
   digital wallets</guimenu> or on the relevant icon. The window of the
   application should then open. Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings
   </guimenu> <guimenu>Set up digital wallet</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <para>
   While KWallet is set up in such a way that passwords for different KDE
   applications are managed centrally, Firefox also offers the option of
   saving data on a website when a user name and password are entered. When
   you accept this, by clicking on <guimenu>Save</guimenu> the password is
   saved on your hard drive in an encrypted format. Firefox fills out the
   registration errors automatically when this website is next accessed.
  </para>

  <para>
   To verify or manage your passwords in Firefox, click on <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Security</guimenu> <guimenu>Saved Passwords...</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.mail">
  <title>E-mail and Calendar</title>

  <para>
   You can use Kontact as your personal information management (PIM) tool to
   read and manage your e-mails and events. Kontact combines KDE
   applications such as KMail, KOrganizer and KAddressBook in a single
   interface. This facilitates access to e-mails, calendar, address book and
   other PIM functions. Kontact can also manage several e-mail accounts.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.mail.kontact">
   <title>First time start-up of Kontact</title>
   <para>
    To start Kontact press &altf2; and enter <command>Kontact</command>. To
    access one of the components (e.g. KMail), click on the relevant icon on
    the left of the sidebar.
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="kontact_kmail.png" width="70%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="kontact_kmail.png" width="65%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
   <para>
    Before you can send or receive e-mail messages, you must configure an
    e-mail identity and an e-mail account:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure
      Kontact</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click on <guimenu>Identities</guimenu> in the left sidebar under
      <guimenu>E-mail</guimenu> and select the identity KMail has
      automatically created for you. <guimenu>Change</guimenu> this identity
      by entering your full name and e-mail address and confirm your changes
      with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click in the left sidebar under <guimenu>E-Mail</guimenu> on
      <guimenu>Accesses</guimenu> and select the <guimenu>Add</guimenu>
      option on the <guimenu>Receiving</guimenu> and/or
      <guimenu>Sending</guimenu> of e-mails tab to create at least one
      account. (Optionally, you can configure several e-mail accounts.)
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select the type of access. To retrieve e-mails, this is usually
      <guimenu>IMAP</guimenu> or <guimenu>POP3</guimenu>. To find out the
      right values to use, please consult the help pages of your e-mail
      provider. Highlight the relevant entry in the list and click
      <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. KWallet reports now, to whom you name the
      (master) password for your wallet. Then fill in the form which
      appears. Dependent on the account, options must also be determined for
      encryption or authentication. If you are unsure which settings or
      objects you should search for, get in touch with your Internet Service
      Provider or your system administrator.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click on <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. Set-up is confirmed and the dialog box
      is closed.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    To write a new e-mail in the main window of Kontact, click on the
    <guimenu>Mail</guimenu> icon and press <keycombo>
    <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>N</keycap> </keycombo> to open the
    E-mail Editor. When you have finished your e-mail, click on
    <guimenu>Send</guimenu> to send it straightaway. If you have configured
    several e-mail accounts, hold down the <guimenu>Send</guimenu> button
    and select the account to send the e-mail from.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.kopete">
  <title>Instant Messaging with Kopete</title>

  <para>
   Kopete is an online messenger application which enables you to chat with
   others over the Internet. Kopete supports many messenger protocols, such
   as AOL&ast; Instant Messenger (AIM), Gadu-Gadu, GroupWise&reg; Messenger,
   ICQ, Jabber&ast;, SMS, and Yahoo!&ast;. To use Instant Messaging (IM),
   you need to register with an IM services provider and then enter this
   data Kopete accordingly.
  </para>

  <para>
   To start Kopete, press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
   <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter <command>kopete</command>. When
   you start the application for the first time, select <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
   Add an <guimenu>Account </guimenu> here in the <guimenu>Accounts
   area</guimenu>. Kopete takes you through the set-up steps, such as
   selecting the news service, entering the necessary account information
   (for example, user name/user ID, server name, port), inputting of
   registration data (e.g. passwords). If you have not yet registered with
   the provider for the selected news service, click on <guimenu>Register
   New Account</guimenu>. Enter your user data into the browser window which
   is now opened to register. Change back to Kopete and enter the data
   received upon registration. Close the configuration of your account by
   clicking on <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you want to go online after configuring your account, you can now add
   contacts in the main window of Kopete. When the status
   <literal>Offline</literal> is displayed in the Kopete window (in the
   status bar), first click on <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Set status</guimenu> <guimenu>Online</guimenu> </menuchoice> and
   enter your password as soon as you are requested. When connected, click
   on <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Add contact</guimenu>
   </menuchoice> and select the Kopete account for which contacts should be
   added. Enter the contact data or search for a contact and click on
   <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   To display all contacts, even if these are currently offline, select
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Show Offline
   Users</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <para>
   When you want to start a chat, click on the desired contact and enter
   your message into the lower section of the chat window. Press
   <keycap function="enter"/> to send the message. The upper part of the
   window displays the messages you have sent and received.
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kopete_chat.png" width="55%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kopete_chat.png" width="50%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.ooo">
  <title>Starting &libo;</title>

  <para>
   The office suite &libo; offers a comprehensive set of office tools, which
   includes a text processor, a spreadsheet application, a slideshow
   application, a vector graphics program and a database application and
   more. As &libo; is available for a range of operating systems, you can
   seamlessly use files created with it on different platforms.
  </para>

  <para>
   Press &altf2; to start and enter <command>libreoffice</command>. When you
   want to create a new document, select <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
   <guimenu>New</guimenu></menuchoice> and then select the desired document
   type. To open an existing document, click <guimenu>Open</guimenu> and
   select the relevant file from the file system.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can find further information in &oofficequick;.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.docview">
  <title>Viewing PDF Files and Other Documents</title>

  <para>
   Documents which need to be approved or printed on several platforms can
   be saved as PDF (Portable Document Format) files, for example with the
   &libo;-Suite. Display these documents with Okular, KDE’s standard
   document display.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.docview.okular">
   <title>Using the Okular document display</title>
   <para>
    Apart from PDF files, you can display a multitude of file formats with
    Okular, such as PostScript, different image formats, the OpenDocument
    Format (ODF), some eBook formats (ePub) and even Microsoft&ast; Compiled
    HTML Help (CHM). Okular also supports bookmarks, comments, formula
    fields and multimedia contents as well as page rotation.
   </para>
   <para>
    Start Okular in the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> or press &altf2; and
    enter <command>okular</command>.
   </para>
   <para>
    To open a document select <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Open</guimenu></menuchoice> and select the relevant file from
    the file system. Navigate through the document with the up or down
    navigation icons in the window. According to which icon you click on the
    left side of the navigation area, the sidebar either shows the
    <guimenu>Content</guimenu>, <guimenu>Preview images</guimenu> of all
    pages, the <guimenu>Reviews</guimenu> or your
    <guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu> for this file. To filter for text which is
    listed in the sidebar or in the entire document, enter a string of
    characters into the input field at the top of the sidebar. If you want
    to select and copy a text or images from the file in Okular, click on
    the <guimenu>Select</guimenu> icon in the toolbar and select one of the
    options from the context menu. Click on the <guimenu>Browse</guimenu>
    icon to return to browsing the document.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Working with bookmarks and comments</title>
    <para>
     With Okular you can verify a document by emphasizing certain passages
     of text or adding comments or bookmarks which Okular then adds to the
     file in the form of metadata. Note that the added comments and
     identifiers cannot be saved in the document. Consequently, it is not
     possible to print them or forward them to other users.
    </para>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To add a bookmark to a page click on the relevant page in the sidebar
      or in the main display field and click on <keycombo>
      <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>B</keycap> </keycombo>. The page
      is added to the list of <guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu> in the left
      sidebar. Right-click on the bookmark entry to access a context menu in
      which you can change to this bookmark, rename it or remove it.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To create a comment for a page, press <keycap>F6</keycap> and select
      one of the comments tools from the toolbar now displayed. The comment
      is added to the list of <guimenu>Reviews</guimenu> and identified with
      the sign-in name of the user who created it. Use the symbols at the
      bottom of the sidebar in order to group the comments by page or author
      or to display only the comments for the current page.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="okular_annotate.png" width="90%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="okular_annotate.png" width="75%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To open a pop-up note and add a text for a comment (or to remove a
      comment), right-click on the comment entry in the list of
      <guimenu>Reviews</guimenu> and select the relevant menu entry. The
      comments or identifiers added are automatically added to the file and
      you do not need to save these.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.docview.acroread" os="osuse">
   <title>Using Acrobat Reader</title>
   <para>
    If Acrobat Reader is not installed as standard, install the
    <systemitem>acroread</systemitem> package with &yast;. To start Acrobat
    Reader, press &altf2; and enter <command>acroread</command>. Click on
    <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Open</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>, search for the desired PDF file and click on
    <guimenu>Open</guimenu>, to display the file.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.find">
  <title>Search for data (with Strigi)</title>

  <para>
   The Strigi desktop search not only searches for files, but also for
   metadata such as tags, evaluations and even source URLs for downloads. To
   use desktop search, the <systemitem class="service">nepomuk</systemitem>
   service must be executed. To activate this service, open Configure
   Desktop, switch to <guimenu>Desktop search</guimenu>, tick all services
   on the <guimenu>Basic Settings</guimenu> tab and terminate the dialog box
   by clicking on <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> and <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   After activation, you can use KRunner (&altf2;) to search for files by
   inputting a keyword. An advanced search interface is available in the
   Dolphin file manager. Press <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/>
   <keycap>F</keycap> </keycombo> in Dolphin to activate the desktop search.
   You can filter the search results by <guimenu>File name</guimenu>,
   <guimenu>Content</guimenu> or place.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.burn">
  <title>Creating a CD or DVD</title>

  <para>
   If your computer has a CD or DVD burner, you can burn K3b files on CD or
   DVD. To create a data CD or DVD, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure id="proc.kdequick.burn">
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Press &altf2; and enter <command>k3b</command>. K3b is opened.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     In the main menu select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
     <guimenu>New Project</guimenu> <guimenu>New Data Project</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Use the tree view in the upper left section of the window to search for
     the files or folders to be burnt to a disc. As soon as this is
     displayed in the top right of the window, drag it into the window using
     <guimenu>Current projects</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="k3b_data_cd.png" width="90%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="k3b_data_cd.png" width="75%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Place a writable CD or DVD into the device and then click on the
     <guimenu>Burn icon</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Check the settings on the <guimenu>Burn tab</guimenu>. The standard
     settings should normally work for almost all files. If desired, you can
     also change further options, such as <guimenu>Data medium
     name</guimenu>, on the <guimenu>File System</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Click on <guimenu>Burn</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.digikam">
  <title>Manage your collection of digital images</title>

  <para>
   With &digikam;, it is easy to manage digital photos: Download your images
   from the camera, edit and optimize them, arrange them in albums (or add
   identifications for simple retrieval, regardless of folders or albums)
   and archive them on CD or DVD or export them into a gallery with web
   images.
  </para>

  <para>
   &digikam; also contains a set of useful stacking functions and plug-ins
   which enable you to convert several images into different formats, rename
   them or automatically improve the quality of images with the help of
   functions such as red eye correction, retouching and Hot Pixel removal.
   Different plug-ins for filters and effects help you to make your digital
   photos into works of art.
  </para>

  <para>
   To start &digikam;, press &altf2; and enter <command>digikam</command>.
   When you start it for the first time, the first time start assistant
   opens which will guide you through setup. In general, you can confirm all
   questions with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="digikam_mainwin.png" width="90%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="digikam_mainwin.png" width="70%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para>
   The main window of &digikam; contains a tree view on the left hand side
   and displays thumbnails of the images on the right hand side. To access
   your images quickly, use the sidebar on the left side which enables you
   to switch between the different views and to sort the photos according to
   the <guimenu>Albums</guimenu> or <guimenu>Keywords</guimenu> for example.
   To change to the display and editing mode of &digikam;, double click on
   the thumbnail of a photo.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.amarok">
  <title>Managing your music collection</title>

  <para>
   With KDE’s &amarok; Music Player you can play back different audio
   formats, create playlists, listen to streaming audio broadcasts on radio
   stations on the Internet and subscribe to podcasts. The file types
   supported vary dependent on the &amarok; module used.
  </para>

  <para>
   To start &amarok;, press the &altf2; key and enter
   <command>amarok</command>.
<!-- &amarok; asks for your country on first
   start-up. Select the relevant country from the dropdown list and then click
   on <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. Then-->
   On the first start you have to select the folder which should be searched
   for your music files. If you want to use the suggested file, simply click
   on <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="amarok_main.png" width="85%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="amarok_main.png" width="60%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para>
   A sidebar with different views is displayed in the main window of
   &amarok;: your local music collection, some addresses for playing back
   podcasts or streams from the Internet, your playlists and a file browser.
   In the middle section, the context browser, information on the current
   title, the Wikipedia page for interpreters and the song text is displayed
   as standard. You can see the current playlist in the right hand section
   of the window. To do so, drag the desired elements from any browser of
   the sidebar into the area for the playlists. To play back an element,
   double-click on it in the playlist.
  </para>

  <para>
   If your music files have the correct identifiers (and contain at least
   information on the artist and the album), different useful functions of
   &amarok; are available to you. To automatically retrieve images from
   Amazon for the album cover, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Cover management</guimenu> </menuchoice> and click on
   <guimenu>Fetch missing cover</guimenu>. The next time you play back a
   piece of music from this album, the cover is displayed in the context
   browser and on the display. For further information on the artist, click
   in the middle section on the <guimenu>Wikipedia</guimenu> button &amarok;
   will then start searching for the relevant Wikipedia article.
  </para>

  <para>
   To configure the use of another module (or other &amarok; functions)
   select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure
   &amarok;</guimenu></menuchoice>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.logout">
  <title>Ending Your Session</title>

  <para>
   Log out (so another use can use the computer next), restart the computer
   or shut it down.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.logout.switch">
   <title>Log out or change user</title>
   <para>
    Click on the <guimenu>Main Menu</guimenu> button in your control bar and
    select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Leave</guimenu> <guimenu>Log Out</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>. This ends your session but the system remains active. To
    start a parallel session as a different user, instead select the option
    <menuchoice> <guimenu>Leave</guimenu> <guimenu>Switch User</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kdequick.logout.restart">
   <title>Restart or shut down the computer</title>
   <para>
    Click on <guimenu>Leave</guimenu> and then select one of the following
    options:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Sleep</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Only available if the computer supports energy management functions.
       Puts the computer into sleep mode without logging the user off. All
       data and the session data are stored in the main memory.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Hibernate</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Only available if the computer supports power management functions.
       Puts the computer into sleep mode without logging the user off. All
       data and session data are stored on the hard drive before the system
       goes into hibernation. This protects the data from being lost if a
       power failure occurs in the meantime.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Restart</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Restarts the computer.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Shut down</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Logs you out of the current session, then turns off the computer.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kdequick.more">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   You can also find more information on KDE and KDE applications at
   <ulink url="http://www.kde.org/"/> and
   <ulink url="http://www.kde-apps.org/"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
