<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:novdoc-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml" 
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN"
                      "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "IGNORE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<?provo dirname="installquick/"?>
<article id="art.sle.installquick" lang="en">
<?suse-quickstart color="suse"?>
 <title>&instquick;</title>
 <subtitle>&productname; &productnumber;</subtitle>
 <articleinfo>
  <productnumber>&productnumber;</productnumber>
  <productname>&productname;</productname>
 </articleinfo>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   Use the following procedures to install a new version of &productnamereg;
   &productnumber;. This document gives a quick overview on how to run
   through a default installation of &productname; on the x86_64
   architecture.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <sect1 id="sec.sle.installquick">
  <title>Welcome to &productname;</title>

  <para>
   For more detailed installation instructions and deployment strategies,
   see the &productname; Documentation at
   <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/documentation/"/>.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.sle.installquick.sysreqs">
   <title>Minimum System Requirements</title>
   
   <remark condition="clarity">
    2014-02-26 - fs: list needs to be updated, ask with Beta 7
   </remark>
   
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Pentium* III 500 MHz or higher processor (Pentium 4 2.4 GHz or higher
      or any AMD64/Intel* EM64T processor recommended)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      512 MB physical RAM (1 GB or more recommended)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      3.5 GB available disk space (more recommended)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      800 x 600 display resolution (1024 x 768 or higher recommended)
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.sle.installquick.install">
   <title>Installing &productname;</title>
   <para>
    Use these instructions if there is no existing Linux system on your
    machine, or if you want to replace an existing Linux system.
   </para>
   <remark>missing from fate #305034: iso image installation into a virtualized
    environment (m)</remark>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Insert the &productname; DVD into the drive, then reboot the computer
      to start the installation program. On machines with a traditional BIOS
      you will see the graphical boot screen shown below. On machines
      equipped with UEFI, a non-graphical boot screen is used. Secure boot
      on UEFI machines is supported.
     </para>
     <para>
      Use <keycap>F2</keycap> to change the language for the installer. A
      corresponding keyboard layout is chosen automatically. Change the video
      resolution for the installer with <keycap>F3</keycap>. See <xref
      linkend="sec.i.yast2.bootscreen"/> or <xref
      linkend="sec.i.yast2.bootscreen_uefi"/> for more information.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_boot.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_boot.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select <guimenu>Installation</guimenu> on the boot screen, then press
      <keycap>Enter</keycap>. This boots the system and loads the
      &productname; installer.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      <guimenu>Language</guimenu> and the <guimenu>Keyboard
      Layout</guimenu> are initialized with the language settings you have
      chosen on the boot screen. Change them here, if necessary.
     </para> 
     <para>
      Read the License Agreement. It is presented in the language you have
      chosen on the boot screen. <guimenu>License Translations</guimenu> are
      available. You need to accept the agreement by checking <guimenu>I
      Agree to the License Terms</guimenu> in order to install
      &productname;. Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_welcome.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_welcome.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
     
     <tip>
      <title>Release Notes</title>
      <para>
       The Release Notes can be viewed from any screen during the installation
       process by selecting <guimenu>Release Notes</guimenu>. 
       <remark condition="clarity">
	2014-02-26 - fs: FIXME: It is planned to show the up-to-date release
        Notes from suse.com in case the network is configured. Ask behlert
	at a later point in time (Beta 7).
       </remark>
      </para>
     </tip>
     
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      After a system analysis (where the installer probes for storage devices
      and tries to find other installed systems on your machine) you can
      register your system at the SUSE Customer Center (SCC). Enter the e-mail
      address associated with your SCC account and the registration code for
      &productname;. A successful registration is a prerequisite for getting
      product updates and being entitled for technical support. Proceed with
      <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_scc.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_scc.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Check <guimenu>Include add-on Products from Separate Media</guimenu> to
      include add-on products during the installation. An add-on product can
      include extensions, third-party products and drivers or additional
      software for your system.
     </para>
     
     <tip>
      <title>
       Installing Product Patches and Drivers during the Installation
      </title>
      <para>
       In case your organization provides the update channel for SUSE Linux
       Enterprise Server via an SMT server, it is possible to specify this
       channel as an add-on product by entering its HTTP address. As a
       consequence, the system will be installed with the most current
       packages without having to apply the updates at the end of the
       installation.
      </para>
      <para>
       You can also add driver update repositories via the Add-On Products
       dialog. Driver updates for SUSE Linux Enterprise are provided at <ulink
       url="http://drivers.suse.com/"/>. These drivers have been created via
       the Partner Linux Driver Program.
      </para>
     </tip>
     <para>
      Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to choose the installation source
      for the add-on product. It can be installed either from a local source
      (CD, DVD, or directory) or from a network source (HTTP, FTP, NFS,
      CIFS,...). A network source can only be used when the network interface
      has been successfully configured via DHCP when the installation system
      started, or when having provided the networking data manually at the
      boot prompt (see <xref
      linkend="sec.deployment.remoteinst.bootinst.custom"/> for details).
     </para>
     <para>
      Check <guimenu>Download Repository Description Files</guimenu> to
      download the files describing the repository now. If unchecked, they
      will be downloaded once the installation starts. Proceed with
      <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and insert a media if required. Depending on the
      product's content it may be necessary to accept additional license
      agreements. Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
     </para>

     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_options.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_options.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>

    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Review and, if necessary, change the partition setup proposed by the
      system. You have the following options:
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>Edit Proposal Settings</guimenu></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 lets you change options of the proposed settings, but not the
	 suggested partition layout itself
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>Create Partition Setup</guimenu></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 select a disk to which to apply the proposal
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>Import Partition Setup</guimenu></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 lets you import a partitioning scheme from a previous installation
	 found on the hard disk(s)
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>Edit Partition Setup</guimenu></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 opens the <guimenu>Expert Partitioner</guimenu> described in <xref
	 linkend="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert"/>
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
     <para>
      To accept the proposed setup without any changes, choose
      <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed.
     </para>

     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_partitioner.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_partitioner.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    
    <step>
     <para>
      Select the clock and time zone to use in your system. To manually adjust
      the time or to configure an NTP server for time synchronization, choose
      <guimenu>Other Settings</guimenu>. See <xref
      linkend="sec.i.yast2.timezone"/> for detailed information. Proceed with
      <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. 
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_timezone.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_timezone.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To create a local user by typing the first and last name in the
      <guimenu>User’s Full Name</guimenu> field, the login name in the
      <guimenu>Username</guimenu> field, and the password in the
      <guimenu>Password</guimenu> field.
     </para>
     <para>
      the password should be at least eight characters long and should contain
      both uppercase and lowercase letters and numbers. The maximum length for
      passwords is 72 characters, and passwords are case-sensitive.
     </para>
     <para>
      For security reasons it is also strongly recommended
      <emphasis>not</emphasis> to enable the <guimenu>Automatic
      Login</guimenu>. You should also <emphasis>not</emphasis> <guimenu>Use
      this Password for the System Administrator</guimenu> but rather provide
      a separate &rootuser; password in the next installation step. Mails
      generated by the system are delivered to the user &rootuser; by
      default. Check <guimenu>Receive System Mail</guimenu> if you would
      rather get them as the user you just created.  
     </para>
     <para>
      Selecting <guimenu>Change</guimenu> gets you to the expert options
      explained at <xref
      linkend="cha.y2.userman"/>. Proceed with
      <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_user.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_user.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>

    <step>
     <para>
      Type a password for the system administrator account (called the
      &rootuser; user).
     </para>
     <para>
      You should never forget the &rootuser; password! After you entered it
      here, the password cannot be retrieved. See <xref
      linkend="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.root"/> for more information. Proceed
      with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_root.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_root.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>

    <step>
     <para>
      Use the <guimenu>Installation Settings</guimenu> screen to review
      and&mdash;if necessary&mdash;change a number of proposed installation
      settings. The current configuration is listed for each setting. To
      change it, click the headline. Some settings, such as firewall or SSH
      can directly be changed by clicking on the respective links.
     </para>

     <tip>
      <title>Default Installation</title>
      <para>
       Changes you can make here, can also be made later at any time from the
       installed system. However, if you need remote access directly after the
       installation, you should adjust the <guimenu>Firewall and SSH</guimenu>
       settings according to your need. 
      </para>
     </tip>

     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>Software</guimenu></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 The default scope of software includes the base system and X Window
	 with the GNOME desktop. Clicking <guimenu>Software</guimenu> opens
	 the <guimenu>Software Selection and System Tasks</guimenu> screen,
	 where you can change the software selection by selecting or
	 deselecting patterns. Each pattern contains a number of software
	 packages needed for specific functions (e.g. Web and LAMP server or a
	 print server). For a more detailed selection based on software
	 packages to install, select <guimenu>Details</guimenu> to switch to
	 the &yast; <guimenu>Software Manager</guimenu>. See <xref
	 linkend="cha.y2.sw"/> for more information.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>Booting</guimenu></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 This section shows the bootloader configuration. Changing the
	 defaults is only recommended if really needed. Refer to <xref
	 linkend="grub2"/> for details.  
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>Firewall and SSH</guimenu></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 By default, the Firewall is enabled with the active network interface
	 configured for the external zone. See <xref
	 linkend="sec.security.firewall.SuSE"/> for configuration details.
	</para>
	<para>
	 The SSH service is disabled by default, it's port (22) is
	 closed. Therefore login in from remote is not possible by default.
	 Click <guimenu>enable and open</guimenu> to toggle these
	 settings.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry os="sles">
       <term><guimenu>Kdump</guimenu></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 Kdump saves the memory image (<quote>core dump</quote>) to the file
	 system in case the Kernel crashes. This enables you to find the cause
	 of the crash by debugging the dump file. Kdump is preconfigured and
	 enabled by default. See <xref linkend="cha.tuning.kdump.basic"/> for
	 more information.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>Default systemd Target and Services</guimenu></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 By default, the system boots into the <guimenu>graphical</guimenu>
	 target, with network, multiuser and display manager support. Switch
	 to <guimenu>multi-user</guimenu> if you do not need to login via
	 display manager. 
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>System</guimenu></term>
       <listitem>
	<para>
	 View detailed hardware information by clicking
	 <guimenu>System</guimenu>. In the resulting screen you can also
	 change <guimenu>Kernel Settings</guimenu>&mdash;see FIXME for more
	 information.
	</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
     <informalfigure os="sles">
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_overview_sles.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_overview_sles.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>

     <informalfigure os="sled">
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_overview_sled.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_overview_sled.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>

    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Once you have finalized the system configuration on the
      <guimenu>Installation Settings</guimenu> screen, click
      <guimenu>Install</guimenu>. Depending on your software selection you may
      have to agree to license agreements before the installation confirmation
      screen pops up. Up to this point no changes have been made to your
      system. Once you click <guimenu>Install</guimenu> again, the
      installation process starts.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_confirm.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_confirm.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      During the installation, the progress is shown in detail on the
      <guimenu>Perform Installation</guimenu> screen.
     </para>
     <informalfigure os="sled">
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_perform_sled.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_perform_sled.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>

     <informalfigure os="sles">
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_perform_sles.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_perform_sles.png" width="100%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>

    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      After the installation routine has finished, the computer is rebooted
      into the installed system. Login and start &yast; to fine-tune the
      system. If you are not using a graphical desktop or working from remote,
      refer to <xref linkend="cha.yast.text"/> for information on using &yast;
      from a terminal.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="common_copyright_quick.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="common_gfdl1.2_i.xml"/>
</article>
