<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml"
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="article-podman" xml:lang="en">
 <title>Podman Guide</title>
 <info>
  <productnumber>&productnumber;</productnumber><productname>&productname;</productname><date>
<?dbtimestamp format="B d, Y"?></date>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    This guide describes Podman and containers.
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <section xml:id="sec-introduction-containers">
  <title>Introduction to containers</title>
  <para>
   Containers offer a lightweight virtualization method to run multiple virtual
   environments (containers) simultaneously on a single host. Unlike
   technologies such as &xen; or &kvm;, where the processor simulates a
   complete hardware environment and a hypervisor controls virtual machines,
   containers provide virtualization on the operating system level, where the
   kernel controls the isolated containers.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <title>Advantages of using containers</title>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Containers make it possible to isolate applications in self-contained
     units.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Containers provide near-native performance. Depending on the runtime, a
     container can use the host kernel directly, thus minimizing overhead.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     It is possible to control network interfaces and apply resources inside
     containers through kernel control groups.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <title>Limitations of containers</title>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Containers run on the host system's kernel, so they cannot use different
     kernels or different kernel versions.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Containers are not secure, and the overall security depends on the host
     system. Containerized applications can be secured through &aa; or &selnx;
     profiles. Securing containers is harder than securing virtual machines,
     due to the larger attack surface.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="sec-introduction-podman">
  <title>Podman overview</title>
  <para>
   Podman is a short name for Pod Manager Tool. It is a daemonless container
   engine that enables you to run and deploy applications using containers and
   container images. Podman provides a command line interface to manage
   containers.
  </para>
  <para>
   As Podman does not have a daemon, it provides integration with systemd. This
   makes it possible to control containers via systemd units. You can create
   these units for existing containers as well as generate units that can start
   containers if they do not exist in the system. Moreover, Podman can run
   systemd inside containers.
  </para>
  <para>
   Podman enables you to organize your containers into pods. Pods share the
   same network interface and resources. A typical use case for organizing a
   group of containers into a pod is a container that runs a database and a
   container with a client that accesses the database. For further information
   about pods, refer to <xref linkend="pod-architecture"/>.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="pod-architecture">
   <title>Pods architecture</title>
   <para>
    A pod is a group of containers that share the same name space, ports, and
    network connection. Usually, containers within one pod can communicate
    directly with each other. Each pod contains an infrastructure container
    (<literal>INFRA</literal>), whose purpose is to hold the name space.
    <literal>INFRA</literal> also enables Podman to add other containers to the
    pod. Port bindings, cgroup-parent values, and kernel name spaces are all
    assigned to the infrastructure container. Therefore, later changes of these
    values are not possible.
   </para>
   <figure xml:id="fig-pod-architecture">
    <title>Pods architecture</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="pods_architecture.svg" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="pods_architecture.svg" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    Each container in a pod has its own instance of a monitoring program. The
    monitoring program watches the container's process and if the container
    dies, the monitoring program saves its exit code. The program also holds
    open the tty interface for the particular container. The monitoring program
    enables you to run containers in the detached mode when Podman exits, because
    this program continues to run and enables you to attach tty later.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="sec-podman-delivery">
  <title>Getting Podman</title>
  <para>
   In case of &slema;, Podman is delivered in all raw images or is installed by
   default if you installed your system manually from ISO. To verify that
   Podman is installed in your system, run the following command:
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;zypper se -i podman</screen>
  <para>
   If Podman is not listed in the output, install it by running:
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;transactional-update pkg install podman*</screen>
  <para>
   In the Cockpit web interface, you need to start Podman as a service by
   clicking <guimenu>Start podman</guimenu> to access container
   management.
  </para>
  <para>
   By default, Podman requires root privileges. To enable rootless mode for the
   current user, run the following command:
  </para>
<screen>
&prompt.user;sudo usermod --add-subuids 200000-201000 \
  --add-subgids 200000-201000 $USER
</screen>
  <para>
   Reboot the machine to enable the change. The command above defines a range
   of local UIDs to which the UIDs allocated to users inside the container are
   mapped on the host. Note that the ranges defined for different users must
   not overlap. It is also important that the ranges do not reuse the UID of an
   existing local user or group. By default, adding a user with the
   <command>useradd</command> command automatically allocates subUID and subGID
   ranges.
  </para>
  <para>
   Running a container with Podman in rootless mode on &slema; may fail,
   because the container needs read access to the SUSE Customer Center
   credentials. Therefore, running containers as &rootuser; is recommended.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="sec-getting-images">
  <title>Getting container images</title>
  <para>
   To run a container, you need an image. An image includes all the
   dependencies needed to run an application. You can obtain images from an
   image registry. Available registries are defined in the
   <filename>/etc/containers/registries.conf</filename> configuration file. If
   you have a local image registry or want to use other registries, add the
   registries into the configuration file.
  </para>
  <important>
   <title>No tools for building images in &slema;</title>
   <para>
    &slema; does not provide tools for building custom images. Therefore, the
    only way to get an image is to pull it from an image registry.
   </para>
  </important>
  <para>
   The <command>podman pull</command> command pulls an image from an image registry.
   The syntax is as follows:
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman pull <replaceable>[OPTIONS]</replaceable> <replaceable>SOURCE</replaceable></screen>
  <para>
   The <replaceable>source</replaceable> can be an image without the registry
   name. In that case, Podman tries to pull the image from all registries
   configured in the <filename>/etc/containers/registries.conf</filename> file.
   The default image tag is <literal>latest</literal>. The default location of
   pulled images is
   <filename>/var/lib/containers/storage/overlay-images/</filename>.
  </para>
  <para>
   To view all possible options of the <command>podman pull</command> command,
   run:
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman pull --help</screen>
  <note>
   <title>Getting images using Cockpit</title>
   <para>
    If you are using Cockpit, you can also pull images from an image registry in
    the <guimenu>Podman containers</guimenu> menu by clicking <guimenu>+ Get
    new image</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   Podman enables you to search for images in an image registry or a list of
   registries using the command:
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman search <replaceable>IMAGE_NAME</replaceable></screen>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="sec-working-containers">
  <title>Working with containers</title>
  <para>
   The following section covers common container management tasks. This
   includes creating, starting, and modifying containers.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="sec-podman-run">
   <title>Running containers</title>
   <para>
    After you have pulled your container image, you can create containers based
    on it. You can run an instance of the image using the <command>podman
    run</command> command. The command syntax is as follows:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman run [<replaceable>OPTIONS</replaceable>] <replaceable>IMAGE</replaceable> [<replaceable>CONTAINER_NAME</replaceable>]</screen>
   <para>
    <replaceable>IMAGE</replaceable> is specified in format
    <emphasis>transport:path</emphasis>. If <emphasis>transport</emphasis> is
    omitted, the default <literal>docker</literal> is used. The
    <emphasis>path</emphasis> can reference to a specific image registry. If
    omitted, Podman searches for the image in registries defined in the
    <filename>/etc/containers/registries.conf</filename> file. An example that
    runs a container called <literal>sles15</literal> based on the
    <literal>sle15</literal> image follows:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman run registry.opensuse.org/suse/templates/images/sle-15-sp3/base/images/suse/sle15 sles15</screen>
   <para>
    Below is a list of frequently used options. For a complete list of
    available options, run the command: <command>podman run --help</command>.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>--detach, -d</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The container will run in the background.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>--env, -e=env</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This option allows arbitrary environment variables that are available
       for the process to be launched inside of the container. If an
       environment variable is specified without a value, Podman will check the
       host environment for a value and set the variable only if it is set on
       the host.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>--help</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Prints help for the <command>podman run</command> command.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>--hostname=</literal><emphasis>name</emphasis>,<literal> -h</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Sets the container host name that is available inside the container.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>--pod=</literal><emphasis>name</emphasis></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Runs container in an existing pod. To create a pod, prefix the pod name
       with <literal>new:</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>--read-only</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Mounts the container’s root file system as read only.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>--systemd=true|false|always</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Runs container in systemd mode. The default is true.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-podman-stop">
   <title>Stopping containers</title>
   <para>
    If the <command>podman run</command> command finished successfully, a new
    container has been started. You can stop the container by running:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman stop <replaceable>[OPTIONS]</replaceable> <replaceable>CONTAINER</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    You can specify a single container name or ID or a space-separated list of
    containers. The command takes the following options:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>--all, -a</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Stops all running containers.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>--latest, -l</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Instead of providing a container name, the last created container will
       be stopped.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>--time, -t=</literal><emphasis>seconds</emphasis></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Seconds to wait before forcibly stopping the container.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    To view all possible options of the <command>podman stop</command> command,
    run the following:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman stop --help</screen>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-podman-start">
   <title>Starting containers</title>
   <para>
    To start already created but stopped containers, use the <command>podman
    start</command> command. The command syntax is as follows:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman start <replaceable>[OPTIONS]</replaceable> <replaceable>CONTAINER</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    <replaceable>CONTAINER</replaceable> can be a container name or a container
    ID.
   </para>
   <para>
    For a complete list of possible options of <command>podman start</command>,
    run the command:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman start --help</screen>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-podman-commit">
   <title>Committing modified containers</title>
   <para>
    You can run a new container with specific attributes that are not part of
    the original image. To save the container with these attributes as a new
    image, you can use the <command>podman commit</command> command:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman commit <replaceable>[OPTIONS]</replaceable> <replaceable>CONTAINER</replaceable> <replaceable>IMAGE</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    <replaceable>CONTAINER</replaceable> is a container name or a container ID.
    <replaceable>IMAGE</replaceable> is the new image name. If the image name
    does not start with a registry name, the value <literal>localhost</literal>
    is used.
   </para>
   <para>
    When using Cockpit, you can perform the <command>commit</command> operation
    directly from a container's <guimenu>Details</guimenu>, by clicking
    <guimenu>Commit</guimenu>. A dialog box opens. Specify all required details
    as shown below and click <guimenu>Commit</guimenu>:
   </para>
   <figure>
    <title>Committing a container in Cockpit</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="cockpit_commit_container.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="cockpit_commit_container.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-podman-ps">
   <title>Listing containers</title>
   <para>
    Podman enables you to list all running containers using the <command>podman
    ps</command> command. The generic syntax of the command is as follows:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman  ps <replaceable>[OPTIONS]</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    Command options can change the displayed information. For example, using
    the <literal>--all</literal> option will output all containers created by
    Podman (not only the running containers).
   </para>
   <para>
    For a complete list of <command>podman ps</command> options, run:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman ps --help</screen>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-podman-rm">
   <title>Removing containers</title>
   <para>
    To remove one or more unused container from the host, use the
    <command>podman rm</command> command as follows:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman rm <replaceable>[OPTIONS]</replaceable> <replaceable>CONTAINER</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    <replaceable>CONTAINER</replaceable> can be a container name or a container
    ID.
   </para>
   <para>
    The command does not remove the specified container if the container is
    running. To remove a running container, use the <literal>-f</literal>
    option.
   </para>
   <para>
    For a complete list of <command>podman rm</command> options, run:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman rm --help</screen>
   <note>
    <title>Deleting all stopped containers</title>
    <para>
     You can delete all stopped containers from your host with a single
     command:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman container prune</screen>
    <para>
     Make sure that each stopped container is intended to be removed before you
     run the command, otherwise you might remove containers that are still in
     use and were stopped only temporarily.
    </para>
   </note>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="sec-working-pods">
  <title>Working with pods</title>
  <para>
   Containers can be grouped into a pod. The containers in the pod then share
   network, pid, and IPC namespace. Pods can be managed by <command>podman
   pod</command> commands. This section provides an overview of the commands
   for managing pods.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="sec-creating-pods">
   <title>Creating pods</title>
   <para>
    The command <command>podman pod create</command> is used to create a pod.
    The syntax of the command is as follows:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman pod create <replaceable>[OPTIONS]</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    The command outputs the pod ID. By default, the pods are created without being
    started. You can start a pod by running a container in the pod, or by
    starting the pod as described in <xref linkend="sec-starting-pods"/>.
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>Default pod names</title>
    <para>
     If you do not specify a pod name with the <literal>--name</literal>
     option, Podman will assign a default name for the pod.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    For a complete list of possible options, run the following command:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman pod create --help</screen>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-listing-pods">
   <title>Listing pods</title>
   <para>
    You can list all pods by running the command:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman pod list</screen>
   <para>
    The output looks as follows:
   </para>
<screen>
POD ID        NAME               STATUS   CREATED       # OF CONTAINERS  INFRA ID
30fba506fecb  upbeat_mcclintock  Created  19 hours ago  1                4324f40c9651
976a83b4d88b  nervous_feynman    Running  19 hours ago  2                daa5732ecd02
</screen>
   <para>
    As each pod includes the <literal>INFRA</literal> container, the number of
    containers in a pod is always larger than zero.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-starting-pods">
   <title>Starting/stopping/restarting pods</title>
   <para>
    After a pod is created, you must start it, as it is not in the state
    <literal>running</literal> by default. In the commands below,
    <replaceable>POD</replaceable> can be a pod name or a pod ID.
   </para>
   <para>
    To start a pod, run the command:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman pod start <replaceable>[OPTIONS]</replaceable> <replaceable>POD</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    For a complete list of possible options, run:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman pod start --help</screen>
   <para>
    To stop a pod, use the <command>podman pod stop</command> as follows:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman pod stop <replaceable>POD</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    To restart a pod, use the <command>podman pod restart</command> command as
    follows:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman pod restart <replaceable>POD</replaceable></screen>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-adding-pods">
   <title>Managing containers in a pod</title>
   <para>
    To add a new container to a pod, use the <command>podman run</command>
    command with the option <literal>--pod</literal>. A general syntax of the
    command follows:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman run <replaceable>[OPTIONS]</replaceable> --pod <replaceable>POD_NAME</replaceable> <replaceable>IMAGE</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    For details about the <command>podman run</command> command, refer to
    <xref linkend="sec-podman-run"/>.
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>Only new containers can be added to a pod</title>
    <para>
     The <command>podman start</command> command does not allow for starting a
     container in a pod if the container was not added to the pod during
     the container's initial running.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    You cannot remove a container from a pod and keep the container running,
    because the container itself is removed from the host.
   </para>
   <para>
    Other actions like start, restart, and stop can be performed on specific
    containers without affecting the status of the pod.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-removing-pods">
   <title>Removing pods</title>
   <para>
    There are two ways to remove pods. You can use the <command>podman pod
    rm</command> command to remove one or more pods. Alternatively, you can
    remove all stopped pods using the <command>podman pod prune</command>
    command.
   </para>
   <para>
    To remove a pod or several pods, run the <command>podman pod rm</command>
    command as follows:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman pod rm <replaceable>POD</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    <replaceable>POD</replaceable> can be a pod name or a pod ID.
   </para>
   <para>
    To remove all currently stopped pods, use the <command>podman pod
    prune</command> command. Make sure that all stopped pods are intended to be
    removed before you run the <command>podman pod prune</command> command,
    otherwise you might remove pods that are still in use.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-monitoring-pods">
   <title>Monitoring processes in pods</title>
   <para>
    To view all containers in all pods, use the following command:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;podman ps -a --pod</screen>
   <para>
    The output of the command will be similar to the following one:
   </para>
   <!-- Decreased text size and removed a few columns to make this fit on the PDF. -->
<screen>
<?dbsuse-fo font-size="0.70em"?>
CONTAINER ID  IMAGE                       COMMAND    CREATED       STATUS                 [...]
4324f40c9651  k8s.gcr.io/pause:3.2                   21 hours ago  Created
daa5732ecd02  k8s.gcr.io/pause:3.2                   22 hours ago  Up 3 hours ago
e5c8e360c54b  localhost/test:latest       /bin/bash  3 days ago    Exited (137) 3 days ago
82dad15828f7  localhost/opensuse/toolbox  /bin/bash  3 days ago    Exited (137) 3 days ago
1a23da456b6f  docker.io/i386/ubuntu       /bin/bash  4 days ago    Exited (0) 6 hours ago
df890193f651  localhost/opensuse/toolbox  /bin/bash  4 days ago    Created
  </screen>
   <para>
    The first two records are the <literal>INFRA</literal> containers of each
    pod, based on the <literal>k8s.gcr.io/pause:3.2</literal> image. Other
    containers in the output are stand-alone containers that do not belong to
    any pod.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
 <xi:include href="podman_terminology.xml"/>
</article>
