<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<article xml:id="article-amd-sev" xml:lang="en" version="5.0"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>&sle_amd_sev_guide;</title>
 <info><productname>&productname;</productname>
  <productnumber>&productnumber;</productnumber><date>
  <?dbtimestamp format="B d, Y" ?></date>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    AMD's Secure Encrypted Virtualization (SEV) allows the memory of virtual
    machines to be encrypted. SEV with Encrypted State (SEV-ES) goes one step
    further by encrypting the virtual machine's CPU register content. These
    technologies increase system security and are ideal for multi-tenant
    environments such as cloud computing. They enable protection from a variety
    of cross-VM and hypervisor-based attacks. As an example, a hostile VM that
    has escaped its hypervisor-enforced confines and is able to read arbitrary
    memory will be unable to steal sensitive data from an SEV or SEV-ES VM.
   </para>

   <para>
    This document aims to provide a basic understanding of how SEV and SEV-ES
    work, and how to enable and configure these features. It also mentions some
    limitations and restrictions that the use of SEV and SEV-ES causes as
    compared to non-encrypted virtualization.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-amd-sev-intro">
  <title>Introducing SEV</title>

  <para>
   Encryption of computer data stored on disk is a widely-deployed feature.
   However, data in RAM is stored in the clear. This can leave that data
   vulnerable to software or hardware probing by intruders on the host system,
   particularly in cloud computing environments where the physical resources
   are shared by many tenants. Consider a virtual machine of a hostile tenant
   escaping its sandbox because of a hypervisor bug and searching memory for
   sensitive data.
  </para>

  <para>
   AMD's SEV (Secure Encrypted Virtualization) is a technology to protect Linux
   KVM virtual machines by transparently encrypting the memory of each VM with
   a unique key. SEV can also calculate a signature of the memory contents,
   which can be sent to the VM's owner as an attestation that the memory was
   encrypted correctly by the firmware. SEV is especially relevant to cloud
   computing environments, where VMs are hosted on remote servers which are not
   under the control of the VMs' owners. SEV can reduce the amount of trust VMs
   need to place in the hypervisor and administrator of their host system.
  </para>

  <para>
   When a virtual machine is processing sensitive data, it can be present in
   CPU registers as well as memory. If the processing is halted, for example,
   to service an interrupt or share time with other processes, the virtual
   machine's CPU register contents are saved to hypervisor memory. This memory
   is readable by the hypervisor even if SEV is enabled. SEV-ES protects
   against this scenario by encrypting all CPU register contents when the
   processing of a virtual machine is halted. SEV-ES builds upon SEV to provide
   an even smaller attack surface for virtual machines running in a
   multi-tenant environment.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <!-- sections: -->
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-amd-sev-hostreqs">
  <title>VM host requirements</title>

  <para>
   The VM host hardware must support AMD's SEV technology. To detect if the
   host hardware supports SEV, check that the <tag class="attribute">sev</tag>
   attribute is in the capabilities of <package>libvirt</package> and that its
   value is set appropriately:
  </para>

<screen>&lt;domainCapabilities&gt;
   ...
   &lt;features&gt;
   ...
   &lt;sev supported='yes'/&gt;
   ...
   &lt;/sev&gt;
   &lt;/features&gt;
&lt;/domainCapabilities&gt;</screen>

  <para>
   Additionally, ensure that the <package>kvm_amd</package> kernel module has
   the <parameter>sev</parameter> parameter enabled:
  </para>

<screen>/sys/module/kvm_amd/parameters/sev = 1</screen>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-amd-sev-vmreqs">
  <title>VM requirements</title>

  <para>
   The VM must be the modern <literal>Q35</literal> machine type and must use
   UEFI firmware. &libvirt; can automatically select an appropriate SEV or
   SEV-ES enabled UEFI firmware, or one can be specified manually. Currently,
   the only firmware supported are
   <filename>/usr/share/qemu/ovmf-x86_64-code.bin</filename> and
   <filename>/usr/share/qemu/ovmf-x86_64-4m-code.bin</filename>. See
   <xref linkend="sec-vt-installation-ovmf"/> for more details on using UEFI
   firmware and the auto-selection feature.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>No IDE support in Q35</title>
   <para>
    The Q35 machine type does not have an IDE controller and does not support
    IDE disks.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   All <literal>virtio-net</literal> devices need to be configured with the
   iPXE option ROM disabled. iPXE is currently not compatible with SEV and
   SEV-ES. In addition, all memory regions used by the VM must be locked for
   Direct Memory Access (DMA) and to prevent swapping. This includes memory for
   the VM and any memory regions allocated by &qemu; to support running the VM,
   such as UEFI pflash for firmware and variable store, video RAM, etc.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-amd-sev-config">
  <title>VM configuration</title>

  <example xml:id="sec-amd-sev-conffile">
   <title>Sample configuration file</title>
   <para>
    As an example, an SEV-encrypted VM configured with 4 GB of memory would
    contain the following XML configuration:
   </para>
<screen>&lt;domain type='kvm'&gt;
    &lt;memory unit='KiB'&gt;4194304&lt;/memory&gt;
    &lt;currentMemory unit='KiB'&gt;4194304&lt;/currentMemory&gt;
    &lt;memoryBacking&gt;
    &lt;locked/&gt; <co xml:id="sec-amd-sev-ex-memlock"/>
    &lt;/memoryBacking&gt;
    &lt;os&gt;
    &lt;type arch='x86_64' machine='pc-q35-2.11'&gt;hvm&lt;/type&gt;
    &lt;loader readonly='yes' type='pflash'&gt;/usr/share/qemu/ovmf-x86_64-ms-4m-code.bin&lt;/loader&gt;
    &lt;nvram&gt;/var/lib/libvirt/qemu/nvram/sles15-sev-guest_VARS.fd&lt;/nvram&gt;
    &lt;boot dev='hd'/&gt;
    &lt;/os&gt;
    &lt;launchSecurity <co xml:id="sec-amd-sev-ex-launchsecurity"/> type='sev'&gt;
    &lt;cbitpos&gt;47&lt;/cbitpos&gt; <co xml:id="sec-amd-sev-ex-cbitpos"/>
    &lt;reducedPhysBits&gt;1&lt;/reducedPhysBits&gt; <co xml:id="sec-amd-sev-ex-reducedphysbits"/>
    &lt;policy&gt;0x0033&lt;/policy&gt; <co xml:id="sec-amd-sev-ex-policy"/>
    &lt;dhCert&gt;AAAABBBB=CCCCCDDDDD&lt;/dhCert&gt; <co xml:id="sec-amd-sev-ex-dhcert"/>
    &lt;session&gt;AAAABBBB=EEEEEFFFFF&lt;/session&gt; <co xml:id="sec-amd-sev-ex-session"/>
    &lt;/launchSecurity&gt;
    &lt;devices&gt;
    &lt;interface type='bridge'&gt;
    &lt;source bridge='br0'/&gt;
    &lt;model type='virtio'/&gt;
    &lt;rom enabled='no'/&gt; <co xml:id="sec-amd-sev-ex-ipxerom"/>
    &lt;/interface&gt;
    ...
    &lt;/devices&gt;
    ...
    &lt;/domain&gt;</screen>
   <calloutlist>
    <callout arearefs="sec-amd-sev-ex-memlock">
     <para>
      The <tag class="element">memoryBacking</tag> element, along with its
      child element <tag class="element">locking</tag>, is used to ease memory
      limit restrictions libvirt places on the VM's cgroup. Otherwise, VM
      creation would fail when &qemu; attempts to lock the VM's memory regions
      along with other regions used to support the VM operation. See
      <link xlink:href="https://libvirt.org/kbase/launch_security_sev.html#memory"/>
      for more information on VM memory configuration requirements for SEV VMs.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="sec-amd-sev-ex-launchsecurity">
     <para>
      The <tag class="element">launchSecurity type='sev'</tag> element and its
      contents enable encryption of the VM's memory contents.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="sec-amd-sev-ex-cbitpos">
     <para>
      When memory encryption is enabled, one of the physical address bits (also
      known as the "C-bit") is used to mark if a memory page is protected. The
      required <tag class="element">cbitpos</tag> element provides the location
      of the C-bit in a guest page table entry. For example, the value
      <literal>47</literal> indicates that bit position 47 in a page table
      entry will determine whether that page is encrypted or not. The C-bit
      number is read from the host's CPUID and is thus hardware-dependent. The
      value of <tag class="element">cbitpos</tag> is hypervisor-dependent, and
      can be obtained through the <tag class="element">sev</tag> element in the
      capabilities of the domain.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="sec-amd-sev-ex-reducedphysbits">
     <para>
      When memory encryption is enabled, we lose certain bits of the physical
      address space. The required <tag class="element">reducedPhysBits</tag>
      element provides this physical address bit reduction. Similarly to
      <tag class="element">cbitpos</tag>, the value of
      <tag class="element">reducedPhysBits</tag> is processor-family-dependent
      and can be obtained through the <tag class="element">sev</tag> element in
      the domain capabilities.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="sec-amd-sev-ex-policy">
     <para>
      The required <tag class="element">policy</tag> element provides the guest
      policy which must be maintained by the SEV firmware. This policy is
      enforced by the firmware, and restricts what configuration and
      operational commands can be performed on the VM by the hypervisor. The
      guest policy provided when starting the VM is bound to that VM and cannot
      be changed throughout its lifetime.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="sec-amd-sev-ex-dhcert">
     <para>
      The optional <tag class="element">dhCert</tag> element provides the guest
      owner's base64-encoded Diffie-Hellman (DH) key. The key is used to
      negotiate a master secret key between the SEV firmware and guest owner.
      This master secret key is then used to establish a trusted channel
      between the SEV firmware and guest owner.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="sec-amd-sev-ex-session">
     <para>
      The optional <tag class="element">session</tag> element provides the
      guest owner's base64-encoded session blob, as defined in the SEV API
      specification. See the LAUNCH_START section of the SEV specification for
      the session-blob format.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="sec-amd-sev-ex-ipxerom">
     <para>
      In addition to the <tag class="element">launchSecurity</tag> settings,
      SEV-encrypted VMs must have the iPXE option ROM disabled on all
      virtio-net devices. Currently, iPXE is not compatible with SEV-encrypted
      VMs.
     </para>
    </callout>
   </calloutlist>
  </example>

  <para>
   The guest policy is four unsigned bytes with the following definition:
  </para>

  <table xml:id="table-guestpolicy">
   <title>Guest policy definitions</title>
   <tgroup cols="2">
    <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="20*"/>
    <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="80*"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Bit(s)
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Definition
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        0
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        If set, debugging of the guest is disallowed
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        1
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        If set, sharing keys with other guests is disallowed
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        2
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        If set, SEV-ES is required
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        3
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        If set, sending the guest to another platform is disallowed
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        4
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        If set, the guest must not be transmitted to another platform that is
        not in the domain
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        5
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        If set, the guest must not be transmitted to another platform that is
        not SEV-capable
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        6-15
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Reserved
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        16-32
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        The guest must not be transmitted to another platform with a lower
        firmware version
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-amd-sev-vminst">
  <title>VM installation</title>

  <para>
   <command>virt-install</command> supports the installation of SEV and SEV-ES
   virtual machines. In addition to your standard installation parameters,
   provide <command>virt-install</command> with options to satisfy the VM
   requirements and the <literal>--launchSecurity</literal> option.
  </para>

  <para>
   The following example starts a network installation of a SLES15 SP4 virtual
   machine protected with SEV-ES.
  </para>

<screen>
   virt-install --name sles15sp4-sev-es --location http://192.168.0.1/install/sles15sp4/x86_64 --disk size=20 --network=bridge=br0,model=virtio,rom.bar=off <co xml:id="sec-amd-sev-ex-rombar"/> --vcpus 4 --memory 4096 --noautoconsole --events on_reboot=destroy --machine q35 --memtune hard_limit=4563402 --launchSecurity sev,policy=0x07 <co xml:id="sec-amd-sev-ex-launchsec"/> --boot firmware=efi <co xml:id="sec-amd-sev-ex-fw"/> --vnc --serial pty
  </screen>

  <calloutlist>
   <callout arearefs="sec-amd-sev-ex-rombar">
    <para>
     The iPXE option ROM is not compatible with SEV-encrypted VMs and must be
     disabled on all virtio-net devices. While libvirt supports disabling
     option ROMs using either the <literal>enabled</literal> or
     <literal>bar</literal> attributes of the <tag class="element">rom</tag>
     element, virt-install only supports disabling option ROMs using the
     <literal>bar</literal> attribute.
    </para>
   </callout>
   <callout arearefs="sec-amd-sev-ex-launchsec">
    <para>
     The <literal>launchSecurity</literal> option specifies the type and policy
     to be enforced by the SEV firmware. The policy setting is described in
     <xref linkend="table-guestpolicy"/>.
    </para>
   </callout>
   <callout arearefs="sec-amd-sev-ex-fw">
    <para>
     The <literal>boot</literal> option allows specifying many boot-related
     settings, including the firmware used by the virtual machine. Specifying a
     firmware type <literal>efi</literal> allows libvirt's firmware
     auto-selection feature to select an appropriate SEV capable firmware for
     the virtual machine.
    </para>
   </callout>
  </calloutlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-amd-sev-kubevirt">
  <title>SEV with &kubevirt;</title>

  <para>
   &kubevirt; supports running SEV guests starting from the version
   <literal>0.49.0</literal>. The functionality can be activated by enabling
   the <literal>WorkloadEncryptionSEV</literal> feature gate:
  </para>

<screen>
&prompt.user;kubectl edit kubevirt kubevirt -n kubevirt
[...]
spec:
  configuration:
    developerConfiguration:
      featureGates:
      - WorkloadEncryptionSEV
[...]
  </screen>

  <para>
   To run an SEV-encrypted guest, the virtual machine specification must
   include the entry <literal>sev: {}</literal> under the
   <literal>launchSecurity</literal> domain element. Additionally, you need to
   configure the <literal>firmware/bootloader</literal> parameters to use the
   <literal>efi</literal> option with the <literal>secureBoot</literal> flag
   set to <literal>disabled</literal>. The corresponding YAML snippet will look
   similar to the following:
  </para>

<screen>
[...]
spec:
  domain:
    firmware:
      bootloader:
        efi:
          secureBoot: false
    launchSecurity:
      sev: {}
[...]
  </screen>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-amd-sev-limits">
  <title>Current limitations</title>

  <para>
   SUSE does not recommend using the SEV and SEV-ES features with SUSE Linux
   products on the first generation AMD EPYC™ 7000 series of processors, code
   name Naples. It is recommended to use at least the second generation 7002
   series processors, code name Rome. Additionally, the following limitations
   are placed on SEV and SEV-ES VMs.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The guest operating system running inside an SEV-encrypted VM must contain
     SEV support. &sls; 12 SP4 and newer, and all &sls; 15 releases support
     SEV.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Any operations that involve saving and restoring the memory and state of
     an instance are currently not supported. This means that SEV-encrypted VMs
     cannot be resumed from snapshots, saved/restored, or live migrated.
     Encrypted VMs can be shutdown and restarted on another host as normal.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     SEV-encrypted VMs cannot contain directly-accessible host devices (that
     is, PCI passthrough).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     SEV-encrypted VMs are not compatible with Secure Boot. UEFI firmware
     containing Secure Boot support will not work with SEV or SEV-ES VMs.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     SEV-ES VMs cannot be rebooted from within using <command>reboot</command>,
     <command>shutdown -r now</command>, etc. A reboot must be done by shutting
     down the VM and starting it again. This limitation does not apply to SEV
     VMs, only SEV-ES.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   These limitations will be removed in the future as the hardware, firmware,
   and various layers of software receive new features.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-amd-sev-moreinfo">
  <title>More information</title>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <link xlink:href="https://developer.amd.com/sev"/> &mdash; AMD-SEV landing
     page
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <link xlink:href="https://www.amd.com/system/files/TechDocs/55766_SEV-KM_API_Specification.pdf"/>
     &mdash; AMD SEV-KM API Specification (PDF)
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <link xlink:href="https://github.com/AMDESE/AMDSEV/"/> &mdash; AMD SEV
     GitHub repository containing examples and tools
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <link xlink:href="https://libvirt.org/formatdomain.html#sev"/> &mdash;
     libvirt SEV configuration settings
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <link xlink:href="https://libvirt.org/kbase/launch_security_sev.html"/>
     &mdash; libvirt knowledge base article on AMD SEV
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <xi:include href="common_gfdl1.2_i.xml"/>
</article>
