<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml"
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="article-transactional-updates" xml:lang="en">
<title>&slem; Administration</title>
<subtitle>&productname; &productnumber;</subtitle>
<info>
  <productnumber>&productnumber;</productnumber><productname>&productname;</productname>
  <date><?dbtimestamp format="B d, Y"?></date>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    This guide describes administration of &slem;. 
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <section xml:id="sec-transactional-udate">
 <title>Administration by using transactional updates</title>
 <para>
 &slema; was designed to use the read-only root file system. So after the deployment is complete, you are not able to perform direct modifications to the root file system, e.g. by using <command>zypper</command>. The concept of transactional updates has been implemented to enable you to modify and keep your system up to date.
 </para>
 
 <para>
 Transactional updates key features are the following: 
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 they are atomic - the update is applied only if it completes successfully.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 changes are applied in a separate snapshot and thus they do not influence the running system.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 they provide easy rollback.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 
 <para>
 Each time you call the <command>transactional-update</command> to change your system&mdash;either to install a package, perform an update or apply a patch; the following actions take place: 
 </para>
 <procedure>
 <title>Modifying the root file system</title>
 <step>
 <para>
 A new read-write snapshot is created from your current root file system or from a snapshot that you specified.
 </para>
 </step> 
 <step>
 <para>
 All changes are applied (update, patches or package installation).
 </para>
 </step>
 <step>
 <para>
 The snapshot is switched back to the read-only mode.
 </para>
 </step>
 <step>
 <para>
 The new root file system snapshot is prepared to be applied after reboot.
 </para>
 </step>
 <step>
 <para>
 After rebooting the new root file system is used instead of the current root file system.
 </para>
 <note>
 <para>
 Bear in mind that without rebooting your system, the changes won't be applied.
 </para>
 </note>
 </step>
 </procedure>
 
 <para>
 In case you do not reboot your machine before performing further changes to the file system, the new snapshot are created always from the current root. You will end up with several parallel snapshots, each spanshots includes the particular change, but not changes from the other snapshots. After reboot, the last created snapshot will be used as your current root file system and will not include changes done in the previous snapshots.
 </para>
 
 
 
 
 
 <section xml:id="sec-command-list">
 <title><command>transactional-update</command> usage</title>
 <para>
   The <command>transactional-update</command> command enables atomic installation 
   or removal of updates; updates are applied only
   if all of them can be successfully installed.
   <command>transactional-update</command> creates a snapshot of your system
   before the update is applied, and you can restore this snapshot. All changes become 
   active only after reboot.
  </para>
  <para>
  The <command>transactional-update</command> command syntax is the following: 
  </para>
<screen>
transactional-update <option>[option]</option> <replaceable>[general command]</replaceable> <replaceable>[package command]</replaceable> <replaceable>standalone command</replaceable>
</screen>
<para>
Each command parameter is described further.
</para>
<variablelist>
<title><command>transactional-update</command> options</title>
<varlistentry>
<term><literal>--interactive, -i</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Can be used along with the a package command to turn on the interactive mode.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><literal>--non-interactive, -n</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Can be used along with the a package command to turn on the non-interactive mode.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><literal>--continue [&lt;number&gt;], -c</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>
         The <command>--continue</command> option is for making multiple changes to an
         existing snapshot without rebooting.
     </para>
     <para>
         The default <command>transactional-update</command> behavior 
         is to create a new snapshot from the current root file system. If you
         forget something, such as installing a new package, you have to reboot
         to apply your previous changes, run <command>transactional-update</command>
         again to install the forgotten package, and reboot again. You cannot run the
         <command>transactional-update</command> command multiple times without rebooting
         to add more changes to the snapshot, because that creates separate 
         independent snapshots that do not include changes from the previous snapshots.
     </para>
     <para>
         Use the <command>--continue</command> option to make as many changes as you
         want without rebooting. A separate snapshot is made each time, and each
         snapshot contains all the changes you made in the previous snapshots, plus your 
         new changes. Repeat this process as many times as you want, and when the final
         snapshot includes everything you want reboot the system, and your final snapshot
         becomes the new root file system.
     </para>
     <para>
         Another useful feature of the <command>--continue</command> option is you may
         select any existing snapshot as the base for your new snapshot. The following example
         demonstrates running <command>transactional-update</command> to install a new
         package in a snapshot based on snapshot 13, and then running it again to install 
         another package:
     </para>
     <screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg install <replaceable>package_1</replaceable></command></screen>
    <screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update --continue 13 pkg install <replaceable>package_2</replaceable></command></screen>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><literal>--no-selfupdate</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Disables self updating of <command>transactional-update</command>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><literal>--drop-if-no-change, -d</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>
The snapshot created when the <command>transactional-update</command> command is run, is removed if there has not been any change to the file system.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><literal>--quiet</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>
The <command>transactional-update</command> command will not output to stdout.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><literal>--help, -h</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Prints help for the <command>transactional-update</command> command.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><literal>--version</literal></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Displays the version of the <command>transactional-update</command> command.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>


<para>
The general commands are the following:
</para>
<variablelist>
<title>General commands</title>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><literal>cleanup-snapshots</literal></term>
   <listitem>
  <para>
    The command marks all unused snapshots that are intended to be removed.
  </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>   
   <varlistentry>
   <term><literal>cleanup-overlays</literal></term>
   <listitem>
  <para>
    The command removes all unused overlay layers of <filename>/etc</filename>.
  </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   
  <varlistentry>
   <term><literal>cleanup</literal></term>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   The command combines the <literal>cleanup-snapshots</literal> and <literal>cleanup-overlays</literal> commands.
   </para>
  <para>
    If the current root filesystem is identical to the active root
    filesystem (after a reboot, before <command>transactional-update</command>
    creates a new snapshot with updates), all old snapshots without a
    cleanup algorithm get a cleanup algorithm set. This ensures that old 
    snapshots will be deleted. (This also removes all unreferenced (and thus 
    unused) <filename>/etc</filename> overlay directories in 
    <filename>/var/lib/overlay</filename>:
  </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry> 
   <varlistentry>
   <term><literal>grub.cfg</literal></term>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   Use this command to rebuild the GRUB bootloader configuration file.
   </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
   <term><literal>bootloader</literal></term>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   The command reinstall the bootloader.
   </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
   <term><literal>initrd</literal></term>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   Use the command to rebuild initrd.
   </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
   <term><literal>kdump</literal></term>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   In case you perform changes to your hardware or storage, you may need to rebuild the kdump initrd.
   </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
   <term><literal>shell</literal></term>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   Opens a read-write shell in the new snapshot before exiting.
   </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
   <term><literal>reboot</literal></term>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   The system reboots after the transactional-update is complete.
   </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
   <term><literal>run </literal><replaceable>&lt;command&gt;</replaceable></term>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   Runs the provided command in a new snapshot.
   </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
   <term><literal>setup-selinux</literal></term>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   Installs and enables targeted SELinux policy.
   </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
   The package commands are the following:
   </para>
    <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>dup</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Performs upgrade of your system. The default option for this command is <literal>--non-interactive</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>up</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Updates installed packages to newer versions. The default option for this command is <literal>--non-interactive</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>patch</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Checks for available patches and installs them. The default option for this command is <literal>--non-interactive</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>pkg install</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Installs individual packages from the available channels using the
      <command>zypper install</command> command. This command can also be used
      to install Program Temporary Fix (PTF) RPM files. The default option for this command is <literal>--interactive</literal>.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg install <replaceable>package_name</replaceable></command></screen>
     <para>
      or
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg install <replaceable>rpm1 rpm2</replaceable></command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>pkg remove</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Removes individual packages from the active snapshot using the
      <command>zypper remove</command> command. This command can also be used
      to remove PTF RPM files. The default option for this command is <literal>--interactive</literal>.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg remove <replaceable>package_name</replaceable></command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>pkg update</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Updates individual packages from the active snapshot using the
      <command>zypper update</command> command. Only packages that are part of
      the snapshot of the base file system can be updated. The default option for this command is <literal>--interactive</literal>.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg remove <replaceable>package_name</replaceable></command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   
   <para>
   The standalone commnads are the following:
   </para>
   
   <variablelist>
   <title>Standalone commands</title>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>rollback</literal> <replaceable>&lt;snapshot number&gt;</replaceable></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This sets the default subvolume. The current system is set to a new default root
      file system. If you specify a number, that snapshot is used as the
      default root file system. On a read-only file system, it does not create
      any additional snapshots.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update rollback <replaceable>snapshot_number</replaceable></command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>rollback last</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This command sets the last working snapshot as the default.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>status</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This prints a list of available snapshots. The currently booted one is marked with an asterisk, the default snapshot is marked with a plus sign.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="sec-rollback-procedure">
 <title>System rollback</title>
 <para>
 GRUB 2 enables to boot from btrfs snapshots and thus allows you to use any older functional snapshot in case the new snapshot is corrupted.
 </para>
 <para>
 When booting a snapshot, the parts of the file system included in the snapshot are mounted read-only; all other file systems and parts that are excluded from snapshots are mounted read-write and can be modified.
 </para>
 <tip>
   <title>Rolling back to a specific installation state</title>
   <para>
    An initial bootable
    snapshot is created at the end of the initial system installation. You can
    go back to that state at any time by booting this snapshot. The snapshot
    can be identified by the description <literal>after installation</literal>.
   </para>
   </tip>
   <para>
   There are two methods how you can perform a system rollback.
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   From a running system you can set the default snapshot, see more in <xref linkend="proc-running-snapshot"/>.
   </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   Especially in cases where the current snapshot is broken, you can boot to the new snapshot and set it then default, for details refer to <xref linkend="proc-boot-snapshot"/>.
   </para>
   </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
   In case your current snapshot is functional, you can use the following procedure for system rollback.
   </para>
   <procedure xml:id="proc-running-snapshot">
  <step>
  <para>
  Choose the snapshot that should be set as default, run:
  </para>
  <screen>
  &prompt.root;transactional-update status
  </screen>
  <para>
  to get a list of available snapshots. Note the number of the snapshot to be set as default.
  </para>
  </step>
  <step>
  <para>
  Set the snapshot as the default by running:
  </para>
  <screen>
  &prompt.root;transactional-update rollback <replaceable>snapshot number</replaceable>
  </screen>
  <para>
  If you omit the <replaceable>snapshot number</replaceable>, the current snapshot will be set as default.
  </para>
  </step>
  <step>
  <para>
  Reboot your system to boot in to the new default snapshot.
  </para>
  </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
   The following procedure is used in case, the current snapshot is broken and you are not able to boot into it.
   </para>
   <procedure xml:id="proc-boot-snapshot">
   <step>
   <para>
   Reboot your system and select <literal>Start bootloader from a read-only snapshot</literal>
   </para>
   </step>
   <step>
   <para>
   Choose a snapshot to boot. The snapshots are sorted according to the date of creation, the latest being the top one.
   </para>
   </step>
   <step>
   <para>
   Log in to your system and check whether everything works as expected. Bear in mind that the snapshot directories are read-only, so you cannot write into them. Data written to directories excluded from the snapshots will stay untouched.
   </para>
   </step>
   <step>
   <para>
   If the snapshot you booted into is not suitable for rollback, reboot your system and choose another one.
   </para>
   <para>
   If the snapshot works as expected, you can perform rollback by running the following command:
   </para>
   <screen>
   &prompt.root; <command>transactional-update rollback</command>
   </screen>
   <para>
   And reboot afterwards.
   </para>
   </step>
   </procedure>
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="sec-automatic-updates">
 <title>Managing automatic transactional updates</title>
 <para>
      Automatic updates are controlled by a <command>systemd.timer</command> 
      that runs once per day. This applies all updates, and informs 
      <command>rebootmgrd</command> that the machine should be rebooted. You may
      adjust the time when the update runs, see systemd.timer(5). To adjust the
      maintenance window, which is when <command>rebootmgrd</command> reboots the
      system, see rebootmgrd(8).
  </para>
  <para>
   You can disable automatic transactional updates with this command:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.root;<command>systemctl --now disable transactional-update.timer</command></screen>
 
 </section>
 
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="sec-snapshots">
 <title>Snapshots</title>
 <warning>
 <title>Snapshots are mandatory</title>
 <para>
 As snapshots are crucial for &slema; correct functioning, do not disable the feature and ensure that the root partition is big enough to store the snapshots.
 </para>
 </warning>
 <para>
 When a snapshot is created, both the snapshot and the original point to the same blocks in the file system. So, initially a snapshot does not occupy additional disk space. If data in the original file system is modified, changed data blocks are copied while the old data blocks are kept for the snapshot.
 </para>
 <para>
 Snapshots always reside on the same partition or subvolume on which the snapshot has been taken. It is not possible to store snapshots on a different partition or subvolume. As a result, partitions containing snapshots need to be larger than partitions not containing snapshots. The exact amount depends strongly on the number of snapshots you keep and the amount of data modifications. As a rule of thumb, give partitions twice as much space as you normally would. To prevent disks from running out of space, old snapshots are automatically cleaned up. 
 </para>
 
 
 <section xml:id="sec-exclude-directories">
 <title>Directories excluded from snapshots</title>
 <para>
 As some directories store user specific or volatile data, these directories are excluded from snapshots:
 </para>
 <variablelist>
 <varlistentry>
 <term><filename>/home</filename></term>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 Contains user's data. To avoid overwriting this data, this directory is excluded from snapshots.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 <varlistentry>
 <term><filename>/root</filename></term>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 <varlistentry>
 <term><filename>/opt</filename></term>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 Third-party products usually get installed to <filename>/opt</filename>. It is excluded to avoid uninstalling these applications on rollbacks.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 <varlistentry>
 <term><filename>/srv</filename></term>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 Contains data for Web and FTP servers. It is excluded to avoid data loss on rollbacks.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 <varlistentry>
 <term><filename>/usr/local</filename></term>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 This directory is used when manually installing software. It is excluded to avoid uninstalling these installations on rollbacks.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 <varlistentry>
 <term><filename>/var</filename></term>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 This directory contains many variable files, including logs, temporary caches, third party products in <filename>/var/opt</filename>, and is the default location for virtual machine images and databases. Therefore this subvolume is created to exclude all of this variable data from snapshots and has Copy-On-Write disabled.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 <varlistentry>
 <term><filename>/tmp</filename></term>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 The directory contains temporal data.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 <varlistentry>
 <term>the architecture specific <filename>/boot/grub2</filename> directory</term>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 A rollback of the boot loader binaries is not supported. 
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="sec-snapshot-size">
 <title>Showing exclusive disk space used by snapshots</title>
 <para>
      Snapshots share data, for efficient use of storage space, so using ordinary
      commands like <command>du</command> and <command>df</command> won't measure
      used disk space accurately. When you want to free up disk space on Btrfs 
      with quotas enabled, you need to know how much exclusive disk space is 
      used by each snapshot, rather than shared space. The <command>btrfs</command> command provides a view of space used by 
    snapshots:
</para>
<screen>
&prompt.root;btrfs qgroup show -p /
qgroupid         rfer         excl parent  
--------         ----         ---- ------  
0/5          16.00KiB     16.00KiB ---     
[...]    
0/272         3.09GiB     14.23MiB 1/0     
0/273         3.11GiB    144.00KiB 1/0     
0/274         3.11GiB    112.00KiB 1/0     
0/275         3.11GiB    128.00KiB 1/0     
0/276         3.11GiB     80.00KiB 1/0     
0/277         3.11GiB    256.00KiB 1/0     
0/278         3.11GiB    112.00KiB 1/0     
0/279         3.12GiB     64.00KiB 1/0     
0/280         3.12GiB     16.00KiB 1/0     
1/0           3.33GiB    222.95MiB --- 
</screen>
<para>
    The <literal>qgroupid</literal> column displays the identification number for
    each subvolume, assigning a qgroup level/ID combination.
</para> 
<para>
    The <literal>rfer</literal> column displays the total amount of data 
    referred to in the subvolume.
</para>
<para>
    The <literal>excl</literal> column displays the exclusive data in each
    subvolume. 
</para>
<para>
    The <literal>parent</literal> column shows the parent qgroup of the subvolumes.
</para>
<para>    
    The final item, <literal>1/0</literal>, shows the totals for the parent 
    qgroup. In the above example, 222.95 MiB will be freed if all subvolumes
    are removed. Run the following command to see which snapshots are associated
    with each subvolume:
</para>
 </section>
  
 
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="sec-health-checker">
 <title>Health checker</title>
 <para>
 TBD
 </para>
 </section>
</article>
