<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml"
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="article-transactional-updates" xml:lang="en">
<title>&slem; Administration</title>
<subtitle>&productname; &productnumber;</subtitle>
<info>
  <productnumber>&productnumber;</productnumber><productname>&productname;</productname>
  <date><?dbtimestamp format="B d, Y"?></date>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    This guide describes administration of &slem;. 
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <section xml:id="sec-transactional-udate">
 <title>Administration by using transactional updates</title>
 <para>
 &slema; was designed to use the read-only root file system. So after the deployment is complete, you are not able to perform direct modifications to the root file system, e.g. by using <command>zypper</command>. The concept of transactional updates has been implemented to enable you to modify and keep your system up to date.
 </para>
 
 <para>
 Transactional updates key features are the following: 
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 they are atomic - the update is applied only if it completes successfully.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 changes are applied in a separate snapshot and thus they do not influence the running system.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 they provide easy rollback.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 
 <para>
 Each time you call the <command>transactional-update</command> to change your system&mdash;either to install a package, perform an update or apply a patch; the following actions take place: 
 </para>
 <procedure>
 <title>Modifying the root file system</title>
 <step>
 <para>
 A new read-only snapshot is created from your current root file system.
 </para>
 </step>
 <step>
 <para>
 The snapshot is switched to the read-write mode.
 </para>
 </step>
 <step>
 <para>
 All changes are applied (update, patches or package installation).
 </para>
 </step>
 <step>
 <para>
 The snapshot is switched back to the read-only mode.
 </para>
 </step>
 <step>
 <para>
 A new root file system snapshot is created and the snapshots is prepared to be applied after reboot.
 </para>
 </step>
 <step>
 <para>
 After rebooting the new root file system is used instead of the current root file system.
 </para>
 <note>
 <para>
 Bear in mind that without rebooting your system, the changes won't be applied.
 </para>
 </note>
 </step>
 </procedure>
 
 <para>
 In case you do not reboot your machine before performing further changes to the file system, the new snapshot are created always from the current root. You will end up with several parallel snapshots, each spanshots includes the particular change, but not changes from the other snapshots. After reboot, the last created snapshot will be used as your current root file system and will not include changes done in the previous snapshots.
 </para>
 
 
 
 
 
 <section xml:id="sec-command-list">
 <title><command>transactional-update</command> usage</title>
 <para>
   The <command>transactional-update</command> command enables atomic installation 
   or removal of updates; updates are applied only
   if all of them can be successfully installed.
   <command>transactional-update</command> creates a snapshot of your system
   before the update is applied, and you can restore this snapshot. All changes become 
   active only after reboot.
  </para>

<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><literal>--continue</literal></term>
   <listitem>
     <para>
         The <command>--continue</command> option is for making multiple changes to an
         existing snapshot without rebooting.
     </para>
     <para>
         The default <command>transactional-update</command> behavior 
         is to create a new snapshot from the current root file system. If you
         forget something, such as installing a new package, you have to reboot
         to apply your previous changes, run <command>transactional-update</command>
         again to install the forgotten package, and reboot again. You cannot run the
         <command>transactional-update</command> command multiple times without rebooting
         to add more changes to the snapshot, because that creates separate 
         independent snapshots that do not include changes from the previous snapshots.
     </para>
     <para>
         Use the <command>--continue</command> option to make as many changes as you
         want without rebooting. A separate snapshot is made each time, and each
         snapshot contains all the changes you made in the previous snapshots, plus your 
         new changes. Repeat this process as many times as you want, and when the final
         snapshot includes everything you want reboot the system, and your final snapshot
         becomes the new root file system.
     </para>
     <para>
         Another useful feature of the <command>--continue</command> option is you may
         select any existing snapshot as the base for your new snapshot. The following example
         demonstrates running <command>transactional-update</command> to install a new
         package in a snapshot based on snapshot 13, and then running it again to install 
         another package:
     </para>
     <screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg install <replaceable>package_1</replaceable></command></screen>
    <screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update --continue 13 pkg install <replaceable>package_2</replaceable></command></screen>
    <para>
        The <command>--continue [num]</command> option calls <command>snapper create --from</command>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><literal>cleanup</literal></term>
   <listitem>
  <para>
    If the current root filesystem is identical to the active root
    filesystem (after a reboot, before <command>transactional-update</command>
    creates a new snapshot with updates), all old snapshots without a
    cleanup algorithm get a cleanup algorithm set. This ensures that old 
    snapshots will be deleted by Snapper. (See the section about cleanup 
    algorithms in snapper(8).) This also removes all unreferenced (and thus 
    unused) <filename>/etc</filename> overlay directories in 
    <filename>/var/lib/overlay</filename>:
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update cleanup</command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>  
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>pkg in/install</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Installs individual packages from the available channels using the
      <command>zypper install</command> command. This command can also be used
      to install Program Temporary Fix (PTF) RPM files.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg install <replaceable>package_name</replaceable></command></screen>
     <para>
      or
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg install <replaceable>rpm1 rpm2</replaceable></command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>pkg rm/remove</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Removes individual packages from the active snapshot using the
      <command>zypper remove</command> command. This command can also be used
      to remove PTF RPM files.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg remove <replaceable>package_name</replaceable></command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>pkg up/update</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Updates individual packages from the active snapshot using the
      <command>zypper update</command> command. Only packages that are part of
      the snapshot of the base file system can be updated.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg remove <replaceable>package_name</replaceable></command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>up/update</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If there are new updates available, a new snapshot is created and
      <command>zypper up/update</command> updates the snapshot.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update up</command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>dup</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If there are new updates available, a new snapshot is created and
      <command>zypper dup –no-allow-vendor-change</command> updates the
      snapshot. The snapshot is activated afterwards and becomes the new root
      file system after reboot.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update dup</command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>patch</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If there are new updates available, a new snapshot is created and
      <command>zypper patch</command> updates the snapshot.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update patch</command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>rollback</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This sets the default subvolume. On systems with a read-write file system
      <command>snapper rollback</command> is called. On a read-only file system
      and without any argument, the current system is set to a new default root
      file system. If you specify a number, that snapshot is used as the
      default root file system. On a read-only file system, it does not create
      any additional snapshots.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update rollback <replaceable>snapshot_number</replaceable></command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>grub.cfg</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This creates a new GRUB2 configuration. Sometimes it is necessary to
      adjust the boot configuration, for example adding additional kernel
      parameters. Edit <replaceable>/etc/default/grub</replaceable>, run
      <command>transactional-update grub.cfg</command>, and then reboot to
      activate the change. You must immediately reboot, or the new GRUB2
      configuration will be overwritten with the default by the next
      transactional-update.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update grub.cfg</command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>reboot</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This parameter triggers a reboot after the action is completed.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update <replaceable>dup</replaceable> reboot</command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>--help</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This prints a help screen with options and subcommands.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update --help</command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="sec-rollback-procedure">
 <title>System rollback</title>
 <para>
 GRUB 2 enables to boot from btrfs snapshots and thus allows you to use any older functional snapshot in case the new snapshot is corrupted.
 </para>
 <para>
 When booting a snapshot, the parts of the file system included in the snapshot are mounted read-only; all other file systems and parts that are excluded from snapshots are mounted read-write and can be modified.
 </para>
 <tip>
   <title>Rolling back to a specific installation state</title>
   <para>
    An initial bootable
    snapshot is created at the end of the initial system installation. You can
    go back to that state at any time by booting this snapshot. The snapshot
    can be identified by the description <literal>after installation</literal>.
   </para>
   </tip>
   <para>
   Before a rollback is performed, a snapshot of the running file system is created. The description references the ID of the snapshot that was restored in the rollback.
   </para>
   <para>
    Snapshots created by rollbacks receive the value <literal>number</literal>
    for the <literal>Cleanup</literal> attribute. The rollback snapshots are
    therefore automatically deleted when the set number of snapshots is reached.
    If the snapshot contains important data, extract the data from the snapshot
    before it is removed.
   </para>
   <para>
   The following procedure describes how you can perform a rollback:
   </para>
   <procedure>
   <step>
   <para>
   Reboot your system and select <literal>Start bootloader from a read-only snapshot</literal>
   </para>
   </step>
   <step>
   <para>
   Choose a snapshot to boot. The snapshots are sorted according to the date of creation, the latest being the top one.
   </para>
   </step>
   <step>
   <para>
   Log in to your system and check whether everything works as expected. Bear in mind that the snapshot directories are read-only, so you cannot write into them. Data written to directories excluded from the snapshots will stay untouched.
   </para>
   </step>
   <step>
   <para>
   If the snapshot you booted into is not suitable for rollback, reboot your system and choose another one.
   </para>
   <para>
   If the snapshot works as expected, you can perform rollback by running the following command:
   </para>
   <screen>
   &prompt.root; <command>transactional-update rollback</command>
   </screen>
   <para>
   And reboot afterwards.
   </para>
   </step>
   </procedure>
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="sec-automatic-updates">
 <title>Managing automatic transactional updates</title>
 <para>
      Automatic updates are controlled by a <command>systemd.timer</command> 
      that runs once per day. This applies all updates, and informs 
      <command>rebootmgrd</command> that the machine should be rebooted. You may
      adjust the time when the update runs, see systemd.timer(5). To adjust the
      maintenance window, which is when <command>rebootmgrd</command> reboots the
      system, see rebootmgrd(8).
  </para>
  <para>
   You can disable automatic transactional updates with this command:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.root;<command>systemctl --now disable transactional-update.timer</command></screen>
 
 </section>
 
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="sec-snapshots">
 <title>Snapshots</title>
 <warning>
 <title>Snapshots are mandatory</title>
 <para>
 As snapshots are crucial for &slema; correct functioning, do not disable the feature and ensure that the root partition is big enough to store the snapshots.
 </para>
 </warning>
 <para>
 When a snapshot is created, both the snapshot and the original point to the same blocks in the file system. So, initially a snapshot does not occupy additional disk space. If data in the original file system is modified, changed data blocks are copied while the old data blocks are kept for the snapshot.
 </para>
 <para>
 Snapshots always reside on the same partition or subvolume on which the snapshot has been taken. It is not possible to store snapshots on a different partition or subvolume. As a result, partitions containing snapshots need to be larger than partitions not containing snapshots. The exact amount depends strongly on the number of snapshots you keep and the amount of data modifications. As a rule of thumb, give partitions twice as much space as you normally would. To prevent disks from running out of space, old snapshots are automatically cleaned up. 
 </para>
 
 
 <section xml:id="sec-exclude-directories">
 <title>Directories excluded from snapshots</title>
 <para>
 As some directories store user specific or volatile data, these directories are excluded from snapshots:
 </para>
 <variablelist>
 <varlistentry>
 <term><filename>/home</filename></term>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 Contains user's data. To avoid overwriting this data, this directory is excluded from snapshots.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 <varlistentry>
 <term><filename>/root</filename></term>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 <varlistentry>
 <term><filename>/opt</filename></term>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 Third-party products usually get installed to <filename>/opt</filename>. It is excluded to avoid uninstalling these applications on rollbacks.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 <varlistentry>
 <term><filename>/srv</filename></term>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 Contains data for Web and FTP servers. It is excluded to avoid data loss on rollbacks.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 <varlistentry>
 <term><filename>/usr/local</filename></term>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 This directory is used when manually installing software. It is excluded to avoid uninstalling these installations on rollbacks.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 <varlistentry>
 <term><filename>/var</filename></term>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 This directory contains many variable files, including logs, temporary caches, third party products in <filename>/var/opt</filename>, and is the default location for virtual machine images and databases. Therefore this subvolume is created to exclude all of this variable data from snapshots and has Copy-On-Write disabled.
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 <varlistentry>
 <term>the architecture specific <filename>/boot/grub2</filename> directory</term>
 <listitem>
 <para>
 A rollback of the boot loader configuration is not supported. 
 </para>
 </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="sec-snapshot-size">
 <title>Showing exclusive disk space used by snapshots</title>
 <para>
      Snapshots share data, for efficient use of storage space, so using ordinary
      commands like <command>du</command> and <command>df</command> won't measure
      used disk space accurately. When you want to free up disk space on Btrfs 
      with quotas enabled, you need to know how much exclusive disk space is 
      used by each snapshot, rather than shared space. The <command>btrfs</command> command provides a view of space used by 
    snapshots:
</para>
<screen>
&prompt.root;btrfs qgroup show -p /
qgroupid         rfer         excl parent  
--------         ----         ---- ------  
0/5          16.00KiB     16.00KiB ---     
[...]    
0/272         3.09GiB     14.23MiB 1/0     
0/273         3.11GiB    144.00KiB 1/0     
0/274         3.11GiB    112.00KiB 1/0     
0/275         3.11GiB    128.00KiB 1/0     
0/276         3.11GiB     80.00KiB 1/0     
0/277         3.11GiB    256.00KiB 1/0     
0/278         3.11GiB    112.00KiB 1/0     
0/279         3.12GiB     64.00KiB 1/0     
0/280         3.12GiB     16.00KiB 1/0     
1/0           3.33GiB    222.95MiB --- 
</screen>
<para>
    The <literal>qgroupid</literal> column displays the identification number for
    each subvolume, assigning a qgroup level/ID combination.
</para> 
<para>
    The <literal>rfer</literal> column displays the total amount of data 
    referred to in the subvolume.
</para>
<para>
    The <literal>excl</literal> column displays the exclusive data in each
    subvolume. 
</para>
<para>
    The <literal>parent</literal> column shows the parent qgroup of the subvolumes.
</para>
<para>    
    The final item, <literal>1/0</literal>, shows the totals for the parent 
    qgroup. In the above example, 222.95 MiB will be freed if all subvolumes
    are removed. Run the following command to see which snapshots are associated
    with each subvolume:
</para>
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="sec-snapshot-cleanup">
 <title>Automatic snapshot clean-up</title>
 <para>
   Snapshots occupy disk space and over time the amount of disk space occupied
   by the snapshots may become large. To prevent disks from running out of
   space, &slema; offers algorithms to automatically delete old snapshots.
  </para>

  <para>
   In addition to that, you can optionally specify a disk space quota, defining
   the maximum amount of disk space the snapshots may occupy. It is also
   possible to automatically delete pre and post snapshots pairs that do not
   differ.
  </para>
  
  <para>
   The default setup (<literal>root</literal>) is configured to do clean-up
   for numbered snapshots and empty pre and post snapshot pairs. Quota support
   is enabled&mdash;snapshots may not occupy more than 50% of the available
   disk space of the root partition. Timeline snapshots are disabled by
   default, therefore the timeline clean-up algorithm is also disabled.
  </para>
 <section xml:id="sec-numbered-cleanup">
  <title>Cleaning up numbered snapshots</title>
   <para>
    Cleaning up numbered snapshots&mdash;administration plus installation
    snapshot pairs&mdash;is controlled by the following parameters of a Snapper
    configuration.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>NUMBER_CLEANUP</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Enables or disables clean-up of installation and admin snapshot pairs.
       If enabled, snapshot pairs are deleted when the total snapshot count
       exceeds a number specified with <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT</literal> and/or
       <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT</literal> <emphasis>and</emphasis> an
       age specified with <literal>NUMBER_MIN_AGE</literal>. Valid values:
       <literal>yes</literal> (enable), <literal>no</literal> (disable).
      </para>
      <para>
       The default value is <literal>"yes"</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
       Example command to change or set:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> set-config "NUMBER_CLEANUP=no"</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>NUMBER_LIMIT</literal> /
      <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Defines how many regular and/or important installation and
       administration snapshot pairs to keep. Ignored if
       <literal>NUMBER_CLEANUP</literal> is set to
       <literal>"no"</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
       The default value is <literal>"2-10"</literal> for
       <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT</literal> and <literal>"4-10"</literal>
       for <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT</literal>. The cleaning
       algorithms delete snapshots above the specified maximum value,
       without taking the snapshot and file system space into
       account. The algorithms also delete snapshots above the minimum
       value until the limits for the snapshot and file system are
       reached.
      </para>
      <para>
       Example command to change or set:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> set-config "NUMBER_LIMIT=10"</screen>
      <important>
       <title>Ranged compared to constant values</title>
       <para>
        In case quota support is enabled (see
        <xref
        linkend="sec-snapper-clean-up-quota"/>) the limit needs
        to be specified as a minimum-maximum range, for example
        <literal>2-10</literal>. If quota support is disabled, a constant
        value, for example <literal>10</literal>, needs to be provided,
        otherwise cleaning-up will fail with an error.
       </para>
      </important>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>NUMBER_MIN_AGE</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Defines the minimum age in seconds a snapshot must have before it can
       automatically be deleted. Snapshots younger than the value specified
       here will not be deleted, regardless of how many exist.
      </para>
      <para>
       The default value is <literal>"1800"</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
       Example command to change or set:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> set-config "NUMBER_MIN_AGE=864000"</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <note>
    <title>Limit and age</title>
    <para>
     <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT</literal>, <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT</literal>
     and <literal>NUMBER_MIN_AGE</literal> are always evaluated. Snapshots are
     only deleted when <emphasis>all</emphasis> conditions are met.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you always want to keep the number of snapshots defined with
     <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT*</literal> regardless of their age, set
     <literal>NUMBER_MIN_AGE</literal> to <literal>0</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The following example shows a configuration to keep the last 10 important
     and regular snapshots regardless of age:
    </para>
<screen>NUMBER_CLEANUP=yes
NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT=10
NUMBER_LIMIT=10
NUMBER_MIN_AGE=0</screen>
    <para>
     On the other hand, if you do not want to keep snapshots beyond a certain
     age, set <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT*</literal> to <literal>0</literal> and
     provide the age with <literal>NUMBER_MIN_AGE</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The following example shows a configuration to only keep snapshots younger
     than ten days:
    </para>
<screen>NUMBER_CLEANUP=yes
NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT=0
NUMBER_LIMIT=0
NUMBER_MIN_AGE=864000</screen>
   </note>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="sec-snapper-clean-up-timeline">
   <title>Cleaning up timeline snapshots</title>
   <para>
    Cleaning up timeline snapshots is controlled by the following
    parameters of a Snapper configuration.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>TIMELINE_CLEANUP</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Enables or disables clean-up of timeline snapshots. If enabled,
       snapshots are deleted when the total snapshot count exceeds a number
       specified with <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_*</literal>
       <emphasis>and</emphasis> an age specified with
       <literal>TIMELINE_MIN_AGE</literal>. Valid values:
       <literal>yes</literal>, <literal>no</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
       The default value is <literal>"yes"</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
       Example command to change or set:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> set-config "TIMELINE_CLEANUP=yes"</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_DAILY</literal>,
      <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_HOURLY</literal>,
      <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_MONTHLY</literal>,
      <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_WEEKLY</literal>,
      <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_YEARLY</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Number of snapshots to keep for hour, day, month, week, and year.
      </para>
      <para>
       The default value for each entry is <literal>"10"</literal>, except for
       <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_WEEKLY</literal>, which is set to
       <literal>"0"</literal> by default.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>TIMELINE_MIN_AGE</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Defines the minimum age in seconds a snapshot must have before it can
       automatically be deleted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The default value is <literal>"1800"</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <example xml:id="ex-snapper-config-timeline">
    <title>Example timeline configuration</title>
<screen>TIMELINE_CLEANUP="yes"
TIMELINE_CREATE="yes"
TIMELINE_LIMIT_DAILY="7"
TIMELINE_LIMIT_HOURLY="24"
TIMELINE_LIMIT_MONTHLY="12"
TIMELINE_LIMIT_WEEKLY="4"
TIMELINE_LIMIT_YEARLY="2"
TIMELINE_MIN_AGE="1800"</screen>
    <para>
     This example configuration enables hourly snapshots which are
     automatically cleaned up. <literal>TIMELINE_MIN_AGE</literal> and
     <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_*</literal> are always both evaluated. In this
     example, the minimum age of a snapshot before it can be deleted is set to
     30 minutes (1800 seconds). Since we create hourly snapshots, this ensures
     that only the latest snapshots are kept. If
     <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_DAILY</literal> is set to not zero, this means
     that the first snapshot of the day is kept, too.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
     <title>Snapshots to be kept</title>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Hourly: The last 24 snapshots that have been made.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Daily: The first daily snapshot that has been made is kept from the last
       seven days.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Monthly: The first snapshot made on the last day of the month is kept
       for the last twelve months.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Weekly: The first snapshot made on the last day of the week is kept from
       the last four weeks.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Yearly: The first snapshot made on the last day of the year is kept for
       the last two years.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </example>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-snapper-clean-up-empty">
   <title>Cleaning up snapshot pairs that do not differ</title>
   <para>
    Whenever you run any transactional-update, a pre snapshot is created on start-up and
    a post snapshot is created when exiting. In case you have not made any
    changes there will be no difference between the pre and post snapshots.
    Such <quote>empty</quote> snapshot pairs can be automatically be deleted by
    setting the following parameters in a Snapper configuration:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>EMPTY_PRE_POST_CLEANUP</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If set to <literal>yes</literal>, pre and post snapshot pairs that do
       not differ will be deleted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The default value is <literal>"yes"</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>EMPTY_PRE_POST_MIN_AGE</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Defines the minimum age in seconds a pre and post snapshot pair that
       does not differ must have before it can automatically be deleted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The default value is <literal>"1800"</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-snapper-clean-up-manual">
   <title>Cleaning up manually created snapshots</title>
   <para>
    Snapper does not offer custom clean-up algorithms for manually created
    snapshots. However, you can assign the number or timeline clean-up
    algorithm to a manually created snapshot. If you do so, the snapshot will
    join the <quote>clean-up queue</quote> for the algorithm you specified.
    You can specify a clean-up algorithm when creating a snapshot, or by
    modifying an existing snapshot:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper create --description "Test" --cleanup-algorithm number</command>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Creates a stand-alone snapshot (type single) for the default (root)
       configuration and assigns the <literal>number</literal> clean-up
       algorithm.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper modify --cleanup-algorithm "timeline" 25</command>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Modifies the snapshot with the number 25 and assigns the clean-up
       algorithm <literal>timeline</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-snapper-clean-up-quota">
   <title>Adding disk quota support</title>
   <para>
    In addition to the number and/or timeline clean-up algorithms described
    above, Snapper supports quotas. You can define what percentage of the
    available space snapshots are allowed to occupy. This percentage value
    always applies to the Btrfs subvolume defined in the respective Snapper
    configuration.
   </para>
   <para> 
       Btrfs quotas are applied to subvolumes, not to users. You may apply 
       disk space quotas to users and groups (for example, with the 
       <command>quota</command> command) in addition to using Btrfs quotas.
   </para>
   <para>
      Quota support is
    automatically enabled along with Snapper. 
   </para>
   <para>
    Quota support is controlled by the following parameters of a Snapper
    configuration.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>QGROUP</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The Btrfs quota group used by Snapper. If not set, run <command>snapper
       setup-quota</command>. If already set, only change if you are familiar
       with <command>btrfs-qgroup(8)</command>. This value is set with
       <command>snapper setup-quota</command> and should not be changed.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>SPACE_LIMIT</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Limit of space snapshots are allowed to use in fractions of 1 (100%).
       Valid values range from 0 to 1 (0.1 = 10%, 0.2 = 20%, ...).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    The following limitations and guidelines apply:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Quotas are only activated in <emphasis>addition</emphasis> to an existing
      number and/or timeline clean-up algorithm. If no clean-up algorithm is
      active, quota restrictions are not applied.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      With quota support enabled, Snapper will perform two clean-up runs if
      required. The first run will apply the rules specified for number and
      timeline snapshots. Only if the quota is exceeded after this run, the
      quota-specific rules will be applied in a second run.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Even if quota support is enabled, Snapper will always keep the number of
      snapshots specified with the <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT*</literal> and
      <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT*</literal> values, even if the quota will be
      exceeded. It is therefore recommended to specify ranged values
      (<literal><replaceable>MIN</replaceable>-<replaceable>MAX</replaceable></literal>)
      for <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT*</literal> and
      <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT*</literal> to ensure the quota can be applied.
     </para>
     <para>
      If, for example, <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT=5-20</literal> is set, Snapper
      will perform a first clean-up run and reduce the number of regular
      numbered snapshots to 20. In case these 20 snapshots exceed the
      quota, Snapper will delete the oldest ones in a second run until the
      quota is met. A minimum of five snapshots will always be kept, regardless
      of the amount of space they occupy.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  
 </section>
 
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="sec-health-checker">
 <title>Health checker</title>
 <para>
 TBD
 </para>
 </section>
</article>
