<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE"> 
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> 
 %entities;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:novdoc-profile.xsl" type="text/xml" title="Profiling step"?>
<chapter xml:base="art_gnome_quick.xml" id="art.gnomequick">
 <title>&gnomequick;</title>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   &productname; provides the tools required by Linux&ast; users for their
   daily activities. It comes with an easy-to-use graphical environment, the
   GNOME&ast; desktop, that communicates with the underlying Linux system to
   let you access and manage files, folders, and programs. &productname;
   provides an integrated suite of applications for a wide range of office,
   multimedia, and Internet activities. It also contains the LibreOffice
   suite which enables editing and saving of files in a variety of formats.
   The office suite is available for several operating systems, meaning you
   can use the same data across different computing platforms.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomequick.start">
  <title>Getting Started</title>

  <para>
   When you start your system, you are usually brought to a login screen.
   Clicking the icon with the stylized little man in the top right-hand
   corner of the screen opens different accessibility settings. You can, for
   example, increase the contrast, switch on a screen keyboard or enlarge
   the font. To activate one of the functions, you must only right-click
   beside the slide switch. An illuminated blue <guimenu>i</guimenu> marks a
   currently active function.
  </para>

  <para>
   Click your name in the middle of the login screen, enter your password
   and click <guimenu>Login</guimenu>. If someone else installed your
   system, ask your system administrator for your user name and password.
   You do not need to select or enter your name and password if you selected
   the automatic login option during installation. Either way, the GNOME
   desktop will appear.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomequick.gnome.overview">
  <title>The GNOME Desktop</title>

  <para>
   The background image takes up most of the GNOME desktop, which is
   initially empty. You will see a narrow black bar on the top edge of the
   screen. This so-called panel allows you to access all functions and
   applications. Specifically, it has the following elements:
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="gnome_desktop.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="gnome_desktop.png" width="73%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Time, calendar and schedule planner:</title>
   <para>
    The current time is ticking in the middle. When you click it, a small
    calendar appears which lists all pending appointments and events on the
    right hand side. You can call up the <guimenu>Time and Date
    Settings</guimenu> via the relevant buttons or start the calendar
    application directly (<guimenu>Open calendar</guimenu>).
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Volume:</title>
   <para>
    The icon with the loudspeaker represents loudness. The more semicircles
    you can see, the louder your loudspeaker becomes. You can adjust the
    volume by clicking the icon and dragging the top slide bar to the left
    or the right while pressing down the mouse button. To silence the sound,
    push the control all the way to the left. The loudspeaker icon will then
    receive a small cross. You can access additional audio playback settings
    by selecting the icon with the screwdriver and wrench and clicking
    <guimenu>Audio</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>User menu:</title>
   <para>
    If you click the power icon in the top right-hand corner, a menu appears
    from which you can manage your computer. You can adjust the screen
    brightness via the second controller from the top. You can access the
    system settings by clicking the symbol with the screwdriver and wrench
    on the bottom left-hand side of the screen. By clicking the lock, you
    can lock the screen for the duration of your lunch break. Clicking the
    bottom right icon allows you to shut down or restart your computer. To
    log out, click your username and select <guimenu>Logout</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Activities:</title>
   <para>
    Clicking <guimenu>Activities</guimenu> on the top left corner of the
    screen takes you to the so-called activities overview where you start
    programs and manage those already running. You also reach this view by
    placing the mouse pointer on the top left corner of the screen or
    pressing the <keycap>Windows</keycap> key (also called the
    <keycap>Super</keycap> key). You return to the normal view by clicking
    <guimenu>Activities</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Notifications panel:</title>
   <para>
    Whenever you insert a flash drive, finish downloading or some other
    important thing happens in your system, a corresponding message appears
    on the bottom edge of the screen. Some of these messages disappear
    quickly by themselves, others offer equally suitable actions. You can,
    for example, eject an inserted data CD immediately or open your content
    in a new window. If you do not wish to do any of the actions, simply
    click the title of the message and it will then disappear from the
    bottom edge. You can retrieve messages that have been closed or that
    have disappeared too early by pressing <keycombo>
    <keycap>Windows</keycap> <keycap>M</keycap> </keycombo>. This brings you
    to the notifications panel. This panel displays all of the messages that
    you have not responded to yet or that still apply. To display the
    relevant message, click the corresponding symbol. You can close the
    notification panel by pressing <keycombo> <keycap>Windows</keycap>
    <keycap>M</keycap> </keycombo>.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomequick.shell.start">
   <title>Start Programs</title>
   <para>
    To start an application, first switch to the activities view (click
    <guimenu>Activities</guimenu> or press the <keycap>Windows</keycap>
    key). You now have three options:
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gnome_shell_start.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gnome_shell_start.png" width="73%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
   <formalpara>
    <title>About the Dash (Favorites bar):</title>
    <para>
     Either click the program icon in the bar on the left edge of the
     screen, the so-called Dash (sometimes also inconsistently called a
     Dock). If you hover over one of the icons with the mouse pointer, GNOME
     will tell you the name of the pertaining application.
    </para>
   </formalpara>
   <formalpara>
    <title>Via the applications view:</title>
    <para>
     If the required program is missing from the Dash, click the icon at the
     bottom of the Dash (the one with nine small white triangles). GNOME
     will then show all the installed programs. You can scroll to the bottom
     of the list by clicking one of the dots on the right-hand side of the
     screen. To display your last used applications, click
     <guimenu>Common</guimenu> at the bottom of the screen. The
     <guimenu>All</guimenu> button displays all of the installed
     applications.
    </para>
   </formalpara>
   <formalpara>
    <title>Via the search box:</title>
    <para>
     You can use the search box at the top of the screen if you cannot find
     what you are looking for, or if you need to do something quickly. As
     soon as you enter a term there, GNOME will show all the matching
     applications and system settings. By the way, you do not have to click
     the search box first, you can just simply begin typing directly.
    </para>
   </formalpara>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomequick.shell.window.management">
   <title>Manage Window</title>
   <para>
    After you start an application, GNOME automatically switches back to the
    workplace. The name of the program and its icon appear in the panel. You
    can end the application by clicking it. The <guimenu>X</guimenu> on the
    title bar of its window does the same thing.
   </para>
   <procedure id="proc.gnomequick.window.max">
    <title>Maximize Window</title>
    <para>
     To enlarge a window to the screen size, proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Bring the mouse to the title bar of the window (with the program name)
      and hold and press the left mouse button.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Pull the window on the top edge against the panel.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      As soon as GNOME turns the screen blue, let the mouse button go.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    To minimize the window again, follow the same steps but vice versa:
    Using the mouse, pull away the title bar of the window from the top
    edge. Alternatively, you can also right-click the title bar. A menu with
    the corresponding options then appears. But beware: In contrast to other
    operating systems, <guimenu>Minimizing</guimenu> the window will bring
    you to the <guimenu>Activities</guimenu> view.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can switch quickly between open windows via the <keycombo>
    <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>Tab</keycap> </keycombo>shortcut.
    <guimenu>Activities</guimenu> view gives an overview of all currently
    open windows. Clicking one of the windows there brings it into the
    foreground, the <guimenu>X</guimenu> symbol closes it.
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gnome_shell_windows.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gnome_shell_windows.png" width="73%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomequick.shell.dash">
   <title>Working with Dash</title>
   <para>
    The small Dash in the <guimenu>Activities</guimenu> view not only keeps
    especially commonly used programs ready, but it can do even more: As
    soon as you start an application, an icon appears for it in the Dash. A
    light shadow underneath its icon indicates that the application is
    running and (at least) one window is open.
   </para>
   <para>
    Right-clicking an icon opens a small menu which offers different actions
    depending on the associated program. With <guimenu>Add to
    Favorites</guimenu>, you can place the application icon permanently in
    Dash. To remove a program icon from Dash, select <guimenu>Remove from
    Favorites</guimenu>. If you wish to rearrange an icon in the dock, hold
    the left mouse button pressed above it and then drag it to its new
    position.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomequick.virtdesk">
   <title>Using Virtual Desktops</title>
   <para>
    GNOME allows you to organize your program window into several virtual
    desktops. If you often run a lot of programs simultaneously, this
    minimizes the number of windows to arrange on your screen. You might,
    for example, use one desktop for e-mails and the calendar and another
    for word processing and graphics applications.
   </para>
   <procedure id="proc.gnomequick.virtdesk.move">
    <title>Move an Application to Another Virtual Desktop</title>
    <para>
     To move an open window to another virtual desktop, proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="gnome_shell_virtdesk.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="gnome_shell_virtdesk.png" width="73%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Open the <guimenu>Activities</guimenu> view.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Bring the mouse pointer to the corresponding window and drag it by
      pressing and holding the left mouse button on the right edge of the
      screen.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      A bar with all existing virtual desktops now opens there. Drag and
      drop the window to the desktop where you would like it to be. In
      GNOME, there is always a blank window that contains only the
      background image of your workspace. If you drag the window, GNOME
      automatically creates another desktop.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Release the left mouse button.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure id="proc.gnomequick.virtdesk.change">
    <title>Switch Virtual Desktops</title>
    <para>
     You can switch between all existing desktops via <keycombo>
     <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>Arrow
     up</keycap> </keycombo> and <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
     <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>Arrow down</keycap> </keycombo>.
     Alternatively, you can also pull up the activities view:
    </para>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Open the activities view (for example, with the
      <keycap>Windows</keycap> key).
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click the desired virtual desktop on the bar on the right-hand side of
      the screen. GNOME now shows all the windows that are there.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click the virtual desktop once again to finally switch to it.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure id="proc.gnomequick.virtdesk.menu">
    <title>Show Window on All Desktops</title>
    <para>
     You can also show a currently open application on all virtual desktops:
    </para>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Right-click the title bar of the application.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Always on the Visible Desktop</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      You can also very quickly move the window to an entirely specific
      desktop via the small menu. To do this, select <guimenu>Move to
      Another Desktop</guimenu> and then the corresponding desktop. The
      corresponding menu item will only appear if there is at least one
      other virtual desktop.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomequick.startprog.runappl">
  <title>&quot;Perform Application&quot; dialog box</title>

  <para>
   Press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo>
   to open a small dialog box. Enter a command, for example
   <command>libreoffice</command>, and press <keycap function="enter"/> to
   start the application. The command to start the application is often (but
   not always) the application name written in lowercase.
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="gnome_shell_runapplication.png" width="70%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="gnome_shell_runapplication.png" width="70%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomequick.nautilus">
  <title>Manage Files, Folders and Media</title>

  <para>
   Use the File Manager to create and view folders and documents, run
   scripts, and create CDs of your data. To open the file manager, switch to
   the Activities view (with the <keycap>Windows</keycap> key for example)
   and click the icon with the filing cabinet in Dash. A new window appears,
   displaying the content of your home directory.
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="nautilus.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="nautilus.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para>
   The elements of the Files window include the following:
  </para>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Path bar</title>
   <para>
    Lets you find files and folders.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Sidebar</title>
   <para>
    Lets you navigate or display information about the selected file or
    folder.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>View pane</title>
   <para>
    Displays folders and files.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Buttons</title>
   <para>
    There are a number of buttons in the top right-hand corner. Use the
    magnifying glass to activate the search function. You can use the icons
    to the right to switch between different display options: The icon with
    the lines displays the items as a list in the view window. The icon with
    the small dotted box displays the items as icons. Using the menu with
    the arrow, you can zoom in or out on the view. The button with the
    cogwheel brings you to another menu with additional options. For
    example, you can create a new folder here.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomequick.mediahandling">
   <title>Handling Media</title>
   <para>
    What happens exactly if you insert a CD or a DVD into the drive or
    connect a device (such as a USB stick or a removable disk) depends on
    the content of the medium. In the simplest case, GNOME automatically
    opens file manager which, in turn, displays the content of the media.
    You have several options available in terms of action. A message with a
    corresponding selection appears on the bottom edge. You must then decide
    whether you would like to open a DVD with a media player or in a file
    manager window.
   </para>
   <para>
    If GNOME does not respond, you must start the file manager manually. The
    File window lists all connected or inserted data carriers in the sidebar
    in the <guimenu>Devices</guimenu> area.By clicking the arrow icon on the
    right adjacent to its name you can eject the CD or the DVD or the
    connected USB stick.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomequick.burn">
   <title>Creating a CD or DVD</title>
   <para>
    If your system has a CD or DVD burner, use the File manager to burn CDs
    and DVDs.
   </para>
   <procedure id="proc.gnomequick.nautilus.burn">
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Insert an empty data medium and open it in the CD/DVD creator. GNOME
      then opens a new File window.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Copy the desired files and folders for the CD or DVD into this window.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="cd_burner.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="cd_burner.png" width="75%" format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To write data to the CD or DVD, click <guimenu>Write to
      CD/DVD</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Change the corresponding data in the <guimenu>CD/DVD Creator</guimenu>
      window via <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> or accept the default
      settings. Then click <guimenu>Burn</guimenu>. Now there is no turning
      back: GNOME will write the files onto the disk. This could take a few
      minutes, depending on the amount of data being burned and the speed of
      your burner.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    To burn data and audio CDs, you can also use the more extensive burning
    program Brasero.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomequick.nautilus.archive">
   <title>Creating and Unpacking Archives</title>
   <para>
    If you have files you have not used recently but want to keep on your
    computer, you can compile and compress them in an archive file.
   </para>
   <procedure id="proc.gnomequick.nautilus.archive">
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      In the File manager, right-click the folder you want to archive and
      then select <guimenu>Compress</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="archive.png" width="60%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="archive.png" width="50%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Accept the default archive file name or provide a new name.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select a file name extension from the drop-down list beside to the
      right. At the same time, you also determine the compression method.
      Use <filename>.zip</filename> if you would like to forward the archive
      to other people or protect it with a password. In Linux the
      <filename>.tar.gz</filename> format is also widely used.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Enter the location where you want to save the archive file.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      If you have decided to use a <filename>.zip</filename> file, you can
      also click <guimenu>Expanded Settings</guimenu> and enter a password
      there. However, please remember: If you forget it, you can no longer
      access the content of the archive.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Then click <guimenu>Create</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    To unpack an archive created in this way, right-click the file and
    select <guimenu>Unpack here</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomequick.nautilus.bookmarks">
   <title>Using Bookmarks</title>
   <para>
    Use the File manager bookmarks feature to highlight your favorite
    folders. A matching entry then appears for quick access in the side
    pane.
   </para>
   <procedure id="proc.gnomequick.nautilus.bookmarks">
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Switch (by double-clicking) to the folder that you want to create a
      bookmark for.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click cogwheel icon and select <guimenu>Create bookmark for this
      location</guimenu>. The bookmark is added to the list. The folder name
      is used as the bookmark name.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To select an item for your bookmarks list, click the required bookmark
      in the File manager underneath
      <guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu>.<guimenu></guimenu>
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    You can also organize your bookmark list by clicking
    <guimenu>Files</guimenu> in the panel at the top of the screen and
    selecting <menuchoice><guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu></menuchoice> from the
    drop-down menu.
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="bookmarks_edit.png" width="55%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="bookmarks_edit.png" width="45%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
   <para>
    To change the order of your bookmarks, click a bookmark shown in the
    <guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu> dialog box and drag it to the desired
    location.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomequick.custom">
  <title>Customizing your Work Environment</title>

  <para>
   You can find more precise settings to adjust the overall appearance and
   behavior of your desktop in System Settings. There you can also change
   keyboard and mouse configurations, regional and language settings,
   parameters for your Internet and network usage, and more.
  </para>

  <para>
   To call the system settings, select the power icon on the right-hand side
   of the (upper) panel and then click the icon with the screwdriver and
   wrench in the pop-up window.
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="controlcenter.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="controlcenter.png" width="55%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomequick.custom.deskback">
   <title>Changing the Desktop Background</title>
   <procedure id="proc.gnomequick.custom.deskback">
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Then click <guimenu>Background</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="desktop_background.png" width="55%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="desktop_background.png" width="45%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click the current background image on the left-hand side.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To select a background image from the pre-installed images, just click
      the image and then click <guimenu>Select</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To add your own image, click <guimenu>Images</guimenu>. GNOME displays
      all of the images from your <guimenu>Image</guimenu> folder that could
      be used as a background image. Images whose dimensions are too small
      or that appear in an unusual file format will not be available here.
      Click an image and then click <guimenu>Select</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To display a colored background, click <guimenu>Colors</guimenu>,
      select the color you want and then click <guimenu>Select</guimenu> at
      the bottom right-hand corner of the window.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      You can return to all system settings using the button in the very top
      left-hand corner of the window.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomequick.firefox">
  <title>Browsing the Internet with Firefox</title>

  <para>
   Firefox&ast; is one of the most popular web browsers. It works like all
   other browsers, but offers additional functions such as tools for
   security and data protection.
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="firefox.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="firefox.png" width="59%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para>
   To start Firefox, switch to the activities view (such as via the
   <keycap>Windows</keycap> key) and click the icon with the globe and the
   fox in Dash.
  </para>

  <para>
   Firefox awaits with all modern web technologies, such as use of tabs,
   pop-up blockers and download and image management. Its easy access to
   different search engines helps you find the information you need. Enter
   an Internet address (URL) in the address bar to start browsing.
  </para>

  <para>
   To open a new empty tab in Firefox, press <keycombo>
   <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>T</keycap> </keycombo> or click the
   <quote>&plus;</quote> sign beside the last tab. Type a new Internet
   address to browse. To open the page behind a link in a new tab,
   middle-click the link. You can change the order of the tabs by dragging
   and dropping them to another position. Right-clicking the tab displays a
   small menu. You can reload the content of a specific tab or all existing
   tabs, or close a single tab or all tabs, for example.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomequick.firefox.search">
   <title>Finding Information</title>
   <procedure id="proc.gnomequick.firefox.search">
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      To start a Web search type the keywords in the integrated search box
      on the right of the address bar, then press
      <keycap function="enter"/>. Firefox will display the results in the
      active tab.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      If you want to use a specific search engine, click the icon with the
      small down arrow in the input field of the search bar.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Click the search engine you want, type in the search word and then
      press <keycap function="enter"/> to start the search.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    To search for words in the current website, press <keycombo>
    <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>F</keycap> </keycombo>. Enter your
    keywords in the <guimenu>search bar</guimenu> now shown on the bottom of
    the window. Use the buttons to the right of the search box to switch the
    search direction or to highlight all results in the text (via
    <guimenu>Highlight</guimenu>).
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomequick.firefox.download">
   <title>Downloading Files from the Web</title>
   <para>
    If you download a file with Firefox, the Firefox download manager starts
    automatically. It then saves the file in the folder previously set in
    the Firefox settings. By default, it uses the
    <filename>Downloads</filename> folder in your home directory. To find
    out which files Firefox has already downloaded and how long this process
    took, click the down arrow to the right of the search box.
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="firefox_downloads.png" width="50%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="firefox_downloads.png" width="45%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomequick.firefox.conf">
   <title>Configuring Preferences</title>
   <para>
    To change the default download folder or to activate or modify the
    pop-up blocking feature, click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="firefox_preferences.png" width="55%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="firefox_preferences.png" width="45%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
   <para>
    You can configure advanced settings here, such as the appearance, the
    language, data protection and the tab options. Click the icons and set
    the options on each page according to your preferences. To apply the
    changes click <guimenu>Close</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomequick.gnomekeyring">
  <title>Managing Passwords</title>

  <para>
   GNOME allows you to store your passwords and encryption keys in a
   <emphasis>Keying</emphasis>. This is particularly useful if you want to
   store passwords for different websites.
  </para>

  <para>
   To create a new key ring, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap>
     </keycombo> and enter <command>seahorse</command>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>New</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Password Key Ring</guimenu> and continue with
     <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Enter a name for the key ring and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. A new
     window appears.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Enter a password for the key ring, confirm the password in the input
     field at the bottom and click <guimenu>Continue</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   You can create as many key rings as you like. For example, you can create
   one for private use and a second one for business. To store passwords in
   your key ring, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap>
     </keycombo> and enter <command>seahorse</command>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>New</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Save password</guimenu> and proceed with
     <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Select your <guimenu>key ring</guimenu>, enter a description and your
     password.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     When finished, click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomequick.mail">
  <title>E-mail and Calendar</title>

  <para>
   To read and manage your mails, contacts, appointments, and tasks,
   &productname;contains the program Evolution&trade;, which allows you to
   conveniently save, organize, and call up your personal information.
  </para>

  <para>
   With its extensive support for current communication and data interchange
   standards, Evolution can be used with existing corporate networks and
   applications, including Microsoft&ast; Exchange.
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="evolution.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="evolution.png" width="55%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para>
   To start Evolution, switch to the activities view (for example, via the
   <keycap>Windows</keycap> key) and click the letter icon.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you are starting Evolution for the first time, you will be asked to
   answer a series of questions. The queried information is needed to set up
   your e-mail account and helps you import e-mail messages from your old
   e-mail client. It then shows you how many new messages you have and lists
   upcoming appointments and tasks, as well as the current weather and news
   from news feeds. The calendar, address book and e-mail tools are
   available on the toolbar on the left side of the program window.
  </para>

  <para>
   Press <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>N</keycap>
   </keycombo> to open a new item in the area of Evolution you are working
   in. This creates a new message in the <guimenu>E-mail</guimenu> area.
   Pressing <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>N</keycap>
   </keycombo> in the address book creates a new contact card and a new
   appointment in the calendar.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you would like additional information about Evolution, go to
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>Help</guimenu> <guimenu>Content</guimenu>
   </menuchoice> in the main Evolution menu.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomequick.empathy">
  <title>Instant Messaging with Empathy</title>

  <para>
   Empathy is a multi-protocol Instant Messaging (IM) client. It is
   compatible with AOL&ast; Instant Messenger (AIM), Google Talk,
   GroupWise&reg; Messenger, ICQ, IRC, MSN Messenger, Jabber/XMPP,
   Yahoo!&ast; and other networks.
  </para>

  <para>
   With Empathy, you can log into multiple accounts on multiple IM networks
   simultaneously. Empathy also supports many features of the various
   networks, such as video chat, file transfer, away messages, and tips.
  </para>

  <para>
   To start Empathy, switch to the activities view (for example, via the
   <keycap>Windows</keycap> key) and click the icon with the speech balloon
   and the blue smiley in the Dash.
  </para>

  <para>
   A startup wizard will appear when you first launch Empathy. It will
   automatically offer you suggestions of other people you can find on the
   network. For this reason, you must populate the name, last name, and
   nickname fields. After you click <guimenu>Connect</guimenu>, Empathy
   displays all the contacts it has found in a new window (<guimenu>Contact
   list</guimenu>).
  </para>

  <para>
   If you want to notify Empathy that an account is for a specific purpose,
   click the plus sign in the <guimenu>Instant message and VoIP
   accounts</guimenu> window. Select the protocol or service you want from
   the drop-down list at the top and enter your login details in the
   relevant fields. Click <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to activate your IM account
   in Empathy.
  </para>

  <para>
   Add your contacts by clicking <guimenu>Empathy</guimenu> in the panel at
   the top of the screen and then select <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Contacts</guimenu> <guimenu>Add contact</guimenu></menuchoice>
   from the pop-up menu. However, you must be online and connected to the
   selected messaging service to add a contact to your list.
  </para>

  <para>
   To start a chat, double-click the desired contact and type your message
   in the lower part of the chat window. Press <keycap function="enter"/> to
   send the message. The upper part of the window displays the messages you
   have sent and received.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomequick.libo">
  <title>Starting &libo;</title>

  <para>
   &libo; offers comprehensive, high-performance office programs, including
   a text processing program, a table calculation application, a program for
   creating presentations, a vector graphic program, and a database
   application. Because LibreOffice is available for a number of operating
   systems, you can use the documents across different operating systems.
  </para>

  <para>
   To start &libo;, switch to the activities view (for example, by pressing
   the <keycap>Windows</keycap> key) and then click the blue document.
   Alternatively, type <command>writer</command> in the search box and press
   <keycap function="enter"/>. To create a new document, click <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>New</guimenu> </menuchoice>, and select
   the document type. To open an existing document, select
   <guimenu>Open</guimenu>, then select the file you want from the file
   system.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomequick.pdf">
  <title>Viewing PDF Files and Other Documents</title>

  <para>
   Documents that need to be shared or printed across different platforms
   are often saved as PDF (Portable Document Format) files. PDF files can be
   created using the LibreOffice suite or other applications. The GNOME PDF
   viewer is called Evince. Evince can be used to view PDFs and many other
   document formats, such as PostScript, JjVu, DVI, and multi-page TIFFs.
  </para>

  <para>
   To start Evince, press <keycombo> <keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2
   </keycap></keycombo> and enter <command>evince</command>.
  </para>

  <procedure id="proc.gnomequick.pdf">
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     To view a PDF file, double-click the file you want.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="evince.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="evince.png" width="55%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Use the navigation icons at the top of the window to navigate through
     the document. If the PDF document contains bookmarks, you can access
     them to the left of the side pane.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomequick.fspot">
  <title>Managing Your Digital Image Collection</title>

  <para>
   Shotwell is a management tool for digital image collections. You can
   assign various category tags to your images. It also offers many
   practical image editing options. For example, you can remove red eye,
   crop an image to size as well as adjust brightness and colors. Shotwell
   supports all important file formats, such as JPEG, PNG, TIFF and various
   manufacturer-specific RAW formats, for example. With Shotwell, you can
   also export photos to your Flickr, Picasa or Facebook account.
  </para>

  <para>
   To access Shotwell, open&nbsp;the activities view (for example, by
   pressing the <guimenu>Windows</guimenu> key) and then click the icon with
   the images in Dash. After you pass through the welcome window by clicking
   <guimenu>OK</guimenu>, Shotwell immediately runs through your image
   folder and automatically packs all the images stored in it into its
   library.
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="shotwell.png" width="85%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="shotwell.png" width="71%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para>
   Shotwell shows thumbnails of the images to the right in the window. As
   soon as you click one of them, you can <guimenu>rotate it</guimenu>,
   re-edit it (<guimenu>enhance it</guimenu>) or <guimenu>publish
   it</guimenu> in an Internet service with the buttons on the lower edge.
   The side bar to the left offers different views of your photo portfolio.
   Provided the photos were stamped with a date, you can limit the display
   to photos from a specific year via <guimenu>Events</guimenu> for example.
  </para>

  <para>
   You import new photos via <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Import from Folder</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Shotwell copies
   these photos to your image folder by default. If you would like to set
   another folder for this, go to <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> </menuchoice> and choose the corresponding
   folder under <guimenu>Import Photos to</guimenu>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomequick.rhythmbox">
  <title>Managing Your Music and Videos</title>

  <para>
   Using &musicplayer;, you can import CDs, manage your digital music
   collection, create playlists with titles from your library, or subscribe
   to, download, and play podcasts. Banshee also has an
   Internet radio plug-in that allows you to listen to audio streams.
  </para>

  <para>
   To open &musicplayer;, switch to the activities view (for example, via
   the <guimenu>Windows</guimenu> key) and click the icon with the speakers.
  </para>

  <para>
   When you start &musicplayer; for the first time, you need to import your
   media to make them available in the library. Click the cogwheel and
   select the <menuchoice> <guimenu>Add music</guimenu></menuchoice> item.
   The main window now displays all of the music files from the directory
   that is selected in the drop-down menu next to <guimenu>Select a location
   that you would like to add to your library</guimenu>. Highlight an item
   and click <guimenu>Add title</guimenu>. Once you have highlighted all
   music items in this way, click <guimenu>Close</guimenu>. The imported
   music will then appear as below:
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="rhythmbox.png" width="87%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="rhythmbox.png" width="75%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para>
   To play a song, click <guimenu>Music</guimenu> on the left-hand side of
   the screen, highlight the <guimenu>Artist</guimenu> and the
   <guimenu>Album</guimenu> that you want and then the song in the list at
   the bottom of the screen. Finally, click <guimenu>Play</guimenu>. You can
   use the same button to stop the song. You can use the other two big
   buttons to play the next or previous song. Use the controller on the
   right-hand side to adjust the volume.
  </para>

  <para>
   Banshee also has an integrated CD player. When you insert a CD, the CD
   title appears in the left panel. Click here. If you want to play a CD,
   highlight the first title and then click <guimenu>Play</guimenu>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomequick.logout">
  <title>Logging Out</title>

  <para>
   Once you have finished your work on the computer, you can log out and
   exit the system. However, you can also restart the system or shut down
   the computer.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomequick.logout.switch">
   <title>Logging out and locking the screen</title>
   <para>
    Click the power icon at the top right of the panel and select one of the
    following options:
   </para>
   <formalpara>
    <title>Log out</title>
    <para>
     By selecting your name and clicking <guimenu>Log out</guimenu>, you are
     logging out of your current session and will be brought back to the
     login screen.
    </para>
   </formalpara>
   <formalpara>
    <title>Lock</title>
    <para>
     Clicking the icon with the lock activates the screensaver. To stop
     this, you must click the screen and drag the mouse upwards while
     keeping the left mouse key pressed down. Enter your password in the
     input field that appears and click <guimenu>Unlock</guimenu>. This
     prevents unauthorized persons from working on or playing around with
     your computer during your absence.
    </para>
   </formalpara>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomequick.logout.restart">
   <title>Restarting or Shutting Down the Computer</title>
   <para>
    You can <guimenu>Shut down</guimenu> or <guimenu>Restart</guimenu> your
    computer by clicking the power icon at the top right of the panel, and
    then clicking again on the power icon at the bottom right-hand corner.
   </para>
   <para>
    Alternatively, you can set your computer to power saving mode. To do
    this, &productname; must have detected and be able to use your
    computer&apos;s power-saving settings. Once this requirement is met, you
    can click the power icon at the top right of the panel and press down
    the <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/></keycombo> key. The power icon
    in the bottom right-hand corner then turns into two bars. When you click
    these, your computer goes into hibernation mode.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomequick.more">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   To learn more about GNOME and GNOME applications, go to
   <ulink url="http://www.gnome.org/"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
