<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<article xml:id="article-openscap"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 version="5.0"
 xml:lang="en"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Hardening &productname; with &openscap;</title>
  <titleabbrev>Hardening &productnameshort; with &openscap;</titleabbrev>
  <info><productname>&productname;</productname><date>
<?dbtimestamp format="B d, Y"?></date>
    <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
      <dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:url>https://bugzilla.suse.com/enter_bug.cgi</dm:url>
        <dm:component>Security</dm:component>
        <dm:product>Documentation</dm:product>
        <dm:assignee>souvik.sarkar@suse.com</dm:assignee>
      </dm:bugtracker>
      <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/doc-unversioned/edit/main/openscap/xml/</dm:editurl>
      <dm:translation>no</dm:translation>
    </dm:docmanager>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        To audit and harden &productname; (&productnameshort;), administrators use the &openscap;
        framework and the <literal>&ssg;</literal> to automate configuration checks, vulnerability
        scanning and compliance tracking. This guide details infrastructure preparation, core
        package installation, policy scanning and automated system remediation using native shell
        scripts or Ansible playbooks.
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <meta name="title" its:translate="yes">Hardening &productnameshort; with &openscap;</meta>
    <meta name="series" its:translate="no">Products &amp; Solutions</meta>
    <meta name="description" its:translate="yes">How to audit and harden &productnameshort; with &openscap; and the &ssg;</meta>
    <meta name="social-descr" its:translate="yes">Harden &productnameshort; with &openscap;</meta>
    <meta name="task" its:translate="no"><phrase>Auditing</phrase><phrase>Compliance</phrase>
    </meta>
    <revhistory xml:id="rh-openscap">
     <revision>
      <date>2026-06-25</date>
      <revdescription>
       <para>
        Removed unsupported SSG profiles.
       </para>
      </revdescription>
     </revision>
      <revision><date>2026-04-27</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>
            Initial release of this document: OpenSCAP content for &productnameshort; &product-ga;.
          </para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </info>
  <important xml:id="openscap-disclaimer">
    <title>Disclaimer</title>
    <para>
      &suse; seeks to provide customers with quick and easy guides that can assist them in
      maintaining security compliance. Implementation of the settings contained within this guide
      without its prior testing in a non-operational environment is highly discouraged. The
      developers of these profiles and documentation have made reasonable efforts to ensure overall
      compliance. They assume no responsibility for its use by other parties, and make no
      guarantee, expressed or implied, about its quality, reliability or any other characteristic.
    </para>
  </important>
  <sect1 xml:id="openscap-whatis">
    <title>What are SCAP and &openscap;?</title>

    <para>
      SCAP stands for <systemitem class="protocol">Security Content Automation
      Protocol</systemitem>. It is a framework of specifications that support automated
      configuration, vulnerability scanning, and policy compliance evaluation of systems deployed
      in an organization. SCAP is maintained by the National Institute of Standards and Technology
      (NIST). This framework standardizes how vulnerabilities and security configurations are
      communicated both to machines and humans.
    </para>

    <para>
      &openscap; is a collection of open source tools that implement the SCAP framework for Linux.
      The suite received the SCAP 1.2 certification by NIST in 2014.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="scap-security-guide-whatis">
    <title>What is the &ssg;?</title>

    <para>
      The <literal>&ssg;</literal> (SSG) is an open source project that provides machine-readable
      security policies for Linux systems. It translates established security benchmarks, such as
      &stig;s from the
      <orgname>Defense Information Systems Agency (DISA)</orgname>
      and
      <orgname>Center for Internet Security (CIS)</orgname>
      benchmarks, into SCAP content that can be automatically applied and verified. The
      <literal>&ssg;</literal> delivers XCCDF checklists, OVAL checks, and ready-to-use remediation
      scripts in the form of Ansible playbooks and Bash scripts.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="openscap-benefits">
    <title>The benefits of using &openscap; and the <literal>&ssg;</literal></title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Automated auditing</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The &openscap; tools, together with the <literal>&ssg;</literal>, can be used for
            auditing your system in an automated way.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Authoritative guidance</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <literal>&ssg;</literal> implements security guidelines recommended by respected
            authorities.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Machine-readable format</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These security guidelines are transformed into a machine-readable format, which then
            can be used by &openscap; and other tools.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="openscap-prepare-infrastructure">
    <title>Preparing your infrastructure before hardening &productnameshort;</title>

    <para>
      Before installation and hardening, you must prepare your IT infrastructure for the
      implementation of the &ssg;. Execute the following sequential steps:
    </para>

    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>
          Create an inventory of the hosts on which the &ssg; will be installed.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Create an inventory of IT and business services that will be in the scope of the
          installation.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Split the inventory into a few groups, considering that the configuration of hosts
          belonging to a group will be identical.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Select the standard or profile you plan to implement. For example, you can use the &disa;
          STIG, the &pcidss; (PCI-DSS) or the &hipaa; (HIPAA).
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          For each group member, create a list of rules and recommendations you plan to implement.
          You should consider the following:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Preconditions necessary for some of the rules
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Configuration parameters for each recommendation, if they exist
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Recommendations to be applied manually
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Recommendations to be applied automatically
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Recommendations to be excluded
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Additional security controls or measures will be implemented to address excluded
              recommendations
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Create a test environment that simulates your environment. Use it as a reference before
          implementing the technology in your real environment. You should consider the following:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The remediation has to be executed more than twice, because:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The recommendations are executed in alphabetical order.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Between some recommendations, there are dependencies.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The operating system needs to be restarted after each pass.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              A 100% hardening is impossible, and you have to specify an acceptable level of risk
              for members of each group.
            </para>
            <note>
              <para>
                The acceptable level is several rules that will show the result <quote>not
                pass</quote> in case of an audit. Document these rules and apply additional
                security controls to compensate for them.
              </para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Use the test environment to test new patches and new updates of SSG.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          In case of an error during the remediation, try the following:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Apply the rule manually.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Exclude the rule using tailoring and use an additional security control instead.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Register a bug, providing details about the SSG version, logs from execution and
              steps performed by you.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Create an implementation plan covering your production environment.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Create backups.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="openscap-installation">
    <title>Installing &openscap; and the <literal>&ssg;</literal> on &productnameshort;</title>

    <para>
      To use the &openscap; tools and the <literal>&ssg;</literal> for hardening your target system
      by scanning and remediating vulnerabilities, install the following core packages:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <package>openscap-utils</package>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <package>scap-security-guide</package>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>zypper install openscap-utils scap-security-guide</command>
</screen>

    <note>
      <para>
        These packages are dependencies for other optional packages discussed below.
      </para>
    </note>

    <para>
      Optionally, install the following packages:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <package>scap-workbench</package>: This package provides the SCAP Workbench graphical
          utility to perform common <systemitem>oscap</systemitem> tasks.
        </para>
        <note>
          <para>
            The <package>scap-workbench</package> package, being a GUI software, is available only
            for desktop installations of &productnameshort;.
          </para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <package>ssg-apply</package>: When used along with SCAP Workbench, this package helps you
          conveniently apply a tailoring file for customized hardening.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>zypper install scap-workbench ssg-apply</command></screen>

    <tip>
      <title>Security best practice for SCAP Workbench</title>
      <para>
        As a security best practice, avoid installing application software such as SCAP Workbench
        on the target system that you plan to harden. Instead, install SCAP Workbench on a client
        machine and apply the hardening on the target system, while maintaining an air gap before
        the target system is connected to a potentially insecure network.
      </para>
    </tip>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="openscap-components">
    <title>What are the key components of the SCAP framework?</title>

    <para>
      SCAP consists of the following important components, which interact with each other:
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Open Vulnerability and Assessment Language (OVAL)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            An XML format for testing the presence of a specific state.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Extensible Configuration Checklist Description Format (XCCDF)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            An XML format that specifies security checklists, benchmarks and configuration
            documentation. The XCCDF file includes a benchmark as a set of different profiles
            related to different groups. Each group is a set of rules that has OVAL definitions.
            Each profile is related to different good practices such as &stiga;, &hipaaa;,
            &pcidssa;, or ANSSI.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Common Platform Enumeration (CPE)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A structured naming scheme to identify information technology systems, platforms and
            software packages. It is maintained by NIST and NDV. The naming scheme consists of the
            following elements:
            <literal>cpe:/<replaceable>part</replaceable>:<replaceable>vendor</replaceable>:<replaceable>product</replaceable>:<replaceable>version</replaceable>:<replaceable>update</replaceable>:<replaceable>edition</replaceable>:<replaceable>language</replaceable></literal>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>DataStreams (DS)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            An XML format that packs different SCAP components (CPE, XCCDF, OVAL) into a single
            file. It can be used to distribute SCAP content over the network. The DataStreams files
            are useful because they include everything you need when you want to harden and audit
            your &suselinux; system.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Common Configuration Enumeration (CCE)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Unique identifiers for security-related system configuration issues.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="openscap-ssg">
    <title>&ssg; content and directories</title>

    <para>
      &suse; ships the SSG toolset in the <package>scap-security-guide</package> package. It
      contains the latest set of security policies for Linux systems. The <literal>&ssg;</literal>
      is maintained upstream in the
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/ComplianceAsCode/">ComplianceAsCode</link> repository.
    </para>

    <para>
      After you have installed the package, the SSG security content and the related files are
      available in your system from the following directories:
    </para>

    <sect2 xml:id="ssg-directories">
      <title>Overview of files and directories</title>
      <variablelist xml:id="ssg-directories-overview">
        <varlistentry>
          <term><filename>/usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/</filename></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Contains the SSG security content. It consists of several
              <xref linkend="openscap-components" xrefstyle="select:title"/>, which are all based
              on XML. All XML files in that directory are named according to the SCAP component and
              to the product they apply to.
            </para>
            <para>
              You can view all available security policies by getting a list of datastream files:
            </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>ls -l /usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-*-ds.xml</command></screen>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><filename>/usr/share/doc/scap-security-guide/guides/</filename></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Contains profiles for different hardening policies in a human-readable format. They
              describe the profiles that are included in the DataStream files. Each profile is a
              guide on securing your operating system to ensure compliance with a regulation.
            </para>
            <para>
              The guides usually have the following structure:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Short description
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Profile title. For example: <citetitle>&disaa; &stiga; for &productname;
                  &product-ga;</citetitle>
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Profile ID. For example:
                  <citetitle>xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_profile_stig</citetitle>
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Revision history. Information about the current version and status of the
                  profile. For example:
                  <citetitle>xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_profile_stig</citetitle>
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Platforms (in CPE notation). Lists the products or systems to which the profile
                  applies. For example:
                  <citetitle>cpe:/o:suse:linux_enterprise_server:15</citetitle>
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  A table of contents
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  A checklist that consists of groups (and subgroups) with rules
                </para>
                <para>
                  Each rule consists of a short description, the rationale behind the rule, a
                  severity (low, medium or high) and a unique identifier in the <literal>Common
                  Configuration Enumeration (CCE)</literal> format. The CCE number for each rule is
                  provided to &suse; by NIST.
                </para>
                <para>
                  Each rule also lists references to different good practices. For example, the
                  rule known by the unique identifier <literal>CCE-83289-9</literal> in &stiga; has
                  a reference to a specific good practice <literal>A.12.4.1</literal> in ISO/IEC
                  27001:2013.
                </para>
                <para>
                  If remediation options exist for a rule, they are listed in different formats.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><filename>/usr/share/scap-security-guide</filename></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Contains subdirectories with fix scripts that can be used to remediate the target
              system in case a vulnerability is found during a scan. Fix scripts are available in
              the following two formats: Shell scripts
              (<filename>bash/<replaceable>*.sh</replaceable></filename>) and &ansible; snippets
              (<filename>ansible/<replaceable>*.yml</replaceable></filename>).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="openscap-ssg-profiles">
      <title>&ssg; profiles</title>
      <para>
        The <literal>&ssg;</literal> contains multiple profiles. The applicable profiles are
        specific to the individual product and its underlying development stream.
      </para>
      <para>
        They are maintained and hosted in the following repository:
        <link xlink:href="https://github.com/ComplianceAsCode/content/tree/master/products/sle15/profiles"/>
      </para>
      <para>
        After the installation of the <package>scap-security-guide</package> package,
        human-readable versions of the profiles are available in your file system in
        <filename>/usr/share/doc/scap-security-guide/guides</filename>.
      </para>
      <para>
        To list the guides for each profile in an HTML format, run the following command:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>ls -l /usr/share/doc/scap-security-guide/guides/ssg*.html</command></screen>
      <para>
        You can then see the guide related to a specific profile in your Web browser. For example,
        to see the &productnameshort; &product-ga; &stiga; profile using the Mozilla Firefox Web
        browser, run the following command:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>firefox
/usr/share/doc/scap-security-guide/guides/ssg-sle15-guide-stig.html</command></screen>
      <para>
        Alternatively, find the same content online as static HTML pages:
        <link xlink:href="https://complianceascode.github.io/content-pages/guides/index.html"/>
      </para>
      <para>
        In the online versions, scroll to the appropriate product and select one of the available
        profiles.
      </para>
      <sect3 xml:id="openscap-ssg-profiles-info">
        <title>Viewing information on SSG profiles</title>
        <para>
          Each security policy can have multiple profiles, which provide policies implemented
          according to specific security baselines. Every profile can select different rules and
          use different values. You can list these profiles using the following command format:
        </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>oscap info --fetch-remote-resources
/usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-<replaceable>OPERATING-SYSTEM</replaceable>-<replaceable>TYPE-OF-FILE</replaceable>.xml</command><co
xml:id="ssg-profiles-info-view"></co></screen>
        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="ssg-profiles-info-view">
            <para>
              In the above command:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Replace <replaceable>OPERATING-SYSTEM</replaceable> with <literal>sle15</literal>
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Replace <replaceable>TYPE-OF-FILE</replaceable> with either <literal>ds</literal>
                  or <literal>xccdf</literal>
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>
        <para>
          For example, you can view information about the <literal>ds</literal> files of
          &productnameshort; &product-ga; using the following command:
        </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>oscap info
/usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-sle15-ds.xml</command></screen>
        <para>
          The following technical terms appear in the <command>oscap info</command> output for
          <literal>ds</literal> and <literal>xccdf</literal> files:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Document type</title>
              <para>
                Describes the file format. Common types include XCCDF, OVAL, Source Data Stream and
                Result Data Stream.
              </para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Checklist version</title>
              <para>
                The XCCDF version only shown for XCCDF files. Common values are
                <literal>1.1</literal> and <literal>1.2</literal>.
              </para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Imported</title>
              <para>
                The date the file was imported for use with &openscap;. As &openscap; uses the
                local file system and has no proprietary database format, the imported date is the
                same as the file modification date.
              </para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Status</title>
              <para>
                The XCCDF Benchmark status. Common values include <literal>accepted</literal>,
                <literal>draft</literal>, <literal>deprecated</literal>, and
                <literal>incomplete</literal>. Please refer to the XCCDF specification for details.
                This is only shown for XCCDF files.
              </para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Generated</title>
              <para>
                The date the file was created. This date is shown for XCCDF files and Checklists,
                and is sourced from the XCCDF Status element.
              </para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Profiles</title>
              <para>
                Available profile IDs that you can use for the <option>--profile</option>
                command-line attribute with the <command>oscap xccdf eval</command> command.
              </para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Checklists</title>
              <para>
                Lists available checklists incorporated in the Data Stream that you can use for the
                <option>--benchmark-id</option> command-line attribute with the <command>oscap
                xccdf eval</command> command. Also, each checklist has detailed information
                displayed.
              </para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
          For example, for &stiga; profiles, the following is relevant:
          <literal>xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_profile_stig</literal>.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 xml:id="openscap-ssg-profiles-sle15">
        <title>Supported profiles</title>
        <para>
          For &productnameshort; &product-ga;, the following profiles are
          <emphasis role="strong">supported</emphasis> by &suse;:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              ANSSI-BP-028 (enhanced)
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              ANSSI-BP-028 (high)
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              ANSSI-BP-028 (intermediary)
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              ANSSI-BP-028 (minimal)
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              &disaa; &stiga; for &productname; &product-ga;
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Hardening for Public Cloud Image of &productname; for SAP Applications &product-ga;
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              &hipaa;
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              &pcidssa; v4 Control Baseline for &productname; &product-ga;
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Public Cloud Hardening for &productname; &product-ga;
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <note>
          <title>Text-based list as updated information on supported profiles</title>
          <para>
            If there is a mismatch between the supported profiles listed above and the profiles
            shown in the image below, refer to the text-based list above as the updated
            information. The image below is for illustration only, and may not reflect the updated
            list of supported profiles.
          </para>
        </note>
        <figure>
          <title>&ssg; profiles for &productnameshort; &product-ga;</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="openscap-ssg-static-html-sle15.png" width="95%"/>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="openscap-ssg-static-html-sle15.png" width="90%"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject role="description"><phrase>&ssg; profiles for &productnameshort; &product-ga;</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="openscap-customize-scap-security-guide">
    <title>Customizing the &ssg;</title>

    <para>
      To customize the &ssg; for policies and profiles of your choice, perform the following steps:
    </para>

    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>
          Run the SCAP Workbench GUI software installed earlier.
        </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>scap-workbench</command></screen>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Select <literal>SLe15</literal> as the variant for the target system, then select
          <guilabel>Load Content</guilabel>.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Using the <guilabel>Profile</guilabel> drop-down list, select a profile with the desired
          policy, then select <guilabel>Customize</guilabel>.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Set a new ID for your custom profile. Set the ID in the following format:
          <literal>xccdf_<replaceable>REVERSE-DNS</replaceable>_profile_<replaceable>REST-OF-THE-ID</replaceable></literal>.
          For example,
          <literal>xccdf_org.<replaceable>mycorporation</replaceable>_profile_<replaceable>server</replaceable></literal>.
        </para>
        <warning>
          <para>
            You cannot change the ID of the custom profile later, using the SCAP Workbench.
          </para>
        </warning>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Deselect the rules that you do not want in the custom profile. For example, you can
          deselect the following rule: <literal>Record Events that Modify the System's
          Discretionary Access Controls - chmod</literal>.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          To save the changes to the profile, select <guilabel>OK</guilabel>. The main guide window
          is displayed again.
        </para>
        <stepalternatives>
          <step>
            <para>
              To save only the customization, select <menuchoice><guimenu>Select customization
              file</guimenu><guimenu>Open</guimenu><guimenu>Save customization
              only</guimenu></menuchoice>. This creates a small file containing only the changes
              made to the original profile, and is called a customization or
              <emphasis>tailoring</emphasis> file. The advantage of this approach is that when a
              new version of the profile is available, you can simply apply your tailoring to it,
              instead of customizing it from scratch.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              Alternatively, you can save the entire modified content in a directory. In that case,
              select the file, followed by <guilabel>Save all</guilabel>&gt;<guilabel>Into a
              directory</guilabel>.
            </para>
          </step>
        </stepalternatives>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          To use the customization file with the <command>oscap</command> command-line tool, use
          the <option>--tailoring-file <replaceable>NAME-OF-TAILORING-FILE</replaceable></option>
          option. For example:
        </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>oscap xccdf eval \
--profile xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_profile_stig_customized \
--report report_sle15_stig.html \
--tailoring-file ssg-sle15-ds-tailoring.xml \
/usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-sle15-ds.xml
</command>
</screen>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="openscap-scan">
    <title>Scanning for security vulnerabilities using &openscap;</title>

    <sect2 xml:id="openscap-scan-targets">
      <title>Targets to scan</title>
      <para>
        The content provided by the <literal>&ssg;</literal> can be used to scan the following
        targets for vulnerabilities:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            bare-metal machines
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            virtual machines
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            virtual machine images
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            containers
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            container images
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        Automated checks help to identify the target and to select only the rules that make sense
        for this specific target. For example, checks for separate partitions make sense for
        bare-metal machines but not for containers.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="openscap-scan-tools">
      <title>Tools for scanning</title>
      <note>
        <para>
          Before using the tools described in this section, ensure that you have installed them as
          described in <xref linkend="openscap-installation"/>, as they are interdependent.
        </para>
      </note>
      <para>
        Depending on your setup and the target to scan (remote or local), you can use either of the
        following tools:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>oscap</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              A command-line interface that can be used to scan local machines. Both the
              <package>openscap-utils</package> and <package>scap-security-guide</package> packages
              need to be installed on the local machine.
            </para>
            <para>
              To understand the basic usage of <command>oscap</command>, run it with the
              <command>-h</command> option:
            </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>oscap -h</command>

  oscap

  OpenSCAP command-line tool

  Usage: oscap [options] module operation [operation-options-and-arguments]

  Common options:
    --verbose &lt;verbosity_level&gt;   - Turn on verbose mode at specified verbosity level.
                                    Verbosity level must be one of: DEVEL, INFO, WARNING, ERROR.
    --verbose-log-file &lt;file&gt;     - Write verbose information into file.

  oscap options:
    -h --help                     - show this help
    -q --quiet                    - quiet mode
    -V --version                  - print info about supported SCAP versions

  Commands:
      ds - Data stream utilities
      oval - Open Vulnerability and Assessment Language
      xccdf - eXtensible Configuration Checklist Description Format
      cvss - Common Vulnerability Scoring System
      cpe - Common Platform Enumeration
      cve - Common Vulnerabilities and Exposures
      cvrf - Common Vulnerability Reporting Framework
      info - Print information about a SCAP file.

</screen>
            <para>
              To understand <literal>oscap</literal> in greater detail, read its man pages by
              running <command>man oscap</command>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>oscap-ssh</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              A command-line interface that can be used to scan a remote machine via SSH with an
              interface resembling the <command>oscap</command> tool. On the local machine, the
              package <package>openscap-utils</package> needs to be installed. On the remote
              machine, the <package>openscap-utils</package> package needs to be installed.
            </para>
            <para>
              To understand the basic usage of <command>oscap-ssh</command>, run it with the
              <command>-h</command> option:
            </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>oscap -h</command>

  oscap-ssh -- Tool for running oscap over SSH and collecting results.

  Usage:

  $ oscap-ssh user@host 22 info INPUT_CONTENT
  $ oscap-ssh user@host 22 xccdf eval [options] INPUT_CONTENT

  Only source data streams are supported as INPUT_CONTENT!

  supported oscap xccdf eval options are:
    --profile
    --tailoring-file
    --tailoring-id
    --cpe (external OVAL dependencies are not supported yet!)
    --oval-results
    --results
    --results-arf
    --report
    --skip-valid
    --skip-validation
    --fetch-remote-resources
    --local-files
    --progress
    --datastream-id
    --xccdf-id
    --benchmark-id
    --remediate

  $ oscap-ssh user@host 22 oval eval [options] INPUT_CONTENT

  supported oscap oval eval options are:
    --id
    --variables
    --directives
    --results
    --report
    --skip-valid
    --skip-validation
    --datastream-id
    --oval-id

  $ oscap-ssh user@host 22 oval collect [options] INPUT_CONTENT

  supported oscap oval collect options are:
    --id
    --syschar
    --variables
    --skip-valid
    --skip-validation

  specific option for oscap-ssh (must be first argument):
    --sudo

  To supply additional options to ssh/scp, define the SSH_ADDITIONAL_OPTIONS variable
  For instance, to ignore known hosts records, define SSH_ADDITIONAL_OPTIONS='-o StrictHostKeyChecking=no -o UserKnownHostsFile=/dev/null'

  specific option for oscap-ssh (must be first argument):

  See `man oscap` to learn more about semantics of these options.

</screen>
            <para>
              To understand <literal>oscap-ssh</literal> in greater detail, read its man pages by
              running <command>man oscap-ssh</command>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>SCAP Workbench</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              SCAP Workbench is a graphical user interface for &openscap;. You can use it for
              convenience instead of using <literal>oscap</literal>. For example, you can use SCAP
              Workbench for scanning a single machine, either local or remote (via SSH).
            </para>
            <para>
              To use SCAP Workbench, both the <package>scap-workbench</package> and
              <package>scap-security-guide</package> packages need to be installed on the local
              machine. On the remote machine, the <package>openscap-utils</package> package needs
              to be installed.
            </para>
            <para>
              To start SCAP Workbench, run the following command:
            </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>scap-workbench</command></screen>
            <figure>
              <title>SCAP Workbench</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                  <imagedata fileref="scap-workbench.png" width="90%"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                  <imagedata fileref="scap-workbench.png" width="95%"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject role="description"><phrase>Start screen of SCAP Workbench</phrase>
                </textobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>
              Although not recommended, you can invoke and perform certain basic operations by
              using SCAP Workbench as a command-line tool. To know more, read its man page by
              running <command>man scap-workbench</command>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="openscap-scan-sle15">
      <title>Scanning a &productnameshort; system</title>
      <para>
        You can scan your system locally with <command>oscap</command> for vulnerability issues
        according to a certain profile. You can save the results in XML format and generate an HTML
        report.
      </para>
      <example xml:id="ex-oscap-scan-sle15">
        <title>Scanning &productnameshort; with oscap</title>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>oscap</command> xccdf eval<co xml:id="co-oscap-eval"/> \
    --profile <replaceable>stig</replaceable><co xml:id="co-oscap-eval-profile"/> \
    --results <replaceable>/tmp/results.xml</replaceable><co xml:id="co-oscap-eval-results"/> \
    --report <replaceable>/tmp/report.html</replaceable><co xml:id="co-oscap-eval-report"/> \
    /usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-sle15-ds.xml<co xml:id="co-oscap-eval-ssg"/></screen>
        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="co-oscap-eval">
            <para>
              Calls the <command>oscap xccdf</command> module and tells it to perform an evaluation
              (vulnerability scan).
            </para>
          </callout>
          <callout arearefs="co-oscap-eval-profile">
            <para>
              Specifies the profile to use, in this case, <literal>stig</literal>.
            </para>
          </callout>
          <callout arearefs="co-oscap-eval-results">
            <para>
              Saves the results of the evaluation to <replaceable>/tmp/results.xml</replaceable>.
            </para>
          </callout>
          <callout arearefs="co-oscap-eval-report">
            <para>
              Generates an HTML report called <replaceable>/tmp/report.html</replaceable> in
              addition to the results in XML.
            </para>
          </callout>
          <callout arearefs="co-oscap-eval-ssg">
            <para>
              Specifies the <literal>&ssg;</literal> policy file to use. In this example, we use a
              policy file in the <literal>DataStream</literal> format. To list all available
              policies, run: <command>ls -1 /usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-*-ds.xml</command>.
              For more information about a particular policy, run <command>oscap info</command> on
              the file.
            </para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>
        <para>
          The evaluation process usually takes a few minutes, depending on the number of selected
          rules.
        </para>
      </example>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="openscap-evaluate-rules">
      <title>Evaluating with rules</title>
      <para>
        For each rule, we have the following fields:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Rule</title>
            <para>
              For example, <literal>Install AIDE</literal>
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Rule ID</title>
            <para>
              For example,
              <literal>xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_rule_package_aide_installed</literal>.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        After determining the security policy and profile, use <command>oscap xccdf eval</command>
        to perform an evaluation against them. For example, to evaluate the profile
        <literal>xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_profile_stig</literal> and generate an HTML report,
        you can use the following command format:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>oscap xccdf eval \
--profile <replaceable>xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_profile_stig</replaceable> \
--report report_sle15_stig.html \
/usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-sle15-ds.xml</command>
</screen>
      <para>
        To evaluate with a specific rule, you can specify the <guilabel>Rule ID</guilabel> using
        the <option>--rule</option> command option. For example, you can evaluate only with the
        rule <guilabel>xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_rule_package_aide_installed</guilabel>:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>oscap xccdf eval \
--profile <replaceable>xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_profile_stig</replaceable> \
--report report_sle15_stig.html \
--rule <replaceable>xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_rule_package_aide_installed</replaceable> \
/usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-sle15-ds.xml</command>
</screen>
      <para>
        To evaluate <emphasis>without</emphasis> a specific rule, you can specify to skip the
        <guilabel>Rule ID</guilabel> using the <option>--skip-rule</option> command option. For
        example, you can evaluate without the rule
        <guilabel>xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_rule_package_aide_installed</guilabel>:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>oscap xccdf eval \
--profile <replaceable>xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_profile_stig</replaceable> \
--report report_sle15_stig.html \
--skip-rule <replaceable>xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_rule_package_aide_installed</replaceable> \
/usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-sle15-ds.xml</command>
</screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="openscap-external-remote-resources-eval">
      <title>Using external or remote resources for scanning</title>
      <para>
        SCAP content may reference external resources. For example, the &ssg; uses an external OVAL
        file to check whether the system is up to date and patched against known security
        vulnerabilities. However, &openscap; can handle remote resources differently, based on the
        options used while invoking the <command>oscap</command> command. In addition, you can use
        strategies like downloading specific remote resources in advance and pointing the
        &openscap; tool towards the downloaded resources while invoking it.
      </para>
      <sect3>
        <title>Default warning for remote resources by &openscap; while performing evaluation</title>
        <para>
          While evaluating SCAP content with external resources, the &openscap; tool displays a
          <emphasis role="strong">warning</emphasis>. For example, &openscap; displays the
          following warning while performing the default evaluation of a system based on the &ssg;:
        </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;oscap xccdf eval \
--profile xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_profile_stig \
--results ssg-sle15-xccdf-stig-results.xml \
/usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-sle15-ds.xml

WARNING: Datastream component 'scap_org.open-scap_cref_pub-projects-security-oval-suse.linux.enterprise.15-
patch.xml.bz2' points out to the remote 'https://ftp.suse.com/pub/projects/security/oval/suse.linux.enterprise.
15-patch.xml.bz2'. Use '--fetch-remote-resources' option to download it.

WARNING: Skipping 'https://ftp.suse.com/pub/projects/security/oval/suse.linux.enterprise.15-patch.xml.bz2' file
which is referenced from datastream

WARNING: Skipping ./pub-projects-security-oval-suse.linux.enterprise.15-patch.xml.bz2 file which is referenced
from XCCDF content</screen>
        <para>
          The following sections describe certain strategies to force &openscap; to fetch remote
          resources in real time, or download them in advance and use them for evaluation and
          scanning the system.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 xml:id="openscap-fetching-remote-resource">
        <title>Fetching remote resources for evaluation</title>
        <para>
          If you trust your local content and the remote content it references, you can use the
          <option>--fetch-remote-resources</option> option to automatically download it when
          invoking the &openscap; tool.
        </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;oscap xccdf eval \
--fetch-remote-resources \
--profile xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_profile_stig \
--results ssg-sle15-xccdf-stig-results.xml \
/usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-sle15-ds.xml

Downloading: https://ftp.suse.com/pub/projects/security/oval/suse.linux.enterprise.15-patch.xml.bz2 ... ok

--- Starting Evaluation —
...</screen>
        <para>
          However, if access to the Internet is unavailable at the time of evaluation, or is
          considered a security risk, you can instruct &openscap; to use local files instead of
          remote resources.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 xml:id="openscap-downloading-saving-remote-resource">
        <title>Downloading and saving remote resources locally for evaluation</title>
        <para>
          On systems without Internet access, or in security-sensitive deployments where &openscap;
          cannot connect to the Internet, download the remote content using other tools and save it
          locally. You can then pass it to &openscap; as a local file using the
          <option>--local-files</option> option, instead of the
          <option>--fetch-remote-resources</option> option.
        </para>
        <para>
          For example, to prevent &openscap; from accessing the Internet but still use the patch
          file
          <link xlink:href="https://ftp.suse.com/pub/projects/security/oval/suse.linux.enterprise.15-patch.xml.bz2"/>,
          perform the following procedure.
        </para>
        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>
              <emphasis>(Optional)</emphasis> Create a directory for storing the downloaded remote
              resources.
            </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;mkdir ~/scap-files <co xml:id="scap-files-directory"></co></screen>
            <calloutlist>
              <callout arearefs="scap-files-directory">
                <para>
                  Directory to store downloaded remote resources. If you have identified a suitable
                  directory, skip this step.
                </para>
              </callout>
            </calloutlist>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              Download the remote resource and save it as a local file.
            </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;wget -O ~/scap-files/pub-projects-security-oval-suse.linux.enterprise.15-patch.xml.bz2<co
xml:id="scap-local-file"></co> \
https://ftp.suse.com/pub/projects/security/oval/suse.linux.enterprise.15-patch.xml.bz2<co xml:id="scap-remote-resource"></co></screen>
            <calloutlist>
              <callout arearefs="scap-local-file">
                <para>
                  The path to the locally saved file.
                </para>
              </callout>
              <callout arearefs="scap-remote-resource">
                <para>
                  The remote resource to be downloaded and saved locally.
                </para>
              </callout>
            </calloutlist>
            <note>
              <para>
                In this example, the name of the local file is
                <emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis> arbitrary. Notice the following information
                in the SCAP source data stream file available at
                <filename>/usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-sle15-ds.xml</filename>:
              </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;cat /usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-sle15-ds.xml | \
grep -n "scap_org.open-scap_cref_pub-projects-security-oval-suse.linux.enterprise.15-patch.xml.bz2"

17:          &lt;cat:uri name="pub-projects-security-oval-suse.linux.enterprise.15.xml" uri="#scap_org.open-scap_cref_pub-projects-security-oval-suse.linux.enterprise.15-patch.xml.bz2"/&gt;
25:      &lt;ds:component-ref id="scap_org.open-scap_cref_pub-projects-security-oval-suse.linux.enterprise.15-patch.xml.bz2" xlink:href="https://ftp.suse.com/pub/projects/security/oval/suse.linux.enterprise.15-patch.xml.bz2"/&gt;
</screen>
            </note>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              Run the evaluation using the local files downloaded earlier from the remote source.
            </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;oscap xccdf eval \
 --local-files ~/scap-files \
 --profile xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_profile_stig \
 --results ssg-sle15-xccdf-stig-results.xml \
 /usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-sle15-ds.xml

 WARNING: Using local file '~/scap-files/pub-projects-security-oval-suse.linux.enterprise.15-patch.xml.bz2'
 instead of 'https://ftp.suse.com/pub/projects/security/oval/suse.linux.enterprise.15-patch.xml.bz2'

 --- Starting Evaluation —
</screen>
            <tip>
              <para>
                Download and use the specific files that are relevant for your &productnameshort;
                product version, and avoid more generic ones. Being specific about the purpose and
                the files helps reduce the usage of server resources such as the processor, memory,
                storage and bandwidth. In addition, smaller file sizes also reduce the time
                required to complete the evaluation. For example, if you are interested only in
                &productnameshort; &product-ga; SP&product-sp;, use the file available at
                <link xlink:href="https://ftp.suse.com/pub/projects/security/oval/suse.linux.enterprise.15-sp5-patch.xml.bz2"/>.
              </para>
            </tip>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Optionally</emphasis>, you can generate an HTML report from the XML results
              file.
            </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;oscap xccdf generate report ssg-sle15-xccdf-stig-results.xml &gt;
ssg-sle15-xccdf-stig-report.html</screen>
            <tip>
              <para>
                You can generate an HTML report directly using the <command>oscap xccdf eval
                --report</command> option, but separating the scan and the HTML report generation
                leads to less usage of server resources.
              </para>
            </tip>
          </step>
        </procedure>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="openscap-scanning-audits-oval-files">
      <title>Scanning and auditing systems using OVAL files</title>
      <para>
        Using the OVAL content files for &productnameshort; products, you can assess your
        &productnameshort; systems and generate reports on the RPM package names and versions that
        are known to be affected by security issues in published CVEs.
      </para>
      <para>
        The OVAL data provided by &suse; includes the following:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The patch-style OVAL data, which expresses all security updates on a patch level. These
            can include multiple CVEs per patch.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The vulnerability OVAL data, which expresses security vulnerabilities on a CVE level.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        For detailed information on OVAL support provided by &suse;, refer to
        <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/security/oval/"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can download OVAL files provided by &suse; from
        <link xlink:href="https://ftp.suse.com/pub/projects/security/oval/"/>. As a best practice
        for scanning and auditing systems using OVAL files, perform the following procedure:
      </para>
      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>
            <emphasis>(Optional)</emphasis> Create a directory for downloading and storing remote
            resources.
          </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;mkdir ~/oval-files <co xml:id="oval-files-directory"></co></screen>
          <calloutlist>
            <callout arearefs="oval-files-directory">
              <para>
                Directory to store downloaded remote resources such as OVAL patch files. If you
                have identified a suitable directory, skip this step.
              </para>
            </callout>
          </calloutlist>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Download the remote resource and save it as a local file.
          </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;wget -O ~/oval-files/suse.linux.enterprise.15-patch.xml.bz2<co
xml:id="oval-local-file"></co> \
https://ftp.suse.com/pub/projects/security/oval/suse.linux.enterprise.15-patch.xml.bz2<co xml:id="oval-remote-resource"></co></screen>
          <calloutlist>
            <callout arearefs="oval-local-file">
              <para>
                The path to the locally saved file.
              </para>
            </callout>
            <callout arearefs="oval-remote-resource">
              <para>
                The remote resource to be downloaded and saved locally.
              </para>
            </callout>
          </calloutlist>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Run the evaluation using the local files downloaded earlier from the remote source.
          </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;oscap oval eval \
--results sle15-oval-results.xml \
~/oval-files/suse.linux.enterprise.15-patch.xml.bz2

Definition oval:org.opensuse.security:def:45435: false
Definition oval:org.opensuse.security:def:45434: false
Definition oval:org.opensuse.security:def:45433: false
Definition oval:org.opensuse.security:def:45432: false
Definition oval:org.opensuse.security:def:45431: false
Definition oval:org.opensuse.security:def:45430: false
Definition oval:org.opensuse.security:def:45429: false
...

Evaluation done.
</screen>
          <tip>
            <para>
              Download and use the specific files that are relevant for your &productnameshort;
              product version, and avoid more generic ones. Being specific about the purpose and
              the files helps reduce the usage of server resources such as the processor, memory,
              storage and bandwidth. In addition, smaller file sizes also reduce the time required
              to complete the evaluation. For example, if you are interested only in
              &productnameshort; &product-ga; SP&product-sp;, use the file available at
              <link xlink:href="https://ftp.suse.com/pub/projects/security/oval/suse.linux.enterprise.15-sp5-patch.xml.bz2"/>.
            </para>
          </tip>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Optionally</emphasis>, you can generate an HTML report from the XML results
            file.
          </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;oscap oval generate report sle15-oval-results.xml &gt;
sle15-oval-report.html</screen>
          <tip>
            <para>
              You can generate an HTML report directly using the <command>oscap oval eval
              --report</command> option, but separating the scan and the HTML report generation
              leads to less usage of server resources.
            </para>
          </tip>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="openscap-remediate">
    <title>How to automatically remediate non-compliant configurations?</title>

    <para>
      Beyond scanning and reporting, the <literal>&ssg;</literal> security profiles can
      automatically remediate the target system by applying necessary fixes.
    </para>

    <important>
      <title>Automatic remediation not always available</title>
      <para>
        Automatic remediation is <emphasis>not</emphasis> offered in case the automatic application
        of a fix is too dangerous to be enforced in a running target system.
      </para>
    </important>

    <sect2 xml:id="openscap-remediate-process">
      <title>&openscap; remediation process</title>
      <para>
        &openscap; allows to automatically remediate target systems that have been found in a
        non-compliant state. This requires an XCCDF file with instructions. The overall process is
        as follows:
      </para>
      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>
            The <command>oscap</command> command-line tool performs a system scan.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Each rule that fails is marked as a candidate for remediation.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Within the XCCDF file, <command>oscap</command> then searches for an appropriate
            &lt;xccdf:fix&gt; element, resolves it, prepares the environment, and executes the fix
            script. The fix scripts can be either Bash <filename>*.sh</filename> files or &ansible;
            playbook <filename>*.yml</filename> files.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            After the execution of the script, the respective rule is evaluated again to check if
            the fix was successful.
          </para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
      <para>
        All results of the remediation are stored in an output XCCDF file.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="openscap-remediate-options">
      <title>&openscap; remediation options</title>
      <para>
        For remediating a target system with <command>oscap</command>, you have the following
        options:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Remediation on the fly</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              You can remediate a target system on the fly, while you are scanning it. In this
              case, evaluation and remediation are performed as a part of a single command. For
              details, see <xref linkend="oscap-remediate-sle-fly"/>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Remediation after scanning</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              You can remediate a target system after you have scanned it. In the first step, the
              system is only evaluated, and the results are stored in the XCCDF results file. In
              the second step, <command>oscap</command> executes the fix scripts and verifies the
              result. For details, see <xref linkend="oscap-remediate-sle-post"/>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Review mode</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The review mode allows to save remediation instructions to a file for further review.
              The remediation content is not executed during this operation. For details, see
              <xref linkend="oscap-remediate-sle-review"/>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="openscap-remediate-specific-profile-shell-script">
      <title>Remediating for a specific profile using shell scripts</title>
      <para>
        For simple remediation of a profile without any condition, you can use the shell scripts
        that are shipped with the &ssg;.
      </para>
      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>
            Find the shell scripts that perform remediation without any condition:
          </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>ls -l /usr/share/scap-security-guide/bash/</command></screen>
          <para>
            The names of the scripts follow the format:
            <filename>sle15-script-<replaceable>NAME-OF-PROFILE</replaceable>.sh</filename>.
          </para>
          <para>
            The supported profiles are as follows: <literal>stig</literal>,
            <literal>anssi_bp28_xxx</literal>, <literal>hipaa</literal>,
            <literal>pci-dss-4</literal>, and <literal>pcs-hardening</literal>.
          </para>
          <note>
            <para>
              The standard profile is officially <emphasis>not supported</emphasis>.
            </para>
          </note>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Understand the format of the shell scripts and the rules within. In the scripts, each
            rule or recommendation maintains the following format:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Starts with <literal># BEGIN fix
                (<replaceable>CURRENT-NUMBER</replaceable>/<replaceable>TOTAL-NUMBER-OF-RULES</replaceable>)
                for <replaceable>RULE-ID</replaceable></literal>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Ends with <literal># END fix for <replaceable>RULE-ID</replaceable></literal>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <note>
            <title>Exceptions to the rule format</title>
            <para>
              Certain rules contain a line ending with <literal>IS MISSING!</literal> in between
              the <literal>BEGIN</literal> and <literal>END</literal> lines for a rule block. These
              rules do not have a remediation part. You need to do remediation manually to apply
              them.
            </para>
          </note>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Although the recommended approach for excluding rules from remediation is to use
            tailoring, you can also do it manually if there are bugs, or for tests. In that case,
            open the intended script with a text editor and comment out the necessary lines between
            <literal>BEGIN</literal> and <literal>END</literal> for a rule block.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Make the script executable:
          </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>chmod +x sle15-script-<replaceable>NAME-OF-PROFILE</replaceable>.sh</command></screen>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Run the script:
          </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>./sle15-script-<replaceable>NAME-OF-PROFILE</replaceable>.sh</command></screen>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="openscap-remediate-sle">
      <title>Remediating a &productnameshort; system with <command>oscap</command></title>
      <para>
        The following examples show how to scan and remediate &productnameshort; locally with
        <command>oscap</command> to comply with a certain profile.
      </para>
      <sect3 xml:id="oscap-remediate-sle-fly">
        <title>Remediating &productnameshort; (on the fly)</title>
        <para>
          To remediate a system (on the fly), you can use a combination of <option>--eval</option>
          and <option>--remediate</option> options of the <command>oscap</command> command. In this
          case, the system is first scanned (audited), and then the command attempts to fix the
          system. During the execution of the audit, you will see the status after each rule as
          <literal>pass</literal>, <literal>fail</literal>, or <literal>not applicable</literal>.
          During the execution of the remediation, you will see the status as
          <literal>fixed</literal> or <literal>error</literal> after some of the rules.
        </para>
        <example xml:id="ex-oscap-remediate-sle-fly">
          <title>Remediating &productnameshort; systems (on the fly)</title>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>oscap</command> xccdf eval --remediate<co xml:id="co-oscap-remedy-fly"/> \
--profile <replaceable>stig</replaceable><co xml:id="co-oscap-remedy-fly-profile"/> \
--results <replaceable>/tmp/results.xml</replaceable><co xml:id="co-oscap-remedy-fly-results"/> \
--report <replaceable>/tmp/report.html</replaceable><co xml:id="co-oscap-remedy-fly-report"/> \
--skip-rule xccdf_org.ssgproject.content_rule_accounts_authorized_local_users<co xml:id="co-oscap-remedy-skip-rules"/> \
/usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-sle15-ds.xml<co xml:id="co-oscap-remedy-fly-ssg"/></screen>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>reboot</command></screen>
          <calloutlist>
            <callout arearefs="co-oscap-remedy-fly">
              <para>
                Calls the <command>oscap xccdf</command> module and tells it to perform an
                evaluation plus a remediation of the target system in one go.
              </para>
            </callout>
            <callout arearefs="co-oscap-remedy-fly-profile">
              <para>
                Specifies the profile to use, in this case, <literal>stig</literal>.
              </para>
            </callout>
            <callout arearefs="co-oscap-remedy-fly-results">
              <para>
                Saves the results of the evaluation to <replaceable>/tmp/results.xml</replaceable>.
              </para>
            </callout>
            <callout arearefs="co-oscap-remedy-fly-report">
              <para>
                Saves the report of the evaluation to <replaceable>/tmp/report.html</replaceable>.
              </para>
            </callout>
            <callout arearefs="co-oscap-remedy-skip-rules">
              <para>
                Rules that you want to skip.
              </para>
            </callout>
            <callout arearefs="co-oscap-remedy-fly-ssg">
              <para>
                Specifies the <literal>&ssg;</literal> policy file to use for &productnameshort;
                &product-ga;.
              </para>
            </callout>
          </calloutlist>
          <para>
            In the resulting <replaceable>/tmp/results.xml</replaceable> file, the first
            <tag class="element">TestResult</tag> element shows the result of the scan
            <emphasis>before</emphasis> the remediation. The second
            <tag class="element">TestResult</tag> element shows the result of the scan
            <emphasis>after</emphasis> applying the remediation. In the second
            <tag class="element">TestResult</tag> element, if the result of a rule is
            <literal>fixed</literal>, this means that the fix was successfully applied, and this
            rule now passes evaluation. If the result of a rule is <literal>error</literal>, this
            means that the remediation for this rule was not successful, and the rule still does
            not pass evaluation.
          </para>
        </example>
        <warning>
          <title>Usage of the <option>--skip-rule</option> option</title>
          <para>
            In the above example, the <literal>--skip-rule</literal> option is optional. However,
            it is necessary to use it if you did not change the variable
            <literal>var_accounts_authorized_local_users_regex</literal>. Otherwise, you will not
            be able to do a <command>sudo</command> after reboot.
          </para>
        </warning>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 xml:id="oscap-remediate-sle-post">
        <title>Remediating &productnameshort; (after scanning)</title>
        <para>
          In this example, we first execute a scan and then run the remediation as the next step.
        </para>
        <example xml:id="ex-oscap-remediate-sle15-post">
          <title>Remediating &productnameshort; (after scanning)</title>
          <procedure>
            <step>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>oscap</command> xccdf eval<co xml:id="co-oscap-remedy-post1"/> \
      --profile <replaceable>stig</replaceable><co xml:id="co-oscap-remedy-post1-profile"/> \
      --results <replaceable>/tmp/results.xml</replaceable><co xml:id="co-oscap-remedy-post1-results"/> \
      /usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-sle15-ds.xml<co xml:id="co-oscap-remedy-post1-ssg"/></screen>
              <calloutlist>
                <callout arearefs="co-oscap-remedy-post1">
                  <para>
                    Calls the <command>oscap xccdf</command> module and tells it to perform an
                    evaluation.
                  </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="co-oscap-remedy-post1-profile">
                  <para>
                    Specifies the profile to use, in this case, <literal>stig</literal>.
                  </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="co-oscap-remedy-post1-results">
                  <para>
                    Saves the results of the evaluation as an XCCDF file to
                    <replaceable>/tmp/results.xml</replaceable>.
                  </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="co-oscap-remedy-post1-ssg">
                  <para>
                    Specifies the <literal>&ssg;</literal> policy file to use. In this example, we
                    use a policy file in the <literal>DataStream</literal> format that applies to
                    &productnameshort; &product-ga;. To list all available policies, run:
                    <command>ls -1 /usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-*-ds.xml</command>. For more
                    information about a particular policy, run <command>oscap info</command> on the
                    file.
                  </para>
                </callout>
              </calloutlist>
              <para>
                During this step, the system is only evaluated, and the results are stored in a
                <tag class="element">TestResult</tag> element in
                <replaceable>/tmp/results.xml</replaceable>.
              </para>
            </step>
            <step>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>oscap</command> xccdf remediate<co xml:id="co-oscap-remedy-post2-command"/> \
     --results <replaceable>/tmp/results.xml</replaceable><co xml:id="co-oscap-remedy-post2-results"/> \
     <replaceable>/tmp/results.xml</replaceable><co xml:id="co-oscap-remedy-post2-ssg"/></screen>
              <calloutlist>
                <callout arearefs="co-oscap-remedy-post2-command">
                  <para>
                    Calls the <command>oscap xccdf</command> module and tells it to perform a
                    remediation.
                  </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="co-oscap-remedy-post2-results">
                  <para>
                    Saves the results of the remediation to
                    <replaceable>/tmp/results.xml</replaceable>.
                  </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="co-oscap-remedy-post2-ssg">
                  <para>
                    Uses the <replaceable>/tmp/results.xml</replaceable> XCCDF file from the first
                    step (evaluation) as input file.
                  </para>
                </callout>
              </calloutlist>
              <para>
                During this step, the results file from the first step is used as input for the
                <command>oscap</command> command. You can safely store the results from the second
                step in the same file that you use as the input file,
                <replaceable>/tmp/results.xml</replaceable>. During this run,
                <command>oscap</command> creates a new <tag class="element">xccdf:TestResult</tag>
                element in the file. The new element is based on the previous one and inherits all
                the data. The newly created <tag class="element">xccdf:TestResult</tag> element
                differs only in the <tag class="element">rule-result</tag> elements which failed in
                the first run. Only for those is the remediation executed.
              </para>
            </step>
          </procedure>
        </example>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 xml:id="oscap-remediate-bash-ansible">
        <title>Remediating systems using <command>oscap</command> and scripts</title>
        <para>
          To remediate a system, you have to generate a script that will fix the system. You have
          to decide in advance the profile and type of the script&mdash;bash or &ansible;.
        </para>
        <note>
          <title>Evaluate the system before remediation</title>
          <para>
            Before running the examples in this section, ensure that you have evaluated the system
            using the <command>oscap xccdf eval</command> commands.
          </para>
        </note>
        <example>
          <title>Remediating &productnameshort; systems using <command>oscap</command> and bash</title>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>oscap xccdf generate fix --profile stig --fetch-remote-resources \
--fix-type bash --output <replaceable>GENERATED-BASH-REMEDIATION-SCRIPT-NAME</replaceable>.sh \
/usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-sle15-ds.xml</command></screen>
        </example>
        <example>
          <title>Remediating &productnameshort; systems using <command>oscap</command> and &ansible;</title>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>oscap xccdf generate fix --profile stig --fetch-remote-resources \
--fix-type ansible --output <replaceable>GENERATED-ANSIBLE-REMEDIATION-SCRIPT-NAME</replaceable>.yml \
/usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-sle15-ds.xml</command></screen>
        </example>
        <para>
          After running any of the above commands, you can run the generated script to remediate
          the system.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 xml:id="oscap-remediate-sle-review">
        <title>Storing &productnameshort; remediation instructions for review</title>
        <para>
          You can also run <command>oscap</command> in review mode to store remediation
          instructions to a file for further review. During this operation, the remediation content
          is <emphasis>not</emphasis> executed. The following shows how to generate remediation
          instructions in the form of a shell script:
        </para>
        <example xml:id="ex-oscap-remediate-sle15-review">
          <title>Storing &productnameshort; remediation instructions for review</title>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>oscap</command> xccdf generate fix<co xml:id="co-oscap-generate-fix"/> \
     --template urn:xccdf:fix:script:sh<co xml:id="co-oscap-generate-template"/> \
     --profile <replaceable>stig</replaceable><co xml:id="co-oscap-generate-profile"/> \
     --output <replaceable>my-remediation-script.sh</replaceable><co xml:id="co-oscap-generate-output"/> \
     /usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-sle15-ds.xml<co xml:id="co-oscap-generate-ssg"/></screen>
          <calloutlist>
            <callout arearefs="co-oscap-generate-fix">
              <para>
                Calls the <command>oscap xccdf</command> module and tells it to generate a file
                with remediation instructions.
              </para>
            </callout>
            <callout arearefs="co-oscap-generate-template">
              <para>
                Specifies the template to use, in this case, a shell script.
              </para>
            </callout>
            <callout arearefs="co-oscap-generate-profile">
              <para>
                Specifies the profile to use, in this case, <literal>stig</literal>.
              </para>
            </callout>
            <callout arearefs="co-oscap-generate-output">
              <para>
                Specifies the file to which the remediation instructions are written.
              </para>
            </callout>
            <callout arearefs="co-oscap-generate-ssg">
              <para>
                Specifies the <literal>&ssg;</literal> policy file to use. In this example, we use
                a policy file in the <literal>DataStream</literal> format that applies to
                &productnameshort; &product-ga;. To list all available policies, run: <command>ls
                -1 /usr/share/xml/scap/ssg/content/ssg-*-ds.xml</command>. For more information
                about a particular policy, run <command>oscap info</command> on the file.
              </para>
            </callout>
          </calloutlist>
        </example>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="openscap-remediate-sle-ansible">
      <title>Remediating a &productnameshort; system with &ansible;</title>
      <para>
        You can use the &ansible; playbooks provided by the <literal>&ssg;</literal> to remediate a
        local system.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <package>ansible</package> package is available from <literal>&ph;</literal>. Register
        your &productnameshort; system and enable the <literal>&ph;</literal> module. Then install
        the package with <command>sudo zypper in ansible</command>.
      </para>
      <example xml:id="ex-remediate-sle15-ansible">
        <title>Remediating &productnameshort; &product-ga; with &ansible;</title>
        <para>
          For example, to remediate your system using the &stiga; &ansible; playbook for
          &productnameshort; &product-ga; provided by the <literal>&ssg;</literal>, use the
          following command.
        </para>
        <warning>
          <title>System configuration changes</title>
          <para>
            The following command alters the configuration of your system immediately. Make sure to
            test this thoroughly in a non-production system first.
          </para>
        </warning>
<screen>&prompt.user;ansible-playbook -i "localhost," -c local \
/usr/share/scap-security-guide/ansible/sle15-playbook-stig.yml</screen>
        <para>
          After the playbook has finished, you are prompted to log in to your system, which is now
          compliant with the chosen policy.
        </para>
      </example>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="openscap-remediate-specific-profile-ansible">
      <title>Remediating for a specific profile using &ansible;</title>
      <para>
        For simple remediation of a profile without any condition, you can use the &ansible;
        playbooks that are shipped with the &ssg;.
      </para>
      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>
            List the &ansible; playbooks that are shipped with the &ssg;.
          </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>ls -l /usr/share/scap-security-guide/ansible/</command></screen>
          <para>
            The file names are in the following format:
            <filename>sle15-playbook-<replaceable>NAME-OF-PROFILE</replaceable>.yml</filename>.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Create a file <filename>ansible_inventory.yml</filename> and include the following
            configuration snippet:
          </para>
<screen>
all:
  hosts:
    localhost:
  vars:
    ansible_connection: local
</screen>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Then run the following command:
          </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>ansible-playbook -i ansible_inventory.yml
sle15-playbook-<replaceable>NAME-OF-PROFILE</replaceable>.yml</command><co
xml:id="scap-ansible"></co></screen>
          <calloutlist>
            <callout arearefs="scap-ansible">
              <para>
                Substitute <replaceable>NAME-OF-PROFILE</replaceable> with any of the supported
                profiles, as seen in the file names within the directory
                <filename>/usr/share/scap-security-guide/ansible/</filename>.
              </para>
            </callout>
          </calloutlist>
          <para>
            To skip some of the rules during the execution, use the <option>--tag</option> option.
            You can find the tag of a specific rule by searching for the rule's tag in the playbook
            file. For example, to skip some rules for &productnameshort;, run the following
            command:
          </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>ansible-playbook -i ansible_inventory.yml sle15-playbook-<replaceable>NAME-OF-PROFILE</replaceable>.yml \
--tags "package_aide_installed,aide_build_database"</command></screen>
        </step>
      </procedure>
      <note>
        <para>
          You might need to repeat the steps above more than twice, because of the following
          reasons:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Some of the rules require a restart of the system to take effect.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The rules are executed in alphabetical order.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </note>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="oscap-related-topics">
    <title>Related topics</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Check out the <literal>&ssg;</literal> pages online at
          <link xlink:href="https://www.open-scap.org/security-policies/scap-security-guide/"/>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          For general instructions on how to use the <literal>&ssg;</literal>, see the README in
          <link xlink:href="https://github.com/ComplianceAsCode/content/"/>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Find the <citetitle>&openscap; User Manual</citetitle> at
          <link xlink:href="https://static.open-scap.org/openscap-1.2/oscap_user_manual.html"/>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  <xi:include href="common_copyright_quick.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="common_license_gfdl1.2.xml"/>
</article>
