<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.audit.setup">
 <title>Setting Up the Linux Audit Framework</title>
 <info/>
 <para>
  This chapter shows how to set up a simple audit scenario. Every step
  involved in configuring and enabling audit is explained in detail. After
  you have learned to set up audit, consider a real-world example scenario
  in <xref linkend="cha.audit.scenarios"/>.
 </para>
 <para>
  To set up audit on &productname;, you need to complete the following
  steps:
 </para>
 <procedure>
  <title>Setting Up the Linux Audit Framework</title>
  <step>
   <para>
    Make sure that all required packages are installed:
    <systemitem class="resource">audit</systemitem>,
    <systemitem class="resource">audit-libs</systemitem>, and optionally
    <systemitem class="resource">audit-libs-python</systemitem>. To use the
    log visualization as described in <xref linkend="sec.audit.viz"/>,
    install <systemitem class="resource">gnuplot</systemitem> and
    <systemitem class="resource">graphviz</systemitem> from the
    &productname; media.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Determine the components to audit. Refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.audit.choose"/> for details.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Check or modify the basic audit daemon configuration. Refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.audit.config"/> for details.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Enable auditing for system calls. Refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.audit.syscall"/> for details.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Compose audit rules to suit your scenario. Refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.audit.aurules"/> for details.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Generate logs and configure tailor-made reports. Refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.audit.aurepo"/> for details.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Configure optional log visualization. Refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.audit.viz"/> for details.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
 <important>
  <title>Controlling the Audit Daemon</title>
  <para>
   Before configuring any of the components of the audit system, make sure
   that the audit daemon is not running by entering <command>systemctl
   status auditd.service</command> as &rootuser;. On a default
   &productname; system, audit is started on boot, so you need to turn it
   off by entering <command>systemctl stop auditd.service</command>. Start
   the daemon after configuring it with <command>systemctl start
   auditd.service</command>.
  </para>
 </important>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.audit.choose">
  <title>Determining the Components to Audit</title>

  <para>
   Before starting to create your own audit configuration, determine to
   which degree you want to use it. Check the following general rules to
   determine which use case best applies to you and your requirements:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If you require a full security audit for CAPP/EAL certification, enable
     full audit for system calls and configure watches on various
     configuration files and directories, similar to the rule set featured
     in <xref linkend="cha.audit.scenarios"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If you need to trace a process based on the audit rules, use
     <command>autrace</command>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If you require file and directory watches to track access to important
     or security-sensitive data, create a rule set matching these
     requirements. Enable audit as described in
     <xref linkend="sec.audit.syscall"/> and proceed to
     <xref linkend="sec.audit.aurules"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.audit.config">
  <title>Configuring the Audit Daemon</title>

  <para>
   The basic setup of the audit daemon is done by editing
   <filename>/etc/audit/auditd.conf</filename>. You may also use &yast;
   to configure the basic settings by calling <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>&yast;</guimenu> <guimenu>Security and Users</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Linux Audit Framework (LAF)</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Use the
   tabs <guimenu>Log File</guimenu> and <guimenu>Disk Space</guimenu> for
   configuration.
  </para>

<screen>log_file = /var/log/audit/audit.log
log_format = RAW
log_group = root
priority_boost = 4
flush = INCREMENTAL
freq = 20
num_logs = 5
disp_qos = lossy
dispatcher = /sbin/audispd
name_format = NONE
##name = mydomain
max_log_file = 6
max_log_file_action = ROTATE
space_left = 75
space_left_action = SYSLOG
action_mail_acct = root
admin_space_left = 50
admin_space_left_action = SUSPEND
disk_full_action = SUSPEND
disk_error_action = SUSPEND
##tcp_listen_port =
tcp_listen_queue = 5
tcp_max_per_addr = 1
##tcp_client_ports = 1024-65535
tcp_client_max_idle = 0
cp_client_max_idle = 0</screen>

  <para>
   The default settings work reasonably well for many setups. Some values,
   such as <literal>num_logs</literal>, <literal>max_log_file</literal>,
   <literal>space_left</literal>, and <literal>admin_space_left</literal>
   depend on the size of your deployment. If disk space is limited, you
   might want to reduce the number of log files to keep if they are rotated
   and you might want get an earlier warning if disk space is running out.
   For a CAPP-compliant setup, adjust the values for
   <literal>log_file</literal>, <literal>flush</literal>,
   <literal>max_log_file</literal>, <literal>max_log_file_action</literal>,
   <literal>space_left</literal>, <literal>space_left_action</literal>,
   <literal>admin_space_left</literal>,
   <literal>admin_space_left_action</literal>,
   <literal>disk_full_action</literal>, and
   <literal>disk_error_action</literal>, as described in
   <xref linkend="sec.audit.auditd"/>. An example CAPP-compliant
   configuration looks like this:
  </para>

<screen>log_file = <replaceable>path_to_separate_partition</replaceable>/audit.log
log_format = RAW
priority_boost = 4
flush = SYNC                       ### or DATA
freq = 20
num_logs = 4
dispatcher = /sbin/audispd
disp_qos = lossy
max_log_file = 5
max_log_file_action = KEEP_LOGS
space_left = 75
space_left_action = EMAIL
action_mail_acct = root
admin_space_left = 50
admin_space_left_action = SINGLE   ### or HALT
disk_full_action = SUSPEND         ### or HALT
disk_error_action = SUSPEND        ### or HALT</screen>

  <para>
   The <literal>###</literal> precedes comments where you can choose from
   several options. Do not add the comments to your actual configuration
   files.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>For More Information</title>
   <para>
    Refer to <xref linkend="sec.audit.auditd"/> for detailed background
    information about the <filename>auditd.conf</filename> configuration
    parameters.
   </para>
  </tip>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.audit.syscall">
  <title>Enabling Audit for System Calls</title>

  <para>
   If the audit framework is not installed, install the
   <systemitem>audit</systemitem> package. A standard &productname;
   system does not have auditd running by default. Enable it with:
  </para>

<screen>systemctl enable auditd.service</screen>

  <para>
   There are different levels of auditing activity available:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Basic Logging</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Out of the box (without any further configuration) auditd logs only
      events concerning its own configuration changes to
      <filename>/var/log/audit/audit.log</filename>. No events (file access,
      system call, etc.) are generated by the kernel audit component until
      requested by <command>auditctl</command>. However, other kernel
      components and modules may log audit events outside of the control of
      <command>auditctl</command> and these appear in the audit log. By
      default, the only module that generates audit events is &aa;.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Advanced Logging with System Call Auditing</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To audit system calls and get meaningful file watches, you need to
      enable audit contexts for system calls.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   As you need system call auditing capabilities even when you are
   configuring plain file or directory watches, you need to enable audit
   contexts for system calls. To enable audit contexts for the duration of
   the current session only, execute <command>auditctl -e 1</command> as
   &rootuser;. To disable this feature, execute <command>auditctl -e
   0</command> as &rootuser;.
  </para>

  <para>
   The audit contexts are enabled by default. To turn this feature off
   temporarily, use <command>auditctl -e 0</command>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.audit.aurules">
  <title>Setting Up Audit Rules</title>

  <para>
   Using audit rules, determine which aspects of the system should be
   analyzed by audit. Normally this includes important databases and
   security-relevant configuration files. You may also analyze various
   system calls in detail if a broad analysis of your system is required. A
   very detailed example configuration that includes most of the rules that
   are needed in a CAPP compliant environment is available in
   <xref linkend="cha.audit.scenarios"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Audit rules can be passed to the audit daemon on the
   <command>auditctl</command> command line as well as by composing a rule
   set in <filename>/etc/audit/audit.rules</filename> which is processed
   whenever the audit daemon is started. To customize
   <filename>/etc/audit/audit.rules</filename> either edit it directly, or
   use &yast;: <menuchoice> <guimenu>Security and Users</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Linux Audit Framework (LAF)</guimenu> <guimenu>Rules for
   'auditctl'</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Rules passed on the command line are
   not persistent and need to be re-entered when the audit daemon is
   restarted.
  </para>

  <para>
   A simple rule set for very basic auditing on a few important files and
   directories could look like this:
  </para>

<screen># basic audit system parameters
-D
-b 8192
-f 1
-e 1

# some file and directory watches with keys
-w /var/log/audit/ -k LOG_audit
-w /etc/audit/auditd.conf -k CFG_audit_conf -p rxwa
-w /etc/audit/audit.rules -k CFG_audit_rules -p rxwa

-w /etc/passwd -k CFG_passwd -p rwxa
-w /etc/sysconfig/ -k CFG_sysconfig  

# an example system call rule
-a entry,always -S umask

### add your own rules</screen>

  <para>
   When configuring the basic audit system parameters (such as the backlog
   parameter <literal>-b</literal>) test these settings with your intended
   audit rule set to determine whether the backlog size is appropriate for
   the level of logging activity caused by your audit rule set. If your
   chosen backlog size is too small, your system might not be able to handle
   the audit load and consult the failure flag (<literal>-f</literal>) when
   the backlog limit is exceeded.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Choosing the Failure Flag</title>
   <para>
    When choosing the failure flag, note that <option>-f 2</option> tells
    your system to perform an immediate shutdown without flushing any
    pending data to disk when the limits of your audit system are exceeded.
    Because this shutdown is not a clean shutdown, restrict the use of
    <option>-f 2</option> to only the most security-conscious environments
    and use <option>-f 1</option> (system continues to run, issues a warning
    and audit stops) for any other setup to avoid loss of data or data
    corruption.
   </para>
  </important>

  <para>
   Directory watches produce less verbose output than separate file watches
   for the files under these directories. To get detailed logging for your
   system configuration in <filename>/etc/sysconfig</filename>, for example,
   add watches for each individual file. Audit does not support globbing,
   which means you cannot create a rule that says <literal>-w
   /etc/*</literal> and watches all files and directories below
   <filename>/etc</filename>.
  </para>

  <para>
   For better identification in the log file, a key has been added to each
   of the file and directory watches. Using the key, it is easier to comb
   the logs for events related to a certain rule. When creating keys,
   distinguish between mere log file watches and configuration file watches
   by using an appropriate prefix with the key, in this case
   <literal>LOG</literal> for a log file watch and <literal>CFG</literal>
   for a configuration file watch. Using the file name as part of the key
   also makes it easier for you to identify events of this type in the log
   file.
  </para>

  <remark>jsegitz 2014-07-23: this isn't a good suggestion IMHO since it can 
be queried with -w anyway</remark>

  <para>
   Another thing to bear in mind when creating file and directory watches is
   that audit cannot deal with files that do not exist when the rules are
   created. Any file that is added to your system while audit is already
   running is not watched unless you extend the rule set to watch this new
   file.
  </para>

  <para>
   For more information about creating custom rules, refer to
   <xref linkend="sec.audit.rules"/>.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Changing Audit Rules</title>
   <para>
    After you change audit rules, always restart the audit daemon with
    <command>systemctl restart auditd.service</command> to reread the
    changed rules.
   </para>
<!-- 2011-08-25 toba: Stave Grubb has it that there is no need to stop the
       daemon before making changes to the rules.
   <para>
    Never change audit rules in a running audit system. Always stop the
    audit daemon with <command>systemctl stop auditd.service</command> before touching the
    audit configuration and reread the audit configuration by restarting the
    daemon with <command>systemctl start auditd.service</command>.
   </para>
   -->
  </important>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.audit.aurepo">
  <title>Configuring Audit Reports</title>

  <para>
   To avoid having to dig through the raw audit logs to get an impression of
   what your system is currently doing, run custom audit reports at certain
   intervals. Custom audit reports enable you to focus on areas of interest
   and get meaningful statistics on the nature and frequency of the events
   you are monitoring. To analyze individual events in detail, use the
   ausearch tool.
  </para>

  <para>
   Before setting up audit reporting, consider the following:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     What types of events do you want to monitor by generating regular
     reports? Select the appropriate aureport command lines as described in
     <xref linkend="sec.audit.aureport.gen"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     What do you want to do with the audit reports? Decide whether to create
     graphical charts from the data accumulated or whether it should be
     transferred into any sort of spreadsheet or database. Set up the
     aureport command line and further processing similar to the examples
     shown in <xref linkend="sec.audit.viz"/> if you want to visualize your
     reports.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     When and at which intervals should the reports run? Set up appropriate
     automated reporting using cron.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   For this example, assume that you are interested in finding out about any
   attempts to access your audit, PAM, and system configuration. Proceed as
   follows to find out about file events on your system:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Generate a full summary report of all events and check for any
     anomalies in the summary report, for example, have a look at the
     <quote>failed syscalls</quote> record, because these might have failed
     because of insufficient permissions to access a file or a file not
     being there at all:
    </para>
<screen><command>aureport</command>

Summary Report
======================
Range of time in logs: 03/02/09 14:13:38.225 - 17/02/09 16:30:10.352
Selected time for report: 03/02/09 14:13:38 - 17/02/09 16:30:10.352
Number of changes in configuration: 24
Number of changes to accounts, groups, or roles: 0
Number of logins: 9
Number of failed logins: 15
Number of authentications: 19
Number of failed authentications: 578
Number of users: 3
Number of terminals: 15
Number of host names: 4
Number of executables: 20
Number of files: 279
Number of AVC's: 0
Number of MAC events: 0
Number of failed syscalls: 994
Number of anomaly events: 0
Number of responses to anomaly events: 0
Number of crypto events: 0
Number of keys: 2
Number of process IDs: 1238
Number of events: 5435</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run a summary report for failed events and check the
     <quote>files</quote> record for the number of failed file access
     events:
    </para>
<screen><command>aureport</command> <option>--failed</option>

Failed Summary Report
======================
Range of time in logs: 03/02/09 14:13:38.225 - 17/02/09 16:30:10.352
Selected time for report: 03/02/09 14:13:38 - 17/02/09 16:30:10.352
Number of changes in configuration: 0
Number of changes to accounts, groups, or roles: 0
Number of logins: 0
Number of failed logins: 15
Number of authentications: 0
Number of failed authentications: 578
Number of users: 1
Number of terminals: 7
Number of host names: 4
Number of executables: 12
Number of files: 77
Number of AVC's: 0
Number of MAC events: 0
Number of failed syscalls: 994
Number of anomaly events: 0
Number of responses to anomaly events: 0
Number of crypto events: 0
Number of keys: 2
Number of process IDs: 713
Number of events: 1589</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To list the files that could not be accessed, run a summary report of
     failed file events:
    </para>
<screen><command>aureport</command> <option>-f -i --failed --summary</option>

Failed File Summary Report
===========================
total  file                
===========================
80  /var                   
80  spool                  
80  cron                   
80  lastrun                
46  /usr/lib/locale/en_GB.UTF-8/LC_CTYPE
45  /usr/lib/locale/locale-archive      
38  /usr/lib/locale/en_GB.UTF-8/LC_IDENTIFICATION
38  /usr/lib/locale/en_GB.UTF-8/LC_MEASUREMENT   
38  /usr/lib/locale/en_GB.UTF-8/LC_TELEPHONE     
38  /usr/lib/locale/en_GB.UTF-8/LC_ADDRESS       
38  /usr/lib/locale/en_GB.UTF-8/LC_NAME          
38  /usr/lib/locale/en_GB.UTF-8/LC_PAPER         
38  /usr/lib/locale/en_GB.UTF-8/LC_MESSAGES      
38  /usr/lib/locale/en_GB.UTF-8/LC_MONETARY      
38  /usr/lib/locale/en_GB.UTF-8/LC_COLLATE       
38  /usr/lib/locale/en_GB.UTF-8/LC_TIME          
38  /usr/lib/locale/en_GB.UTF-8/LC_NUMERIC       
8  /etc/magic.mgc                           
...</screen>
    <para>
     To focus this summary report on a few files or directories of interest
     only, such as <filename>/etc/audit/auditd.conf</filename>,
     <filename>/etc/pam.d</filename>, and
     <filename>/etc/sysconfig</filename>, use a command similar to the
     following:
    </para>
<screen><command>aureport -f -i --failed --summary |grep -e "/etc/audit/auditd.conf" -e "/etc/pam.d/" -e "/etc/sysconfig"</command>

1  /etc/sysconfig/displaymanager</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     From the summary report, then proceed to isolate these items of
     interest from the log and find out their event IDs for further
     analysis:
    </para>
<screen><command>aureport -f -i --failed |grep -e "/etc/audit/auditd.conf" -e "/etc/pam.d/" -e "/etc/sysconfig"</command>

993. 17/02/09 16:47:34 /etc/sysconfig/displaymanager readlink no /bin/vim-normal root 7887
994. 17/02/09 16:48:23 /etc/sysconfig/displaymanager getxattr no /bin/vim-normal root 7889</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Use the event ID to get a detailed record for each item of interest:
    </para>
<screen><command>ausearch -a</command> <replaceable>7887</replaceable> -i
----
time-&gt;Tue Feb 17 16:48:23 2009
type=PATH msg=audit(1234885703.090:7889): item=0 name="/etc/sysconfig/displaymanager" inode=369282 dev=08:06 mode=0100644 ouid=0 ogid=0 rdev=00:00
type=CWD msg=audit(1234885703.090:7889):  cwd="/root"
type=SYSCALL msg=audit(1234885703.090:7889): arch=c000003e syscall=191 success=no exit=-61 a0=7e1e20 a1=7f90e4cf9187 a2=7fffed5b57d0 a3=84 items=1 ppid=25548 pid=23045 auid=0 uid=0 gid=0 euid=0 suid=0 fsuid=0 egid=0 sgid=0 fsgid=0 tty=pts2 ses=1166 comm="vim" exe="/bin/vim-normal" key=(null)</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <tip>
   <title>Focusing on a Certain Time Frame</title>
   <para>
    If you are interested in events during a particular period of time, trim
    down the reports by using start and end dates and times with your
    <command>aureport</command> commands (<option>-ts</option> and
    <option>-te</option>). For more information, refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.audit.aureport.gen"/>.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
   All steps (except for the last one) can be run automatically and would
   easily be scriptable and configured as cron jobs. Any of the
   <literal>--failed --summary</literal> reports could be transformed easily
   into a bar chart that plots files versus failed access attempts. For more
   information about visualizing audit report data, refer to
   <xref linkend="sec.audit.viz"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.audit.viz">
  <title>Configuring Log Visualization</title>

  <para>
   Using the scripts <command>mkbar</command> and <command>mkgraph</command>
   you can illustrate your audit statistics with various graphs and charts.
   As with any other <command>aureport</command> command, the plotting
   commands are scriptable and can easily be configured to run as cron jobs.
  </para>

  <para>
   <command>mkbar</command> and <command>mkgraph</command> were created by
   Steve Grubb at Red Hat. They are available from
   <link xlink:href="http://people.redhat.com/sgrubb/audit/visualize/"/>.
   Because the current version of audit in &productname; does not ship
   with these scripts, proceed as follows to make them available on your
   system:
  </para>

  <warning>
   <para>
    Use <command>mkbar</command> and <command>mkgraph</command> at your own
    risk. Any content downloaded from the Web can be potentially dangerous
    to your system, even more when run under &rootuser; privileges.
   </para>
  </warning>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Download the scripts to &rootuser;'s <filename>~/bin</filename>
     directory:
    </para>
<screen>wget http://people.redhat.com/sgrubb/audit/visualize/mkbar -O ~/bin/mkbar
wget http://people.redhat.com/sgrubb/audit/visualize/mkgraph -O ~/bin/mkgraph</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Adjust the file permissions to read, write, and execute for
     &rootuser;:
    </para>
<screen>chmod 744 ~/bin/mk{bar,graph}</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   To plot summary reports, such as the ones discussed in
   <xref linkend="sec.audit.aurepo"/>, use the script
   <command>mkbar</command>. Some example commands could look like the
   following:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Create a Summary of Events</term>
    <listitem>
<screen>aureport -e -i --summary | mkbar events</screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Create a Summary of File Events</term>
    <listitem>
<screen>aureport -f -i --summary | mkbar files</screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Create a Summary of Login Events</term>
    <listitem>
<screen>aureport -l -i --summary | mkbar login</screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Create a Summary of User Events</term>
    <listitem>
<screen>aureport -u -i --summary | mkbar users</screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Create a Summary of System Call Events</term>
    <listitem>
<screen>aureport -s -i --summary | mkbar syscalls</screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   To create a summary chart of failed events of any of the above event
   types, add the <option>--failed</option> option to the respective
   <command>aureport</command> command. To cover a certain period of time
   only, use the <option>-ts</option> and <option>-te</option> options on
   aureport. Any of these commands can be tweaked further by narrowing down
   its scope using grep or egrep and regular expressions. See the comments
   in the <command>mkbar</command> script for an example. Any of the above
   commands produces a PNG file containing a bar chart of the requested
   data.
  </para>

  <para>
   To illustrate the relationship between different kinds of audit objects,
   such as users and system calls, use the script
   <command>mkgraph</command>. Some example commands could look like the
   following:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Users versus Executables</term>
    <listitem>
<screen>LC_ALL=C aureport -u -i | awk '/^[0-9]/ { print $4" "$7 }' | sort | uniq | mkgraph users_vs_exec</screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Users versus Files</term>
    <listitem>
<screen>LC_ALL=C aureport -f -i | awk '/^[0-9]/ { print $8" "$4 }' | sort | uniq | mkgraph users_vs_files</screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>System Calls versus Commands</term>
    <listitem>
<screen>LC_ALL=C aureport -s -i | awk '/^[0-9]/ { print $4" "$6 }' | sort | uniq | mkgraph syscall_vs_com</screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>System Calls versus Files</term>
    <listitem>
<screen>LC_ALL=C aureport -s -i | awk '/^[0-9]/ { print $5" "$4 }' | sort | uniq | mkgraph | syscall_vs_file</screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   Graphs can also be combined to illustrate complex relationships. See the
   comments in the <command>mkgraph</command> script for further information
   and an example. The graphs produced by this script are created in
   PostScript format by default, but you can change the output format by
   changing the <envar>EXT</envar> variable in the script from
   <literal>ps</literal> to <literal>png</literal> or
   <literal>jpg</literal>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
