<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" 
xml:id="Invoking">
 <title>The auto-installation process</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="Installation-process">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>
   After the system has booted into an automatic installation and the control
   file has been retrieved, &yast; configures the system according to the
   information provided in the control file. All configuration settings are
   summarized in a window that is shown by default and should be deactivated if
   a fully automatic installation is needed.
  </para>

  <para>
   By the time &yast; displays the summary of the configuration, &yast; has
   only probed hardware and prepared the system for auto-installation. Nothing
   has been changed in the system yet. In case of any error, you can still
   abort the process.
  </para>

  <para>
   A system should be automatically installable without the need to have any
   graphic adapter or monitor. Having a monitor attached to the client machine
   is nevertheless recommended so you can supervise the process and to get
   feedback in case of errors. Choose between the graphical and the text-based
   Ncurses interfaces. For headless clients, system messages can be monitored
   using the serial console.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="Installation-Interface-X11">
   <title>X11 interface (graphical)</title>
   <para>
    This is the default interface while auto-installing. No special variables
    are required to activate it.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="Installation-Interface-SerialConsole">
   <title>Serial console</title>
   <para>
    Start installing a system using the serial console by adding the keyword
    <literal>console</literal> (for example <literal>console=ttyS0</literal>)
    to the command line of the kernel. This starts <command>linuxrc</command>
    in console mode and later &yast; in serial console mode.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="Installation-Interface-Ncurses">
   <title>Text-based &yast; installation</title>
   <para>
    This option can also be activated on the command line. To start &yast; in
    text mode, add <literal>textmode=1</literal> on the command line.
   </para>
   <para>
    Starting &yast; in the text mode is recommended when installing a client
    with less than 64 MB or when X11 should not be configured, especially on
    headless machines.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="bootmedium">
  <title>Choosing the right boot medium</title>

  <para>
   There are different methods for booting the client. The computer can boot
   from its network interface card (NIC) to receive the boot images via DHCP or
   TFTP. Alternatively a suitable kernel and initrd image can be loaded from a
   flash disk (for example, a USB stick) or a bootable DVD-ROM.
  </para>

  <para>
   &yast; will check for <filename>autoinst.xml</filename> in the root
   directory of the boot medium or the initrd upon start-up and switch to an
   automated installation if it was found. In case the control file is named
   differently or located elsewhere, specify its location on the kernel command
   line with the parameter
   <literal>&ay;=<replaceable>URL</replaceable></literal>.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="bootmedium-flash">
   <title>Booting from a flash disk (for example, a USB stick)</title>
   <para>
    For testing/rescue purposes or because the NIC does not have a PROM or PXE,
    you can build a bootable flash disk to use with &ay;. Flash disks can also
    store the control file.
   </para>
   <tip>
    <title>Copying the installation medium image to a removable flash disk</title>
    <para>
     Use the following command to copy the contents of the installation image
     to a removable flash disk.
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;dd if=<replaceable>IMAGE</replaceable> of=<replaceable>FLASH_DISK</replaceable> bs=4M &amp;&amp; sync</screen>
    <para>
     <replaceable>IMAGE</replaceable> needs to be replaced with the path to the
     <filename>&installmedia;</filename> or <filename>&packagemedia;</filename>
     image file. <replaceable>FLASH_DISK</replaceable> needs to be replaced
     with the flash device. To identify the device, insert it and run:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;grep -Ff &lt;(hwinfo --disk --short) &lt;(hwinfo --usb --short)
      disk:
      /dev/sdc             General USB Flash Disk</screen>
    <para>
     Make sure the size of the device is sufficient for the desired image. You
     can check the size of the device with:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;fdisk -l /dev/sdc | grep -e "^/dev"
      /dev/sdc1  *     2048 31490047 31488000  15G 83 Linux</screen>
    <para>
     In this example, the device has a capacity of 15 GB. The command to use
     for the <filename>&packagemedia;</filename> would be:
    </para>
<screen>dd if=&packagemedia; of=/dev/sdc1 bs=4M &amp;&amp; sync</screen>
    <para>
     The device must not be mounted when running the <command>dd</command>
     command. Note that all data on the partition will be erased!
    </para>
   </tip>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="bootmedium-installer">
   <title>Booting from the &sle; installation medium</title>
   <para>
    You can use the &sle; installation medium
    (<filename>&installmedia;</filename> or
    <filename>&packagemedia;</filename>) in combination with other media. For
    example, the control file can be provided via a flash disk or a specified
    location on the network. Alternatively, create a customized installation
    media that includes the control file.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="bootmedium-pxe">
   <title>Booting via PXE over the network</title>
   <para>
    Booting via PXE requires a DHCP and a TFTP server in your network. The
    computer will then boot without a physical medium.
    <phrase
     os="sles;sled">For instructions on setting up the required
    infrastructure, see <xref linkend="cha-remote-installation"/>.</phrase>
   </para>
   <para>
    If you install via PXE, the installation will run in an endless loop. This
    happens because after the first reboot, the machine performs the PXE boot
    again and restarts the installation instead of booting from the hard
    disk<phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"> for the second stage of the
    installation</phrase>.
   </para>
   <para>
    There are several ways to solve this problem. You can use an HTTP server to
    provide the &ay; control file. Alternatively, instead of a static control
    file, run a CGI script on the Web server that provides the control file and
    changes the TFTP server configuration for your target host. This way, the
    next PXE boot of the machine will be from the hard disk by default.
   </para>
   <para>
    Another way is to use &ay; to upload a new PXE boot configuration for the
    target host via the control file:
   </para>
<screen>&lt;pxe&gt;
  &lt;pxe_localboot config:type="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/pxe_localboot&gt;
  &lt;pxelinux-config&gt;
    DEFAULT linux
    LABEL linux
    localboot 0
  &lt;/pxelinux-config&gt;
  &lt;tftp-server&gt;&tftpip;&lt;/tftp-server&gt;
  &lt;pxelinux-dir&gt;/pxelinux.cfg&lt;/pxelinux-dir&gt;
  &lt;filename&gt;__MAC__&lt;/filename&gt;
&lt;/pxe&gt;</screen>
   <para>
    This entry will upload a new configuration for the target host to the TFTP
    server shortly before the first reboot happens. In most installations the
    TFTP daemon runs as user <systemitem class="username">nobody</systemitem>.
    You need to make sure this user has write permissions to the
    <filename>pxelinux.cfg</filename> directory. You can also configure the
    file name that will be uploaded. If you use the <quote>magic</quote>
    <literal>__MAC__</literal> file name, the file name will be the MAC address
    of your machine like, for example <literal>01-08-00-27-79-49-ee</literal>.
    If the file name setting is missing, the IP address will be used for the
    file name.
   </para>
   <para>
    To do another auto-installation on the same machine, you need to remove the
    file from the TFTP server.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="invoking-autoinst">
  <title>Invoking the auto-installation process</title>

  <para>
   <remark role="fixme">Add a short description</remark>
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="invoking-autoinst-options">
   <title>Command line options</title>
   <para>
    Adding the command line variable <literal>autoyast</literal> causes
    <command>linuxrc</command> to start in automated mode. The
    <command>linuxrc</command> program searches for a configuration file, which
    should be distinguished from the main control file, in the following
    places:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      in the root directory of the initial RAM disk used for booting the
      system;
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      in the root directory of the boot medium.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    The <command>linuxrc</command> configuration file supports multiple
    keywords. For a detailed description of how <command>linuxrc</command>
    works and other keywords, see <xref linkend="appendix-linuxrc"/>. Some of
    the more common ones are:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry os="sles;sled;osuse">
     <term>autoupgrade</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Initiate an automatic upgrade using &ay;; see
       <xref linkend="CreateProfile-upgrade"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>autoyast</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Location of the control file for automatic installation; see
       <xref linkend="Commandline-ay"/> for details.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>ifcfg</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Configure and start the network. Required if the &ay; is to be fetched
       from a remote location. See <xref linkend="ay-adv-network"/> for
       details.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>insmod</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Kernel modules to load
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>install</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Location of the installation directory, for example
       <literal>install=nfs://192.168.2.1/CDs/</literal>.
      </para>
      <note>
       <title>Disabling SSL checks</title>
       <para>
         When you are using HTTPS, SSL checking is enabled by default. If 
         necessary, you can disable SSL checking by appending <literal>ssl_verify=no</literal>
          to your HTTPS URL, like the following examples:
        </para>
        <screen>install=<replaceable>https://192.168.2.1/CDs/</replaceable>?ssl_verify=no</screen>
        <para>
          If you are passing multiple query options, separate them with 
          ampersands:
        </para>
         <screen>install=<replaceable>https://192.168.2.1/CDs/</replaceable>?foo=bar&amp;ssl_verify=no</screen>       
        <para>
          See the "FTP/HTTP/HTTPS directory tree" section of 
          <command>man 8 zypper</command> for more information.
        </para>
        </note>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>instmode</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Installation mode, for example <literal>nfs</literal>,
       <literal>http</literal> etc. (not needed if <literal>install</literal>
       is set).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>rootpassword</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Password for root user if not specified in &ay; profile
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>server</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Server (NFS) to contact for source directory
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>serverdir</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Directory on NFS Server
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>y2confirm</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Even with &lt;confirm&gt;no&lt;/confirm&gt; in the control file, the
       confirm proposal comes up.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <!-- fs 2016-07-29: better use ifcfg
    <para>
    <literal>gateway</literal>
    <literal>nameserver</literal>
    <literal>netdevice</literal>
    </para>
    <para>
    Network device to use for network setup (for BOOTP and DHCP
    requests)
    </para>
    <literal>netmask</literal>
    <literal>hostip</literal>
    <para>
    When empty, client sends BOOTP request, otherwise client is
    configured with entered IP configuration.
    </para>
    -->
   <para>
    These variables and keywords will bring the system up to the point where
    &yast; can take over with the main control file. Currently, the source
    medium is automatically discovered, which in some cases makes it possible
    to initiate the auto-install process without giving any instructions to
    <command>linuxrc</command>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The traditional <command>linuxrc</command> configuration file
    (<filename>info</filename>) has the function of giving the client enough
    information about the installation server and the location of the sources.
    Usually, this file is not required, but it is needed in special network
    environments where DHCP and BOOTP are not used or when special kernel
    modules need to be loaded.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can pass keywords to <command>linuxrc</command> using the kernel
    command line. This can be done in several ways. You can specify
    <command>linuxrc</command> keywords along with other kernel parameters
    interactively at boot time, in the usual way. You can also insert kernel
    parameters into custom network-bootable disk images. It is also possible to
    configure a DHCP server to pass kernel parameters in combination with
    Etherboot or PXE.
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>Using <literal>autoyast2</literal> boot option instead of <literal>autoyast</literal></title>
    <para>
     The <literal>autoyast2</literal> option is similar to the
     <literal>autoyast</literal> option, but <command>linuxrc</command> parses
     the provided value and, for example, tries to configure a network when
     needed. This option is not described in this documentation. For
     information about differences between the &ay; and
     <command>linuxrc</command> URI syntax, see the <command>linuxrc</command>
     appendix: <xref linkend="appendix-linuxrc"/>. &ay;'s rules and classes are
     <emphasis>not</emphasis> supported.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    The command line variable <literal>autoyast</literal> can be used in the
    format described in the following list.
   </para>
   <variablelist xml:id="Commandline-ay">
    <title>&ay; control file locations</title>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Format of URIs</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The <literal>autoyast</literal> syntax for the URIs for your control
       file locations can be confusing. The format is
       SCHEMA://HOST/PATH-TO-FILE. The number of forward slashes to use varies.
       For remote locations of your control file, the URI looks like this
       example for an NFS server, with two slashes:
       <literal>autoyast=nfs://SERVER/PATH</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
       It is different when your control file is on a local file system. For
       example, <literal>autoyast=usb:///profile.xml</literal> is the same as
       <literal>autoyast=usb://localhost/profile.xml</literal>. You may omit
       the local host name, but you must keep the third slash.
       <literal>autoyast=usb://profile.xml</literal> will fail because
       <literal>profile.xml</literal> is interpreted as the host name.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>When no control file specification is needed</term>
     <listitem>
      <para os="sles;sled;osuse">
       For upgrades, no <literal>autoyast</literal> variable is needed for an
       automated offline upgrade, see
       <xref linkend="pro-upgrade-offline-upgrade-mode"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
       For new installations, <literal>autoyast</literal> will be started if a
       file named <filename>autoinst.xml</filename> is in one of the following
       three locations:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         The root directory of the installation flash disk (for example, a USB
         stick)
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         The root directory of the installation medium
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         The root directory of the initial RAM disk used to boot the system
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>autoyast=file:///<replaceable>PATH</replaceable></literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Looks for control file in the specified path, relative to the source
       root directory, for example <literal>file:///autoinst.xml</literal> when
       the control file is in the top-level directory of any local file system,
       including mounted external devices such as a CD or USB drive. (This is
       the same as
       <literal>file://<replaceable>localhost/autoinst.xml</replaceable></literal>.)
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>autoyast=device://<replaceable>DEVICE</replaceable>/<replaceable>FILENAME</replaceable></literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Looks for the control file on a storage device. Do not specify the full
       path to the device, but the device name only (for example,
       <literal>device://<replaceable>vda1/autoyast.xml</replaceable></literal>).
       You may also omit specifying the device and trigger
       <literal>autoyast</literal> to search all devices, for example,
       <literal>autoyast=device://<replaceable>localhost/autoinst.xml</replaceable></literal>,
       or
       <literal>autoyast=device:///<replaceable>autoinst.xml</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>autoyast=nfs://<replaceable>SERVER</replaceable>/<replaceable>PATH</replaceable></literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Looks for the control file on an NFS server.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>autoyast=http://[user:password@]<replaceable>SERVER</replaceable>/<replaceable>PATH</replaceable></literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Retrieves the control file from a Web server using the HTTP protocol.
       Specifying a user name and a password is optional.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>autoyast=https://[user:password@]<replaceable>SERVER</replaceable>/<replaceable>PATH</replaceable></literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Retrieves the control file from a Web server using HTTPS. Specifying a
       user name and a password is optional.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>autoyast=tftp://<replaceable>SERVER</replaceable>/<replaceable>PATH</replaceable></literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Retrieve the control file via TFTP.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>autoyast=ftp://[user:password@]<replaceable>SERVER</replaceable>/<replaceable>PATH</replaceable></literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Retrieve the control file via FTP. Specifying a user name and a password
       is optional.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>autoyast=usb:///<replaceable>PATH</replaceable></literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Retrieve the control file from USB devices (<literal>autoyast</literal>
       will search all connected USB devices).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>autoyast=relurl://<replaceable>PATH</replaceable></literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Retrieve the control file from the installation source: either from the
       default installation source or from the installation source defined in
       <literal>install=<replaceable>INSTALLATION_SOURCE_PATH</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>autoyast=cifs://<replaceable>SERVER</replaceable>/<replaceable>PATH</replaceable></literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Looks for the control file on a CIFS server.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>autoyast=label://<replaceable>LABEL</replaceable>/<replaceable>PATH</replaceable></literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Searches for a control file on a device with the specified label.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    Several scenarios for auto-installation are possible using different types
    of infrastructure and source media. The simplest way is to use the
    appropriate installation media of &productname;
    <phrase os="sles;osuse">(<filename>&installmedia;</filename> or
    <filename>&packagemedia;</filename>)</phrase>. But to initiate the
    auto-installation process, the auto-installation command line variable
    should be entered at system boot-up and the control file should be
    accessible for &yast;.
   </para>
   <para>
    In a scripting context, you can use a serial console for your virtual
    machine, that allows you to work in text mode. Then you can pass the
    required parameters from an expect script or equivalent.
   </para>
   <para>
    The following list of scenarios explains how the control file can be
    supplied:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Using the &productname; installation media</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       When using the original installation media
       <phrase os="sles;osuse">(<filename>&installmedia;</filename> or
       <filename>&packagemedia;</filename> is needed)</phrase>, the control
       file needs to be accessible via flash disk (for example, a USB stick) or
       network:
      </para>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Flash disk (for example, a USB stick)</title>
       <para>
        Access the control file via the
        <literal>autoyast=usb://<replaceable>PATH</replaceable></literal>
        option.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Network</title>
       <para>
        Access the control file via the following commands:
        <literal>autoyast=nfs://..</literal>,
        <literal>autoyast=ftp://..</literal>,
        <literal>autoyast=http://..</literal>,
        <literal>autoyast=https://..</literal>,
        <literal>autoyast=tftp://..</literal>, or
        <literal>autoyast=cifs://..</literal>. Network access needs to be
        defined using the boot options in linuxrc. This can be done via DHCP:
        <command>netsetup=dhcp
        autoyast=http://<replaceable>163.122.3.5/autoyast.xml</replaceable></command>
       </para>
      </formalpara>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Using a custom installation media</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In this case, you can include the control file directly on the
       installation media. When placing it in the root directory and naming it
       <filename>autoinst.xml</filename>, it will automatically be found and
       used for the installation. Otherwise use
       <literal>autoyast=file:///<replaceable>PATH</replaceable></literal> to
       specify the path to the control file.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Using a network installation source</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This option is the most important one because installations of multiple
       machines are usually done using SLP or NFS servers and other network
       services like BOOTP and DHCP. The easiest way to make the control file
       available is to place it in the root directory of the installation
       source, naming it <filename>autoinst.xml</filename>. In this case, it
       will automatically be found and used for the installation. The control
       file can also reside in the following places:
      </para>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Flash disk (for example, a USB stick)</title>
       <para>
        Access the control file via the
        <literal>autoyast=usb://<replaceable>PATH</replaceable></literal>
        option.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Network</title>
       <para>
        Access the control file via the following commands:
        <literal>autoyast=nfs://..</literal>,
        <literal>autoyast=ftp://..</literal>,
        <literal>autoyast=http://..</literal>,
        <literal>autoyast=https://..</literal>,
        <literal>autoyast=tftp://..</literal>, or
        <literal>autoyast=cifs://..</literal>.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <note>
    <title>Disabling network and DHCP</title>
    <para>
     To disable the network during installations where it is not needed or
     unavailable, for example when auto-installing from DVD-ROMs, use the
     <command>linuxrc</command> option <literal>netsetup=0</literal> to disable
     the network setup.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    With all &ay; invocation options it is possible to specify the location of
    the control file in the following ways:
   </para>
   <!-- numeration="arabic" -->
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Specify the exact location of the control file:
     </para>
<screen>autoyast=http://192.168.1.1/control-files/client01.xml</screen>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Specify a directory where several control files are located:
     </para>
<screen>autoyast=http://192.168.1.1/control-files/</screen>
     <para>
      In this case the relevant control file is retrieved using the hex digit
      representation of the IP as described below.
     </para>
     <para>
      The path of this directory needs to end with a <literal>/</literal>.
     </para>
     <para>
      The files in the directory must not have any extension, for example
      <literal>.xml</literal>. So the file name needs to be the IP or MAC
      address only.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;ls -r control-files
C00002 0080C8F6484C default</screen>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
   <para>
    If only the path prefix variable is defined, &yast; will fetch the control
    file from the specified location in the following way:
   </para>
   <!-- numeration="arabic" -->
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      First, it will search for the control file using its own IP address in
      uppercase hexadecimal, for example <literal>192.0.2.91 -&gt;
      C000025B</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If this file is not found, &yast; will remove one hex digit and try
      again. This action is repeated until the file with the correct name is
      found. Ultimately, it will try looking for a file with the MAC address of
      the client as the file name (mac should have the following syntax:
      <literal>0080C8F6484C</literal>) and if not found a file named
      <filename>default</filename> (in lowercase).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
   <para>
    As an example, for 192.0.2.91, the HTTP client will try:
   </para>
   <!-- role="literallayout" -->
<screen>C000025B
C000025
C00002
C0000
C000
C00
C0
C
0080C8F6484C
default</screen>
   <para>
    in that order.
   </para>
   <para>
    To determine the hex representation of the IP address of the client, use
    the utility called <command>/usr/bin/gethostip</command> available with the
    <systemitem class="resource">syslinux</systemitem> package.
   </para>
   <example>
    <title>Determine HEX code for an IP address</title>
<screen>&prompt.user;/usr/bin/gethostip 10.10.0.1
10.10.0.1 10.10.0.1 0A0A0001</screen>
   </example>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="autoinstall-singlesystem">
   <title>Auto-installing a single system</title>
   <para>
    The easiest way to auto-install a system without any network connection is
    to use the original &productname; DVD-ROMs and a flash disk (for example, a
    USB stick). You do not need to set up an installation server nor the
    network environment.
   </para>
   <para>
    Create the control file and name it <filename>autoinst.xml</filename>. Copy
    the file <filename>autoinst.xml</filename> to the flash disk.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="invoking-autoinst-linuxrc">
   <title>Combining the <command>linuxrc</command> <filename>info</filename> file with the &ay; control file</title>
   <para>
    If you choose to pass information to <command>linuxrc</command> using the
    <filename>info</filename> file or as boot options, you may integrate the
    keywords into the &ay; control file. Add an <literal>info_file</literal>
    section as shown in the example below. This section contains
    keyword&mdash;value pairs, separated by colons, one pair per line.
   </para>
   <para></para>
   <example>
    <title><command>linuxrc</command> Options in the &ay; control file</title>
<screen><![CDATA[....
  <install>
....
    <init>
        <info_file>

install: nfs://192.168.1.1/CDs/full-x86_64
dud: https://example.com/driver_updates/filename.dud
upgrade: 1
textmode: 1
      </info_file>
    </init>
......
  </install>
  ....]]>
</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    Note that the <literal>autoyast2</literal> keyword must point to the same
    file. If it is on a flash disk (for example, a USB stick), then the option
    <literal>usb://</literal> needs to be used. If the
    <filename>info</filename> file is stored in the initial RAM disk, the
    <literal>file:///</literal> option needs to be used.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 os="sles;sled;osuse" xml:id="System-Configuration">
  <title>System configuration</title>

  <para>
   The system configuration during auto-installation is the most important part
   of the whole process. As you have seen in the previous chapters, almost
   anything can be configured automatically on the target system. In addition
   to the pre-defined directives, you can always use post-scripts to change
   other things in the system. Additionally you can change any system
   variables, and if required, copy complete configuration files into the
   target system.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="System-Configuration-post">
   <title>Post-install and system configuration</title>
   <para>
    The post-installation and system configuration are initiated directly after
    the last package is installed on the target system and continue after the
    system has booted for the first time.
   </para>
   <para>
    Before the system is booted for the first time, &ay; writes all data
    collected during installation and writes the boot loader in the specified
    location. In addition to these regular tasks, &ay; executes the
    chroot-scripts as specified in the control file. Note that these scripts
    are executed while the system is not yet mounted.
   </para>
   <para>
    If a different kernel than the default is installed, a hard reboot will be
    required. A hard reboot can also be forced during auto-installation,
    independent of the installed kernel. Use the <literal>reboot</literal>
    property of the <literal>general</literal> resource (see
    <xref linkend="CreateProfile-General"/>).
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="System-Configuration-custom">
   <title>System customization</title>
   <para>
    Most of the system customization is done in the second stage of the
    installation. If you require customization that cannot be done using &ay;
    resources, use post-install scripts for further modifications.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can define an unlimited number of custom scripts in the control file,
    either by editing the control file or by using the configuration system.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
