<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" role="General" 
  xml:id="cha-autoyast-control-file"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>The &ay; control file</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="Profile-Intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>
   A <emphasis>control file</emphasis>, also known as a
   <emphasis>profile</emphasis>, is a configuration description for a single
   system. It consists of sets of resources with properties including support
   for complex structures such as lists, records, trees and large embedded or
   referenced objects.
  </para>

  <important os="osuse;sles;sled">
   <title>Control files from OS releases older than &slsa; 12&nbsp;GA and &opensuse; 42.0 are incompatible</title>
   <para>
    Many major changes were introduced with &slsa; 12 and &opensuse; Leap 42.0,
    such as the switch to systemd and &grub;. These changes also required
    fundamental changes in &ay; Therefore you cannot use &ay; control files
    created on &slsa; 11 to install &productname; &productnumber; and vice
    versa.
   </para>
  </important>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="Profile-Format">
  <title>Format</title>

  <para>
   The XML configuration format provides a consistent file structure, which is
   easy to learn and to remember when attempting to configure a new system.
  </para>

  <para>
   The &ay; control file uses XML to describe the system installation and
   configuration. XML is a commonly used markup, and many users are familiar
   with the concepts of the language and the tools used to process XML files.
   If you edit an existing control file or create a control file using an
   editor from scratch, it is strongly recommended to validate the control
   file. This can be done using a validating XML parser such as
   <literal>xmllint</literal> or <literal>jing</literal>, for example (see
   <xref linkend="CreateProfile-Manual"/>).
  </para>

  <para>
   The following example shows a control file in XML format:
  </para>

  <example>
   <title>&ay; control file (profile)</title>
<screen>&lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;
&lt;!DOCTYPE profile&gt;
&lt;profile
  xmlns="http://www.suse.com/1.0/yast2ns"
  xmlns:config="http://www.suse.com/1.0/configns"&gt;
  &lt;partitioning config:type="list"&gt;
    &lt;drive&gt;
      &lt;device&gt;/dev/sda&lt;/device&gt;
      &lt;partitions config:type="list"&gt;
        &lt;partition&gt;
          &lt;filesystem config:type="symbol"&gt;btrfs&lt;/filesystem&gt;
          &lt;size&gt;10G&lt;/size&gt;
          &lt;mount&gt;/&lt;/mount&gt;
        &lt;/partition&gt;
        &lt;partition&gt;
          &lt;filesystem config:type="symbol"&gt;xfs&lt;/filesystem&gt;
          &lt;size&gt;120G&lt;/size&gt;
          &lt;mount&gt;/data&lt;/mount&gt;
        &lt;/partition&gt;
      &lt;/partitions&gt;
    &lt;/drive&gt;
  &lt;/partitioning&gt;
  &lt;scripts&gt;
    &lt;pre-scripts&gt;
      &lt;script&gt;
        &lt;interpreter&gt;shell&lt;/interpreter&gt;
        &lt;filename&gt;start.sh&lt;/filename&gt;
        &lt;source&gt;
        &lt;![CDATA[
#!/bin/sh
echo "Starting installation"
exit 0

]]&gt;

        &lt;/source&gt;
      &lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;/pre-scripts&gt;
  &lt;/scripts&gt;
&lt;/profile&gt;</screen>
  </example>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="Profile-Structure">
  <title>Structure</title>

  <para>
   Below is an example of a basic control file container, the actual content of
   which is explained later on in this chapter.
  </para>

  <example>
   <title>Control file container</title>
<screen>&lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;
&lt;!DOCTYPE profile&gt;
&lt;profile
  xmlns="http://www.suse.com/1.0/yast2ns"
  xmlns:config="http://www.suse.com/1.0/configns"&gt;
  &lt;!-- RESOURCES --&gt;
&lt;/profile&gt;</screen>
  </example>

  <para>
   The <literal>&lt;profile&gt;</literal> element (root node) contains one or
   more distinct resource elements. The permissible resource elements are
   specified in the schema files
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="Profile-Format-ressources">
   <title>Resources and properties</title>
   <para>
    A resource element either contains multiple and distinct property and
    resource elements, or multiple instances of the same resource element, or
    it is empty. The permissible content of a resource element is specified in
    the schema files.
   </para>
   <para>
    A property element is either empty or contains a literal value. The
    permissible property elements and values in each resource element are
    specified in the schema files
   </para>
   <para>
    An element can be either a container of other elements (a resource) or it
    has a literal value (a property); it can never be both. This restriction is
    specified in the schema files. A configuration component with more than one
    value must either be represented as an embedded list in a property value or
    as a nested resource.
   </para>
   <para>
    An empty element, such as <literal>&lt;foo&gt;&lt;/foo&gt;</literal> or
    <literal>&lt;bar/&gt;</literal>, will <emphasis>not</emphasis> be in the
    parsed data model. Usually this is interpreted as wanting a sensible
    default value. In cases where you need an explicitly empty string instead,
    use a CDATA section:
    <literal>&lt;foo&gt;&lt;![CDATA[]]&gt;&lt;/foo&gt;</literal>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="Profile-Format-ressources-nested">
   <title>Nested resources</title>
   <para>
    Nested resource elements allow a tree-like structure of configuration
    components to be built to any level.
   </para>
   <para>
    There are two kinds of nested resources: maps and lists. Maps, also known
    as associative arrays, hashes, or dictionaries, contain mixed contents,
    identified by their tag names. Lists, or arrays, have all items of the same
    type.
   </para>
   <example>
    <title>Nested resources</title>
<screen>...
&lt;drive&gt;
  &lt;device&gt;/dev/sda&lt;/device&gt;
  &lt;partitions config:type="list"&gt;
     &lt;partition&gt;
        &lt;size&gt;10G&lt;/size&gt;
        &lt;mount&gt;/&lt;/mount&gt;
     &lt;/partition&gt;
     &lt;partition&gt;
        &lt;size&gt;1G&lt;/size&gt;
        &lt;mount&gt;/tmp&lt;/mount&gt;
     &lt;/partition&gt;
  &lt;/partitions&gt;
&lt;/drive&gt;
....</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    In the example above, the <literal>drive</literal> resource is a map
    consisting of a <literal>device</literal> property and a
    <literal>partitions</literal> resource. The <literal>partitions</literal>
    resource is a list containing multiple instances of the
    <literal>partition</literal> resource. Each <literal>partition</literal>
    resource is a map containing a <literal>size</literal> and
    <literal>mount</literal> property.
   </para>
   <para>
    The default type of a nested resource is map, although you can specify it
    as you want. Lists must be marked as such using the
    <literal>config:type="list"</literal> attribute.
   </para>
   <tip>
    <title>Using sorter type annotations</title>
    <para>
     Starting with &productname; <phrase os="sles;sled">15 SP3</phrase>
     <phrase os="osuse">15.3</phrase><phrase os="slemicro">5.0</phrase>, it is
     possible to use the attribute <literal>t</literal> instead of
     <literal>config:type</literal> to specify the element type.
    </para>
<screen>&lt;mode t="boolean"&gt;true&lt;/mode&gt;</screen>
   </tip>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="Profile-Format-attributes">
   <title>Attributes</title>
   <para>
    Global attributes are used to define metadata on resources and properties.
    Attributes are used to define context switching. They are also used for
    naming and typing properties as shown in the previous sections. Attributes
    are in a separate namespace so they do not need to be treated as reserved
    words in the default namespace.
   </para>
   <para>
    The <literal>config:type</literal> attribute determines the type of the
    resource or property in the parsed data model. For resources, lists need a
    <literal>list</literal> type whereas a map is the default type that does
    not need an attribute. There is one exception. When the map is empty, it
    needs to be marked as a map so it does not get confused with a simple
    string value.
   </para>
   <example>
    <title>An empty map</title>
<screen>&lt;general t="map" /&gt;</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    For properties, <literal>boolean</literal>, <literal>symbol</literal>, and
    <literal>integer</literal> can be used, the default being a string.
   </para>
   <para>
    Except for map and string values, as explained before, attributes are not
    optional. It may appear that attributes are optional, because various parts
    of the schema are not very consistent in their usage of data types. In some
    places an enumeration is represented by a symbol, elsewhere a string is
    required. One resource needs <literal>config:type="integer"</literal>,
    another will parse the number from a string property. Some resources use
    <literal>config:type="boolean"</literal>, others want
    <literal>yes</literal> or even <literal>1</literal>. If in doubt, consult
    the schema file.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
