<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<!--
ATM, root priveledges are required.  I consider this a bug:
http://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=579894
If it will not get fixed, we probably must document it.
taroth 2011-08-05: bug was fixed, but only temporarily, reopened for SP2 -
taroth 2013-02-19: reopended for SP3
-->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-userbackup">
 <title>Backing Up User Data</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    The Backup tool is a simple framework to let users back up and restore
    their own data such as home directories or selected files. It is possible
    to create scheduled backups or backups on request, and to play back a
    previous state of this data.
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
<para>
 To start the <guimenu>Backups</guimenu> application open the Activities
 Overview by pressing <keycap function="meta"/> and search for
 <literal>back</literal>.
</para>

<informalfigure>
 <mediaobject>
  <textobject role="description">
   <phrase>&gnome; backup</phrase>
  </textobject>
  <imageobject role="fo">
   <imagedata fileref="gnome_backup.png" width="75%"/>
  </imageobject>
  <imageobject role="html">
   <imagedata fileref="gnome_backup.png" width="75%"/>
  </imageobject>
 </mediaobject>
</informalfigure>

<sect1 xml:id="sec-gnome-backup-config">
 <title>Configuring Backups</title>
 <para>
  Before you can start to backup data, configure which files to back up, which
  ones to ignore and where to store the backup.
 </para>
 <procedure>
  <step>
   <para>
    Configure which folders to back up by clicking <guimenu>Folders to
    save</guimenu>. By default, your home directory is preconfigured. Use the
    plus and minus signs to add or delete folders.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Optionally, configure folders that should be ignored when backing up data
    by clicking <guimenu>Folders to ignore</guimenu>. By default the trash bin
    and the <filename>Download</filename> directory are preconfigured. Use the
    plus and minus signs to add or delete folders.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    To define a location where to store the backup, click <guimenu>Storage
    Location</guimenu>. You may choose a <guimenu>Local Folder</guimenu>, a
    <guimenu>Network Server</guimenu>, or an cloud storage. If you opt for the
    latter, either choose an existing service from the list or add a service by
    clicking <guimenu>Open Online Account Settings</guimenu>. Make sure you
    have provided your login credentials for the respective online service via
    <guimenu>Open Online Account Settings</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Regardless of the Storage location, provide a directory name under which
    the backup(s) will be stored. It is recommended to choose a name that can
    easily be associated with backups for the respective machine and data.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="sec-gnome-backup-start">
 <title>Creating Backups</title>
 <para>
  Once you have configured which folders to back up and where to store them,
  you have two choices for backing up. First, by manually starting the
  backup. Switch to the <guimenu>Overview</guimenu> screen and click
  <guimenu>Back Up Now</guimenu>. Choose whether you want to protect the backup
  with a password or not. Proceed with <guimenu>Forward</guimenu>.
 </para>
 <para>
  The second option is to schedule automatic backups: Create a backup schedule
  by clicking <guimenu>Scheduling</guimenu>. Enter the backup frequency and
  decide how long to keep backups. Enable scheduled backups by turning the
  <guimenu>Automatic Backup</guimenu> switch <guimenu>On</guimenu>.
 </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="cha-userbackup-restore">
 <title>Restoring Data</title>

 <para>
  To restore a previous state of your data, switch to the
  <guimenu>Overview</guimenu> screen and click
  <guimenu>Restore</guimenu>.
 </para>

 <procedure>
  <step>
   <para>
    Choose a backup location, a directory name and
    proceed with <guimenu>Forward</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Select the backup date which you want to restore and
    proceed with <guimenu>Forward</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Choose whether to restore the files from the backup to their original
    location or to a different directory. Proceed with
    <guimenu>Forward</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Review your settings. If necessary, go <guimenu>Back</guimenu> to change
    them. To start restoring data from the backup, click
    <guimenu>Restore</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
