<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-ntp">
<!-- =============================================================== -->
<!-- ==                                                           == -->
<!-- =============================================================== -->
 <title>Time Synchronization with NTP</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    The NTP (network time protocol) mechanism is a protocol for synchronizing
    the system time over the network. First, a machine can obtain the time from
    a server that is a reliable time source. Second, a machine can itself act
    as a time source for other computers in the network. The goal is
    twofold&mdash;maintaining the absolute time and synchronizing the system
    time of all machines within a network.
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  Maintaining an exact system time is important in many situations. The
  built-in hardware clock does often not meet the requirements of applications
  such as databases or clusters. Manual correction of the system time would
  lead to severe problems because, for example, a backward leap can cause
  malfunction of critical applications. Within a network, it is usually
  necessary to synchronize the system time of all machines, but manual time
  adjustment is a bad approach. NTP provides a mechanism to solve these
  problems. The NTP service continuously adjusts the system time with reliable
  time servers in the network. It further enables the management of local
  reference clocks, such as radio-controlled clocks.
 </para>
 <para>
  Since &productname; 15, &chrony; is the default implementation of NTP.
  &chrony; includes two parts; &chronyd; is a daemon that can be started at
  boot time and &chronyc; is a command line interface program to monitor the
  performance of &chronyd;, and to change various operating parameters at
  runtime.
 </para>
 <para>
  Starting with &productname;&nbsp;15.2, the &yast; module for NTP client
  configuration configures the systemd-timer instead of the cron daemon
  to execute &chrony;, when it is not configured to run as a daemon.
 </para>
 <note os="sled;osuse">
  <para>
   To enable time synchronization by means of active directory, follow the
   instructions found at <xref linkend="proc-ad-join"/>.
  </para>
 </note>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ntp-yast">
  <title>Configuring an NTP Client with &yast;</title>

  <para>
   The NTP daemon (&chronyd;) coming with the <systemitem>chrony</systemitem>
   package is preset to use the local computer hardware clock as a time
   reference. The precision of the hardware clock heavily depends on its time
   source. For example, an atomic clock or GPS receiver is a very precise time
   source, while a common RTC chip is not a reliable time source. &yast;
   simplifies the configuration of an NTP client.
  </para>

  <para>
   In the &yast; NTP client configuration (<menuchoice><guimenu>Network
   Services</guimenu> <guimenu>NTP Configuration</guimenu></menuchoice>)
   window, you can specify when to start the NTP daemon, the type of the
   configuration source, and add custom time servers.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>NTP Configuration Window</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="ntp_client.png" width="70%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="ntp_client.png" width="70%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect2>
   <title>NTP Daemon Start</title>
   <para>
    You can choose from three options for when to start the NTP daemon:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Only Manually</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Select <guimenu>Only Manually</guimenu>, if you want to manually start
       the &chrony; daemon.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Synchronize without Daemon</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Select <guimenu>Synchronize without Daemon</guimenu> to set the system
       time periodically without a permanently running &chrony;. You can set
       the <guimenu>Interval of the Synchronization in Minutes</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Now and On Boot</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Select <guimenu>Now and On Boot</guimenu> to start &chronyd;
       automatically when the system is booted. This setting is recommended.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Type of the Configuration Source</title>
   <para>
    In the <guimenu>Configuration Source</guimenu> drop-down box, select
    either <guimenu>Dynamic</guimenu> or <guimenu>Static</guimenu>. Set
    <guimenu>Static</guimenu> if your server uses only a fixed set of (public)
    NTP servers, while <guimenu>Dynamic</guimenu> is better if your internal
    network offers NTP servers via DHCP.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-net-ntp-yast-new-sync">
   <title>Configure Time Servers</title>
   <para>
    Time servers for the client to query are listed in the lower part of the
    <guimenu>NTP Configuration</guimenu> window. Modify this list as needed
    with <guimenu>Add</guimenu>, <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>, and
    <guimenu>Delete</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Click <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to add a new time server:
   </para>
   <figure>
    <title>Adding a Time Server</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="ntp_client_serveradd.png" width="70%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="ntp_client_serveradd.png" width="70%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the <guimenu>Address</guimenu> field, type the URL of the time server
      or pool of time servers with which you want to synchronize the machine
      time. After the URL is complete, click <guimenu>Test</guimenu> to verify
      that it points to a valid time source.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Activate <guimenu>Quick Initial Sync</guimenu> to speed up the time
      synchronization by sending more requests at the &chronyd; daemon start.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Activate <guimenu>Start Offline</guimenu> to speed up the boot time on
      systems that start the &chronyd; daemon automatically and may not have an
      Internet connection at boot time. This option is useful, for example, for
      laptops with network connection managed by &nm;.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Confirm with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

<!-- ==================================================================== -->
 </sect1>
<!-- =============================================================== -->
<!-- ==                                                           == -->
<!-- =============================================================== -->
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-netz-xntp-netconf">
  <title>Manually Configuring NTP in the Network</title>

  <para>
   &chrony; reads its configuration from the
   <filename>/etc/chrony.conf</filename> file. To keep the computer clock
   synchronized, you need to tell &chrony; what time servers to use. You can
   use specific server names or IP addresses, for example:
  </para>

<screen>0.suse.pool.ntp.org
1.suse.pool.ntp.org
2.suse.pool.ntp.org
3.suse.pool.ntp.org</screen>

  <para>
   You can also specify a <emphasis>pool</emphasis> name. Pool name resolves to
   several IP addresses:
  </para>

<screen>pool pool.ntp.org</screen>

  <tip>
   <title>Computers on the Same Network</title>
   <para>
    To synchronize time on multiple computers on the same network, we do not
    recommend to synchronize all of them with an external server. A good
    practice is to make one computer the time server which is synchronized with
    an external time server, and the other computers act as its clients. Add a
    <literal>local</literal> directive to the server's
    <filename>/etc/chrony.conf</filename> to distinguish it from an
    authoritative time server:
   </para>
<screen>local stratum 10</screen>
  </tip>

  <para>
   To start &chrony;, run:
  </para>

<screen>systemctl start chronyd.service</screen>

  <para>
   After initializing &chronyd;, it takes some time before the time is
   stabilized and the drift file for correcting the local computer clock is
   created. With the drift file, the systematic error of the hardware clock can
   be computed when the computer is powered on. The correction is used
   immediately, resulting in a higher stability of the system time.
  </para>

  <para>
   To enable the service so that &chrony; starts automatically at boot time,
   run:
  </para>

<screen>systemctl enable chronyd.service</screen>
  <warning>
   <title>Conflicting <systemitem class="daemon">yast-timesync.service</systemitem> service</title>
   <para>
    In addition to the <systemitem class="daemon">chronyd.service</systemitem>
    service, &productnameshort; includes <systemitem
    class="daemon">yast-timesync.service</systemitem>. <systemitem
    class="daemon">yast-timesync.service</systemitem> is triggered by a timer
    every 5 minutes and runs &chronyd; with the <option>-q</option> option to
    set the system time and exit. Because only one instance of &chronyd; can be
    running at any given time, do not enable or start both &chronyd;-related
    services at the same time.
   </para>
  </warning>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="ntp-chronyc">
  <title>Configure &chronyd; at Runtime Using &chronyc;</title>

  <para>
   You can use &chronyc; to change the behavior of &chronyd; at runtime. It
   also generates status reports about the operation of &chronyd;.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can run &chronyc; either in interactive or non-interactive mode. To
   run &chronyc; interactively, enter &chronyc; on the command line. It
   displays a prompt and waits for your command input. For example, to check
   how many NTP sources are online or offline, run:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.root;&chronyc;
chronyc> activity
200 OK
4 sources online
2 sources offline
1 sources doing burst (return to online)
1 sources doing burst (return to offline)
0 sources with unknown address</screen>

  <para>
   To exit &chronyc;'s prompt, enter <command>quit</command> or
   <command>exit</command>.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you do not need to use the interactive prompt, enter the command
   directly:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.root;&chronyc; activity</screen>

  <note>
   <title>Temporary Changes</title>
   <para>
    Changes made using &chronyc; are not permanent. They will be lost after the
    next &chronyd; restart. For permanent changes, modify
    <filename>/etc/chrony.conf</filename>.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   For a complete list of &chronyc; commands, see its manual page (<command>man
   1 chronyc</command>).
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-netz-xntp-dynamic">
  <title>Dynamic Time Synchronization at Runtime</title>

<!-- For reference see fate#306288 -->

  <para>
  Although &chronyd; starts up normally on a system that boots without a network
  connection, the tool cannot resolve the DNS names of the time servers
  specified in the configuration file.
  </para>

  <para>
   &chronyd; keeps trying to resolve the time server names specified by the
   <option>server</option>, <option>pool</option>, and <option>peer</option>
   directives in an increasing time interval until it succeeds.
  </para>

  <para>
   If the time server will not be reachable when &chronyd; is started, you can
   specify the <option>offline</option> option:
  </para>

<screen>server <replaceable>server_address</replaceable> offline</screen>

  <para>
   &chronyd; will then not try to poll the server until it is enabled using the
   following command:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.root;chronyc online <replaceable>server_address</replaceable></screen>

  <para>
   When the <option>auto_offline</option> option is set, &chronyd; assumes that
   the time server has gone offline when two requests have been sent to it
   without receiving a response. This option avoids the need to run the
   'offline' command from &chronyc; when disconnecting the network link.
  </para>
 </sect1>
<!-- =============================================================== -->
<!-- ==                                                           == -->
<!-- =============================================================== -->
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-netz-xntp-normal">
  <title>Setting Up a Local Reference Clock</title>

  <para>
   The software package &chrony; relies on other programs (such as
   <systemitem>gpsd</systemitem>) to access the timing data via the SHM or SOCK
   driver. Use the <option>refclock</option> directive in
   <filename>/etc/chrony.conf</filename> to specify a hardware reference clock
   to be used as a time source. It has two mandatory parameters: a driver name
   and a driver-specific parameter. The two parameters are followed by zero or
   more <option>refclock</option> options. &chronyd; includes the following
   drivers:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     PPS - driver for the kernel 'pulse per second' API. For example:
    </para>
<screen>refclock PPS /dev/pps0 lock NMEA refid GPS</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     SHM - NTP shared memory driver. For example:
    </para>
<screen>refclock SHM 0 poll 3 refid GPS1
refclock SHM 1:perm=0644 refid GPS2</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     SOCK - Unix domain socket driver. For example:
    </para>
<screen>refclock SOCK /var/run/chrony.ttyS0.sock</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     PHC - PTP hardware clock driver. For example:
    </para>
<screen>refclock PHC /dev/ptp0 poll 0 dpoll -2 offset -37
refclock PHC /dev/ptp1:nocrossts poll 3 pps</screen>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   For more information on individual drivers' options, see <command>man 8
   chrony.conf</command>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-netz-xntp-etr" arch="zseries">
  <title>Clock Synchronization to an External Time Reference (ETR)</title>

<!-- taken from bnc#341392; also see fate#301693 -->

  <para>
   Support for clock synchronization to an external time reference (ETR) is
   available. The external time reference sends an oscillator signal and a
   synchronization signal every 2**20 (2 to the power of 20) microseconds to
   keep TOD clocks of all connected servers synchronized.
  </para>

  <para>
   For availability two ETR units can be connected to a machine. If the clock
   deviates for more than the sync-check tolerance all CPUs get a machine check
   that indicates that the clock is not synchronized. If this happens, all DASD I/O
   to XRC enabled devices is stopped until the clock is synchronized again.
  </para>

  <para>
   The ETR support is activated via two <literal>sysfs</literal> attributes;
   run the following commands as &rootuser;:
  </para>

<screen>echo 1 &gt; /sys/devices/system/etr/etr0/online
echo 1 &gt; /sys/devices/system/etr/etr1/online
</screen>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
