<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<sect1 version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Support</title>

 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
    <!--<dm:assignee></dm:assignee>-->
   </dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>

 <para>
  Find the support statement for &productname; and general information about
  technology previews below. For details about the product life cycle, see
  <xref os="sles;slemicro" linkend="cha-upgrade-background"/>.
 </para>

 <para os="sles;sled;osuse">
  If you are entitled to support, find details on how to collect information
  for a support ticket in <xref linkend="cha-adm-support"/>.
 </para>

 <sect2>
  <title>Support statement for &productname;</title>
  <para>
   To receive support, you need an appropriate subscription with &suse;. To
   view the specific support offerings available to you, go to
   <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/"/> and select your product.
  </para>
  <para>
   The support levels are defined as follows:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>L1</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Problem determination, which means technical support designed to provide
      compatibility information, usage support, ongoing maintenance,
      information gathering and basic troubleshooting using available
      documentation.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>L2</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Problem isolation, which means technical support designed to analyze
      data, reproduce customer problems, isolate problem area and provide a
      resolution for problems not resolved by Level&nbsp;1 or prepare for
      Level&nbsp;3.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>L3</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Problem resolution, which means technical support designed to resolve
      problems by engaging engineering to resolve product defects which have
      been identified by Level&nbsp;2 Support.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
   For contracted customers and partners, &productname; is delivered with L3
   support for all packages, except for the following:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem os="sles;sled">
    <para>
     technology previews.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     sound, graphics, fonts, and artwork.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     packages that require an additional customer contract.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem os="sles;sled">
    <para>
     some packages shipped as part of the module <emphasis>Workstation
     Extension</emphasis> are L2-supported only.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     packages with names ending in <package>-devel</package> (containing header
     files and similar developer resources) will only be supported together
     with their main packages.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   &suse; will only support the usage of original packages. That is, packages
   that are unchanged and not recompiled.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 os="sles;sled">
  <title>Technology previews</title>
  <para>
   Technology previews are packages, stacks, or features delivered by &suse; to
   provide glimpses into upcoming innovations. The previews are included for
   your convenience to give you the chance to test new technologies within your
   environment. We would appreciate your feedback! If you test a technology
   preview, contact your &suse; representative and let them know about your
   experience and use cases. Your input is helpful for future development.
  </para>
  <para>
   However, technology previews come with the following limitations:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Technology previews are still in development. Therefore, they may be
     functionally incomplete, unstable, or in other ways
     <emphasis>not</emphasis> suitable for production use.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Technology previews are <emphasis>not</emphasis> supported.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Technology previews may only be available for specific hardware
     architectures.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Details and functionality of technology previews are subject to change. As
     a result, upgrading to subsequent releases of a technology preview may be
     impossible and require a fresh installation.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Technology previews can be dropped at any time. For example, if &suse;
     discovers that a preview does not meet the customer or market needs, or
     does not prove to comply with enterprise standards. &suse; does not commit
     to providing a supported version of such technologies in the future.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   For an overview of technology previews shipped with your product, see the
   release notes at <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/"/>.
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
