<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha-containers-build"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <info>
  <title>Building Containers</title>
 </info>
 <para>
  This chapter provides an overview of tools for creating containers. Most of the tools mentioned below are part of the
  <emphasis role="strong">&sls; 15 SP2 Containers Module</emphasis>. You can
  see the full list of packages in the <emphasis role="strong">Containers
  Module</emphasis> in the &suse;
  <link xlink:href="https://scc.suse.com/packages?name=SUSE%20Linux%20Enterprise%20Server&amp;version=15.2&amp;arch=x86_64&amp;query=&amp;module=1963">Customer
  Center</link>.
 </para>
 <sect1 xml:id="id-build-tools-available-to-customers">
  <title>Build Tools Available to Customers</title>

  <sect2 xml:id="id-docker">
   <title>Docker</title>
   <para>
    Docker is a system for creating and managing containers. Its core is
    the <emphasis role="strong">Docker Open Source Engine</emphasis>&mdash;a
    lightweight virtualization solution to run containers simultaneously on a
    single control host. Docker containers are defined using Dockerfiles. A Dockerfiles describes how to assemble a private filesystem for a container. The file can also
    contain metadata that describes how to run the container. Most Dockerfiles
    start from a parent image. For an introduction on how to create custom base
    &sle; docker images, see <xref linkend="book-sles-docker"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="podman">
   <title>Podman</title>
   <para>
    Podman is short for Pod Manager tool,
    and its purpose extends beyond just building images. It is a
    daemonless container engine for
    developing, managing, and running Open Containers
    Initiative (OCI) containers on a Linux system, and
    it offers a drop-in alternative for Docker. Podman is the default
    container runtime in openSUSE
    Kubic&mdash;a certified Kubernetes distribution built on top of &opensuse;. Podman
    can be used to create OCI-compliant container images using a Dockerfile and
    a range of commands similar to Docker. For example, the <literal>podman
    build</literal> command performs the same task as
    <literal>docker build</literal>, except that it does not use the Docker
    daemon to do it. Another important feature of Podman are rootless container builds. Because Podman relies on user namespaces&mdash;which provide an isolation mechanism for Linux processes&mdash;it does not require root privileges to create and run containers.
   </para>
   <para>
    For instructions on how to install and use Podman see
    <link xlink:href="https://podman.io/">the Podman Documentation</link>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="id-buildah">
   <title>Buildah</title>
   <para>
    Buildah facilitates building OCI container images. It is a complimentary tool to
    Podman (see<xref linkend="podman"/> ), and <literal>podman
    build</literal> uses Buildah to perform container image builds. Buildah makes it possible to build images from existing images, from scratch, and using Dockerfiles.
    OCI images built using the Buildah command-line
    tool and the underlying OCI-based technologies (for
    example, containers/image and containers/storage) are portable and can
    therefore run in a Docker environment.
   </para>
   <para>
    For instructions on how to install and use Buildah see
    the <link xlink:href="https://buildah.io/">Buildah Documentation</link> and
    <link xlink:href="https://github.com/containers/buildah/blob/master/docs/tutorials">tutorials</link>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="id-suse-internal-build-tools">
  <title>Internal SUSE Build Tools</title>

  <sect2 xml:id="id-open-build-service">
   <title>Open Build Service</title>
   <para>
    The Open Build Service (OBS) provides
    free infrastructure for building and storing RPM packages including various
    container formats. The
    <link xlink:href="https://registry.opensuse.org/cgi-bin/cooverview">OBS
    Container Registry</link> provides a detailed listing of all container
    images built by the OBS complete with commands for pulling the images
    into your local docker environment. The OBS &opensuse;
    <link xlink:href="https://build.opensuse.org/image_templates">container
    image templates</link> can be modified to specific needs, which offers the
    easiest way to create your own container branch. Container images can be built with native Docker tools from an existing image using a Dockerfile. Alternatively, images can be built
    from scratch using the &kiwi; image building
    solution.
   </para>
   <para>
    Instructions on how to build images on OBS can be found at
    <link xlink:href="https://openbuildservice.org/2018/05/09/container-building-and-distribution/"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="id-kiwi">
   <title>&kiwi;</title>
   <para>
    KIWI Next Generation is a multi purpose
    image building solution. In addition to container images, regular installation ISO images, and
    images for virtual machines, &kiwi; can build images that boot via PXE
    or Vagrant boxes. The main building block in &kiwi; is an image XML description, a directory that includes the
    <filename>config.xml</filename> or <filename>.kiwi</filename> file along with scripts or configuration data. The image
    creation process with &kiwi; is fully automated and does not require any user
    interaction. Any information required for the image creation process is
    provided by the primary configuration file <literal>config.xml</literal>.
    The image can be customized using the
    <filename>config.sh</filename> and <filename>images.sh</filename> scripts.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     It is important to distinguish between KIWI NG (currently version 9.20.9)
     and its unmaintained legacy versions (7.x.x or older), now called
     <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/kiwi/">KIWI
     Legacy</link>.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    For specific information on how to install &kiwi; and use it to build
    images, see the <link xlink:href="http://osinside.github.io/kiwi/">KIWI
    documentation</link>. A collection of example image descriptions can be
    found on the
    <link xlink:href="https://github.com/OSInside/kiwi-descriptions">KIWI
    GitHub repository</link>.
   </para>
   <para>
    &kiwi;'s man pages provide information on using the tool. To access man pages, install the <package>kiwi-man-pages</package> package.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="id-building-official-slea-images">
  <title>Building Official &slea; Images</title>

  <para>
  Images are considered official only if they are built using the Internal Build Service.
  </para>

  <para>
   There are no official &slea; container images on
   <link xlink:href="https://build.opensuse.org" />, and the RPMs exported there
   are not identical to the internal ones. This means that it is not
   possible to build officially supported images on
   <link xlink:href="https://build.opensuse.org" />.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
