<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha-containers-troubleshoot"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <info>
  <title>Troubleshooting</title>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-container-diff">
  <title>Analyze container images with container-diff</title>

  <para>
   In case a custom &deng; container image built on top of the &slea; base
   container image is not working as expected, the
   <package>container-diff</package> tool can help you analyze the image and
   collect information relevant for troubleshooting.
  </para>

  <para>
   <package>container-diff</package> makes it possible to analyze image changes
   by computing differences between images and presenting the diff in a
   human-readable and actionable format. The tool can find differences in
   system packages, language-level packages, and files in a container image.
  </para>

  <para>
   <package>container-diff</package> can handle local container images (using
   the prefix <literal>daemon://</literal>), images in a remote registry (using
   the prefix <literal>remote://</literal>), and images saved as
   <literal>.tar</literal> archives. You can use
   <package>container-diff</package> to compute the diff between a local
   version of an image and a remote version.
  </para>

  <para>
   To install <package>container-diff</package>, run the <command>sudo zypper
   in container-diff</command> command.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-container-diff-basics">
   <title>Basic container-diff commands</title>
   <para>
    The command <command>container-diff analyze
    <replaceable>IMAGE</replaceable></command> runs a standard analysis on a
    single image. By default, it returns a hash and size of the container image.
    For more information that can help you to identify and fix problems, use
    the specific analyzers. Use the <literal>--type</literal> parameter to
    specify the desired analyzer. Two of the most useful analyzers are
    <literal>history</literal> (returns a list of descriptions of how an image
    layer was created) and <literal>file</literal> (returns a list of file
    system contents, including names, paths, and sizes):
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;sudo container-diff analyze --type=history daemon://<replaceable>IMAGE</replaceable>
&prompt.user;sudo container-diff analyze --type=file daemon://<replaceable>IMAGE</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    To view all available parameters and their brief descriptions, run the
    <command>container-diff analyze --help</command> command.
   </para>
   <para>
    Using the <command>container-diff diff</command> command, you can compare
    two container images and examine differences between them. Similar to the
    <command>container-diff analyze</command> command, <command>container-diff
    diff</command> supports several parameters. The example command below
    compares two images and returns a list of descriptions of how IMAGE_2 was
    created from IMAGE_1.
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;sudo container-diff diff daemon://<replaceable>IMAGE_1</replaceable> daemon://<replaceable>IMAGE_2</replaceable> --type=history</screen>
   <para>
    To view all available parameters and their brief descriptions, run the
    <command>container-diff diff --help</command> command.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
