<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
    [
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<chapter xml:id="cha-buildah-overview" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>&buildah; overview</title>
 <para>
  <link xlink:href="https://buildah.io/">&buildah;</link> is tool for building
  OCI-compliant container images. &buildah; can handle the following tasks:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Create containers from scratch or from existing images.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Create an image from a working container or via Dockerfile.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Build images in the OCI or &deng; image formats.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Mount a working container's root file system for manipulation.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Use the updated contents of a container's root file system as a file system
    layer to create a new image.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Delete a working container or an image and rename a local container.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  Compared to &deng;, &buildah; has several advantages:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The tool makes it possible to mount a working container's file system, so it
    becomes accessible by the host.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The process of building container images using &buildah; can be automated
    via scripts by using &buildah;'s subcommands instead of a Containerfile or
    Dockerfile.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Similar to &podman;, &buildah; does not require a daemon to run and can be
    used by unprivileged users.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    It is possible to build images inside a container without mounting the
    &docker; socket, which improves security.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <sect1 xml:id="cha-podman-buildah">
  <title>&podman; and &buildah;</title>

  <para>
   Both &podman; and &buildah; can be used to build container images. While
   &podman; makes it possible to build images using Dockerfiles, &buildah;
   offers an expanded range of image building options and capabilities.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="cha-buildah-install">
  <title>&buildah; installation</title>

  <para>
   To install &buildah;, run the command
   <command>sudo zypper in buildah</command>. Run the command
   <command>buildah --version</command> to check whether &buildah; has been
   installed successfully.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you already have &podman; installed and set up for use in rootless mode,
   &buildah; can be used in an unprivileged environment without any further
   configuration. If you need to enable rootless mode for &buildah;, run the
   following command:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.user;sudo usermod --add-subuids 100000-165535 --add-subgids 100000-165535 <replaceable>USER</replaceable></screen>

  <para>
   This command enables rootless mode for the current user. After running the
   command, log out and log in again to enable the changes.
  </para>

  <para>
   The command above defines a range of local UIDs on the host, onto which the
   UIDs allocated to users inside the container are mapped. Note that the
   ranges defined for different users must not overlap. It is also important
   that the ranges do not reuse the UID of any existing local users or groups.
   By default, adding a user with the <command>useradd</command> command on
   &slsa; &product-ga; automatically allocates subUID and subGID ranges.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>&buildah; in rootless mode</title>
   <para>
    In rootless mode, &buildah; commands must be executed in a modified user
    namespace of the user. To enter this user namespace, run the command
    <command>buildah unshare</command>. Otherwise, the <command>buildah
    mount</command> command will fail.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="cha-buildah-build-images">
  <title>Building images with &buildah;</title>

  <para>
   Instead of a special file with instructions, &buildah; uses individual
   commands to build an image. Building an image with &buildah; involves
   several steps: Run a container based on the specified image, edit the
   container (install packages, configure settings, etc.), configure the
   container options, and commit all changes into a new image. While this
   process may include additional steps, such as mounting the container's file
   system and working with it, the basic workflow logic remains the same.
  </para>

  <para>
   The following example can give you a general idea of how to build an image
   with &buildah;.
  </para>

  <example>
   <title>Build image example</title>
<screen>container=$(buildah from suse/sle15) <co xml:id="ctr"/>
buildah run $container zypper up <co xml:id="run"/>
buildah copy $container . /usr/src/example/ <co xml:id="copy"/>
buildah config --workingdir /usr/src/example $container
buildah config --port 8000 $container
buildah config --cmd "php -S 0.0.0.0:8000" $container <co xml:id="config"/>
buildah config --label maintainer="Tux" $container
buildah config --label version="0.1" $container <co xml:id="label"/>
buildah commit $container example <co xml:id="commit"/>
buildah rm $container <co xml:id="rm"/>
</screen>
   <calloutlist>
    <callout arearefs="ctr">
     <para>
      Run a container (also called a working container) based on the specified
      image (in this case, <literal>sle15</literal>).
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="run">
     <para>
      Run a command in the working container you just created. In this example,
      &buildah; runs the <command>zypper up</command> command.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="copy">
     <para>
      Copy files and directories to the specified location in the container. In
      this example, &buildah; copies the entire contents of the current
      directory to <filename>/usr/src/example/</filename>.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="config">
     <para>
      The <command>buildah config</command> commands specify container options.
      These include defining a working directory, exposing a port, and running
      a command inside the container.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="label">
     <para>
      The <command>buildah config --label</command> command allows you to
      assign labels to the container. This may include
      <literal>maintainer</literal>, <literal>description</literal>,
      <literal>version</literal>, and so on.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="commit">
     <para>
      Create an image from the working container by committing all the
      modifications.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="rm">
     <para>
      Delete the working container.
     </para>
    </callout>
   </calloutlist>
  </example>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
