<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
    [
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<chapter xml:id="cha-orchestration" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <info>
  <title>Container orchestration</title>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-pod-deployment-with-podman">
  <title>Pod deployment with &podman;</title>

  <para>
   In addition to building and managing images, &podman; makes it possible to
   work with pods. A pod is a group of one or more containers with shared
   resources, such as the network interface. A pod usually encapsulates an
   application composed of multiple containers into a single unit.
  </para>

  <para>
   The <command>podman pod</command> can be used to create, delete, query, and
   inspect pods. To create a new pod, run the <command>podman pod
   create</command> command. This creates a pod with a random name. To list the
   existing pods, use the <command>podman pod list</command> command. To view a
   list of running pods, run <command>podman ps -a --pod</command>. The output
   of the command looks as follows (the <literal>STATUS</literal> and
   <literal>CREATED</literal> columns are omitted for brevity):
  </para>

<screen>POD ID        NAME                # OF CONTAINERS   INFRA ID
399a120a09ff  suspicious_curie    1                 e57820093817
</screen>

  <para>
   Notice that the command assigned a random name to the pod
   (<literal>suspicious_curie</literal> in this case). You can use the
   <parameter>--name</parameter> parameter to assign the desired name to a pod.
  </para>

  <para>
   To examine the pod and its contents, run the <command>podman ps -a
   --pod</command> command and take a look at the output (the
   <literal>COMMAND</literal>, <literal>CREATED</literal>,
   <literal>STATUS</literal>, <literal>PORTS</literal>, and <literal>POD
   ID</literal> columns are omitted for brevity):
  </para>

<screen>CONTAINER ID  IMAGE                 NAMES              PODNAME
e57820093817  k8s.gcr.io/pause:3.2  399a120a09ff-infra suspicious_curie
</screen>

  <para>
   The created pod has an <literal>infra</literal> container identified by the
   <filename>k8s.gcr.io</filename> name. The purpose of this container is to
   reserve the namespaces associated with the pod and allow &podman; to add
   other containers to the pod.
  </para>

  <para>
   Using the <command>podman run --pod</command> command, you can run a
   container and add it to the desired pod. For example, the command below runs
   a container based on the <literal>suse/sle15</literal> image and adds the
   container to the <filename>suspicious_curie</filename> pod:
  </para>

<screen>podman run -d --pod suspicious_curie registry.suse.com/suse/sle15 sleep 1h</screen>

  <para>
   The command above adds a container that sleeps for 60 minutes and then
   exits. Run the <command>podman ps -a --pod</command> command again and you
   should see that the pod now has two containers.
  </para>

  <para>
   Containers in a pod can be restarted, stopped, and started without affecting
   the overall status of the pod. For example, you can stop a container using
   the <command>sudo podman stop <replaceable>CONTAINER_NAME</replaceable></command>
   command.
  </para>

  <para>
   To stop the pod, use the <command>podman pod stop</command> command:
  </para>

<screen>podman pod stop suspicious_curie</screen>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
