<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha-containers-support"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <info>
  <title>Compatibility and support conditions</title>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-sle-container-support-matrix">
  <title>Support information</title>
<para>
  The term "support" refers to two distinct concepts: a) technical enablement of a feature or combination of, for example, host and container, and b) enterprise support as delivered by &suse; to &suse; customers. Enterprise support requires a subscription for &suse; products according to <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/terms_and_conditions.pdf" />. Technical enablement is described below.
</para>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-sle-container-non-sle-host-support">
   <title>Support for &slsa; hosts</title>
   <para>
    Consult the following support and compatibility matrix to make sure that
    the desired host system and container combination is compatible and
    supported.
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="container_support_matrix.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="container_support_matrix.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
   <para>
    In most scenarios, all &slea; containers are expected to be interoperable
    if the application or its dependencies do not interact directly with kernel
    version-specific data structures (<literal>ioctl</literal>,
    <literal>/proc</literal>, <literal>/sys</literal>,
    <literal>routing</literal>, <literal>iptables</literal>,
    <literal>nftables</literal>, <literal>eBPF</literal>, etc.) or modules
    (KVM, OVS, SystemTap, etc.). Support for <literal>ioctl</literal> and
    access to <literal>/proc</literal> is limited to the most common scenarios
    needed by unprivileged users.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-sle-container-sle-host-support">
   <title>Support for non-&slsa; hosts</title>
   <para>
    While &suse;-based containers are fully supported, issues in the host
    environment must be handled by the host environment vendor. &suse; supports
    components that are part of the &suse; base containers. Packages from
    &suse; repositories are also supported. Additional components and
    applications in the containers are not covered by &suse; support. A &sle;
    subscription is required for building derived containers.
   </para>
   <para>
    Containers based on &sls; 12 SP5 and &sls; 15 (all service packs) are
    supported according to their official lifecycles and the following table.
   </para>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">The following third-party container host platforms
    are supported.</emphasis>
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="container_non-sle_support.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="container_non-sle_support.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-sle-container-support-plans">
  <title>Support plans</title>

  <para>
   There are three guiding principles of &suse; container support.
  </para>

  <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The container image lifecycle follows the lifecycle of the related
     products.
    </para>
    <para>
     For example, &slsa; &productnumber; container images follow the &slsa;
     &productnumber; lifecycle.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Container release status also matches the status of the related product.
    </para>
    <para>
     For example, if &slsa; &productnumber; is in Alpha, Beta, RC, or GA stage,
     the related containers have the same release status.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Containers are built using the packages from the related products.
    </para>
    <para>
     For example, &slsa; &productnumber; container images are built using the
     same packages as the main &slsa; &productnumber; release.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>
   For further information, refer to the
   <link
  xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/lifecycle">Product Support
   Lifecycle</link> page and the documentation available for specific container
   images on <link
 xlink:href="https://registry.suse.com">&suse;
   Registry</link>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Container images can have different support status, and they can have
   limited support. Refer to the appropriate
   <link
  xlink:href="https://registry.suse.com">&suse; Registry</link> page
   for the further information about a specific container image.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-supported-containers-suse-host">
  <title>Supported containers on SUSE host environments</title>

  <para>
   The following support options (tiers) apply to &sls; containers on &suse;
   host environments.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-tier-suse-one">
   <title>Tier one</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Containers delivered by &suse;</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Containers delivered by &suse; are fully supported. This applies to both
       the container and host environment as well as all products under
       support. This includes both general support and
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/long-term-service-pack-support/">Long
       Term Service Pack Support</link> (LTSS).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-tier-suse-two">
   <title>Tier two</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Containers delivered by partners with an agreement ensuring a joint engineering collaboration</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This tier targets important Independent Software Vendors (ISVs). Partner
       containers with a joint engineering collaboration agreement are fully
       supported. This applies to both the container and host environment as
       well as all products under support (both general, as well as LTSS)
       covered by the agreement. Products not covered by the agreement fall
       under Tier Three.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-tier-suse-three">
   <title>Tier three</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>All other third-party containers</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The &suse; container host environment is fully supported. However the
       container vendor is responsible for handling issues related to
       third-party containers they maintain.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-supported-container-host-environments">
  <title>Supported container host environments</title>

  <para>
   The support options (tiers) covered below apply to the following container
   options:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &sle; base containers
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Containers delivered by &suse;
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Third-party container environments derived from the &slea; base containers
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Third-party containers built from &slea; packages using &kiwi; (see
     <xref
     linkend="sec-internal-build-tools-kiwi" />) and &obs; (see
     <xref
     linkend="sec-internal-build-tools-obs" />)
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-tier-one">
   <title>Tier one</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>&suse; products</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This tier applies to &sls;. Both the containers and host environments
       delivered by &suse; are fully supported as well as all products under
       support. This includes both general support and LTSS.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-tier-two">
   <title>Tier two</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Third-party vendors with an agreement ensuring a joint engineering collaboration</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Partner containers and host environments with a joint engineering
       collaboration agreement are fully supported. This applies to both the
       container and host environment as well as all products under support
       (both general and LTSS) covered by the agreement.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-tier-three">
   <title>Tier three</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Selected third-party vendors with no agreement</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This tier targets environments delivered by selected third-party
       vendors. While &suse;-based containers are fully supported, issues in
       the host environment must be handled by the host environment vendor.
       &suse; supports components that come from the &suse; base containers.
       Packages from &suse; repositories are also supported. Additional
       components and applications in the containers are not covered by &suse;
       support. No subscription is required for building derived containers based on the content of the &bci;s or the &bci; Repository. To build containers that include packages from the full &sle; universe, you need a subscription that grants you access to the repositories containing these packages.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-tier-four">
   <title>Tier four</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Any other container host environment</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Any container host environment not mentioned in the support tiers above
       has limited support. Details can be discussed with the &suse; Support
       Team, who might triage the issue and recommend alternative solutions. In
       any other case, issues in the host environment must be handled by the
       host environment vendor.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-tech-previews">
  <title>Technology previews</title>

  <para>
   Container images labeled as Tech Preview are provided by &suse; to give you
   an opportunity to test new technologies within your environment and share
   your feedback. If you test a technology preview, contact your &suse;
   representative to share your experiences and use cases. Your input is helpful
   for future development.
  </para>

  <para>
   Technology previews come with the following limitations:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Technology previews can be functionally incomplete, unstable, and not
     suitable for production use.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Technology previews are not supported.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Technology previews can be available only for specific hardware
     architectures.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Specifics and functionality of technology previews are subject to change.
     As a result, upgrading to subsequent releases of a technology preview may
     not be possible and may require a fresh installation.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Technology previews can be canceled at any time. For example, if &suse;
     discovers that a preview does not meet the customer or market needs, or it
     does not comply with enterprise standards. &suse; does not commit to
     providing a supported version of such technologies in the future.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   Container images are labeled as <literal>Tech Preview</literal> and are marked as such at
   <link
xlink:href="https://registry.suse.com">registry.suse.com</link>.
   Additionally, container images that are technology previews include the
   <literal>com.suse.supportlevel="techpreview"</literal> label in the container
   image metadata. You can check whether the metadata includes the label using
   the <command>docker inspect</command> command, or an appropriate command in
   other container runtimes.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
