<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha-install"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Installation steps</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    This chapter describes the procedure in which the data for
    &productname; is copied to the target device. Some basic
    configuration parameters for the newly installed system are set
    during the procedure. A graphical user interface will guide you
    through the installation. <phrase os="sles;sled">The procedure
    described in the following also applies to remote installation
    procedures as described in <xref linkend="cha-remote-installation"/>.</phrase> The text mode installation
    has the same steps and only looks different. <phrase
    os="sles;osuse">For information about performing non-interactive
    automated installations, see <xref
    linkend="book-autoyast"/>.</phrase>
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>

 <para os="sles">
  Before running the installer, read <xref linkend="part-prep"/>. Depending on
  the architecture of your system, it describes the steps necessary to start
  the installation.
 </para>

 <para>
  If you are a first-time user of &productname;, you should follow the
  default &yast; proposals in most parts, but you can also adjust the settings
  as described here to fine-tune your system according to your
  preferences. Help for each installation step is provided by clicking
  <guimenu>Help</guimenu>.
 </para>

 <tip>
  <title>Installation without a mouse</title>
  <para>
   If the installer does not detect your mouse correctly, use
   <keycap function="tab"/> for navigation, arrow keys to scroll, and
   <keycap function="enter"/> to confirm a selection. Various buttons or
   selection fields contain a letter with an underscore. Use
   <keycombo><keycap function="alt"/><keycap>Letter</keycap></keycombo> to
   select a button or a selection directly instead of navigating there with
   <keycap function="tab"/>.
  </para>
 </tip>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-install-overview">
  <title>Overview</title>
  <para>
   This section provides an overview of all installation steps. Each step
   contains a link to a more detailed description.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step os="sles;sled;osuse">
    <para>
     Before the installation starts, the installer can update itself. For
     details, see <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-self-update" />.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     <phrase os="sles;sled">The actual installation starts with choosing the
     language and the product.</phrase><phrase os="osuse">The actual
     installation starts with choosing the language and accepting the license
     agreement.</phrase> For details, see <xref
     linkend="sec-yast-install-welcome" />.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step os="sles;sled;slemicro">
    <para>
     Accept the license agreement. For details,
     see <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-license-agreement" />.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step arch="zseries" os="sles;slemicro">
    <para>
     &zseries; machines need to activate disks. For details, see
     <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-s390-part"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Configure the network. This is only required when you need network access
     during the installation and the automatic network configuration via DHCP
     failed. If the automatic network configuration succeeded, this step is
     skipped. For details, see <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-network"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step os="sles;sled">
    <para>
     With a working network connection you can register the machine at the
     &scc; or an &rmt; server. For details, see <xref
     linkend="sec-yast-install-scc-registration"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step os="sles;sled">
    <para>
     Select the modules you want to enable for the machine. This impacts the
     availability of system roles in the next step and packages later on.
     For details, see <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-modules"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step os="sles;sled">
    <para>
     You can manually add repositories.
     For details, see <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-addons"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step os="osuse">
    <para>
     Configure the online repositories. By adding official &opensuse;
     repositories, you get access to more software and get the latest security
     updates already during installation. For details, see <xref
     linkend="sec-yast-install-online-repos"/>. This step is
     optional and can be skipped.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step os="sles;sled;osuse">
    <para>
     Select <phrase os="osuse">a desktop or</phrase> a role for your
     system. Among other things, this defines the default list of packages to
     install and makes a suggestion for partitioning the hard disks. For
     details, see <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-system-role"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step os="sles;sled;osuse">
    <para>
     Partition the hard disks of your system. For details, see
     <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-partitioning"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Choose a time zone. For details, see
     <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-date-time"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step os="sles">
    <para>
     Create a user. For details, see
     <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-user"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Optionally, set a different password for the system administrator
     &rootuser;. For details, see <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-user-root"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In a final step, the installer presents an overview of all settings.  If
     required, you can change them. For details, see <xref
     linkend="sec-yast-install-proposal"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The installer copies all required data and informs you about the progress.
     For details, see <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-perform" />.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 os="sles;sled;osuse" xml:id="sec-yast-install-self-update">
  <title>Installer self-update</title>

  <para>
   During the installation and upgrade process, &yast; can update itself to
   solve bugs in the installer that were discovered after the release.  This
   functionality is enabled by default; to disable it, set the boot parameter
   <option>self_update</option> to <literal>0</literal>. For more information,
   see <xref linkend="sec-boot-parameters-advanced-self-update"/>.
  </para>

<!--taroth 2019-09-12: same note used in ay_bigfile.xml-->
  <important os="sles;sled">
   <title>Quarterly media update: self-update disabled</title>
   <para>
    The installer self-update is only available if you use the <literal>GM</literal>
    images of the &leanos; and Packages ISOs. If you install from the ISOs published
    as quarterly update (they can be identified by the string <literal>QU</literal>
    in the name), the installer cannot update itself, because this feature has
    been disabled in the update media.
   </para>
  </important>

  <important>
   <title>Networking during self-update</title>
   <para>
    To download installer updates, &yast; needs network access. By default,
    it tries to use DHCP on all network interfaces. If there is a DHCP server
    in the network, it will work automatically.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you need a static IP setup, you can use the <literal>ifcfg</literal>
    boot argument. For more details, see the linuxrc documentation at
    <link xlink:href="https://en.opensuse.org/Linuxrc"/>.
   </para>
  </important>

  <tip>
   <title>Language selection</title>
   <para>
    The installer self-update is executed before the language selection step.
    This means that progress and errors which happen during this process are
    displayed in English by default.
   </para>
   <para>
    To use another language for this part of the installer, use the
    <literal>language</literal> boot parameter if available for your
    architecture, for example, <literal>language=de_DE</literal>.  On machines
    equipped with a traditional BIOS, alternatively, press <keycap>F2</keycap>
    in the boot menu and select the language from the list.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
   Although this feature was designed to run without user intervention, it is
   worth knowing how it works. If you are not interested, you can jump directly
   to <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-welcome"/> and skip the rest of this
   section.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-self-update-process">
   <title>Self-update process</title>

   <para>
    The process can be broken down into two different parts:
   </para>

   <orderedlist spacing="normal">
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Determine the update repository location.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Download and apply the updates to the installation system.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>

   <sect3 xml:id="sec-yast-install-self-update-determine-repo">
    <title>Determining the update repository location</title>

    <para>
     Installer Self-Updates are distributed as regular RPM packages via a
     dedicated repository, so the first step is to find out the repository URL.
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>Installer self-update repository only</title>
     <para>
      No matter which of the following options you use, only the installer
      self-update repository URL is expected, for example:
     </para>
<screen>self_update=https://www.example.com/my_installer_updates/</screen>
     <para>
      Do not supply any other repository URL&mdash;for example the URL of the
      software update repository.
     </para>
    </important>
    <para>
     &yast; will try the following sources of information:
    </para>

    <orderedlist spacing="normal">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The <literal>self_update</literal> boot parameter. (For more details,
       see <xref linkend="sec-boot-parameters-advanced-self-update"/>.) If you
       specify a URL, it will take precedence over any other method.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The <literal>/general/self_update_url</literal> profile element in case
       you are using &ay;.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem os="sles;sled">
      <para>
       A registration server. &yast; will query the registration server for the
       URL. The server to be used is determined in the following order:
      </para>
      <orderedlist spacing="normal">
       <listitem>
        <para>
         By evaluating the <literal>regurl</literal> boot
         parameter (<xref linkend="sec-boot-parameters-advanced-smt"/>).
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         By evaluating the <literal>/suse_register/reg_server</literal> profile
         element if you are using &ay;.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         By performing an SLP lookup. If an SLP server is found, &yast; will
         ask you whether it should be used because there is no authentication
         involved and everybody on the local network could announce a
         registration server.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         By querying the &scc;.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If none of the previous attempts worked, the fallback URL (defined in
       the installation media) will be used.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
   </sect3>

   <sect3 xml:id="sec-yast-install-self-update-apply-updates">
    <title>Downloading and applying the updates</title>

    <para>
     When the updates repository is determined, &yast; will check whether an
     update is available. If so, all the updates will be downloaded and
     applied to the installation system.
    </para>

    <para>
     Finally, &yast; will be restarted to load the new version and the welcome
     screen will be shown. If no updates were available, the installation will
     continue without restarting &yast;.
    </para>

    <note>
     <title>Update integrity</title>
     <para>
      Update signatures will be checked to ensure integrity and
      authorship. If a signature is missing or invalid, you will be asked
      whether you want to apply the update.
     </para>
    </note>
   </sect3>

   <sect3 xml:id="sec-yast-install-self-update-temporary-addon-repo">
    <title>Temporary self-update add-on repository</title>

    <para>
     Some packages distributed in the self-update repository provide additional
     data for the installer, like the installation defaults, system role
     definitions and similar. If the installer finds such packages in the
     self-update repository, a local temporary repository is created, to which
     those packages are copied.  They are used during the installation process,
     but at the end of the installation, the temporary local repository is
     removed. Its packages are <emphasis>not</emphasis> installed onto the
     target system.
    </para>

    <para>
     This additional repository is not displayed in the list of add-on
     products, but during installation it may still be visible as
     <literal>SelfUpdate0</literal> repository in the package management.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-self-update-custom">
   <title>Custom self-update repositories</title>

   <para>
    &yast; can use a user-defined repository instead of the official
    repository by specifying a URL through the
    <literal>self_update</literal> boot parameter.
   </para>
   <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
    <listitem>
     <para>
      HTTP/HTTPS and FTP repositories are supported.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Starting with <package>yast2-installation-4.4.30</package>, the
      <literal>relurl://</literal> schema is supported, as a boot
      parameter or in an &ay; profile. The URL is relative to the main
      installation repository, and you may navigate the file tree with the
      usual <literal>../</literal> notation, for example
      <replaceable>relurl://../self_update</replaceable>. This is useful
      when serving the packages via a local installation server, or when
      building a custom installation medium which includes a self-update
      repository.
     </para>
     <para>
      The following examples assume the installation repository is at the
      medium root (/), and the self-update repository in the
      <filename>self_update</filename> subdirectory. This structure makes
      the <literal>relurl://</literal> portable, and it will work anywhere
      without changes as a boot parameter, copied to an USB stick, hard
      disk, network server, or in an &ay; profile.
     </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Custom DVD/USB medium</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Add the <literal>self_update=relurl://self_update</literal>
      boot option directly to the default boot parameters, and it will work
      properly even if the medium is copied to an USB stick, hard disk, or a
      network server.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Installation server</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Assume that the installation packages are available via
      <replaceable>http://example.com/repo</replaceable> and a self-update repository is available at
      <replaceable>http://example.com/self_update</replaceable>.
      </para>
      <para>
       Then you can use the
       <replaceable>http://example.com/repo</replaceable> and
       <replaceable>http://example.com/self_update</replaceable> boot
       parameters, without having to change the
       <literal>self_update</literal> parameter when the repositories are moved to a different location.
      </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Only RPM-MD repositories are supported (required by &rmt;).
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Packages are not installed in the usual way: They are uncompressed only
      and no scripts are executed.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      No dependency checks are performed. Packages are installed in
      alphabetical order.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Files from the packages override the files from the original
      installation media. This means that the update packages might not need to
      contain all files, only files that have changed. Unchanged files are
      omitted to save memory and download bandwidth.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>


   <note>
    <title>Only one repository</title>
    <para>
     Currently, it is not possible to use more than one repository as source
     for installer self-updates.
    </para>
   </note>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-install-welcome">
  <title>
   <phrase os="sles;sled">Language, keyboard, and product selection</phrase>
   <phrase os="osuse">Language, keyboard, and license agreement</phrase>
  </title>
  <figure>
  <title>
   <phrase os="sles;sled">Language, keyboard, and product selection</phrase>
   <phrase os="osuse;slemicro">Language, keyboard, and license agreement</phrase>
  </title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Language, keyboard, and product selection</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata os="sled" fileref="install_product_sled.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="sles;slemicro" fileref="install_product_sles.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_welcome_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata os="sled" fileref="install_product_sled.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="sles;slemicro" fileref="install_product_sles.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_welcome_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Language</guimenu> and <guimenu>Keyboard Layout</guimenu>
   settings are initialized with the language you chose on the boot
   screen. If you did not change the default, it will be English (US). Change
   the settings here, if necessary.
  </para>
  <para>
   Changing the language will automatically preselect a corresponding keyboard
   layout.  Override this proposal by selecting a different keyboard layout
   from the drop-down box. Use the <guimenu>Keyboard Test</guimenu> text box to
   test the layout. The language selected here is also used to assume a time
   zone for the system clock.<phrase os="sles"> This setting can be modified later in the
   installed system as described in <xref linkend="cha-yast-lang"/>.</phrase>
  </para>
  &product_selection;
  <para os="sles;sled">
   Select a product for installation. You need to have a registration code
   for the respective product. In this document it is assumed
   you have chosen <phrase os="sles">&sls;</phrase><phrase
   os="sled">&sled;</phrase>. Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
  </para>
  <para os="osuse">
   Read the license agreement. It is presented in the language you
   have. Translations are available via the <guimenu>License Language</guimenu>
   drop-down box. Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu> if you agree to the
   terms and conditions. If you do not agree, click <guimenu>Abort</guimenu> to
   terminate the installation.
  </para>
  <tip>
   <title>Light and high-contrast themes</title>
   <para>
    If you are having difficulties when reading the labels in the installer, you can
    change the colors and the theme.
   </para>
   <para>
    <keycombo><keycap function="shift"/><keycap>F4</keycap></keycombo>
    switches to the color scheme for vision-impaired users. Press the buttons
    again to switch back to the default scheme.
   </para>
   <para>
    <keycombo><keycap function="shift"/><keycap>F3</keycap></keycombo>
    opens a theme selection dialog. Select a theme from the list and
    <guimenu>Close</guimenu> the dialog.
   </para>
  </tip>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-install-license-agreement" os="sles;sled">
  <title>License agreement</title>
  <figure os="sles;sled;slemicro">
   <title>License agreement</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>License Agreement</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata os="sled" fileref="install_license_sled.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="sles;slemicro" fileref="install_license_sles.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata os="sled" fileref="install_license_sled.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="sles;slemicro" fileref="install_license_sles.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
   Read the License Agreement. It is presented in the language you have chosen
   on the boot screen. Translations are available via the <guimenu>License
   Language</guimenu> drop-down box. <phrase os="sles;sled">If you agree to the
   terms, check <guimenu>I Agree to the License Terms</guimenu> and click
   <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed with the installation. If you do not
   agree to the license agreement, you cannot install &productname;; click
   <guimenu>Abort</guimenu> to terminate the installation.</phrase><phrase
   os="osuse">By proceeding with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>, you agree to the
   license agreement. Choose <guimenu>Abort</guimenu> to cancel the
   installation if you do not agree to the license terms.</phrase>
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-install-s390-part" arch="zseries" os="sles;slemicro">
  <title>&zseries;: disk activation</title>
  <para>
   When installing on &zseries; platforms, the language selection dialog is
   followed by a dialog to configure the attached hard disks.
  </para>
  <figure>
   <title>Disk activation</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Disk Activation</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="install_zseries_disk_activation.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="install_zseries_disk_activation.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
   Select DASD, Fibre Channel Attached SCSI Disks (zFCP), or iSCSI for
   installation of &productname;. The DASD and zFCP configuration buttons are
   only available if the corresponding devices are attached.<phrase os="sles"> For instructions
   on how to configure iSCSI disks, refer to <xref
   linkend="sec-iscsi-initiator"/>.</phrase>
  </para>
  <para>
   You can also change  the <guimenu>Network Configuration</guimenu> in this
   screen by launching the <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu> dialog. Choose a
   network interface from the list and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> to change
   its settings. Use the tabs to configure DNS and routing.<phrase os="sles"> See
   <xref linkend="sec-network-yast"/> for more details.</phrase>
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-s390-part-dasd">
   <title>Configuring DASD disks</title>
   <para>
    Skip this step if you are not installing on &zseries; hardware.
   </para>
   <figure xml:id="fig-s390-yast2-i-y2-sel-dasd">
    <title>DASD disk management</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <textobject role="description">
      <phrase>DASD Disk Management</phrase>
     </textobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata width="100%" fileref="install_zseries_dasd.png"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata width="100%" fileref="install_zseries_dasd.png"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    After selecting <guimenu>Configure DASD Disks</guimenu>, an overview lists
    all available DASDs. To get a clearer picture of the available devices, use
    the text box located above the list to specify a range of channels to
    display. To filter the list according to such a range, select
    <guimenu>Filter</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Specify the DASDs to use for the installation by selecting the
    corresponding entries in the list. Use <guimenu>Select All</guimenu> to
    select all DASDs currently displayed. Activate and make the selected DASDs
    available for the installation by selecting <menuchoice> <guimenu>Perform
    Action</guimenu> <guimenu>Activate</guimenu> </menuchoice>. To format the
    DASDs, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Perform Action</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Format</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Alternatively, use the &yast;
    partitioner later as described in
    <xref linkend="sec-expert-partitioner"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-s390-part-zfcp">
   <title>Configuring zFCP disks</title>
   <para>
    Skip this step if you are not installing on &zseries; hardware.
   </para>
   <figure xml:id="fig-install-zseries-zfcp">
    <title>Configured zFCP Devices</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <textobject role="description">
      <phrase>Configured zFCP Devices</phrase>
     </textobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata width="100%" fileref="install_zseries_zfcp.png"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata width="100%" fileref="install_zseries_zfcp.png"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    After selecting <guimenu>Configure zFCP Disks</guimenu>, a dialog with a
    list of the zFCP disks available on the system opens. In this dialog, select
    <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to open another dialog in which to
    enter zFCP parameters.
   </para>
   <para>
    To make a zFCP disk available for the &productname; installation, choose an
    available <guimenu>Channel Number</guimenu> from the drop-down box.
    <guimenu>Get WWPNs</guimenu> (World Wide Port Number) and <guimenu>Get
    LUNs</guimenu> (Logical Unit Number) return lists with available WWPNs and
    FCP-LUNs, respectively, to choose from. Automatic LUN scanning only works
    with NPIV enabled.
   </para>
   <para>
    When completed, exit the zFCP
    dialog with <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and the general hard disk configuration
    dialog with <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> to continue with the rest of the
    configuration.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-install-network">
  <title>Network settings</title>
  <para>
   After booting into the installation, the installation routine is set up.
   During this setup, an attempt to configure at least one network interface
   with DHCP is made. In case this attempt has failed, the <guimenu>Network
   Settings</guimenu> dialog launches now.
  </para>
  <figure>
   <title>Network settings</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Network Settings</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata os="sles;sled;slemicro" fileref="install_network.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_network_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata os="sles;sled;slemicro" fileref="install_network.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_network_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
   Choose a network interface from the list and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
   to change its settings. Use the tabs to configure DNS and routing.<phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"> See <xref
   linkend="sec-network-yast"/> for more details. </phrase><phrase os="sles"
   arch="zseries">On &zseries; this dialog does not start automatically. It can
   be started in the <guimenu>Disk Activation</guimenu> step.</phrase>
  </para>
  <para>
   In case DHCP was successfully configured during installation setup, you can
   also access this dialog by clicking <guimenu>Network Configuration</guimenu>
   at the <phrase os="sles;sled"><guimenu>&scc; Registration</guimenu>
   and</phrase> the <guimenu>Installation Settings</guimenu> step. It lets you
   change the automatically provided settings.
  </para>
  <note>
   <title>Network configuration with boot parameters</title>
   <para>
    If at least one network interface has been configured via boot parameters
    (see <xref linkend="sec-boot-parameters-list-network"/>), automatic DHCP
    configuration is disabled and the boot parameter configuration is imported
    and used.
   </para>
  </note>
  <tip>
   <title>Accessing network storage or local RAID</title>
   <para>
    To access a SAN or a local RAID during the installation,
    you can use the libstorage command line client for this purpose:
   </para>
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Switch to a console with <keycombo><keycap function="control"/>
      <keycap
      function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Install the libstoragemgmt extension by running <command>extend
      libstoragemgmt</command>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Now you have access to the <command>lsmcli</command> command. For more
      information, run <command>lsmcli --help</command>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To return to the installer, press <keycombo><keycap function="alt"/>
      <keycap>F7</keycap></keycombo>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
   <para>
    Supported are Netapp Ontap, all SMI-S compatible SAN providers, and LSI
    MegaRAID.
   </para>
  </tip>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-install-scc-registration" os="sles;sled;slemicro">
  <title>Registration</title>
  <para>
   To get technical support and product updates, you need to register and
   activate &productname; with the &scc; or a local registration server.
   Registering your product at this stage also grants you immediate access to
   the update repository. This enables you to install the system with the
   latest updates and patches available.
  </para>
  <para>
   When registering, repositories and dependencies for the modules and
   extensions, which you install with the next step, are loaded from the
   registration server.
  </para>
  <para>
   From this dialog, you can switch to the &yast; <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu>
   module by clicking <guimenu>Network Configuration</guimenu>.<phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"> For details, see
   <xref linkend="sec-network-yast"/>.</phrase>
  </para>
  <para>
   If you are offline or want to skip registration, activate <guimenu>Skip
   Registration</guimenu>. See <xref
   linkend="sec-yast-install-scc-registration-none"/> for instructions.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-scc-registration-manually">
   <title>Registering manually</title>
   <para>
    To register with the &scc;, enter the <guimenu>E-mail Address</guimenu>
    associated with your SCC account and the <guimenu>Registration
     Code</guimenu> for &productname;..
   </para>
   <para>
    If your organization provides a local registration server, you may
    alternatively register there. Activate <guimenu>Register System via
     local SMT Server</guimenu> and either choose a URL from the drop-down
    box or type in an address. Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    To register with the &scc;, enter your <guimenu>Registration
    Code</guimenu> for &productname;. If your organization provides a local
    registration server, you may alternatively register there. Activate
    <guimenu>Register System via local &rmt; Server</guimenu> and either choose a
    URL from the drop-down box or type in an address.
   </para>
   <para>
    Start the registration process with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <figure>
    <title>&scc; registration</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <textobject role="description">
      <phrase>&scc; Registration</phrase>
     </textobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata os="sles;slemicro" fileref="install_registration_sles.png" width="100%"/>
      <imagedata os="sled" fileref="install_registration_sled.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata os="sles;slemicro" fileref="install_registration_sles.png" width="100%"/>
      <imagedata os="sled" fileref="install_registration_sled.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <note os="sled">
    <title>Trusting repositories</title>
    <para>
     Depending on your hardware, additional repositories containing hardware
     drivers may be added during the registration. If so, you will be asked
     to <guimenu>Trust</guimenu> each of these repositories.
    </para>
   </note>

   <tip>
    <title>Installing product patches at installation time</title>
    <para>
     After &productname; has been successfully registered, you
     are asked whether to install the latest available online updates during
     the installation. If choosing <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>, the system will be
     installed with the most current packages without having to apply the
     updates after installation. Activating this option is recommended.
    </para>
   </tip>

   &note_firewall_updates;

   <para>
    If the system was successfully registered during installation, &yast; will
    disable repositories from local installation media such as CD/DVD or flash
    disks when the installation has been completed. This prevents problems if
    the installation source is no longer available and ensures that you always
    get the latest updates from the online repositories.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-scc-registration-usb">
   <title>Loading registration codes from USB storage</title>
   <para>
    To make the registration more convenient, you can also store your
    registration codes on a USB storage device such as a flash disk. &yast;
    will automatically pre-fill the corresponding text box. This is
    particularly useful when testing the installation or if you need to
    register many systems or extensions.
   </para>
   <para>
    Create a file named <filename>regcodes.txt</filename> or
    <filename>regcodes.xml</filename> on the USB disk. If both are present, the
    XML takes precedence.
   </para>
   <para>
    In that file, identify the product with the name returned by
    <command>zypper search --type product</command> and assign it a
    registration code as follows:
   </para>
   <example xml:id="ex-i-yast2-conf-manual-cc-usb-txt">
    <title><filename>regcodes.txt</filename></title>
<screen>SLES    cc36aae1
SLED    309105d4

sle-we  5eedd26a
sle-live-patching 8c541494</screen>
   </example>
   <example xml:id="ex-i-yast2-conf-manual-cc-usb-xml">
    <title><filename>regcodes.xml</filename></title>
<screen language="xml"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<profile xmlns="http://www.suse.com/1.0/yast2ns"
 xmlns:config="http://www.suse.com/1.0/configns">
  <suse_register>
    <addons config:type="list">
      <addon>
<name>SLES</name>
<reg_code>cc36aae1</reg_code>
      </addon>
      <addon>
<name>SLED</name>
<reg_code>309105d4</reg_code>
      </addon>
      <addon>
<name>sle-we</name>
<reg_code>5eedd26a</reg_code>
      </addon>
      <addon>
<name>sle-live-patching</name>
<reg_code>8c541494</reg_code>
      </addon>
    </addons>
  </suse_register>
</profile>]]></screen>
   </example>
   <para os="sles;sled">
    Note that <literal>&slsa;</literal> and <literal>&sleda;</literal> are not
    extensions, but listing them as add-ons allows for combining several base
    product registration codes in a single file. <phrase os="sles">See
    <xref
    linkend="CreateProfile-Register-Extension"/> for
    details.</phrase>
   </para>

   <note>
    <title>Limitations</title>
    <para>
     Currently flash disks are only scanned during installation or upgrade, but
     not when registering a running system.
    </para>
   </note>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-scc-registration-none">
   <title>Installing without registration</title>
   <para>
    If you are offline or want to skip registration, activate <guimenu>Skip
     Registration</guimenu>. Accept the warning with <guimenu>OK</guimenu> and
    proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <important>
    <title>Skipping the registration</title>
    <para>
     Your system and extensions need to be registered to retrieve
     updates and to be eligible for support. Skipping the registration is
     only possible when installing from the
     <filename>&packagemedia;</filename> image.
    </para>
   </important>

   <figure>
    <title>Installing without registration</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <textobject role="description">
      <phrase>Installing without Registration</phrase>
     </textobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata os="sles;slemicro" fileref="install_registration_offline_sles.png"
                 width="100%"/>
      <imagedata os="sled" fileref="install_registration_offline_sled.png"
                 width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata os="sles;slemicro" fileref="install_registration_offline_sles.png"
                 width="100%"/>
      <imagedata os="sled" fileref="install_registration_offline_sled.png"
                 width="100%"/>

     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <note>
    <title>Registering &productname;</title>
    <para>
     Your system and extensions need to be registered to retrieve
     updates and to be eligible for support. If you do not register during the
     installation, you can do so at any time later from the running system. To
     do so, run <menuchoice><guimenu>&yast;</guimenu> <guimenu>Product
     Registration</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </note>

   <!-- cwickert 2020-03-18: Old content from the 'offline' section -->
   <!--
   <para>
    If you perform an installation without connecting to a registration server,
    you cannot register your system during the installation. Therefore you
    cannot receive the repository configuration for modules and
    extensions from the registration server. To enable a regular installation,
    &suse; offers a second installation medium, the &packagemedia; image.
   </para>

   <para>
    To perform the installation without registration, make sure the contents
    of the &packagemedia; image can be accessed during the installation. This
    can be achieved by copying it to a local hard disk or a removable flash
    disk or by making it available in the local
    network. Choose a method that is supported by your hardware.
   </para>
   -->

   <tip>
    <title>
     Copying the installation media image to a removable flash disk
    </title>
    <remark>Not a suitable location for this tip.</remark>
    <para>
     Use the following command to copy the contents of the installation image
     to a removable flash disk.
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.sudo;dd if=<replaceable>IMAGE</replaceable> of=<replaceable>FLASH_DISK</replaceable> bs=4M &amp;&amp; sync</screen>
    <para>
     <replaceable>IMAGE</replaceable> needs to be replaced with the path to the
     <filename>&installmedia;</filename> or <filename>&packagemedia;</filename>
     image file. <replaceable>FLASH_DISK</replaceable> needs to be replaced
     with the flash device. To identify the device, insert it and run:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.root;grep -Ff &lt;(hwinfo --disk --short) &lt;(hwinfo --usb --short)
     disk:
     /dev/sdc             General USB Flash Disk</screen>
    <para>
     Make sure the size of the device is sufficient for the desired image. You
     can check the size of the device with:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.root;fdisk -l /dev/sdc | grep -e "^/dev"
     /dev/sdc1  *     2048 31490047 31488000  15G 83 Linux</screen>
    <para>
     In this example, the device has a capacity of 15 GB. The command to use for
     the <filename>&packagemedia;</filename> would be:
    </para>
    <screen>dd if=&packagemedia; of=/dev/sdc bs=4M &amp;&amp; sync</screen>
    <para>
     The device must not be mounted when running the <command>dd</command>
     command. Note that all data on the partition will be erased!
    </para>
   </tip>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-install-modules" os="sles;sled">
  <title>Extension and module selection</title>
  <para>
   In this dialog the installer lists modules and extensions that are available
   for &productname;. Modules are components which allow you to shape the
   product according to your needs. They are free of charge. Extensions add
   functionality to your product. They are offered as subscriptions and require
   a registration key that is liable for costs.
  </para>
  <para>
   The availability of certain modules or extensions depends on the product you
   chose in the first step of this installation. For a description of the
   modules and their lifecycles, select a module to see the accompanying
   text. More detailed information is available in the
   <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles-15/html/SLES-all/article-modules.html">&modulesquick;</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
   The selection of modules indirectly affects the scope of the installation,
   because it defines which software sources (repositories) are available for
   installation and in the running system.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Extension and module selection</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Extension and Module Selection</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata os="sled" fileref="install_extensions_sled.png"
                width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="sles" fileref="install_extensions_sles.png"
                width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata os="sled" fileref="install_extensions_sled.png"
                width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="sles" fileref="install_extensions_sles.png"
                width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  &extension_module_selection;


 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-install-addons" os="sles;sled">
  <title>Add-on product</title>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Add On Product</guimenu> dialog allows you to add additional
   software sources (so-called <quote>repositories</quote>) to &productname;,
   that are not provided by the &scc;. Such add-on products may include
   third-party products and drivers or additional software for your system.
  </para>
  <figure>
   <title>Add-on product</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Add-On Product</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="install_addon.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="install_addon.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
   From this dialog, you can switch to the &yast; <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu>
   module by clicking <guimenu>Network Configuration</guimenu>.<phrase os="sles;sled"> For details, see
   <xref linkend="sec-network-yast"/>.</phrase>
  </para>
  <tip>
   <title>Adding drivers during the installation</title>
   <para>
    You can also add driver update repositories via the <guimenu>Add On
    Product</guimenu> dialog. Driver updates for &sle; are provided at <link
    xlink:href="http://drivers.suse.com/"/>. These drivers have been created
    via the &suse; SolidDriver Program.
   </para>
  </tip>
  <para>
   If you do not want to install add-ons, proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
   Otherwise activate <guimenu>I would like to install an additional Add On
   Product</guimenu>. Specify the Media Type by choosing from CD, DVD, Hard
   Disk, USB Mass Storage, a Local Directory or a Local ISO Image. If
   network access has been configured you can choose from additional remote
   sources such as HTTP, SLP, FTP, etc. Alternatively you may directly specify
   a URL. Check <guimenu>Download repository description files</guimenu> to
   download the files describing the repository now. If deactivated, they will
   be downloaded after the installation starts. Proceed with
   <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and insert a CD or DVD if required.
  </para>
  <para>
   Depending on the add-on's content, it may be necessary to accept additional
   license agreements.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-install-online-repos" os="osuse">
  <title>Online repositories</title>
  <para>
   A system analysis is performed, where the installer probes for storage
   devices, and tries to find other installed systems. If a network
   connection with Internet access is available, you will be asked to
   activate the online repositories. Answer with <guimenu>Yes</guimenu> to
   proceed. In case you do not have Internet access, this step will be
   skipped.
  </para>
  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="install_onlinerepos_ask_osuse.png" width="75%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="install_onlinerepos_ask_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>
   The online repositories are official &opensuse; package sources. They not
   only offer additional packages not included on the installation media, but
   also the update repositories containing security and bug fixes. Using the
   default selection is recommended. Add at least the <guimenu>Main Update
   Repository</guimenu>, because it makes sure the system is installed with the
   latest security patches.
  </para>
  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="install_onlinerepos_osuse.png" width="75%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="install_onlinerepos_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>
   You have the following choices:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The <guimenu>Main Repository</guimenu> contains open-source
     software (OSS). Compared to the DVD installation media, it contains
     many additional software packages, among them many additional
     desktop systems.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The <guimenu>Update repository with updates from SUSE Linux Enterprise
     15</guimenu> and the <guimenu>Update repository from openSUSE
     Backports</guimenu> contain updates for the Main Repository. Enabling
     these repositories is recommended for all installation scenarios.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The <guimenu>Non-OSS Repository</guimenu> contains packages with
     a proprietary software license. Enabling it is not required for
     installing a custom desktop system.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Enabling <guimenu>Update Repository (Non-OSS)</guimenu> is
     recommended if the <guimenu>Non-OSS Repository</guimenu> is enabled.
     This repository contains updates and security fixes for proprietary
     software.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     All other repositories are intended for experienced users and
     developers. Click on a repository name to get more information.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   Confirm your selection with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. Depending on your
   choice, you need to confirm one or more license agreements. Do so by
   choosing <guimenu>Next</guimenu> until you proceed to the <guimenu>System
   Role</guimenu> screen. Now choose <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 os="sles;sled;osuse" xml:id="sec-yast-install-system-role">
  <title>System role</title>
  <para>
   &productname; supports a broad range of features. To simplify the
   installation, the installer offers predefined use cases which adjust the system to
   be installed so it is tailored for the selected scenario.
  </para>
  <figure>
   <title>System role</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>System Role</phrase>
     </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata os="sles" fileref="install_system_role_sles.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="sled" fileref="install_system_role_sled.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_ui_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata os="sles" fileref="install_system_role_sles.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="sled" fileref="install_system_role_sled.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_ui_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
   Choose the <guimenu>System Role</guimenu> that meets your requirements
   best. The availability of system roles depends on your selection of modules
   and extensions. Therefore, the dialog is omitted under the following
   conditions:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If from the enabled modules <emphasis>no role</emphasis> is suitable for
     the respective base product. In this case, the installation proceeds with
     the default settings for this product.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If from the enabled modules <emphasis>only one role</emphasis> is suitable
     for the respective base product. In this case, the installation proceeds
     with the settings of this particular role.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   With the default selection, the following system roles are available:
  </para>
  <variablelist os="sles">
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Text Mode</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option installs a basic &slsa; without a desktop environment
      but with a rich set of command line tools.
     </para>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Dependencies:</emphasis> Basesystem
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Minimal</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Select this role if you want a very small installation with only
      the basic command line tools.
     </para>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Dependencies:</emphasis> None
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>KVM Virtualization Host</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Select this scenario when installing on a machine that should serve as a
      KVM host that can run other virtual
      machines. <filename>/var/lib/libvirt</filename> will be placed on a
      separate partition and the firewall and Kdump will be disabled.
     </para>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Dependencies:</emphasis> Basesystem, Server Applications
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Xen Virtualization Host</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Select this scenario when installing on a machine that should serve as a
      &xen; host that can run other virtual
      machines. <filename>/var/lib/libvirt</filename> will be placed on a
      separate partition and the firewall and Kdump will be disabled.
     </para>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Dependencies:</emphasis> Basesystem, Server Applications
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist os="sled">
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>GNOME Desktop (Wayland)</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Installs a fully featured GNOME desktop environment, including office
      suite, e-mail client, Web browser, and file manager. It is optimized for
      installation on physical systems, using the Wayland technology. Does
      <emphasis>not</emphasis> support accessing the desktop from a remote
      machine.
     </para>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Dependencies:</emphasis> Basesystem, Desktop Applications,
      &slewe;
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>GNOME Desktop (X11)</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Installs a fully featured GNOME desktop environment, including office
      suite, e-mail client, Web browser, and file manager. Comes with support
      for accessing the desktop from a remote machine.
     </para>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Dependencies:</emphasis> Basesystem, Desktop Applications,
      &slewe;
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>GNOME Desktop (Basic)</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Installs a GNOME desktop environment with only essential graphical
      applications (for example file manager, Web browser). It is using the X11
      technology.
     </para>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Dependencies:</emphasis> Basesystem, Desktop Applications
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>IceWM Desktop (Minimal)</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Installs a lightweight IceWM desktop environment with only a bare minimum
      of graphical applications (for example xterm). It is using the X11
      technology.
     </para>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Dependencies:</emphasis> Basesystem
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <variablelist os="osuse">
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Desktop with KDE Plasma</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A powerful desktop environment with a complete PIM suite (mail, calendar,
      tasks, notes, and feeds), widgets running on the desktop and many more
      features. If you are familiar with Windows, KDE is the recommended
      choice. For more information see <link xlink:href="https://kde.org/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Desktop with GNOME</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A desktop environment offering an alternative, innovative user
      experience. GNOME was designed with usability and productivity in
      mind. For more information see <link
      xlink:href="https://www.gnome.org/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Desktop with Xfce</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A lightweight traditional desktop environment. For more information, see
      <link xlink:href="https://www.xfce.org/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Generic Desktop</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      In case you prefer an alternative to the KDE, GNOME, or Xfce desktops,
      choose this option. You will be able to choose between the following
      alternatives later in the installation process by selecting
      <guimenu>Software</guimenu> in the <guimenu>Installation Settings
      dialog</guimenu>:
     </para>
     <simplelist>
      <member>Enlightenment (<link xlink:href="https://www.enlightenment.org/"/>)</member>
      <member>LXDE (<link xlink:href="https://lxde.org/"/>)</member>
      <member>LXQT (<link xlink:href="https://lxqt.org/"/>)</member>
      <member>MATE (<link xlink:href="https://mate-desktop.org/"/>)</member>
     </simplelist>
     <para>
      When installing from the DVD image, these desktop systems are only
      available if you enabled the Main Repository (OSS) in
      the <guimenu>Online Repositories</guimenu> step. You can still enable
      this repository at later points during the installation by using the
      <guimenu>Back</guimenu> button until you
      reach the welcome screen. From there, choose <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and
      then agree to add online repositories.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Server</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If setting up a server, you probably do not need a graphical user
      interface and desktop applications such as an office suite. This option
      gives you a reduced set of packages suitable for servers.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Transactional Server</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Similar to the server role, but with a read-only root partition and
      transactional updates. This selection also is a prerequisite for setting
      up &opensuse; Kubic. See <link
      xlink:href="https://kubic.opensuse.org/blog/2018-04-04-transactionalupdates/"/>
      for more information on transactional updates.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-install-partitioning">
  <title>Partitioning</title>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-partitioning-important">
   <title>Important information</title>
   <remark>Include information that BTRFS with enabled snapshots is mandatory for SLE Micro root fs.</remark>
   <warning>
    <title>Read this section carefully</title>
    <para>
     Read this section carefully before continuing with
     <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-partitioning-suggested"/>.
    </para>
   </warning>
     <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Custom partitioning on UEFI machines</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A UEFI machine <emphasis>requires</emphasis> an EFI system partition
       that must be mounted to <filename>/boot/efi</filename>. This partition
       must be formatted with the <literal>FAT32</literal> file system.
      </para>
      <para>
       If an EFI system partition is already present on your system (for
       example from a previous Windows installation) use it by mounting it to
       <filename>/boot/efi</filename> without formatting it.
      </para>
      <para>
       If no EFI system partition is present on your UEFI machine, make sure to
       create it. The EFI system partition must be a physical partition or RAID
       1. Other RAID levels, LVM and other technologies are not supported. It
       needs to be formatted with the FAT32 file system.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Custom partitioning and <systemitem>Snapper</systemitem></term>
     <listitem>
      <para os="sles;osuse">
       If the root partition is larger than 16 GB, &productname; by
       default enables file system snapshots.
      </para>
      <para os="sled">
       &productname; can be configured to use snapshots which
       provide the ability to do rollbacks of system changes.
      </para>
      <para>
       &productname; uses Snapper together with Btrfs for this
       feature. Btrfs needs to be set up with snapshots enabled for the
       root partition.
      </para>
      <para>
       If the disk is smaller than 16 GB, all Snapper features and
       automatic snapshots are disabled to prevent the system partition
       <filename>/</filename> from running out of space.
      </para>
      <para>
       Being able to create system snapshots that enable rollbacks
       requires important system directories to be mounted on a
       single partition, for example <filename>/usr</filename> and
       <filename>/var</filename>. Only directories that are excluded
       from snapshots may reside on separate partitions, for example
       <filename>/usr/local</filename>, <filename>/var/log</filename>,
       and <filename>/tmp</filename>.
      </para>
      <para>
       If snapshots are enabled, the
       installer will automatically create <literal>single</literal>
       snapshots during and immediately after the installation.
      </para>
      <para os="sles;sled;osuse">
       For details, see <xref linkend="cha-snapper"/>.
      </para>

      <important>
       <title>Btrfs snapshots and root partition size</title>
       <para>
        Snapshots occupy space on their partition. As a rule of thumb, the
        older a snapshot is, or the bigger the changeset they cover is, the
        bigger the snapshot. Plus, the more snapshots you keep, the more
        disk space you need.
       </para>
       <para>
        To prevent the root partition running full with snapshot data, you need to make
        sure it is big enough. In case you do frequent updates or other
        installations, consider at least 30&nbsp;GB for the root partition. If you
        plan to keep snapshots activated for a system upgrade <phrase
        os="sles;sled">or a service pack migration</phrase> (to be able to roll
        back), you should consider 40&nbsp;GB or more.
       </para>
      </important>

     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Btrfs data volumes</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Using Btrfs for data volumes is supported on &productname;
       &productnumber;. For applications that require Btrfs as a data volume,
       consider creating a separate file system with quota groups
       disabled. This is already the default for non-root file systems.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Btrfs on an encrypted root partition</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The default partitioning setup suggests the root partition as Btrfs. To
       encrypt the root partition, make sure to use the GPT partition table
       type instead of the MSDOS type. Otherwise the GRUB2 boot loader may not
       have enough space for the second stage loader.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry os="sles" arch="zseries">
     <term>&zseries;: Using minidisks in z/VM</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If &productname; is installed on minidisks in z/VM, which reside
       on the same physical disk, the access path of the minidisks
       (/dev/disk/by-id/) is not unique. This is because it represents
       the ID of the physical disk. If two or more minidisks are on the
       same physical disk, they all have the same ID.
      </para>
      <para>
       To avoid problems when mounting minidisks, always mount them either
       <emphasis>by path</emphasis> or <emphasis>by UUID</emphasis>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry os="sles" arch="zseries">
     <term>&zseries;: LVM root file system</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If you configure the system with a root file system on LVM or software
       RAID array, you must place <filename>/boot</filename> on a separate,
       non-LVM or non-RAID partition, otherwise the system will fail to boot.
       The recommended size for such a partition is 500&nbsp;MB and the
       recommended file system is Ext4.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry os="sles" arch="power">
     <!-- this warning is duplicated in sec.power.prep -->
     <term>IBM &power;: Installing on systems with multiple Fibre Channel disks</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If more than one disk is available, the partitioning scheme suggested during
       the installation puts the PReP and BOOT partitions on different disks. If
       these disks are Fibre Channel disks, the GRUB boot loader is not able to
       find the BOOT partition and the system cannot be booted.
      </para>
      <para>
       When prompted to select the partition scheme during the installation,
       choose <guimenu>Guided Setup</guimenu> and verify that only one disk is
       selected for installation. Alternatively, run the <guimenu>Expert
       Partitioner</guimenu> and manually set up a partitioning scheme that has
       PReP and BOOT on a single disk.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
     <term>Supported software RAID volumes</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Installing to and booting from existing software RAID volumes is
       supported for Disk Data Format (DDF) volumes and Intel Matrix Storage
       Manager (IMSM) volumes. IMSM is also known by the following names:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Intel Rapid Storage Technology
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Intel Matrix Storage Technology
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Intel Application Accelerator / Intel Application Accelerator RAID
         Edition
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Intel Virtual RAID on CPU (Intel VROC, see <link xlink:href="https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/support/articles/000024498/memory-and-storage/ssd-software.html"/> for more details)
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Mount points for FCoE and iSCSI devices</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       FCoE and iSCSI devices will appear asynchronously during the
       boot process. While the initrd guarantees that those devices are
       set up correctly for the root file system, there are no such
       guarantees for any other file systems or mount points like
       <filename>/usr</filename>. Hence any system mount points like
       <filename>/usr</filename> or <filename>/var</filename> are not
       supported. To use those devices, ensure correct
       synchronization of the respective services and devices.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry os="sled;osuse">
     <term>Handling of Windows partitions in proposals</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In case the disk selected for the suggested partitioning proposal
       contains a large Windows FAT or NTFS partition, it will automatically be
       resized to make room for the &productname; installation. To avoid data
       loss it is strongly recommended to
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
       <listitem>
        <para>
         make sure the partition is not fragmented (run a defragmentation
         program from Windows prior to the &productname; installation)
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         double-check the suggested size for the Windows partition is big enough
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         back up your data prior to the &productname; installation
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
       To adjust the proposed size of the Windows partition, use the
       <guimenu>Expert Partitioner</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry os="osuse">
     <term>Proposal with a separate home partition</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The default proposal no longer suggests to create a separate partition
      for <filename>/home</filename>. The <filename>/home</filename> directory
      contains the user's data and personal configuration files. Placing it on
      a separate directory makes it easier to rebuild the system in the future,
      or allows to share it with different Linux installations on the same
      machine.
     </para>
     <para>
      In case you want to change the proposal to create a separate partition
      for <filename>/home</filename>, choose <guimenu>Guided Setup</guimenu>
      and click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> until you reach the <guimenu>Filesystem
      Options</guimenu> screen. Check <guimenu>Propose Separate Home
      Partition</guimenu>. By default it will be formatted with
      <guimenu>XFS</guimenu>, but you can choose to use a different file
      system. Close the dialog by clicking <guimenu>Next</guimenu> again.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-partitioning-suggested">
   <title>Suggested partitioning</title>
   <para>
    Define a partition setup for &productname; in this step.
   </para>
   <figure>
    <title>Suggested partitioning</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <textobject role="description">
      <phrase>Suggested Partitioning</phrase>
     </textobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata os="sles;sled;slemicro" fileref="install_partitioner.png" width="100%"/>
      <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_partitioner_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata os="sles;sled;slemicro" fileref="install_partitioner.png" width="100%"/>
      <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_partitioner_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para os="sled;osuse">
    The installer creates a proposal for one of the available disks containing
    a root partition formatted with Btrfs and a swap partition. If one or more
    swap partitions have been detected on the available hard disks, these
    partitions will be used. You have several options to proceed:
   </para>
   <para os="sles">
    Depending on the system role, the installer creates a proposal for one of
    the disks available. All proposals contain a root partition formatted with
    Btrfs (with snapshots enabled) and a swap partition. The GNOME desktop and
    the text mode proposals create a separate home partition on disks larger
    than 20 GB. The system roles for virtualization hosts create a separate
    partition for <filename>/var/lib/libvirt</filename>, the directory that
    hosts the image files by default. If one or more swap partitions have been
    detected on the available hard disks, these existing ones will be used
    (rather than proposing a new swap partition). You have several options to
    proceed:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Next</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To accept the proposal without any changes, click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>
       to proceed with the installation workflow.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Guided setup</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To adjust the proposal, choose <guimenu>Guided Setup</guimenu>. First,
       choose which hard disks and partitions to use. In the
       <guimenu>Partitioning Scheme</guimenu> screen, you can enable Logical
       Volume Management (LVM) and activate disk encryption. Afterward specify
       the <guimenu>Filesystem Options</guimenu>. You can adjust the file
       system for the root partition and create a separate home and swap
       partitions. If you plan to suspend your machine, make sure to create a
       separate swap partition and check <guimenu>Enlarge to RAM Size for
       Suspend</guimenu>.  If the root file system format is Btrfs, you can
       also enable or disable Btrfs snapshots here.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Expert Partitioner</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To create a custom partition setup click <guimenu>Expert
        Partitioner</guimenu>. Select either <guimenu>Start with Current
        Proposal</guimenu> if you want start with the suggested disk layout, or
       <guimenu>Start with Existing Partitions</guimenu> to ignore the suggested
       layout and start with the existing layout on the disk.  You can
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu>, <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>,
       <guimenu>Resize</guimenu>, or <guimenu>Delete</guimenu> partitions.
      </para>
      <para>
       You can also set up logical volume management (LVM), configure software
       RAID and device mapping (DM), encrypt partitions, mount NFS shares and
       manage tmpfs volumes with the <guimenu>Expert Partitioner</guimenu>. To
       fine-tune settings such as the subvolume and snapshot handling for each
       Btrfs partition, choose <guimenu>Btrfs</guimenu>. For more information
       about custom partitioning and configuring advanced features, refer to
       <xref linkend="sec-expert-partitioner"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <warning>
    <title>Disk space units</title>
    <para>
     Note that for partitioning purposes, disk space is measured in binary
     units, rather than in decimal units. For example, if you enter sizes of
     <literal>1GB</literal>, <literal>1GiB</literal> or <literal>1G</literal>,
     they all signify 1&nbsp;GiB (Gibibyte), as opposed to 1&nbsp;GB (Gigabyte).
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Binary</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        1&nbsp;GiB = 1&nbsp;073&nbsp;741&nbsp;824 bytes.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       Decimal
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        1&nbsp;GB = 1&nbsp;000&nbsp;000&nbsp;000 bytes.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       Difference
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        1&nbsp;GiB &asymp; 1.07&nbsp;GB.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </warning>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-install-date-time">
  <title>Clock and time zone</title>
  <para>
   In this dialog, select your region and time zone. Both are preselected
   according to the installation language.
  </para>
  <figure>
   <title>Clock and time zone</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Clock and Time Zone</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata os="sles;sled;slemicro" fileref="install_timezone.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_timezone_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata os="sles;sled;slemicro" fileref="install_timezone.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_timezone_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
   To change the preselected values, either use the map or the drop-down boxes
   for <guimenu>Region</guimenu> and <guimenu>Time Zone</guimenu>. When using
   the map, point the cursor at the rough direction of your region and
   left-click to zoom. Now choose your country or region by
   left-clicking. Right-click to return to the world map.
  </para>
  <para>
   To set up the clock, choose whether the <guimenu>Hardware Clock is Set to
   UTC</guimenu>. If you run another operating system on your machine, such as
   Microsoft Windows, it is likely your system uses local time instead. If you
   run Linux on your machine, set the hardware clock to UTC and have the
   switch from standard time to daylight saving time performed automatically.
  </para>
  <important>
   <title>Set the hardware clock to UTC</title>
   <para>
    The switch from standard time to daylight saving time (and vice versa) can
    only be performed automatically when the hardware clock (CMOS clock) is set
    to UTC. This also applies if you use automatic time synchronization with
    NTP, because automatic synchronization will only be performed if the time
    difference between the hardware and system clock is less than 15 minutes.
   </para>
   <para>
    Since a wrong system time can cause serious problems (missed backups,
    dropped mail messages, mount failures on remote file systems, etc.), it is
    strongly recommended to <emphasis>always</emphasis> set the hardware clock
    to UTC.
   </para>
  </important>
  <para arch="power;x86_64" os="sles">
   If a network is already configured, you can configure time synchronization
   with an NTP server. Click <guimenu>Other Settings</guimenu> to either alter
   the NTP settings or to <guimenu>Manually</guimenu> set the time. See
   <xref linkend="cha-ntp"/> for more information on configuring the NTP
   service. When finished, click <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to continue the
   installation.
  </para>
  <para arch="power;x86_64" os="sles">
   If running without NTP configured, consider setting
   <literal>SYSTOHC=no</literal> (<literal>sysconfig</literal> variable) to
   avoid saving unsynchronized time into the hardware clock.
  </para>
  <para os="sled;osuse">
   If a network is already configured, you can configure time synchronization
   with an NTP server. Click <guimenu>Other Settings</guimenu> to either alter
   the NTP settings or to <guimenu>Manually</guimenu> set the time. See
   <xref linkend="cha-ntp"/> for more information on configuring the NTP
   service. When finished, click <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to continue the
   installation.
  </para>
  <para os="sled;osuse">
   If running without NTP configured, consider setting
   <literal>SYSTOHC=no</literal> (<literal>sysconfig</literal> variable) to
   avoid saving unsynchronized time into the hardware clock.
  </para>
  <note arch="zseries" os="sles;slemicro">
   <title>Time cannot be changed on &zseries;</title>
   <para>
    Since the operating system is not allowed to change time and date directly,
    the <guimenu>Other Settings</guimenu> option is not available on
    &zseries;.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 os="sles;sled;osuse" xml:id="sec-yast-install-user">
  <title>Create new user</title>
  <para>
   Create a local user in this step.
  </para>
  <figure>
   <title>Create new user</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Create New User</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata os="sles;sled" fileref="install_user.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_user_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata os="sles;sled" fileref="install_user.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_user_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
   After entering the first name and last name, either accept the proposal or
   specify a new <guimenu>User name</guimenu> that will be used to log in. Only
   use lowercase letters (a-z), digits (0-9) and the characters
   <literal>.</literal> (dot), <literal>-</literal> (hyphen) and
   <literal>_</literal> (underscore). Special characters, umlauts and accented
   characters are not allowed.
  </para>
  <para>
   Finally, enter a password for the user. Re-enter it for confirmation (to
   ensure that you did not type something else by mistake). To provide
   effective security, a password should be at least six characters long and
   consist of uppercase and lowercase letters, numbers and special characters
   (7-bit ASCII). Umlauts or accented characters are not allowed. Passwords you
   enter are checked for weakness. When entering a password that is easy to
   guess (such as a dictionary word or a name) you will see a warning. It is a
   good security practice to use strong passwords.
  </para>
  <important>
   <title>User name and password</title>
   <para>
    Remember both your user name and the password because they are needed each
    time you log in to the system.
   </para>
  </important>
  <para>
   If you install &productname; on a machine with one or more existing Linux
   installations, &yast; allows you to import user data such as user names
   and passwords. Select <guimenu>Import User Data from a Previous
   Installation</guimenu> and then <guimenu>Choose Users</guimenu> for
   import.
  </para>
  <para>If you do not want to configure any
  local users (for example when setting up a client on a network with
  centralized user authentication), skip this step by choosing
  <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and confirming the warning. Network user
  authentication can be configured at any time later in the installed system;
  refer to <xref linkend="cha-yast-userman"/> for instructions.
  </para>
  <para>
   Two additional options are available:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Use this password for system administrator</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If checked, the same password you have entered for the user will be used
      for the system administrator &rootuser;. This option is suitable for
      stand-alone workstations or machines in a home network that are
      administrated by a single user. When not checked, you are prompted for a
      system administrator password in the next step of the installation
      workflow (see <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-user-root"/>).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Automatic login</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option automatically logs the current user in to the system when it
      starts. This is mainly useful if the computer is operated by only one
      user. <phrase os="sles">For automatic login to work, the option must be
      explicitly enabled.</phrase>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <warning>
   <title>Automatic login</title>
   <para>
    With the automatic login enabled, the system boots straight into your
    desktop with no authentication. If you store sensitive data on your system,
    you should not enable this option if the computer can also be accessed by
    others.
   </para>
  </warning>
  <para>
   In an environment where users are centrally managed (for example by NIS or
   LDAP) you should skip the creation of local users. Select <guimenu>Skip
   User Creation</guimenu> in this case.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-install-user-root">
  <title>Authentication for the system administrator &rootuser;</title>
  <para>
   If you have not chosen <guimenu>Use this Password for System
   Administrator</guimenu> in the previous step, you will be prompted to enter
   a password for the System Administrator &rootuser; or provide a public SSH
   key. Otherwise this configuration step is skipped.
  </para>
  <figure>
   <title>Authentication for the system administrator &rootuser;</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Authentication for the System Administrator &rootuser;</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata os="sles;sled;slemicro" fileref="install_root.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_root_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata os="sles;sled;slemicro" fileref="install_root.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_root_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
   &rootuser; is the name of the superuser, or the administrator of the system.
   Unlike regular users, &rootuser; has unlimited
   rights to change the system configuration, install programs, and set up new
   hardware. If users forget their passwords or have other problems with the
   system, &rootuser; can help. The &rootuser; account should only be used for
   system administration, maintenance, and repair. Logging in as &rootuser; for
   daily work is rather risky: a single mistake could lead to irretrievable
   loss of system files.
  </para>
  <para>
   For verification purposes, the password for &rootuser; must be entered
   twice. Do not forget the &rootuser; password. After having been entered,
   this password cannot be retrieved.
  </para>
  <tip>
   <title>Passwords and keyboard layout</title>
   <para>
    It is recommended to only use US ASCII characters. In case of a system
    error or when you need to start your system in rescue mode, the keyboard
    may not be localized.
   </para>
  </tip>
  <para>
   The &rootuser; password can be changed any time later in the installed
   system. To do so run &yast; and start <menuchoice> <guimenu>Security and
   Users</guimenu> <guimenu>User and Group Management</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
  </para>
  <important>
   <title>The <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> user</title>
   <para>
    The user &rootuser; has all the permissions needed to make changes to the
    system. To carry out such tasks, the &rootuser; password is required. You
    cannot carry out any administrative tasks without this password.
   </para>
  </important>

  <para>
   If you want to access the system remotely via SSH using a public key, import
   a key from a removable storage device or an existing partition.
   <!-- FIXME cwickert 2021-06-27: Remove following sentence and use it as
    result of the precedure instead, once we have a style for that. See comment
    further at the end of precedure.
   -->
   After the installation is finished, you can log in through SSH using the
   provided SSH key.
  </para>
  <procedure xml:id="pro-yast-install-user-root-sshkey">
   <title>Adding a public SSH key for user &rootuser;</title>
   <para>
    To import a public SSH key from a medium partition, perform the following
    steps:
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     The public SSH key is located in your <filename
      class="directory">~/.ssh</filename> directory and has the file extension
     <filename class="extension">.pub</filename>. Copy it to a removable storage
     device or an existing partition that is not formatted during installation.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If your key is on a removable storage device, insert it into your computer
     and click <guimenu>Refresh</guimenu>. You should see the device in the
     drop-down box under <guimenu>Import Public Key</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Browse</guimenu>, select the public SSH key and confirm with
     <guimenu>Open</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <!-- FIXME cwickert 2021-06-27 Commented out until we have a style for
    result, see https://github.com/openSUSE/suse-xsl/issues/286 -->
   <!--
   <result>
    <para>
     After the installation is finished, you can log in through SSH using the
     provided SSH key.
    </para>
   </result> -->
  </procedure>
  <!-- cwickert 2021-06-25: Behavior changed in SLE 15 SP3 with SLE-15487:
   No root password set, SSH key only: Port will be opened by yast automatically
   to avoid being locked out of the newly installed system.
   Password and key: Port will not be opened automatically, enable it manually
   if you need remote access right after installation.
  -->
  <para>
   If you have both set a password and added a public SSH key, and need remote
   access right after the installation, do not forget to open the SSH port in
   the <guimenu>Security</guimenu> section of the <guimenu>Installation
   Settings</guimenu> summary. If you set no password but only add a key, the
   port will be opened automatically to prevent you from being locked out of the newly
   installed system.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-install-proposal">
  <title>Installation settings</title>
  <para>
   On the last step before the real installation takes place, you can alter
   installation settings suggested by the installer. To modify the suggestions,
   click the respective headline. After having made changes to a particular
   setting, you are always returned to the Installation Settings window, which
   is updated accordingly.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you have added an SSH key for your &rootuser; as mentioned in <xref
    linkend="pro-yast-install-user-root-sshkey" xrefstyle="select:label"/>,
   make sure to open the SSH port in the <guimenu>Security</guimenu> settings.
  </para>
  <figure>
   <title>Installation settings</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Installation Settings</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata os="sles;slemicro" fileref="install_summary_sles.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="sled" fileref="install_summary_sled.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_summary_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata os="sles;slemicro" fileref="install_summary_sles.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="sled" fileref="install_summary_sled.png" width="100%"/>
     <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_summary_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-proposal-sofware">
   <title><guimenu>Software</guimenu></title>
   <remark>Mention Cockpit here.</remark>
   <para>
    &productname; contains several software patterns for various application
    purposes. The available choice of patterns and packages depends on your
    selection of modules and extensions.
   </para>
   <para>
    Click <guimenu>Software</guimenu> to open the <guimenu>Software
    Selection and System Tasks</guimenu> screen where you can modify the
    pattern selection according to your needs. Select a pattern from the list
    and see a description in the right-hand part of the window.
   </para>
   <para>
    Each pattern contains several software packages needed for specific
    functions (for example <phrase os="sled;osuse">Multimedia or Office
    software</phrase><phrase os="sles">Web and LAMP server or a print
    server</phrase>).  <phrase os="osuse">If you chose <guimenu>Generic
    Desktop</guimenu> in the <guimenu>System Role</guimenu> dialog choose a
    desktop environment from the list of available <guimenu>Graphical
    Environments</guimenu>.</phrase> For a more detailed selection based on
    software packages to install, select <guimenu>Details</guimenu> to switch
    to the &yast; Software Manager.
   </para>
   <figure>
    <title>Software selection and system tasks</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <textobject role="description">
      <phrase>Software Selection and System Tasks</phrase>
     </textobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata os="sles;slemicro" fileref="install_software_sles.png" width="100%"/>
      <imagedata os="sled" fileref="install_software_sled.png" width="100%"/>
      <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_software_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata os="sles;slemicro" fileref="install_software_sles.png" width="100%"/>
      <imagedata os="sled" fileref="install_software_sled.png" width="100%"/>
      <imagedata os="osuse" fileref="install_software_osuse.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para os="sles;sled;osuse">
    You can also install additional software packages or remove software
    packages from your system at any later time with the &yast; Software
    Manager. For more information, refer to <xref linkend="cha-yast-software"/>.
   </para>
   <para os="sles">
    If you choose to install GNOME, &productname; is installed with the X.org
    display server. As an alternative to &gnome;, the lightweight
    window manager IceWM can be installed. Select <guimenu>Details</guimenu>
    from the <guimenu>Software Selection and System Tasks</guimenu> screen and
    search for <literal>icewm</literal>.
   </para>
   <para os="sled;osuse">
    By default, &productname; uses the Wayland display server protocol.
   </para>
   <tip os="sles;slemicro" arch="zseries">
    <title>&zseries;: Hardware cryptography support</title>
    <para>
     The hardware cryptography stack is not installed by default. To install
     it, select <guimenu>System z HW crypto support</guimenu> in the
     <guimenu>Software Selection and System Tasks</guimenu> screen.
    </para>
   </tip>
   <tip xml:id="ann-sec-yast-install-proposal-sofware-language">
    <title>Adding secondary languages</title>
    <para>
     The language you selected with the first step of the installation will be
     used as the primary (default) language for the system. You can add
     secondary languages from within the <guimenu>Software</guimenu> dialog by
     choosing <menuchoice> <guimenu>Details</guimenu> <guimenu>View</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Languages</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </tip>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-proposal-booting">
   <title><guimenu>Booting</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    The installer proposes a boot configuration for your system. Other
    operating systems found on your computer, such as Microsoft Windows or
    other Linux installations, will automatically be detected and added to the
    boot loader. However, &productname; will be booted by default. Normally,
    you can leave these settings unchanged. If you need a custom setup, modify
    the proposal according to your needs. <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse">For information, see
    <xref linkend="sec-grub2-yast2-config"/>.</phrase>
   </para>
   <important>
    <title>Software RAID 1</title>
    <para>
     Booting a configuration where <filename>/boot</filename> resides on a
     software RAID 1 device is supported, but it requires to install the boot
     loader into the MBR (<menuchoice> <guimenu>Boot Loader Location</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Boot from Master Boot Record</guimenu> </menuchoice>). Having
     <filename>/boot</filename> on software RAID devices with a level other
     than RAID 1 is not supported. <phrase os="sles">Also see
     <xref
     linkend="cha-raidroot"/>.</phrase>
    </para>
   </important>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-proposal-security">
   <title><guimenu>Security</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>CPU Mitigations</guimenu> refer to kernel boot command line
    parameters for software mitigations that have been deployed to prevent CPU
    side-channel attacks. Click the selected entry to choose a different
    option.<phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"> For details, see
     <xref linkend="vle-grub2-yast2-cpu-mitigations"/>.</phrase>
   </para>
   <para>
    By default, the <guimenu>Firewall</guimenu> is enabled on all configured
    network interfaces. To completely disable &firewalld;, click
    <guimenu>disable</guimenu> (not recommended).
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>Firewall settings</title>
    <para>
     When the firewall is activated, all interfaces are assigned to the
     <literal>public</literal> zone, where all ports are closed by default,
     ensuring maximum security. The only port you can open during the
     installation is port 22 (SSH), to allow remote access. Other services
     requiring network access (such as FTP, Samba, Web server, etc.) will only
     work after having adjusted the firewall settings. <phrase
      os="sles;sled;osuse">Refer to <xref linkend="cha-security-firewall"/>
      for configuration details.</phrase>
    </para>
   </note>
   &note_firewall_updates;
   <para>
    The <guimenu>SSH service</guimenu> is enabled by default, but its port
    (22) is closed in the firewall. Click <guimenu>open</guimenu> to open the
    port or <guimenu>disable</guimenu> to disable the service. Note that if SSH
    is disabled, remote logins will not be possible. <phrase
     os="sles;sled;osuse">Refer to <xref linkend="cha-ssh"/> for more
     information.</phrase>
   </para>
   <tip>
    <title>Existing SSH host keys</title>
    <para>
     If you install &productname; on a machine with existing Linux
     installations, the installation routine imports an SSH host key. It
     chooses the host key with the most recent access time by default.
     <phrase os="sles;sled">See also
     <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-proposal-sshimport"/>.</phrase>
    </para>
   </tip>
   <para>
    If you are performing a remote administration over VNC, you can also
    specify whether the machine should be accessible via VNC after the
    installation. Note that enabling VNC also requires you to set the
    <guimenu>Default systemd Target</guimenu> to <guimenu>graphical</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The default <guimenu>Major Linux Security Module</guimenu> is
    <guimenu>AppAmpor</guimenu>. To disable it, selese <guimenu>None</guimenu>
    as module in the <guimenu>Security</guimenu> settings. This
    allows you to deselect the <guimenu>AppAmor</guimenu> pattern in the
    <guimenu>Software</guimenu> settings
    (<xref linkend="sec-yast-install-proposal-sofware"/>).
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 os="sles;sled" xml:id="sec-yast-install-proposal-security-profile">
   <!--
    FIXME cwickert 2023-02-09: JSC#SLE-25039; additional profiles will be added
    later and the implementation will likely change.
   -->
   <title><guimenu>Security Profiles</guimenu></title>
   <important>
    <title>Availability in &sle; 15 SP4</title>
    <para>
     This feature is available for &sle; 15 SP4 GM via installer self-update or
     using the QU2 media.
    </para>
   </important>
   <para>
    This category allows hardening your system with &openscap; security
    policies. The first policy that was implemented is the
   <literal>&stig; (&stiga;)</literal> by the <orgname>&disa;</orgname>
   (<orgname>&disaa;</orgname>).
   </para>
   <para>
    Click to <guimenu>enable</guimenu> the security policy. Incompliant
    installation settings will be listed with the rule they violate. Some
    settings can be adjusted automatically by clicking <guimenu>fix
     rule</guimenu>. For settings that require user input, click
    <guimenu>modify settings</guimenu> to open the respective settings screen.
   </para>
   <tip>
    <title>Checking policy compliance during installation</title>
    <para>
     If you do not want to wait for the <guimenu>Installation
      Settings</guimenu> screen but want the installer to check the settings
     from the beginning of the installation process, boot the system with the
     boot parameter
     <literal>YAST_SECURITY_POLICY=<replaceable>POLICY</replaceable></literal>.
     To check for compliance with the &disaa; &stiga;, use 
     <literal>YAST_SECURITY_POLICY=stig</literal>. For more information about
     boot parameters, refer to <xref linkend="cha-boot-parameters"/>.
    </para>
   </tip>
   <para>
    The installer does not check all rules of the profile but only those
    necessary for the installation or that are hard to fix afterward. To apply
    the remaining rules, a full SCAP remediation is performed on first boot. You
    can also perform a <guimenu>scan only</guimenu> or <guimenu>do
     nothing</guimenu> and manually remediate the system later with &openscap;.
    For more information, refer to the articles
    <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/compliance/all/html/SLES-stig/article-stig.html"><citetitle>Hardening &sle; with STIG</citetitle></link>
    and
    <link
     xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/compliance/all/html/SLES-openscap/article-openscap.html"><citetitle>Hardening
      &sle; with &openscap;</citetitle></link>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-proposal-network">
   <title><guimenu>Network configuration</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    This category displays the current network settings, as automatically
    configured after booting into the installation (see <xref
    linkend="sec-yast-install-network" xrefstyle="select:label"/>) or as manually
    configured from the <guimenu>Registration</guimenu> or
    <guimenu>Add-On Product</guimenu> dialog during the respective steps of
    the installation process. If you want to check or adjust the network settings
    at this stage (before performing the installation), click
    <guimenu>Network Configuration</guimenu>. This takes you to the &yast;
    <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu> module.<phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"> For details, see
    <xref linkend="sec-network-yast"/>.</phrase>
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-proposal-kdump" os="sles;slemicro">
   <title><guimenu>Kdump</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    Using Kdump, you can save a dump of the kernel (in case of a crash) to
    analyze what went wrong. Use this dialog to enable and configure Kdump.
    <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse">Find detailed information at <xref linkend="cha-tuning-kexec"/>.</phrase>
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-proposal-blacklist" os="sles;slemicros" arch="zseries">
   <title><guimenu>&zseries;: blacklist devices</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    To save memory, all channels for devices currently not in use are
    blacklisted by default (each channel that is not blacklisted occupies
    approximately 50 KB of memory). To configure additional hardware in the
    installed system using channels that are currently blacklisted, run the
    respective &yast; module to enable the respective channels first.
    <remark condition="clarity">
     2014-06-05 - fs: FIXME What's the name of the yast module?
    </remark>
   </para>
   <para>
    To disable blacklisting, click <guimenu>disable</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-proposal-runlevel">
   <title><guimenu>Default systemd target</guimenu></title>
   <remark>No graphical target.</remark>
   <para>
    &productname; can boot into two different targets (formerly known as
    <quote>runlevels</quote>). The <guimenu>graphical</guimenu> target starts a
    display manager, whereas the <guimenu>multi-user</guimenu> target starts
    the command line interface.
   </para>
   <para>
    The default target is <guimenu>graphical</guimenu>. In case you have not
    installed the <guimenu>X Window System</guimenu> patterns, you need to
    change it to <guimenu>multi-user</guimenu>. If the system should be
    accessible via VNC, you need to choose <guimenu>graphical</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-proposal-sshimport">
   <title><guimenu>Import SSH host keys and configuration</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    If an existing Linux installation on your computer was detected, &yast;
    will import the most recent SSH host key found in
    <filename>/etc/ssh</filename> by default, optionally including other files
    in the directory as well. This makes it possible to reuse the SSH identity
    of the existing installation, avoiding the <literal>REMOTE HOST
    IDENTIFICATION HAS CHANGED</literal> warning on the first connection. Note
    that this item is not shown in the installation summary if &yast; has not
    discovered any other installations. You have the following choices:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>
       I would like to import SSH keys from a previous install:
      </guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Select this option to import the SSH host key and optionally
       the configuration of an installed system. You can select the
       installation to import from in the option list below.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>
       Import SSH Configuration
      </guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Enable this to copy other files in <filename>/etc/ssh</filename> to the
       installed system in addition to the host keys.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-proposal-system">
   <title><guimenu>System</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    This screen lists all the hardware information the installer could obtain
    about your computer. When opened for the first time, the hardware detection
    is started. Depending on your system, this may take some time. Select any
    item in the list and click <guimenu>Details</guimenu> to see detailed
    information about the selected item. Use <guimenu>Save to File</guimenu> to
    save a detailed list to either the local file system or a removable device.
   </para>
   <para>
    Advanced users can also change the <guimenu>PCI ID Setup</guimenu> and
    kernel settings by choosing <guimenu>Kernel Settings</guimenu>. A screen
    with two tabs opens:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>PCI ID setup</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Each kernel driver contains a list of device IDs of all devices it
       supports. If a new device is not in any driver's database, the device is
       treated as unsupported, even if it can be used with an existing driver.
       You can add PCI IDs to a device driver here. Only advanced users should
       attempt to do so.
      </para>
      <para>
       To add an ID, click <guimenu>Add</guimenu> and select whether to
       <guimenu>Manually</guimenu> enter the data, or whether to choose from a
       list. Enter the required data. The <guimenu>SysFS Dir</guimenu> is the
       directory name from <filename>/sys/bus/pci/drivers</filename>&mdash;if
       empty, the <guimenu>driver</guimenu> name is used as the directory name.
       Existing entries can be managed with <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> and
       <guimenu>Delete</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Kernel settings</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Change the <guimenu>Global I/O Scheduler</guimenu> here. If <guimenu>Not
       Configured</guimenu> is chosen, the default setting for the respective
       architecture will be used.<phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"> This setting can also be changed at any time
       later from the installed system. Refer to
       <xref linkend="cha-tuning-io"/> for details on I/O tuning.</phrase>
      </para>
      <para>
       Also activate the <guimenu>Enable SysRq Keys</guimenu> here. These keys
       will let you issue basic commands (such as rebooting the system or
       writing kernel dumps) in case the system crashes. Enabling these keys is
       recommended when doing kernel development. Refer to
       <link xlink:href="https://www.kernel.org/doc/html/latest/admin-guide/sysrq.html"/>
       for details.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-install-perform">
  <title>Performing the installation</title>
  <para>
   After configuring all installation settings, click
   <guimenu>Install</guimenu> in the Installation Settings window to start the
   installation. Some software may require a license confirmation. If your
   software selection includes such software, license confirmation dialogs
   are displayed. Click <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to install the software
   package.  When not agreeing to the license, click <guimenu>I
   Disagree</guimenu> and the software package will not be installed. In the
   dialog that follows, confirm with <guimenu>Install</guimenu> again.
  </para>
  <para>
   The installation usually takes between 15 and 30 minutes, depending on the
   system performance and the selected software scope. After having prepared
   the hard disk and having saved and restored the user settings, the software
   installation starts. Choose <guimenu>Details</guimenu> to switch to the
   installation log or <guimenu>Release Notes</guimenu> to read important
   up-to-date information that was not available when the manuals were printed.
  </para>
  <para>
   After the software installation has completed, the system reboots into the
   new installation where you can log in. To customize the system configuration
   or to install additional software packages, start &yast;.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-s390-inst-reipl" arch="zseries" os="sles;slemicro">
   <title>&zseries;: IPLing the installed system</title>
   <para>
    &yast; usually reboots into the installed system on the &zseries;
    platform. Exceptions are installations where the boot loader
    resides on an FCP device in environments with LPAR on a machine older than
    z196 or with z/VM older than release 5.4. The boot loader gets written to a
    separate partition mounted as <filename>/boot/zipl/</filename>.
   </para>
   <para>
    In cases where an automatic reboot is not possible, &yast; will show a
    dialog containing information about from which device to do an IPL. Accept
    the shutdown option and perform an IPL after the shutdown. The procedure
    varies according to the type of installation:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>LPAR installation</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In the &zseries; HMC, select <guimenu>Load</guimenu>, select
       <guimenu>Clear</guimenu>, then enter the loading address (the address of
       the device containing the <filename>/boot/zipl</filename> directory with
       the boot loader). If using a zFCP disk as the boot device, choose
       <guimenu>Load from SCSI</guimenu> and specify the load address of your
       FCP adapter plus WWPN and LUN of the boot device. Now start the loading
       process.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>z/VM installation</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Log in to the VM guest (see
       <xref linkend="ex-prep-prep-ipl-vm-linux-guest-config"/> for the
       configuration) as <systemitem class="username">LINUX1</systemitem> and
       proceed to IPL the installed system:
      </para>
      <screen>IPL 151 CLEAR</screen>
      <para>
       <literal>151</literal> is an example address of the DASD boot device,
       replace this value with the correct address.
      </para>
      <para>
       If using a zFCP disk as the boot device, specify both the zFCP WWPN and
       LUN of the boot device before initiating the IPL. The parameter length
       is limited to eight characters. Longer numbers must be separated by
       spaces:
      </para>
      <screen>SET LOADDEV PORT 50050763 00C590A9 LUN 50010000 00000000 </screen>
      <para>
       Finally, initiate the IPL:
      </para>
      <screen>IPL FC00</screen>
      <para>
       <literal>FC00</literal> is an example address of the zFCP adapter,
       replace this value with the correct address.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>KVM guest installation</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       After the installation has finished, the virtual machine is shut
       down. At this point, log in to the KVM host, edit the virtual machine's
       description file and restart it to IPL into the installed system:
      </para>
      <procedure>
       <step>
        <para>
        Log in to the KVM host.
        </para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>
        Edit the domain XML file by running
        </para>
        <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>virsh edit s12-1</command></screen>
        <para>
        and remove the following lines:
        </para>
<screen><![CDATA[  <!-- Boot kernel - remove 3 lines after successfull installation -->
  <kernel>/var/lib/libvirt/images/s12-kernel.boot</kernel>
  <initrd>/var/lib/libvirt/images/s12-initrd.boot</initrd>
  <cmdline>linuxrcstderr=/dev/console</cmdline>]]></screen>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>
        Restart the &vmguest; to IPL into the installed system:
        </para>
        <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>virsh start s12-1 --console</command></screen>
       </step>
      </procedure>
      <note>
       <title><literal>cio_ignore</literal> is disabled for KVM installations</title>
       <para>
        The kernel parameter <literal>cio_ignore</literal> prevents the kernel
        from looking at all the available hardware devices. However, for KVM
        guests, the hypervisor already takes care to only provide access to the
        correct devices. Therefore <literal>cio_ignore</literal> is disabled by
        default when installing a KVM guest (for z/VM and LPAR installations it
        is activated by default).
       </para>
      </note>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-s390-inst-reipl-reconnect" arch="zseries" os="sles">
   <title>&zseries;: Connecting to the installed system</title>
   <para>
    After IPLing the system, establish a connection via VNC, SSH, or X to log
    in to the installed system. Using either VNC or SSH is recommended. To
    customize the system configuration or to install additional software
    packages, start &yast;.
   </para>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec-s390-inst-reipl-reconnect-vnc">
    <title>Using VNC to connect</title>
    <para>
     A message in the 3270&nbsp;terminal asks you to connect to the Linux
     system using a VNC client. However, this message is easily missed, because
     it is mixed with kernel messages and the terminal process might quit
     before you notice the message. If nothing happens for five
     minutes, try to initiate a connection to the Linux system using a VNC
     viewer.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you connect using a JavaScript-capable browser, enter the complete URL,
     consisting of the IP address of the installed system along with the port
     number, in the following fashion:
    </para>
<screen>http://<replaceable>IP_OF_INSTALLED_SYSTEM</replaceable>:5801/</screen>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec-s390-inst-reipl-reconnect-ssh">
    <title>Using SSH to connect</title>
    <para>
     A message in the 3270&nbsp;terminal asks you to connect to the Linux
     system with an SSH client. This message is easily missed, however, because
     it is mixed with kernel messages and the terminal process might quit
     before you become aware of the message.
    </para>
    <para>
     When the message appears, use SSH to log in to the Linux system as
     &rootuser;. If the connection is denied or times out, wait for the login
     timeout to expire, then try again (this time depends on server
     settings).
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec-s390-inst-reipl-reconnect-x">
    <title>Using X to connect</title>
    <para>
     When IPLing the installed system, make sure that the X server used for the
     first phase of the installation is up and still available before booting
     from the DASD. &yast; opens on this X server to finish the installation.
     Complications may arise if the system is booted up but unable to connect
     to the X server in a timely fashion.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
