<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha-install"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Installation steps</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    This chapter describes the procedure in which the data for &productname; is
    copied to the target device. Some basic configuration parameters for the
    newly installed system are set during the procedure. A graphical user
    interface will guide you through the installation.
    <phrase os="sles;sled">The procedure described in the following also
    applies to remote installation procedures as described in
    <xref linkend="cha-remote-installation"/>.</phrase> The text-mode
    installation has the same steps but looks different.
    <phrase
    os="sles;osuse;slemicro">For information about performing
    non-interactive automated installations, see
    <xref linkend="book-autoyast"/>.</phrase>
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  If you are a first-time user of &productname;, you should follow the default
  &yast; proposals in most parts, but you can also adjust the settings as
  described here to fine-tune your system according to your preferences. Help
  for each installation step is provided by clicking <guimenu>Help</guimenu>.
 </para>
 <tip>
  <title>Installation without a mouse</title>
  <para>
   If the installer does not detect your mouse correctly, use
   <keycap function="tab"/> for navigation, arrow keys to scroll, and
   <keycap function="enter"/> to confirm a selection. Various buttons or
   selection fields contain a letter with an underscore. Use
   <keycombo><keycap function="alt"/><keycap>Letter</keycap></keycombo> to
   select a button or a selection directly instead of navigating there with
   <keycap function="tab"/>.
  </para>
 </tip>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-man-install-overview">
  <title>Overview</title>

  <para>
   This section provides an overview of all installation steps. Each step
   contains a link to a more detailed description.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     At first, &yast; performs network configuration. For details, refer to
     <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-network"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The actual installation starts with language and keyboard selection and
     the license agreement. For details, refer to
     <xref linkend="sec-language-selection"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Accept the license agreement to proceed to the next step.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step arch="zseries">
    <para>
     &zseries; machines need to activate disks. For details, see
     <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-s390-part"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Register your system. For details, refer ro
     <xref linkend="sec-registration"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Install available extensions. For details, refer to
     <xref linkend="sec-live-extension"/>
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Configure NTP servers as described in
     <xref linkend="sec-ntp-configuration"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Set a password for the system administrator <literal>root</literal>. For
     details, refer to <xref linkend="sec-authentication"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The last installation step is an overview of all installation settings.
     For details, refer to <xref linkend="sec-settings"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-install-network">
  <title>Network settings</title>

  <para>
   After booting into the installation, the installation routine is set up.
   During this setup, an attempt to configure at least one network interface
   with DHCP is made. In case this attempt has failed, the <guimenu>Network
   Settings</guimenu> dialog launches now.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Network settings</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata  fileref="install_network_slem.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="install_network_slem.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   Choose a network interface from the list and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
   to change its settings. Use the tabs to configure DNS and routing. On
   &zseries; this dialog does not start automatically. It can be started in the
   <guimenu>Disk Activation</guimenu> step.
  </para>

  <para>
   In case DHCP was successfully configured during installation setup, you can
   also access this dialog by clicking <guimenu>Network Configuration</guimenu>
   at the <guimenu>&scc; Registration</guimenu> and the <guimenu>Installation
   Settings</guimenu> step. It lets you change the automatically provided
   settings.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>Network configuration with boot parameters</title>
   <para>
    If at least one network interface has been configured via boot parameters
    (see <xref linkend="sec-boot-parameters-list-network"/>), automatic DHCP
    configuration is disabled and the boot parameter configuration is imported
    and used.
   </para>
  </note>

  <tip>
   <title>Accessing network storage or local RAID</title>
   <para>
    To access a SAN or a local RAID during the installation, you can use the
    libstorage command line client for this purpose:
   </para>
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Switch to a console with <keycombo><keycap function="control"/>
      <keycap
      function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Install the libstoragemgmt extension by running <command>extend
      libstoragemgmt</command>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Now you have access to the <command>lsmcli</command> command. For more
      information, run <command>lsmcli --help</command>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To return to the installer, press <keycombo><keycap function="alt"/>
      <keycap>F7</keycap></keycombo>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
   <para>
    Supported are Netapp Ontap, all SMI-S compatible SAN providers, and LSI
    MegaRAID.
   </para>
  </tip>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-language-selection">
  <title>Language, Keyboard, and License Agreement</title>

  <figure>
   <title>License agreement</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata os="slemicro" fileref="install_license_slem.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata os="slemicro" fileref="install_license_slem.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   The <guimenu>Language</guimenu> and <guimenu>Keyboard Layout</guimenu>
   settings are initialized with the language you chose on the boot screen. If
   you did not change the default, it will be English (US). Change the settings
   here, if necessary.
  </para>

  <para>
   Changing the language will automatically preselect a corresponding keyboard
   layout. Override this proposal by selecting a different keyboard layout from
   the drop-down box. Use the <guimenu>Keyboard Test</guimenu> text box to test
   the layout. The language selected here is also used to assume a time zone
   for the system clock.
  </para>

  <para>
   By clicking <guimenu>Release notes</guimenu> you can access the &slema;
   release notes in English.
  </para>

  <para>
   Read the License Agreement. It is presented in the language you have chosen
   on the boot screen. Translations are available via the
   <menuchoice><guimenu>License
   Translations</guimenu><guimenu>Language</guimenu></menuchoice> drop-down
   box. If you agree to the terms, check <guimenu>I Agree to the License
   Terms</guimenu> and click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed with the
   installation. If you do not agree to the license agreement, you cannot
   install &productname;. Click <guimenu>Abort</guimenu> to terminate the
   installation.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-install-s390-part" arch="zseries" os="slemicro">
  <title>&zseries;: disk activation</title>

  <para>
   When installing on &zseries; platforms, the language selection dialog is
   followed by a dialog to configure the attached hard disks.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Disk activation</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="install_zseries_disk_activation.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="install_zseries_disk_activation.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   Select DASD, Fibre Channel Attached SCSI Disks (zFCP), or iSCSI for
   installation of &productname;. The DASD and zFCP configuration buttons are
   only available if the corresponding devices are attached. <phrase os="sles">
   For instructions on how to configure iSCSI disks, refer to
   <xref
   linkend="sec-iscsi-initiator"/>.</phrase>
  </para>

  <para>
   You can also change the <guimenu>Network Configuration</guimenu> in this
   screen by launching the <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu> dialog. Choose a
   network interface from the list and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> to change
   its settings. Use the tabs to configure DNS and routing.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-s390-part-dasd">
   <title>Configuring DASD disks</title>
   <para>
    Skip this step if you are not installing on &zseries; hardware.
   </para>
   <figure xml:id="fig-s390-yast2-i-y2-sel-dasd">
    <title>DASD disk management</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata width="100%" fileref="install_zseries_dasd.png"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata width="100%" fileref="install_zseries_dasd.png"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    After selecting <guimenu>Configure DASD Disks</guimenu>, an overview lists
    all available DASDs. To get a clearer picture of the available devices, use
    the text box located above the list to specify a range of channels to
    display. To filter the list according to such a range, select
    <guimenu>Filter</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Specify the DASDs to use for the installation by selecting the
    corresponding entries in the list. Use <guimenu>Select All</guimenu> to
    select all DASDs currently displayed. Activate and make the selected DASDs
    available for the installation by selecting <menuchoice> <guimenu>Perform
    Action</guimenu> <guimenu>Activate</guimenu> </menuchoice>. To format the
    DASDs, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Perform Action</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Format</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-s390-part-zfcp">
   <title>Configuring zFCP disks</title>
   <para>
    Skip this step if you are not installing on &zseries; hardware.
   </para>
   <figure xml:id="fig-install-zseries-zfcp">
    <title>Configured zFCP Devices</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata width="100%" fileref="install_zseries_zfcp.png"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata width="100%" fileref="install_zseries_zfcp.png"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    After selecting <guimenu>Configure zFCP Disks</guimenu>, a dialog with a
    list of the zFCP disks available on the system opens. In this dialog,
    select <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to open another dialog in which to enter zFCP
    parameters.
   </para>
   <para>
    To make a zFCP disk available for the &productname; installation, choose an
    available <guimenu>Channel Number</guimenu> from the drop-down box.
    <guimenu>Get WWPNs</guimenu> (World Wide Port Number) and <guimenu>Get
    LUNs</guimenu> (Logical Unit Number) return lists with available WWPNs and
    FCP-LUNs, respectively, to choose from. Automatic LUN scanning only works
    with NPIV enabled.
   </para>
   <para>
    When completed, exit the zFCP dialog with <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and the
    general hard disk configuration dialog with <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> to
    continue with the rest of the configuration.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-registration">
  <title>Registration</title>

  <figure>
   <title>Registration</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata os="slemicro" fileref="install_registration_slem.png"
                 width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata os="slemicro" fileref="install_registration_slem.png"
                 width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   To get technical support and product updates, you need to register and
   activate &productname; with the &scc; or a local registration server.
   Registering your product at this stage also grants you immediate access to
   the update repository. This enables you to install the system with the
   latest updates and patches available.
  </para>

  <para>
   From this dialog, you can switch to the &yast; <guimenu>Network
   Settings</guimenu> module by clicking <guimenu>Network
   Configuration</guimenu>.For details, see
   <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-network"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   The dialog offers the following possibilities, each described further:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Register system via scc.suse.com</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To register with the &scc;, enter the <guimenu>E-mail Address</guimenu>
      associated with your SCC account and the <guimenu>Registration
      Code</guimenu> for &productname;. Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Register system via local RMT server</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If your organization provides a local registration server, you may
      alternatively register there. Activate <guimenu>Register System via local
      RMT Server</guimenu> and either choose a URL from the drop-down box or
      type in an address. Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Skip registration</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you want to skip registration or you are offline, click <guimenu>Skip
      Registration</guimenu>. Accept the warning with <guimenu>OK</guimenu> and
      proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <important>
      <title>Skipping registration</title>
      <para>
       Your system needs to be registered in order to retrieve updates and to
       be eligible for support. You can register later, after the installation
       by using <command>SUSEConnect</command>, for details, see
       <xref linkend="sec-images-registration"/>.
      </para>
     </important>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <tip>
   <title>Installing product patches at installation time</title>
   <para>
    After &productname; has been successfully registered, you are asked whether
    to install the latest available online updates during the installation. If
    choosing <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>, the system will be installed with the most
    current packages without having to apply the updates after installation.
    Activating this option is recommended.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
   If the system was successfully registered during installation, &yast; will
   disable repositories from local installation media such as CD/DVD or flash
   disks when the installation has been completed. This prevents problems if
   the installation source is no longer available and ensures that you always
   get the latest updates from the online repositories.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-install-scc-registration-usb">
   <title>Loading registration codes from USB storage</title>
   <para>
    To make the registration more convenient, you can also store your
    registration codes on a USB storage device such as a flash disk. &yast;
    will automatically pre-fill the corresponding text box. This is
    particularly useful when testing the installation or if you need to
    register many systems or extensions.
   </para>
   <para>
    Create a file named <filename>regcodes.txt</filename> or
    <filename>regcodes.xml</filename> on the USB disk. If both are present, the
    XML takes precedence.
   </para>
   <para>
    In that file, identify the product with the name returned by
    <command>zypper search --type product</command> and assign it a
    registration code as follows:
   </para>
   <example xml:id="ex-i-yast2-conf-manual-cc-usb-txt">
    <title><filename>regcodes.txt</filename></title>
<screen>
SLEMicro    cc36aae1
</screen>
   </example>
   <example xml:id="ex-i-yast2-conf-manual-cc-usb-xml">
    <title><filename>regcodes.xml</filename></title>
<screen language="xml"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<profile xmlns="http://www.suse.com/1.0/yast2ns"
 xmlns:config="http://www.suse.com/1.0/configns">
  <suse_register>
    <addons config:type="list">
      <addon>
<name>SLEMicro</name>
<reg_code>cc36aae1</reg_code>
      </addon>
     </addons>
  </suse_register>
</profile>]]></screen>
   </example>
   <note>
    <title>Limitations</title>
    <para>
     Currently flash disks are only scanned during installation or upgrade, but
     not when registering a running system.
    </para>
   </note>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-live-extension">
  <title>Extension and Module Selection</title>

  <figure>
   <title>Extensions</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata os="slemicro" fileref="install_extension_slem.png"
                 width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata os="slemicro" fileref="install_extension_slem.png"
                 width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   &slema; currently offers the <literal>SUSE Linux Enterprise Live
   Patching</literal> extensions that enables you to apply critical patches
   without rebooting your system. Bear in mind that you might need an
   additional subscription on top of the subscription for &slema;.
  </para>

  <para>
   To enable the module, click the checkbox and then <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to
   proceed.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ntp-configuration">
  <title>NTP Configuration</title>

  <figure>
   <title>NTP configuration</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata os="slemicro" fileref="install_ntp_slem.png"
                 width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata os="slemicro" fileref="install_ntp_slem.png"
                 width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   In order to keep time on your system properly synchronized, configure at
   least one NTP server. You can enter more NTP servers as a comma or space
   separated list.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-authentication">
  <title>Authentication for the System Administrator &rootuser;</title>

  <figure>
   <title>Authentication for &rootuser;</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata os="slemicro" fileref="install_authentication_slem.png"
                 width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata os="slemicro" fileref="install_authentication_slem.png"
                 width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   Configure a strong password for &rootuser;. If your &rootuser; password is
   randomly generated, use at least 10 characters. If you set your &rootuser;
   password manually, use a longer password that includes a combination of
   uppercase and lowercase letters and numbers. The maximum length for
   passwords is 72 characters, and passwords are case-sensitive.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you want to access the system remotely via SSH using a public key, import
   a key from a removable storage device or an existing partition. To do so
   click <guimenu>Browse</guimenu> and select the public SSH key.
  </para>

  <para>
   Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed to the next installation step.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-settings">
  <title>Installation Settings</title>

  <figure>
   <title>Installation Settings</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata os="slemicro" fileref="install_settings_slem.png"
                 width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata os="slemicro" fileref="install_settings_slem.png"
                 width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   To access a particular setting, click the respective heading. Or some
   options can be directly changed on the screen by clicking the button next to
   the option.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-settings-partitioning">
   <title>Partitioning</title>
   <figure>
    <title>Suggested partitioning</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="partitioning_slem.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="partitioning_slem.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <warning>
    <title>The use of Btrfs and snapshots is mandatory.</title>
    <para>
     &slema; requires Btrfs on the root partition with snapshots and Snapper
     enabled. Snapper is enabled by default&mdash;do not disable it afterwards.
    </para>
   </warning>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Custom partitioning on UEFI machines</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A UEFI machine <emphasis>requires</emphasis> an EFI system partition
       that must be mounted to <filename>/boot/efi</filename>. This partition
       must be formatted with the <literal>FAT32</literal> file system.
      </para>
      <para>
       If an EFI system partition is already present on your system (for
       example from a previous Windows installation) use it by mounting it to
       <filename>/boot/efi</filename> without formatting it.
      </para>
      <para>
       If no EFI system partition is present on your UEFI machine, make sure to
       create it. The EFI system partition must be a physical partition or RAID
       1. Other RAID levels, LVM and other technologies are not supported. It
       needs to be formatted with the FAT32 file system.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Custom partitioning and <systemitem>Snapper</systemitem></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If the root partition is larger than 12 GB, &productname; by default
       enables file system snapshots. It is not recommended to use the root
       partition smaller than 12&nbsp;GB, because it might cause issues when
       running &slema;.
      </para>
      <para>
       &productname; uses Snapper together with Btrfs for this feature. Btrfs
       needs to be set up with snapshots enabled for the root partition.
      </para>
      <para>
       Being able to create system snapshots that enable rollbacks requires
       important system directories to be mounted on a single partition, for
       example <filename>/usr</filename>. Only directories that are excluded
       from snapshots may reside on separate partitions, for example
       <filename>/usr/local</filename>, <filename>/var</filename>, and
       <filename>/tmp</filename>.
      </para>
      <para>
       The installer will automatically create <literal>single</literal>
       snapshots during and immediately after the installation.
      </para>
      <important>
       <title>Btrfs snapshots and root partition size</title>
       <para>
        Snapshots occupy space on their partition. As a rule of thumb, the
        older a snapshot is, or the bigger the changeset they cover is, the
        bigger the snapshot. Plus, the more snapshots you keep, the more disk
        space you need.
       </para>
       <para>
        To prevent the root partition running full with snapshot data, you need
        to make sure it is big enough. In case you do frequent updates or other
        installations, consider at least 40&nbsp;GB for the root partition.
       </para>
      </important>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Btrfs data volumes</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Using Btrfs for data volumes is supported on &productname;
       &productnumber;. For applications that require Btrfs as a data volume,
       consider creating a separate file system with quota groups disabled.
       This is already the default for non-root file systems.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Btrfs on an encrypted root partition</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The default partitioning setup suggests formatting the root partition to
       Btrfs. To encrypt the root partition, make suere to use the GPT
       partition table type instead of the MSDOS type. Otherwise the GRUB2 boot
       loader may not have enough space for the second stage loader.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry  arch="zseries">
     <term>&zseries;: Using minidisks in z/VM</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If &productname; is installed on minidisks in z/VM, which reside on the
       same physical disk, the access path of the minidisks (/dev/disk/by-id/)
       is not unique. This is because it represents the ID of the physical
       disk. If two or more minidisks are on the same physical disk, they all
       have the same ID.
      </para>
      <para>
       To avoid problems when mounting minidisks, always mount them either
       <emphasis>by path</emphasis> or <emphasis>by UUID</emphasis>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry arch="zseries">
     <term>&zseries;: LVM root file system</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If you configure the system with a root file system on LVM or software
       RAID array, you must place <filename>/boot</filename> on a separate,
       non-LVM or non-RAID partition, otherwise the system will fail to boot.
       The recommended size for such a partition is 500&nbsp;MB and the
       recommended file system is Ext4.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Supported software RAID volumes</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Installing to and booting from existing software RAID volumes is
       supported for Disk Data Format (DDF) volumes and Intel Matrix Storage
       Manager (IMSM) volumes. IMSM is also known by the following names:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Intel Rapid Storage Technology
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Intel Matrix Storage Technology
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Intel Application Accelerator / Intel Application Accelerator RAID
         Edition
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Intel Virtual RAID on CPU (Intel VROC, see
         <link xlink:href="https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/support/articles/000024498/memory-and-storage/ssd-software.html"/>
         for more details)
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Mount points for FCoE and iSCSI devices</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       FCoE and iSCSI devices will appear asynchronously during the boot
       process. While the initrd guarantees that those devices are set up
       correctly for the root file system, there are no such guarantees for any
       other file systems or mount points like <filename>/usr</filename>. Hence
       any system mount points like <filename>/usr</filename> or
       <filename>/var</filename> are not supported. To use those devices,
       ensure correct synchronization of the respective services and devices.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    In case you need to adjust the partitioning scheme, click the
    <guimenu>Partitioning</guimenu> menu to open the <guimenu>Suggested
    partitioning</guimenu> dialog box.
   </para>
   <para>
    The installer creates a proposal for one of the available disks containing
    a root partition formatted with Btrfs and a swap partition. If one or more
    swap partitions have been detected on the available hard disks, these
    partitions will be used. You have several options to proceed:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Accept</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to accept the proposal without any
       changes and return to the <guimenu>Installation Settings</guimenu>
       screen.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Guided setup</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To adjust the proposal, choose <guimenu>Guided Setup</guimenu>. First,
       choose which hard disks and partitions to use. In the
       <guimenu>Partitioning Scheme</guimenu> screen, you can enable Logical
       Volume Management (LVM) and activate disk encryption. Afterward specify
       the <guimenu>Filesystem Options</guimenu>. You can adjust the file
       system for the root partition and create a separate home and swap
       partitions. If you plan to suspend your machine, make sure to create a
       separate swap partition and check <guimenu>Enlarge to RAM Size for
       Suspend</guimenu>. If the root file system format is Btrfs, you can also
       enable or disable Btrfs snapshots here.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Expert Partitioner</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To create a custom partition setup, click <guimenu>Expert
       Partitioner</guimenu>. Select either <guimenu>Start with Current
       Proposal</guimenu> if you want start with the suggested disk layout, or
       <guimenu>Start with Existing Partitions</guimenu> to ignore the
       suggested layout and start with the existing layout on the disk. For
       details, refer to <xref linkend="sec-slemicro-expert-partitioner"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec-slemicro-expert-partitioner">
    <title>Expert Partitioner</title>
    <figure>
     <title>Expert Partitioner</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="expert_partitioner_slem.png" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="expert_partitioner_slem.png" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
     Expert partitioner enables you to set up logical volume management (LVM),
     configure software RAID and device mapping (DM), encrypt partitions, mount
     NFS shares and manage tmpfs volumes. To fine-tune settings such as the
     subvolume and snapshot handling for each Btrfs partition, choose
     <guimenu>Btrfs</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     All existing or suggested partitions on all connected hard disks are
     displayed in the left part of the <guimenu>Expert Partitioner</guimenu>
     dialog. Entire hard disks are listed as devices without numbers, such as
     <filename>/dev/sda</filename><phrase arch="zseries"> (or
     <filename>/dev/dasda</filename>)</phrase>. Partitions are listed as parts
     of these devices, such as
     <filename>/dev/sda1</filename><phrase arch="zseries"> (or
     <filename>/dev/dasda1</filename>, respectively)</phrase>. The size, type,
     encryption status, file system, and mount point of the hard disks and
     their partitions are also displayed. The mount point describes where the
     partition appears in the Linux file system tree.
    </para>
    <sect4 xml:id="sec-partition-table">
     <title>Partition tables</title>
     <para>
      &productname; allows to use and create different <emphasis>partition
      tables</emphasis>. In some cases the partition table is called
      <emphasis>disk label</emphasis>. The partition table is important to the
      boot process of your computer. To boot your machine from a partition in a
      newly created partition table, make sure that the table format is
      supported by the firmware.
     </para>
     <para>
      To change the partition table, click the relevant disk name in the left
      part and choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Device</guimenu> <guimenu>Create New
      Partition Table</guimenu></menuchoice>. You can create the following
      partition tables:
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Master boot record</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         The <emphasis>master boot record (MBR)</emphasis> is the legacy
         partition table used on IBM PCs. It is sometimes also called an
         <emphasis>MS-DOS</emphasis> partition table. The MBR only supports
         four primary partitions. If the disk already has an MBR, &productname;
         allows you to create additional partitions in it which can be used as
         the installation target.
        </para>
        <para>
         The limit of four partitions can be overcome by creating an
         <emphasis>extended partition</emphasis>. The extended partition itself
         is a primary partition and can contain more <emphasis>logical
         partitions</emphasis>.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>GPT partition table</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         UEFI computers use a <emphasis>GUID Partition Table</emphasis> (GPT)
         by default. &productname; will create a GPT on a disk if no other
         partition table exists.
        </para>
        <para>
         Old BIOS firmware does not support booting from GPT partitions.
        </para>
        <para>
         You need a GPT partition table to use more than four primary
         partitions, UEFI Secure Boot or use disks larger than 2&nbsp;TB.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </sect4>
    <sect4 xml:id="sec-creating-partitions">
     <title>Creating partitions</title>
     <para>
      The expert partitioner enables you to add partitions. Bear in mind that
      the root file system must be formatted to Btrfs and snapshots must be
      enabled.
     </para>
     <para>
      The procedure below creates a Btrfs partition with enabled snapshots.
     </para>
     <procedure>
      <step>
       <para>
        Select the desired hard disk in the left part and click <guimenu>Add
        Partition</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Define size of the partition or define the region of disk for the
        partition. Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>
       </para>
       <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
         <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="part_size_slem.png" width="100%"/>
         </imageobject>
         <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="part_size_slem.png" width="100%"/>
         </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
       </informalfigure>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Select a role:
       </para>
       <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
         <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="role_slem.png" width="100%"/>
         </imageobject>
         <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="role_slem.png" width="100%"/>
         </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
       </informalfigure>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Format and mount the partition as needed and proceed with
        <guimenu>Next</guimenu>:
       </para>
       <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
         <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="mount_slem.png" width="100%"/>
         </imageobject>
         <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="mount_slem.png" width="100%"/>
         </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
       </informalfigure>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        (Optional) If you chose to encrypt the partition, enter the encryption
        password and complete the process with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>:
       </para>
       <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
         <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="encryption_slem.png" width="100%"/>
         </imageobject>
         <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="encryption_slem.png" width="100%"/>
         </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
       </informalfigure>
      </step>
     </procedure>
    </sect4>
    <sect4 xml:id="sec-creating-lvm">
     <title>Creating volume groups</title>
     <para>
      To create a volume group follow these steps:
     </para>
     <procedure>
      <title>Creating volume groups</title>
      <step>
       <para>
        Create partitions with the following attributes:
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          the partitions are not mounted
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          <guimenu>PartitionID</guimenu> is <literal>Linux LVM</literal>
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Click <menuchoice><guimenu>LVM Volume Groups</guimenu><guimenu>Add
        Volume Group</guimenu></menuchoice>
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Select partitions to be added to the volume group and click
        <guimenu>Add</guimenu>. Name the volume group, select the
        <guimenu>Physical Extent Size</guimenu> and click
        <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed further.
       </para>
       <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
         <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="volume_groups_slem.png" width="100%"/>
         </imageobject>
         <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="volume_groups_slem.png" width="100%"/>
         </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
       </informalfigure>
      </step>
     </procedure>
    </sect4>
    <sect4 xml:id="sec-creating-raid">
     <title>Creating RAIDs</title>
     <para>
      &slema; supports the following RAID levels: 0, 1, 5, 6 and 10. To create
      a RAID follow proceed as follows:
     </para>
     <procedure>
      <title>Creating RAID</title>
      <step>
       <para>
        Create partitions (the count of partitions depend on the RAID level)
        with these parameters:
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          The partitions have the <guimenu>Raw Volume</guimenu> role assigned.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          The partitions are not formatted to any file system.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          The partitions are not mounted.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          The partitions have the <literal>Linux RAID</literal>
          <guimenu>PartitionID</guimenu>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Click <guimenu>RAID</guimenu> in the left pane and then click
        <guimenu>Add RAID</guimenu>. The <guimenu>Add RAID</guimenu> dialog box
        opens.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Choose the partitions and add them to the RAID. Select RAID level and
        optionally you can name the RAID. Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
       </para>
       <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
         <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="raid_slem.png" width="100%"/>
         </imageobject>
         <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="raid_slem.png" width="100%"/>
         </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
       </informalfigure>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Select the <guimenu>Chunk Size</guimenu>. The default value is usually
        sufficient. Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        In the <guimenu>Device Overview</guimenu> select the created RAID and
        click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Select a role of the RAID and click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Format and mount the device and optionally you can select that the RAID
        will be encrypted.
       </para>
      </step>
     </procedure>
    </sect4>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-settings-software">
   <title>Software</title>
   <figure>
    <title>Software configuration</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="software_slem.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="software_slem.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    &productname; contains several software patterns for various application
    purposes. Click <guimenu>Software</guimenu> to open the <guimenu>Software
    Selection and System Tasks</guimenu> screen where you can modify the
    pattern selection according to your needs. Select a pattern from the list
    and see a description in the right-hand part of the window.
   </para>
   <para>
    In this menu you can select the <literal>Web based remote system
    managment</literal> pattern that will install <literal>Cockpit</literal>
    system. Cockpit is a web monitoring tool that enables you to administer
    your system. For details, refer to <xref linkend="sec-admin-cockpit"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Each pattern contains several software packages needed for specific
    functions (for example Podman). For a more detailed selection based on
    software packages to install, select <guimenu>Details</guimenu> to switch
    to the &yast; Software Manager.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-settings-timezone">
   <title>Timezone</title>
   <figure>
    <title>Time zone configuration</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="timezone_slem.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="timezone_slem.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    By default, the time is synchronized by using the NTP servers you provided
    in the previous steps of the installation procedure. You can select the
    region and time zone either by clicking a particular place on the map or by
    selecting a region and time zone in the drop-down menus.
   </para>
   <important>
    <title>Set the hardware clock to UTC</title>
    <para>
     The switch from standard time to daylight saving time (and vice versa) can
     only be performed automatically when the hardware clock (CMOS clock) is
     set to UTC. This also applies if you use automatic time synchronization
     with NTP, because automatic synchronization will only be performed if the
     time difference between the hardware and system clock is less than 15
     minutes.
    </para>
    <para>
     Since a wrong system time can cause serious problems, it is strongly
     recommended to <emphasis>always</emphasis> set the hardware clock to UTC.
    </para>
   </important>
   <para>
    The button <guimenu>Other settings</guimenu> enables you to set the date
    and time manually or configure NTP servers synchronization.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you want to set the time and date manually, click the <guimenu>Other
    settings</guimenu> button and select <guimenu>Manually</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <note arch="zseries">
    <title>Time cannot be changed on &zseries;</title>
    <para>
     Since the operating system is not allowed to change time and date
     directly, the <guimenu>Other Settings</guimenu> option is not available on
     &zseries;.
    </para>
   </note>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-settings-network">
   <title>Network Configuration</title>
   <para>
    Network is automatically configured at the beginning of the installation
    process, but if it is necessary you can change the configuration by
    clicking <guimenu>Network Configuration</guimenu>. A dialog box opens, for
    details refer to <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-network"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-settings-booting">
   <title>Booting</title>
   <figure>
    <title>Booting</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="booting_slem.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="booting_slem.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    The installer proposes a boot configuration for your system. Other
    operating systems found on your computer, such as Microsoft Windows or
    other Linux installations, will automatically be detected and added to the
    boot loader. However, &productname; will be booted by default. Normally,
    you can leave these settings unchanged. If you need a custom setup, modify
    the proposal according to your needs.
   </para>
   <important>
    <title>Software RAID 1</title>
    <para>
     Booting a configuration where <filename>/boot</filename> resides on a
     software RAID 1 device is supported, but it requires installing the boot
     loader into the MBR (<menuchoice> <guimenu>Boot Loader Location</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Boot from Master Boot Record</guimenu> </menuchoice>). Having
     <filename>/boot</filename> on software RAID devices with a level other
     than RAID 1 is not supported.
    </para>
   </important>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-settings-kdump">
   <title>Kdump</title>
   <figure>
    <title>Kdump configuration</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="kdump_slem.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="kdump_slem.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    Using Kdump, you can save a dump of the kernel (in case of a crash) to
    analyze what went wrong. By default, Kdump is enabled. By clicking
    <guimenu>Kdump</guimenu> you open a dialog box for configuring Kdump.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Start-Up</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Here you can disable Kdump and configure the amount of memory reserved
       for Kdump. Usually you do not have to change the prefilled values.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Dump Filtering</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Dump filtering enables you to select which pages will be included in the
       Kdump, and to define the format of of Kdump.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Dump Target</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       You can select a local directory or you can save KDump to a remote
       location. If you prefer a remote location, you also need to configure
       connection details according to the respective protocol.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Email Notifications</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To receive email notifications if an event occurs, specify an email
       address.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Expert Settings</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This option enables you to define command-line parameters, custom kernel
       dump and other advanced settings related to Kdump.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-settings-system">
   <title>System</title>
   <figure>
    <title>System overview</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="system_slem.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="system_slem.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    This screen lists all the hardware information the installer could obtain
    about your computer. When opened for the first time, the hardware detection
    is started. Depending on your system, this may take some time. Select any
    item in the list and click <guimenu>Details</guimenu> to see detailed
    information about the selected item. Use <guimenu>Save to File</guimenu> to
    save a detailed list to either the local file system or a removable device.
   </para>
   <para>
    Advanced users can also change the <guimenu>PCI ID Setup</guimenu> and
    kernel settings by choosing <guimenu>Kernel Settings</guimenu>. A screen
    with two tabs opens:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>PCI ID setup</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Each kernel driver contains a list of device IDs of all devices it
       supports. If a new device is not in any driver's database, the device is
       treated as unsupported, even if it can be used with an existing driver.
       You can add PCI IDs to a device driver here. Only advanced users should
       attempt to do so.
      </para>
      <para>
       To add an ID, click <guimenu>Add</guimenu> and select whether to
       <guimenu>Manually</guimenu> enter the data, or whether to choose from a
       list. Enter the required data. The <guimenu>SysFS Dir</guimenu> is the
       directory name from <filename>/sys/bus/pci/drivers</filename>&mdash;if
       empty, the <guimenu>driver</guimenu> name is used as the directory name.
       Existing entries can be managed with <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> and
       <guimenu>Delete</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Kernel settings</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Activating the <guimenu>Enable SysRq Keys</guimenu> item, will let you
       issue basic commands (such as rebooting the system or writing kernel
       dumps) in case the system crashes. Enabling these keys is recommended
       when doing kernel development. Refer to
       <link xlink:href="https://www.kernel.org/doc/html/latest/admin-guide/sysrq.html"/>
       for details.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-settings-security">
   <title>Security</title>
   <figure>
    <title>Security configuration</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="security_slem.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="security_slem.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <important>
    <title>Do not use firewall along with Podman</title>
    <para>
     Using firewall along with Podman may cause missing Podman related firewall
     rules after reloading the <literal>firewalld</literal> service. Therefore,
     it is recommended to keep the firewall in its default
     setting&mdash;disabled if you intend to use Podman.
    </para>
   </important>
   <para>
    You can enable the firewall or disable the SSH service directly by clicking
    the respective button. Clicking on the button next to <guimenu>CPU
    mitigations</guimenu> opens the <guimenu>Boot Loader Settings</guimenu>
    dialog box, where you can change kernel parameters including the
    <literal>CPU mitigations</literal> configuration.
   </para>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>CPU Mitigations</guimenu> refer to kernel boot command line
    parameters for software mitigations that have been deployed to prevent CPU
    side-channel attacks. You can configure the following values:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Auto</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       All CPU side channel mitigations are enabled as they are detected based
       on the CPU type. The auto-detection handles both unaffected older CPUs
       and unaffected newly released CPUs and transparently disables
       mitigations. This options leave SMT enabled.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Off</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       All CPU side channel mitigations are disabled. While this option gives
       the higher performance, it also bears the highest risk. Do not use this
       setting where there is a risk of untrusted code.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Auto + No Smt</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       All CPU side channel mitigations are enabled as they are detected based
       on the CPU type. Additionally the symmetric multi-threading of the CPU
       is disabled if necessary, for instance to mitigate the L1 Terminal Fault
       side channel issue.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Manually</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       CPU mitigations are detected manually.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    By default, the firewall is disabled. Click <guimenu>enable</guimenu> to
    change the default.
   </para>
   <para>
    The SSH service is enabled by default. Click <guimenu>disable</guimenu> to
    change the setting. If you disable the SSH service, you will not be able to
    login to your system remotely. The SSH port (22) is open by default.
   </para>
   <para>
    The default SELinux option is <guimenu>disabled</guimenu>. You can change
    the value by clicking <guimenu>Security</guimenu> and selecting another
    option in the <guimenu>Mode</guimenu> menu.
   </para>
   <para>
    In the <guimenu>Security</guimenu> dialog box, you can also select
    PolicyKit privilegs in the <guimenu>PolicyKit Default Privilegs</guimenu>
    dropdown menu.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
