<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<sect1 version="5.0" xml:id="sec-x86-media"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Booting the system</title>

 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>

 <!--
  taroth 2019-07-31: CAVE - same section content is used in
  deployment_prep_aarch64_media.xml
  -->

 <remark>Rewrite this section to include all possibilities for SLE Micro. Review the terminology! Speaking about installation methods and refering to a section of installation control methods is confusing.</remark>

 <para>
  This section gives an overview of the steps required for the complete
  installation of &productnamereg;.
 </para>

 <para os="sles">
  Unlike previous &slea; products, the entire &slea; &productnumber; product
  line can be installed using the &leanos;. <phrase os="sles">For details about
  the changes since &sle; &product-ga; and which media to download for
  installation, see <xref linkend="sec-planning-leanos"/>.</phrase>
 </para>

 <para os="sles">
  For a full description of how to install and configure the system with
  &yast;, refer to
  <xref os="sles" linkend="part-deployment"/><xref os="slemicro" linkend="part-manual-installation"/>.
 </para>

 <important os="sles">
  <title>Hardware support updates</title>
  <para>
   When using very recent hardware, it can be necessary to boot the
   installation with a newer kernel from a <literal>Kernel Update ISO</literal>
   image. For details, refer to <xref linkend="cha-kiso"/>.
  </para>
 </important>

 <para os="slemicro">
  In case of the manual installation, an overview of booting the installation
  system is provided by the following procedure:
 </para>

 <procedure>
  <step>
   <para>
    Prepare the installation media.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>&usbflashdrivecap;</term>
     <listitem>
      <para os="sles;sled;osuse">
       This is the simplest way to start the installation. To create a bootable
       flash disk, you need to copy a DVD image to the device using the
       <command>dd</command> command. The flash disk must not be mounted, and
       all data on the device will be erased.
      </para>
      <para os="slemicro">
       In case of the manual installation from an ISO, creating a bootable
       flash disk is the easiest way to start the installation. You need to
       copy the ISO to the device using the <command>dd</command>. The flash
       disk must not be mounted, and all data on the device will be erased.
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>dd</command> if=<replaceable>PATH_TO_ISO_IMAGE</replaceable> of=<replaceable>USB_STORAGE_DEVICE</replaceable> bs=4M</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <!-- 2020-03-26 tbazant: Full ISO1 no longer fits on DVD
     <varlistentry>
     <term>DVD</term>
     <listitem>
     <para>
     DVD media are available from &suse;, or you can make your own. This method
     is useful if you have multiple machines to provision at the same time. It
     requires either a built-in or removable DVD drive. The process is
     straightforward for most computer users, but requires a lot of
     interaction for every installation process. If you did not receive
     a DVD, get the ISO image from the &suse; home page and burn it to a
     blank, writable DVD.
     </para>
     </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     -->
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Network booting</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If the target computer's firmware supports it, you can boot the computer
       from the network and install from a server. This booting method requires
       a boot server that provides the needed boot images over the network. The
       exact protocol depends on your hardware. Commonly you need several
       services, such as TFTP and DHCP or PXE boot.<phrase os="sles"> For
       details, read <xref linkend="cha-deployment-prep-pxe"/>.</phrase>
      </para>
      <para>
       It is possible to install from many common network protocols, such as
       NFS, HTTP, FTP, or SMB. For more information on how to perform such an
       installation, refer to <xref linkend="cha-remote-installation"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Configure the target system firmware to boot the medium you chose. Refer to
    the documentation of your hardware vendor about how to configure the
    correct boot order.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Set the boot parameters required for your installation control method. An
    overview of the different methods is provided in
    <xref linkend="sec-x86-prep-installation-methods"/>. A list of boot
    parameters is available in <xref linkend="cha-boot-parameters"/>.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Perform the installation as described in <xref linkend="cha-install"/>. The
    system needs to restart after the installation is finished.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Optional: Change the boot order of the system to directly boot from the
    medium to which &productname; has been installed. If the system boots from
    the installation medium, the first boot parameter will be to boot the
    installed system.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>

 <para os="slemicro">
  For the deployment of raw images, the procedure is the following:
 </para>

 <procedure os="slemicro">
  <step>
   <para>
    Prepare the raw image, for details refer to
    <xref linkend="proc-prepare-image"/>.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Prepare the configuration media, for details refer to
    <xref linkend="pro-preparing-configuration-device"/>.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Configure the target system firmware to boot the medium where you copied
    the raw image. Refer to the documentation of your hardware vendor about how
    to configure the correct boot order.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Perform the installation as described in
    <xref linkend="cha-images-procedure"/>. The system needs to restart after
    the installation is finished.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
</sect1>
