<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<sect1 version="5.0" xml:id="deployment-encryption" os="sles;sled;osuse"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Device encryption</title>

  <info>
    <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
      <dm:bugtracker/>
      <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
    </dm:docmanager>
  </info>

  <para>
    Linux Unified Key Setup (LUKS) is the standard for Linux disk encryption. It provides a
    standardized on-disk format and enables users to transport or migrate data seamlessly.
  </para>
  <para>
    LUKS is used to encrypt block devices. The contents of the encrypted device are arbitrary, and
    therefore any file system can be encrypted, including swap partitions. All necessary setup
    information, like encryption keys and parameters, such as cipher type and key size, is stored
    in the partition header.
  </para>
  <para>
    Encryption is done with a multi-layer approach. First, the block device is encrypted using a
    master key. Then, this master key is encrypted with each active user key. User keys are derived
    from passphrases, FIDO2 security keys, TPMs or smart cards. This multi-layer approach allows
    users to change their passphrase without re-encrypting the whole block device.
  </para>
  <para>
    For more information about LUKS, refer to <xref linkend="cha-configure-cryptctl"/>.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="deployment-encryption-methods">
    <title>Encryption methods</title>
    <para>
      To encrypt a device, follow the instructions in <xref
        linkend="sec-expert-partitioner-options"/>.
    </para>
    <tip>
      <title>Enabling LUKS2 support in &yast;</title>
      <para>
        LUKS2 encryption is supported by the &yast; Partitioner as of &sle; 15 SP4, but needs to be
        enabled explicitly. There are two ways to do this:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            At boot time, by adding the parameter <literal>YAST_LUKS2_AVAILABLE</literal> to the
            kernel command line. For information about boot parameters, refer to <xref
              linkend="cha-boot-parameters"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            During installation in the &yast; configuration:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                In the graphical interface, press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap>
                  <keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                In the text interface, press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>D</keycap></keycombo>
                and then <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>
            Check <guimenu>Enable Experimental LUKS2 Encryption Support</guimenu> and exit the
            configuration screen with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </tip>
    <para>
      If you do not enable LUKS2 support, the <guimenu>Encryption method</guimenu> selection is not
      visible and you only need to enter the encryption password.
    </para>
    <variablelist xml:id="vl-encryption-methods">
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guimenu>Regular LUKS1</guimenu></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This method allows to encrypt the device using LUKS1. You have to provide the encryption
            password. Additional passwords&mdash;up to eight in total&mdash;can be added later with
            <command>cryptsetup luksAddKey</command>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guimenu>Regular LUKS2</guimenu></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            LUKS2 uses a newer version of the header format, which is resilient to corruption, and
            supports up to 32 user keys and device labels. You have to provide the encryption password
            and the password-based key derivation function (PBKDF) that will be used to protect
            that passphrase (see <xref linkend="deployment-encryption-pbkdf"/>).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guimenu>Pervasive LUKS2</guimenu> (only on &zseries;)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This method allows to encrypt the device using LUKS2 with a master secure key processed
            by a Crypto Express cryptographic coprocessor configured in CCA mode. If the
            cryptographic system already contains a secure key associated to this volume, that key
            will be used. Otherwise, a new secure key will be generated and registered in the
            system. You need to provide an encryption password that will be used to protect the
            access to that master key. Moreover, when there are several APQNs in the system, you can
            select which ones to use.
          </para>
          <para>
            For more information about pervasive encryption, refer to
            <link xlink:href="https://www.ibm.com/docs/en/linux-on-systems?topic=security-pervasive-encryption"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guimenu>Encryption with Volatile Random Key</guimenu> (only for swap devices)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This method encrypts a swap device with a randomly generated key at boot and therefore
            does not support hibernation to hard disk. The swap device is re-encrypted on every
            boot, and its previous content is destroyed. To avoid data loss, disable hibernation and
            configure your system to shut down instead.
          </para>
          <para>
            In addition to the encryption key, the device label and the UUID change every time the
            swap is re-encrypted, so neither is a valid option to mount a randomly encrypted swap
            device. Make sure the swap device is referenced by a stable name that is not subject to
            change on every reboot in the <filename>/etc/crypttab</filename> file. For example, for
            a swap partition it is safer to use the udev device ID or path instead of the partition
            device name, since that device name may be assigned to a different partition during the
            next boot. If that happens, a wrong device could be encrypted instead of your swap!
          </para>
          <para>
            &yast; tries to use stable names in <filename>/etc/crypttab</filename>, unless it is
            configured to always use device names (see the <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> section of
            the partitioner). But for some devices, finding a fully stable name may not be possible.
            Only use encryption with volatile keys if you are sure about the implications.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guimenu>Protected Swap</guimenu> (only for swap devices)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This method encrypts a swap device with a volatile protected AES key without requiring a
            cryptographic coprocessor. It is an improvement over the <literal>Encryption with
              Volatile Random Key</literal> method and all considerations for that method still apply.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guimenu>Secure Swap</guimenu> (only for swap devices)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This method encrypts a swap device with a volatile secure AES key generated from a
            cryptographic coprocessor. It is an improvement over the <literal>Encryption with
              Volatile Random Key</literal> method and all considerations for that method still apply.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="deployment-encryption-pbkdf">
    <title>Password-based key derivation functions</title>
    <para>
      The password-based key derivation function (PBKDF) to use depends on the context, the hardware
      capabilities and the needed level of compatibility with other system components:
    </para>
    <variablelist xml:id="vl-pbkdf">
      <varlistentry>
        <term>PBKDF2</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>PBKDF2</literal> is the function that LUKS1 uses. It is defined in
            <link xlink:href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2898">RFC 2898</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Argon2i</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Argon2 is a function designed to be more secure and to require a lot of memory to be
            computed. It is defined in <link
              xlink:href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc9106">RFC 9106</link>. Argon2i is a variant
            of Argon2 optimized to resist side-channel attacks by accessing the memory array in a
            password-independent order.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Argon2id</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Argon2id is a hybrid version of Argon2. It follows the Argon2i approach for the first
            half pass over memory and the Argon2d (not supported by &yast;) approach to limit GPU
            cracking attacks for subsequent passes. RFC 9106 recommends using Argon2id if you do not
            know the difference between the types or you consider side-channel attacks to be a
            viable threat.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      While <literal>Argon2</literal> is more secure, there are still use cases for
      <literal>PBKDF2</literal>:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          As an intentional security feature, Argon2 requires a lot more memory to be computed.
          This may result in problems on some systems. If the strength of the password can be fully
          assured, then using PBKDF2 may still be secure and save memory.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <systemitem>grub2</systemitem> offers limited support to boot from devices encrypted with
          LUKS2, but only if PBKDF2 is used. This means you cannot use Argon2 for a file system that
          contains the <filename>/boot</filename> directory. Note that even if PBKDF2 is used, some
          manual <systemitem>grub2</systemitem> configuration may be needed to boot from a LUKS2
          device.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <!--
    <para>
      Use the Help button in the installer to see more information about configuring LUKS2.
      Please note that you need a separate, unencrypted boot partition in order to
      encrypt the root file system.
    </para>
    -->
    <para>
      For more information on configuring device encryption with LUKS, use the
      <literal>Help</literal> button in the installer and refer to
      <xref linkend="cha-configure-cryptctl"/>.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
