<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha-images-description"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Description of raw images</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  &slema; raw images are delivered for the &x86-64; architecture (an image with
  RT kernel is available), &zseries; ZSeries (an image of the KVM host, images
  to be used with FBA or DASD devices) and also &aarch64;. These images are
  intended to be configured on the first boot by using either Ignition or
  Combustion. The boot loader detects the first boot, see more in
  <xref linkend="sec-first-boot"/>. Each image has default mounted subvolumes
  as described in <xref linkend="sec-default-partitioning"/>. The procedure of
  deploying these images is described in
  <xref linkend="cha-images-procedure"/>.
 </para>
 <important>
  <title>Do not use firewall along with Podman</title>
  <para>
   Using firewall along with Podman may cause missing Podman related firewall
   rules after reloading the <literal>firewalld</literal> service. Therefore,
   it is recommended to keep the firewall disabled if you intend to use Podman.
  </para>
 </important>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-default-partitioning">
  <title>Default partitioning</title>

  <para>
   The raw images are delivered with a default partitioning scheme, which can
   be changed during the first boot by using Ignition or Combustion. For a
   procedure to repartition the system, refer to
   <xref linkend="sec-ignition-configuration"/> or
   <xref linkend="sec-combustion-script"/>.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Btrfs is mandatory for the root file system</title>
   <para>
    If you intend to perform any changes to the default partitioning scheme,
    the root file system must be btrfs.
   </para>
  </important>

  <para>
   Each image has the following subvolumes:
  </para>

<screen>
 /home
 /root
 /opt
 /srv 
 /usr/local
 /var
 </screen>

  <para>
   The images also have mounted subvolumes for booting by default. The specific
   subvolumes differ according to the architecture.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can recognize the subvolumes mounted by default by the option
   <literal>x-initrd.mount</literal> in <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>. Other
   subvolumes or partitions must be configured either by Ignition or
   Combustion.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-first-boot">
  <title>First boot detection</title>

  <para>
   The configuration runs on the first boot only. To distinguish between the
   first and subsequent boots, the flag file
   &mdash;<filename>/boot/firstboot_happened</filename> is created after the
   first boot took place. If the file is not present in the file system, the
   attribute <literal>ignition.firstboot</literal> is passed to the kernel
   command line, which triggers the creation of
   <filename>initramfs</filename> in case of Ignition or running the dracut module in
   case of Combustion. After completing the first boot, the
   <filename>/boot/firstboot_happened</filename> flag file is created.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>The flag file is always created</title>
   <para>
    Even though the configuration may not be successful, due to improper or
    missing configuration files, the
    <filename>/boot/firstboot_happened</filename> flag file is created.
   </para>
   <!--JH: ADD HOW! -->
   <para>
    You may force the first boot configuration on subsequent boot by passing
    the <literal>ignition.firstboot</literal> attribute to the kernel command
    line or by deleting the <filename>/boot/firstboot_happened</filename> flag
    file.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
