<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<preface version="5.0" xml:id="preface.deployment"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>About This Guide</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  Installations of &productname; are possible in different ways. It is
  impossible to cover all combinations of boot, or installation server,
  automated installations or deploying images. This manual should help with
  selecting the appropriate method of deployment for your installation.
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry os="sles">
   <term><xref linkend="part.prep"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The standard deployment instructions differ depending on the architecture
     used. For differences and requirements regarding the architecture, see
     this part.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part.mandeploy"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Most tasks that are needed during installations are described here. This
     includes the manual setup of your computer and installation of additional
     software.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part.installserver"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &productnamereg; can be installed in different ways. Apart from the usual
     media installation, you can choose from various network-based approaches.
     This part describes setting up an installation server and how to prepare
     the boot of the target system for installation.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part.remoteinstall"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     This part introduces the most common installation scenarios for remote
     installations. While some still require user interaction or some degree of
     physical access to the target system, others are completely automated and
     hands-off. Learn which approach is best for your scenario.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part.sysconfig"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Learn how to configure your system after installation. This part covers
     common tasks like setting up hardware components, installing or removing
     software, managing users, or changing settings with YaST.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part.update"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     This part will give you some background information on terminology, &suse;
     product lifecycles and Service Pack releases, and recommended upgrade
     policies.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_target_audience_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_available_doc_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_feedback_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_typografie_i.xml"/>
</preface>
