<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" role="General" xml:id="cha-installation-troubleshooting"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Troubleshooting</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    This section highlights some typical problems you may run into during
    installation and offers possible solutions or workarounds.
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-installation-troubleshooting-checking-media">
  <title>Checking media</title>

  <para>
   If you encounter any problems using the &productname; installation media,
   check the integrity of your installation media. Boot from the media and
   choose<menuchoice><guimenu>More</guimenu> <guimenu>Check Installation
   Media</guimenu></menuchoice> from the boot menu. A minimal system boots and
   lets you choose which device to check. Select the respective device and
   confirm with <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to perform the check.
  </para>

  <para>
   In a running system, start &yast; and choose <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Software</guimenu> <guimenu>Media Check</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
   Insert the medium and click <guimenu>Start Check</guimenu>. Checking may
   take several minutes.
  </para>

  <para>
   If errors are detected during the check, do not use this medium for
   installation. Media problems may, for example, occur when having burned the
   medium on DVD yourself. Burning the media at a low speed (4x) helps to avoid
   problems.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-installation-troubleshooting-dvd">
  <title>No bootable drive available</title>

  <para>
   If your computer cannot boot from USB or DVD drive, there are several
   alternatives. This is also an option if your drive is not supported by
   &productname;.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Using an external &usbflashdrive; or DVD drive</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Linux supports most existing &usbflashdrive;s and DVD drives. If the
      system has no &usbflashdrive; or DVD drive, it is still possible that an
      external drive, connected through USB, FireWire, or SCSI, can be used to
      boot the system. Sometimes a firmware update may help if you encounter
      problems.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Network boot via PXE</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If a machine lacks both a &usbflashdrive; and DVD drive, but provides a
      working Ethernet connection, perform a completely network-based
      installation. <phrase
      os="sles;sled">See
      <xref
      linkend="sec-remote-installation-scenario-vncpxe"/> and
      <xref
      linkend="sec-remote-installation-scenario-sshpxe"/> for
      details.</phrase>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>&usbflashdrive;</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      You can use a &usbflashdrive; if your machine lacks a DVD drive and
      network connection. <phrase os="sles;sled">For details, see:</phrase>
     </para>
     <itemizedlist os="sles;sled">
      <listitem>
       <para arch="x86_64">
        <xref linkend="sec-x86-media"/>
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem os="sles">
       <para arch="aarch64">
        <xref linkend="sec-aarch64-media"/>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-installation-troubleshooting-bios">
  <title>Booting from installation media fails</title>

  <para>
   One reason a machine does not boot the installation media can be an
   incorrect boot sequence setting in BIOS. The BIOS boot sequence must have
   &usbflashdrive; or DVD drive set as the first entry for booting. Otherwise
   the machine would try to boot from another medium, typically the hard disk.
   Guidance for changing the firmware boot sequence can be found in the
   documentation provided with your mainboard, or in the following paragraphs.
  </para>

  <para>
   The BIOS is the software that enables the very basic functions of a
   computer. Motherboard vendors provide a BIOS specifically made for their
   hardware. Normally, the BIOS setup can only be accessed at a specific
   time&mdash;when the machine is booting. During this initialization phase,
   the machine performs several diagnostic hardware tests. One of them is a
   memory check, indicated by a memory counter. When the counter appears, look
   for a line, usually below the counter or somewhere at the bottom, mentioning
   the key to press to access the BIOS setup. Usually the key to press is one
   of <keycap function="delete"/>, <keycap>F1</keycap>, or
   <keycap function="escape"/>. Press this key until the BIOS setup screen
   appears.
  </para>

  <procedure xml:id="pro-tinstallation-troubleshooting-bios">
   <title>Changing the BIOS boot sequence</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the BIOS using the proper key as announced by the boot routines and
     wait for the BIOS screen to appear.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To change the boot sequence in an AWARD BIOS, look for the <guimenu>BIOS
     FEATURES SETUP</guimenu> entry. Other manufacturers may have a different
     name for this, such as <guimenu>ADVANCED CMOS SETUP</guimenu>. When you
     have found the entry, select it and confirm with
     <keycap function="enter"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the screen that opens, look for a subentry called <guimenu>BOOT
     SEQUENCE</guimenu> or <guimenu>BOOT ORDER</guimenu>. Change the settings
     by pressing <keycap function="pageup"/> or <keycap function="pagedown"/>
     until the &usbflashdrive; or DVD drive is listed first.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Leave the BIOS setup screen by pressing <keycap function="escape"/>. To
     save the changes, select <guimenu>SAVE &amp; EXIT SETUP</guimenu>, or
     press <keycap>F10</keycap>. To confirm that your settings should be saved,
     press <keycap>Y</keycap>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure>
   <title>Changing the boot sequence in an SCSI BIOS (Adaptec host adapter)</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open the setup by pressing <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/>
     <keycap>A</keycap> </keycombo>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Disk Utilities</guimenu>. The connected hardware
     components are now displayed.
    </para>
    <para>
     Make note of the SCSI ID of your &usbflashdrive; or DVD drive.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Exit the menu with <keycap function="escape"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open <guimenu>Configure Adapter Settings</guimenu>. Under
     <guimenu>Additional Options</guimenu>, select <guimenu>Boot Device
     Options</guimenu> and press <keycap function="enter"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the ID of the &usbflashdrive; or DVD drive and press
     <keycap
      function="enter"/> again.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Press <keycap function="escape"/> twice to return to the start screen of
     the SCSI BIOS.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Exit this screen and confirm with <guimenu>Yes</guimenu> to boot the
     computer.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   Regardless of what language and keyboard layout your final installation will
   be using, most BIOS configurations use the US keyboard layout as shown in
   the following figure:
  </para>

  <figure xml:id="fig-trouble-install-keyboard-us">
   <title>US keyboard layout</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="keyboard_us.svg" width="75%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="keyboard_us.png" width="75%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-installation-troubleshooting-noboot">
  <title>Boot failure</title>

  <para>
   Some hardware types, mainly very old or very recent ones, fail to boot.
   Reasons can be missing support for hardware in the installation kernel or
   drivers causing problems on some specific hardware.
  </para>

  <para>
   If your system fails to install using the standard
   <guimenu>Installation</guimenu> mode from the first installation boot
   screen, try the following:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     With the installation media still in the drive, reboot the machine with
     <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/> <keycap function="alt"/>
     <keycap
       function="delete"/> </keycombo> or using the hardware reset
     button.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     When the boot screen appears, press <keycap>F5</keycap>, use the arrow
     keys of your keyboard to navigate to <guimenu>No ACPI</guimenu> and press
     <keycap function="enter"/> to launch the boot and installation process.
     This option disables the support for ACPI power management techniques.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Proceed with the installation as described in
     <xref linkend="cha-install"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   If this fails, proceed as above, but choose <guimenu>Safe Settings</guimenu>
   instead. This option disables ACPI and DMA support. Most hardware will boot
   with this option.
  </para>

  <para>
   If both of these options fail, use the boot parameters prompt to pass any
   additional parameters needed to support this type of hardware to the
   installation kernel. For more information about the parameters available as
   boot parameters, refer to the kernel documentation located in
   <filename>/usr/src/linux/Documentation/kernel-parameters.txt</filename>.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>Obtaining kernel documentation</title>
   <para>
    Install the <systemitem class="systemname">kernel-source</systemitem>
    package to view the kernel documentation.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
   There are other ACPI-related kernel parameters that can be entered at the
   boot prompt prior to booting for installation:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><systemitem>acpi=off</systemitem></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This parameter disables the complete ACPI subsystem on your computer.
      This may be useful if your computer cannot handle ACPI or if you think
      ACPI in your computer causes trouble.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><systemitem>acpi=force</systemitem></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Always enable ACPI even if your computer has an old BIOS dated before the
      year 2000. This parameter also enables ACPI if it is set in addition to
      <systemitem>acpi=off</systemitem>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><systemitem>acpi=noirq</systemitem></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Do not use ACPI for IRQ routing.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><systemitem>acpi=ht</systemitem></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Run only enough ACPI to enable hyper-threading.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><systemitem>acpi=strict</systemitem></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Be less tolerant of platforms that are not strictly ACPI specification
      compliant.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><systemitem>pci=noacpi</systemitem></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Disable PCI IRQ routing of the new ACPI system.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><systemitem>pnpacpi=off</systemitem></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option is for serial or parallel problems when your BIOS setup
      contains wrong interrupts or ports.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><systemitem>notsc</systemitem></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Disable the time stamp counter. This option can be used to work around
      timing problems on your systems. It is a recent feature, so if you see
      regressions on your machine, especially time related or even total hangs,
      this option is worth a try.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><systemitem>nohz=off</systemitem></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Disable the nohz feature. If your machine hangs, this option may help.
      Otherwise it is of no use.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   When you have determined the right parameter combination, &yast;
   automatically writes them to the boot loader configuration to make sure that
   the system boots properly next time.
  </para>

  <para>
   If inexplicable errors occur when the kernel is loaded or during the
   installation, select <guimenu>Memory Test</guimenu> in the boot menu to
   check the memory. If <guimenu>Memory Test</guimenu> returns an error, it is
   usually a hardware error.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-installation-troubleshooting-graph">
  <title>Fails to launch graphical installer</title>

  <para>
   After you insert the medium into your drive and reboot your machine, the
   installation screen comes up, but after you select
   <guimenu>Installation</guimenu>, the graphical installer does not start.
  </para>

  <para>
   There are several ways to deal with this situation:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Try to select another screen resolution for the installation dialogs.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Text Mode</guimenu> for installation.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Do a remote installation via VNC using the graphical installer.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <procedure xml:id="pro-installation-troubleshooting-graph">
   <title>Change screen resolution for installation</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Boot for installation.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Press <keycap>F3</keycap> to open a menu from which to select a lower
     resolution for installation purposes.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Installation</guimenu> and proceed with the installation
     as described in <xref linkend="cha-install"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure xml:id="pro-installation-troubleshooting-text">
   <title>Installation in text mode</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Boot for installation.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Press <keycap>F3</keycap> and select <guimenu>Text Mode</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Installation</guimenu> and proceed with the installation
     as described in <xref linkend="cha-install"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure xml:id="pro-trouble-install-vnc">
   <title>VNC installation</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Boot for installation.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the following text at the boot parameters prompt:
    </para>
<screen>vnc=1 vncpassword=<replaceable>SOME_PASSWORD</replaceable></screen>
    <para>
     Replace <replaceable>SOME_PASSWORD</replaceable> with the password to use
     for VNC installation.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Installation</guimenu> then press
     <keycap function="enter"/> to start the installation.
    </para>
    <para>
     Instead of starting right into the graphical installation routine, the
     system continues to run in a text mode. The system then halts, displaying
     a message containing the IP address and port number at which the installer
     can be reached via a browser interface or a VNC viewer application.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If using a browser to access the installer, launch the browser and enter
     the address information provided by the installation routines on the
     future &productname; machine and press <keycap function="enter"/>:
    </para>
<screen>http://<replaceable>IP_ADDRESS_OF_MACHINE</replaceable>:5801</screen>
    <para>
     A dialog opens in the browser window prompting you for the VNC password.
     Enter it and proceed with the installation as described in
     <xref linkend="cha-install"/>.
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>Cross-platform support</title>
     <para>
      Installation via VNC works with any browser under any operating system,
      provided Java support is enabled.
     </para>
    </important>
    <para>
     Provide the IP address and password to your VNC viewer when prompted. A
     window opens, displaying the installation dialogs. Proceed with the
     installation as usual.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-installation-troubleshooting-mini">
  <title>Only minimalist boot screen started</title>

  <para>
   You inserted the medium into the drive, the BIOS routines are finished, but
   the system does not start with the graphical boot screen. Instead it
   launches a very minimalist text-based interface. This may happen on any
   machine not providing sufficient graphics memory for rendering a graphical
   boot screen.
  </para>

  <para>
   Although the text boot screen looks minimalist, it provides nearly the same
   functionality as the graphical one:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Boot options</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Unlike the graphical interface, the different boot parameters cannot be
      selected using the cursor keys of your keyboard. The boot menu of the
      text mode boot screen offers some keywords to enter at the boot prompt.
      These keywords map to the options offered in the graphical version. Enter
      your choice and press <keycap function="enter"/> to launch the boot
      process.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Custom boot options</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      After selecting a boot parameter, enter the appropriate keyword at the
      boot prompt or enter some custom boot parameters as described in
      <xref linkend="sec-installation-troubleshooting-noboot"/>. To launch the
      installation process, press <keycap function="enter"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Screen resolutions</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use the function keys (<keycap>F1</keycap> ... <keycap>F12</keycap>) to
      determine the screen resolution for installation. If you need to boot in
      text mode, choose <keycap>F3</keycap>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-installation-troubleshooting-log" os="sles">
  <title>Log files</title>

  <para os="sles">
   For more information about log files that are created during installation,
   see <xref linkend="sec-admsupport-install"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
