<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<!--
  IMPORTANT: The content of this file is included into the AArch64 section
  via xpointers. Make sure to add xpointers if needed or update the section
  accordingly.
-->

<sect1 version="5.0" xml:id="sec.deployment.xpointer.source"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Source File for XPointers - Do Not Include</title>

 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>

 <!-- element(/1/3) -->
 <sect2>
  <title>Deployment Guide x86 / aarch64 Workflow</title>
  
  <!-- element(/1/3/2) -->
  <para>
   This section offers an overview of the steps required for the complete
   installation of &productnamereg; in the required mode.
   <xref linkend="part.deployment"/> contains a full description of how to
   install and configure the system with &yast;.
  </para>

  <!-- element(/1/3/3) -->
  <procedure>
   <!-- element(/1/3/3/1) -->
   <step>
    <para>
     Prepare the boot and installation media as described in
     <xref linkend="sec.x86.media"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <!-- element(/1/3/3/2) -->
   <step>
    <para>
     Configure the target system firmware to boot the medium you chose. Refer to the
     documentation of your hardware vendor about how to configure the correct
     boot order.
    </para>
   </step>
   <!-- element(/1/3/3/3) -->
   <step>
    <para>
     <!-- Platform dependent text -->
    </para>
   </step>
   <!-- element(/1/3/3/4) -->
   <step>
    <para>
     Perform the installation as described in <xref linkend="cha.install"/>.
     The system needs to restart after the installation is finished.
    </para>
   </step>
   <!-- element(/1/3/3/5) -->
   <step>
    <para>
     Optional: Change the boot order of the system to directly boot from the
     medium to which &productname; has been installed. If the system boots
     from the installation medium, the first boot parameter will be to boot the
     installed system.
    </para>
   </step>
   <!-- element(/1/3/3/6) -->
   <step>
    <para>
     Perform the initial system configuration as described in
     <xref linkend="part.sysconfig"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect2>

 <!-- Installation Boot Media for x86 and aarch64 -->
 <!-- element(/1/4) -->
 <sect2>
  <!-- element(/1/4/1) -->
  <title>Boot and Installation Media</title>

  <!-- element(/1/4/2) -->
  <para>
   When installing the system, the media for booting and for installing the
   system may be different. All combinations of supported media for booting and
   installing may be used. <phrase os="sles">When using very recent hardware,
   it can be necessary to boot the installation with a newer kernel. For
   details, refer to <xref linkend="cha.kiso"/>.</phrase>
  </para>

  <!-- element(/1/4/3) -->
  <sect3>
   <!-- element(/1/4/3/1) -->
   <title>Boot Media</title>

   <!-- element(/1/4/3/2) -->
   <para>
    Booting a computer depends on the capabilities of the hardware used and the
    availability of media for the respective boot parameter.
   </para>

   <!-- element(/1/4/3/3) -->
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Booting from DVD</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This is the most common possibility of booting a system. It is
       straightforward for most computer users, but requires a lot of
       interaction for every installation process. If you did not receive
       a DVD, get the ISO image from the &suse; home page and burn it to a
       DVD. The DVD also contains the data required for the basic installation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Booting from a USB Flash Drive</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In case your machine is not equipped with an optical drive, you can
       boot the installation image from a flash disk. To create a bootable
       flash disk, you need to copy a DVD image to the device using the
       <command>dd</command> command. The flash disk must not be mounted,
       all data on the device will be erased.
      </para>
      <screen>&prompt.root;<command>dd</command> if=<replaceable>PATH_TO_ISO_IMAGE</replaceable> of=<replaceable>USB_STORAGE_DEVICE</replaceable> bs=4M</screen>
      <para>
       The ISO image also contains the data required for the basic installation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Booting from the Network</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       You can only boot a computer directly from the network if this is
       supported by the computer's firmware or BIOS. This booting method
       requires a boot server that provides the needed boot images over the
       network. The exact protocol depends on your hardware. Commonly you need
       several services, such as TFTP and DHCP or PXE boot. For details, read
       <xref linkend="cha.deployment.prep_pxe"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <!-- element(/1/4/4) -->
  <sect3>
   <!-- element(/1/4/4/1) -->
   <title>Installation Media</title>

   <!-- element(/1/4/4/2) -->
   <para>
    The installation media contain all the necessary packages and meta
    information that is necessary to install a &productname;. These must be
    available to the installation system after booting for installation. Several
    possibilities for providing the installation media to the system are
    available with &productname;.
   </para>

   <!-- element(/1/4/4/3) -->
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Installation from DVD</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       All necessary data is delivered on the boot media. Depending on the
       selected installation, a network connection or add-on media may be
       necessary.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Installation from USB Flash Drive</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       All necessary data is delivered on the boot media. Depending on the
       selected installation, a network connection or add-on media may be
       necessary.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Networked Installation</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If you plan to install several systems, providing the installation media
       over the network makes things a lot easier. It is possible to install
       from many common protocols, such as NFS, HTTP, FTP, or SMB. For more
       information on how to run such an installation, refer to
       <xref linkend="cha.remote_installation"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>

 <!-- element(/1/5) -->
 <sect2>
  <!-- element(/1/5/1) -->
  <title>Installation Considerations</title>
  <!-- element(/1/5/2) -->
  <sect3>
   <!-- element(/1/5/2/1) -->
   <title>Installation on Hardware or Virtual Machine</title>
   <!-- element(/1/5/2/2) -->
   <para>
    &productname; is normally installed as an independent operating system. With
    virtualization it is also possible to run multiple instances of &sls; on
    the same hardware. However, the installation of the &vmhost; is performed
    like a typical installation with some additional packages.
    <phrase os="sles;osuse">The installation of virtual guests is
    described in <xref linkend="cha.kvm.inst"/>.</phrase>
   </para>
  </sect3>
  <!-- element(/1/5/3) -->
  <sect3>
   <!-- element(/1/5/3/1) -->
   <title>Installation Target</title>
   <!-- element(/1/5/3/2) -->
   <para>
    Most installations are to a local hard disk. Therefore, it is necessary for
    the hard disk controllers to be available to the installation system. If a
    special controller (like a RAID controller) needs an extra kernel module,
    provide a kernel module update disk to the installation system.
   </para>
   <!-- element(/1/5/3/3) -->
   <para>
    Other installation targets may be various types of block devices that
    provide sufficient disk space and speed to run an operating system. This
    includes network block devices like <systemitem>iSCSI</systemitem> or
    <systemitem>SAN</systemitem>. It is also possible to install on network file
    systems that offer the standard Unix permissions. However, it may be
    problematic to boot these, because they must be supported by the
    <systemitem>initramfs</systemitem> before the actual system can start. Such
    installations can be useful when you need to start the same system in
    different locations or you plan to use virtualization features like
    domain migration.
   </para>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>

 <!-- element(/1/6) -->
 <sect2>
  <!-- element(/1/6/1) -->
  <title>Controlling the Installation</title>
  <!-- element(/1/6/2) -->
  <para>
   Control the installation in one of several ways. Boot the setup with one of
   the options listed in <xref linkend="sec.x86.media.boot"/>. To enable the
   different control methods refer to
   <xref linkend="sec.boot_parameters.list.remote_access"/>. For information
   about how to use each remote control method, refer to
   <xref linkend="cha.remote_installation"/>.
  </para>
  <!-- element(/1/6/3) -->
  <para>
   A brief overview of the different methods:
  </para>
  <!-- element(/1/6/4) -->
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Local with Monitor and Keyboard</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This is the method most frequently used to install &productname;. This
      also requires the smallest preparation effort but requires a lot of
      direct interaction.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Remote via SSH</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      You can control the installation via SSH either in text mode or use
      X-forwarding for a graphical installation. For details refer to
      <xref linkend="sec.remote_installation.monitor_ssh"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Remote via Serial Console</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      For this installation method you need a second computer connected by a
      <emphasis>null modem</emphasis> cable to the computer on which to install &productname;.
      The installation then proceeds in text mode. For details refer to
      <xref linkend="sec.remote_installation.monitor_serial"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Remote via VNC</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use this method if you want a graphical installation without direct access
      to the target machine. For details refer to
      <xref linkend="sec.remote_installation.monitor_vnc"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry os="sles">
    <term>Automatic via &ay;</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you need to install &productname; on several computers with similar
      hardware, it is recommended you perform the installations with the aid
      of &ay;. In this case, start by installing one &productname; and use
      this to create the necessary &ay; configuration files. For details
      refer to <xref linkend="book.autoyast"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
