<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha-images-combustion"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Configuring with Combustion</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    This chapter describes Combustion&dash;the tool used to configure your
    system on first boot according to your configuration.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-about-combustion">
  <title>About Combustion</title>

  <para>
   Combustion is a dracut module that enables you to configure your system on
   its first boot. Combustion reads a provided file, called
   <filename>script</filename> and executes commands in it and thus perform
   changes to the file system. You can use Combustion to change the default
   partitions, set users' passwords, create files, install packages, etc.
  </para>

  <para>
   The Combustion dracut module is invoked after the
   <literal>ignition.firstboot</literal> argument is passed to the kernel
   command line. Combustion then reads configuration from
   <filename>script</filename>. Combustion tries to configure network, if the
   network flag has been found in <filename>script</filename>. After
   <literal>/sysroot</literal> is mounted, Combustion tries to activate all
   mount points in <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> and then call
   <command>transactional-update</command> to apply other changes (like setting
   &rootuser; password or installing packages).
  </para>

  <para>
   When using Combustion, you need to label the configuration device with the
   name <literal>combustion</literal>, create a specific directory structure in
   that configuration medium, and include a configuration file named
   <filename>script</filename>. In the root directory of the configuration
   medium, create a directory called <filename>combustion</filename> and place
   the <filename>script</filename> into this directory along with other
   files&mdash;SSH key, configuration files, etc. The directory structure then
   should look as follows:
  </para>

<screen>
&lt;root directory&gt;
└── combustion
    └── script
    └── other files

	</screen>

  <para>
   You can use Combustion to configure your QEMU/KVM virtual machine. In this
   case, pass the location of the <filename>script</filename> file using the
   <literal>fw_cfg</literal> parameter of the <command>qemu</command> command:
  </para>

<screen>
	-fw_cfg name=opt/org.opensuse.combustion/script,file=/var/combustion-script
	</screen>

  <para>
   Combustion can be used along with Ignition. If you intend to do so, label
   your configuration medium <literal>ignition</literal> and include the
   <filename>ignition</filename> directory with the
   <filename>config.ign</filename> to your directory structure as shown below:
  </para>

<screen>
&lt;root directory&gt;
└── combustion
    └── script
    └── other files
└── ignition 
    └── config.ign
	</screen>

  <para>
   In this scenario, Ignition runs before Combustion.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-combustion-script">
  <title>The <filename>script</filename> configuration file</title>

  <para>
   The <filename>script</filename> configuration file is a set of commands that
   are executed on your system in a transactional-update shell. This section
   provides examples for performing various configuration tasks by using
   Combustion.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Include interpreter declaration</title>
   <para>
    As the <filename>script</filename> file is interpreted by bash, make sure
    to start the file with the interpreter declaration at the first line:
   </para>
<screen>
 #!/bin/bash
 </screen>
  </important>

  <para>
   If you want to log in to your system, include at least the &rootuser;
   password. Though it is recommend to establish the authentication using SSH
   keys. If you need to use a &rootuser; password, make sure to configure a
   secure password. In case you use a randomly generated password, use at least
   10 characters. If you create your password manually, use even more than 10
   characters and combine uppercase and lowercase letters, and numbers.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-script-network">
   <title>Network configuration</title>
   <para>
    To configure and use network connection during the first boot, add the
    following statement to your <filename>script</filename>:
   </para>
<screen>
 # combustion: network
 </screen>
   <para>
    Using this statement will pass the <literal>rd.neednet=1</literal> argument
    to dracut. If you do not use the statement, the system will be configured
    without any network connection.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-script-partitioning">
   <title>Partitioning</title>
   <para>
    &slema; raw images are delivered with a default partitioning scheme as
    described in <xref linkend="sec-default-partitioning"/>. You might want to
    use a different partitioning. The following set of example snippets moves the
    <filename>/home</filename> to a different partition.
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>Performing changes outside of directories included in snapshots</title>
    <para>
     The following script performs changes that are not included in snapshots.
     If the script fails and the snapshot get discarded, some changes remains
     visible and cannot be reverted (like the changes to the
     <literal>/dev/vdb</literal> device.)
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    The following snippet creates a GPT with a single partition on the
    <literal>/dev/vdb</literal> device:
   </para>
<screen>
sfdisk /dev/vdb &lt;&lt;EOF
label: gpt
type=linux
EOF 

partition=/dev/vdb1
   </screen>
   <para>
    The partition is formatted to BTRFS:
   </para>
<screen>
wipefs --all ${partition}
mkfs.btrfs ${partition} 
   </screen>
   <para>
    Possible content of <filename>/home</filename> is moved to the new
    <filename>/home</filename> folder location by the following snippet:
   </para>
<screen>
mount /home
mount ${partition} /mnt 
rsync -aAXP /home/ /mnt/
umount /home /mnt
   </screen>
   <para>
    The snippet below removes an old entry in <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>
    and creates a new entry:
   </para>
<screen>
awk -i inplace '$2 != "/home"' /etc/fstab
echo "$(blkid -o export ${partition} | grep ^UUID=) /home btrfs defaults 0 0" >>/etc/fstab
   </screen>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-cript-security">
   <title>Setting a password for &rootuser;</title>
   <para>
    Before you set the &rootuser; password, generate a hash of the password,
    e.g. by using the <command>openssl passwd -6</command>. To set the
    password, add the following to your <filename>script</filename>:
   </para>
<screen>
 echo 'root:$5$.wn2BZHlEJ5R3B1C$TAHEchlU.h2tvfOpOki54NaHpGYKwdNhjaBuSpDotD7' | chpasswd -e
 </screen>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-script-sshkeys">
   <title>Adding SSH keys</title>
   <para>
    The following snippet creates a directory to store the &rootuser;'s SSH key
    and then copies the public SSH key located on the configuration device to
    the <filename>authorized_keys</filename> file.
   </para>
<screen>
 mkdir -pm700 /root/.ssh/
cat id_rsa_new.pub >> /root/.ssh/authorized_keys
 </screen>
   <note>
    <para>
     The SSH service must be enabled in case you need to use remote login via
     SSH. For details, refer to <xref linkend="sec-script-services"/>.
    </para>
   </note>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-script-services">
   <title>Enabling services</title>
   <para>
    You may need to enable some services, for example the SSH service. To
    enable the SSH service add the following line to
    <filename>script</filename>:
   </para>
<screen>
 systemctl enable sshd.service
 </screen>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-script-install">
   <title>Installing packages</title>
   <important>
    <title>Network connection and registering your system might be necessary</title>
    <para>
     As some package may require additional subscription, you might need to
     register your system beforehand. Also available network connection may be
     needed to install additional packages.
    </para>
   </important>
   <para>
    During the first boot configuration, you can install additional packages to
    your system. For example, you can install the <literal>vim</literal> editor
    by adding:
   </para>
<screen>
zypper --non-interactive install vim-small
 </screen>
   <note>
    <para>
     Bear in mind that you will not be able to use <command>zypper</command>
     after the configuration is complete and you boot to the configured system.
     To perform changes later, you must use the
     <command>transactional-update</command> command to create a changed
     snapshot. For details, refer to <xref linkend="sec-transactional-udate"/>.
    </para>
   </note>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
