<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha-deployment-overview"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Overview of the deployment process</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  &productname; provides pre-built images (raw and selfinstall ISOs) that can be directly deployed to your
  device storage: a memory card, USB flash drive, or a hard disk. The
  options for which type of device you can deploy the image to depend on your
  particular hardware&mdash;follow the guidance in your vendor documentation.
 </para>
 <para>
  To prepare the setup, you need the following:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    a disk (either a physical or a virtual) where &slema; will run
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    in case of the selfinstall ISO image - a bootable device with the selfinstall ISO (for example a USB disk)
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    (optionally) a device that serves as a configuration medium. You can perform basic configuration even
    without the configuration medium. 
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 
 <para>
  The deployment process of &productnameshort; pre-built images can be summarized into threes stages:
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
  <term>Preparing a configuration device</term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
If you need a more complex configuration other than setting time, &rootuser; password and language,
you have to prepare a configuration device as described in <xref linkend="cha-prepare-device"/>. 
    </para>
    <para>
      Bear in mind that, if used, the configuration device must be plugged in
   throughout the whole configuration process on the first boot. It is
   recommended to plug in the device before starting the installation process.
   However, if your firmware does not support having two or more USB disks
   attached on boot, you can exchange the USB device before starting the
   configuration process.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Deploying the pre-built image</term>
    <listitem>
<para>
After downloading the image, you can boot your machine with  either the configuration device
attached or using &jeosfirstboot; to perform basic configuration. 
</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Post-deployment procedures</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
After you deploy the image, register it or activate extensions. 
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
</chapter>
