<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<preface version="5.0" xml:id="preface.deployment"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>About This Guide</title>
 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
        </dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <para>
  Installations of &productname; are possible in many different ways. It
  is impossible to cover all combinations of boot, or installation server,
  automated installations or deploying images. This manual should help with
  selecting the appropriate method of deployment for your installation.
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry os="sles">
   <term><xref linkend="part.archspec"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The standard deployment instructions differ depending on the
     architecture used. For differences and requirements regarding the
     architecture, see this part.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part.mandeploy"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Most tasks that are needed during installations are described here.
     This includes the manual setup of your computer as well as additional
     software and remote installations.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part.imaging"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Mass installations often require the preparation of images or products
     furnished with the features that are needed in this special case.
     Several options are described that allow the administrator to prepare
     these deployment methods.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><xref linkend="part.autoinstall"/>
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To do unattended installations, either use the installation with
     &ay; or prepare an image with kiwi or firstboot. This part describes
     methods to deploy these installations with a minimum of user
     interaction.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <para>
  Many chapters in this manual contain links to additional documentation
  resources, including additional documentation that is available on the
  system as well as documentation available on the Internet.
 </para>
 <para>
  For an overview of the documentation available for your product and the
  latest documentation updates, refer to
  <link xlink:href="http://www.suse.com/doc"/> or to the following section.
 </para>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_available_doc_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_feedback_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_typografie_i.xml"/>
</preface>