<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<sect1 version="5.0" xml:id="sec.prep.boot"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Controlling the Installation</title>

 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>

 <para>
  Control the installation in one of several ways. The method most frequently
  used is to install &productnamereg; from the computer console. Other options
  are available for different situations.
<!-- cwickert 2016-04-14: FIXME DEPLOY_REWRITE
   Find more information about the available installation methods in
   <xref linkend="cha.deployment"/>.
  -->
 </para>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.prep.boot.terminal">
  <title>Installation on the Computer Console</title>
  <para>
   The simplest way to install &productname; is using the computer console.
   With this method, a graphical installation program guides you through the
   installation. This installation method is discussed in detail in
   <xref linkend="cha.install"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can still perform the installation on the console without a working
   graphics mode. The text-based installation program offers the same
   functionality as the graphical version. Find some hints about navigation in
   this mode in <xref linkend="sec.yast.text.navi_module"/>.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.prep.boot.serial">
  <title>Installation Using a Serial Console</title>
  <para>
   For this installation method, you need a second computer that is connected
   by a <emphasis>null modem</emphasis> cable to the computer on which to
   install &productname;. Depending on the hardware, even the firmware or BIOS
   of the computer may already be accessible to the serial console. If this is
   possible, you can carry out the entire installation using this method. To
   activate the serial console installation, specify the additional
   <option>console=ttyS0</option> parameter at the boot prompt. This should be
   done after the boot process has completed and before the installation system starts.
  </para>
  <para>
   On most computers, there are two serial interfaces,
   <emphasis>ttyS0</emphasis> and <emphasis>ttyS1</emphasis>. For the
   installation, you need a terminal program like minicom or screen. To
   initiate the serial connection, launch the screen program in a local console
   by entering the following command:
  </para>
<screen>
screen /dev/ttyS0 9600
</screen>
  <para>
   This means that screen listens to the first serial port with a baud rate of
   9600. From this point on, the installation proceeds similarly to the
   text-based installation over this terminal.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.prep.boot.ssh">
  <title>Installation with SSH</title>
  <para>
   If you do not have direct access to the machine and the installation
   initiated from a management console, you can control the
   entire installation process over the network. To do this, enter the
   parameters <option>ssh=1</option> and
   <option>ssh.password=<replaceable>SECRET</replaceable></option> at the boot
   prompt. An SSH daemon is then launched in the system and you can log in as
   user &rootuser; with the password <replaceable>SECRET</replaceable>.
  </para>
  <para>
   To connect, use <command>ssh -X</command>. X-Forwarding over SSH is
   supported, if you have a local X server available. Otherwise, &yast;
   provides a text interface over ncurses. &yast; then guides you through the
   installation. This procedure is described in detail in
   <xref
        linkend="sec.deployment.remoteinst.scenario.sshdyn"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you do not have a DHCP server available in your local network, manually
   assign an IP address to the installation system. Do this by entering the
   option <option>HostIP=<replaceable>IPADDR</replaceable></option> at the boot
   prompt.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.prep.boot.vnc">
  <title>Installation over VNC</title>
  <para>
   If you do not have direct access to the system, but want a graphical
   installation, install &productname; over VNC. This method is described in
   detail in <xref linkend="sec.deployment.remoteinst.monitor.vnc"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   As suitable VNC clients are also available for other operating systems, such
   as Microsoft Windows and mac OS, the installation can also be controlled from
   computers running those operating systems.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.prep.boot.autoyast">
  <title>Installation with &ay;</title>
  <para>
   If you need to install &productname; on several computers with similar
   hardware, it is recommended you perform the installations using
   &ay;. In this case, start by installing one &productname; and use this to
   create the necessary &ay; configuration files.
  </para>
  <para os="sles,osuse">
   &ay; is extensively documented in <xref linkend="book.autoyast"/> .
  </para>
  <para os="sled">
   &ay; is extensively documented at
   <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/documentation/sles-12/book_autoyast/data/book_autoyast.html"/>
   .
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
