<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<sect1 version="5.0" xml:id="sec-x86-prep-considerations"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Installation considerations</title>

 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>

 <para>
  This section encompasses many factors that need to be considered before
  installing &productname; on &amd64; and &intel64; hardware.
 </para>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-x86-prep-considerations-virtualization">
  <title>Installation on hardware or virtual machine</title>
  <!--
   taroth 2019-07-31: CAVE - same para is used in
   deployment_prep_aarch64_choose.xml-->
  <para>
   &productname; is normally installed as an independent operating system. With
   virtualization it is also possible to run multiple instances of <phrase os="sles">&sls;</phrase><phrase os="slemicro">&slem;</phrase> on the
   same hardware.<phrase os="sles"> However, the installation of the &vmhost; is performed like a
   typical installation with some additional packages.</phrase>
   <phrase os="sles;osuse">The installation of virtual guests is described in
   <xref linkend="cha-kvm-inst"/>.</phrase>
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-x86-prep-considerations-target">
  <title>Installation target</title>
  <!--
   taroth 2019-07-31: CAVE - same paras are used in
   deployment_prep_aarch64_choose.xml-->
  <para>
   Most installations are to a local hard disk. Therefore, it is necessary for
   the hard disk controllers to be available to the installation system. If a
   special controller (like a RAID controller) needs an extra kernel module,
   provide a kernel module update disk to the installation system.
  </para>
  <para>
   Other installation targets may be various types of block devices that
   provide sufficient disk space and speed to run an operating system. This
   includes network block devices like <systemitem>iSCSI</systemitem> or
   <systemitem>SAN</systemitem>. It is also possible to install on network file
   systems that offer the standard Unix permissions. However, it may be
   problematic to boot these, because they must be supported by the
   <systemitem>initramfs</systemitem> before the actual system can start. Such
   installations can be useful when you need to start the same system in
   different locations or you plan to use virtualization features like domain
   migration.
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
