<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<sect1 version="5.0" xml:id="sec-aarch64-deprpi"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>&rpi;</title>

 <para>
  &slsreg; is the first enterprise Linux distribution to support the inexpensive
  &rpireg; single-board computer. &productname; &productnumber; supports the
  following models:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    &rpi; 3 Model B
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    &rpi; 3 Model B+
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    &rpi; 3 Compute Module
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>

 <para>
  There are two different ways to deploy &sls; onto &rpi; hardware:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Copy a pre-installed system image onto a MicroSD card.
   </para>
   <para>
    This is the most common method for deploying operating systems on the
    &rpi; platform.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Boot from USB media or the network, then install onto another drive.
   </para>
   <para>
    This is the more conventional way to install &productname;, although it is less
    common for &rpi; operating systems.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>

 <para>
  There are several points to note regarding both methods.
 </para>

 <sect2>
  <title>Deploying from a Pre-installed Image</title>
  <para>
   This method is the simplest and easiest method. However, it allows little
   customization of the product being deployed except for network and account
   settings.
  </para>
  <para>
   &suse; provides a pre-configured bootable image of &productname; for &rpi; 3
   series
   hardware. This comes with the lightweight IceWM desktop and the Btrfs file
   system, with compression enabled to improve performance and reduce wear on
   MicroSD media.
  </para>
  <para>
   A MicroSD card with a minimum size of 8 GB is recommended. Faster cards will
   give better system performance. On the first boot, the operating system
   automatically expands the file system to fill the card. This means that the
   first boot will be substantially slower than subsequent boots.
  </para>
  <para>
   The process of writing the card image onto MicroSD media is described in the
   <link xlink:href="&dsc-sles;/html/SLES-rpi-quick/art-rpiquick.html">&rpiquick;</link>.
  </para>

 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>Installation from USB Media</title>
  <para>
   This method will be more familiar as it is the way &sls; is deployed
   on other platforms. Installation can be performed from a removable USB
   medium, such as a memory stick, onto a MicroSD card in the machine's internal
   slot, or from a removable USB medium onto another USB medium, such as a
   USB-connected hard disk.
  </para>
  <note>
   <title>USB Bandwidth Limitations</title>
   <para>
    Note that the Ethernet, Wi-Fi and Bluetooth controllers on the &rpi; 3 are
    all connected to the device's on-board USB 2 bus. Therefore an operating
    system running from a disk attached via USB must share the total 480 Mbps
    bandwidth of the USB controller. This will limit performance, and could
    significantly impact network performance.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   Installation on the &rpi; has some aspects that are unlike other
   platforms.
  </para>
  <para>
   The &rpi; differs from more conventional machines in two important ways:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The &rpi; hardware does not have any built-in firmware. Its firmware is
     loaded from a special reserved FAT16 partition on the MicroSD card every
     time that the machine is powered on. There is also no battery-backed clock
     or non-volatile memory to hold configuration information.
    </para>
    <para>
     This means there are no conventional settings to adjust for boot device
     order, time and date, and so on.
    </para>
    <para>
     Instead, the &rpi; has a very small amount of One-Time Programmable Memory
     (OTP memory) which can be used to configure some settings, such as whether
     the machine should attempt to boot from USB devices or over Ethernet. It is
     only possible to program this by preparing a bootable MicroSD card and
     placing certain configuration files on it.
    </para>
    <para>
     This OTP memory is described on the &rpi; Foundation Web site:
     <link xlink:href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/documentation/hardware/raspberrypi/otpbits.mdd"/>
    </para>
    <note>
     <title>Time Synchronization</title>
     <para>
      The lack of a Real Time Clock (RTC) also means that &rpi; devices need to
      be configured to fetch the time from a network server by
      &ntp;.
    </para>
    </note>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The primary processor on the &rpi; is the VideoCore IV Graphics Processing
     Unit (GPU), not the &arm; processor. It is the GPU which initialises the
     hardware and loads the operating system. As a result, most &rpi; operating
     systems do not use a boot loader.
    </para>
    <para>
     &sle; for the &rpi; is configured with a boot loader called
     <literal>Das U-Boot</literal>, which is loaded before the operating system
     and can optionally show a boot menu, like GRUB on &x86; hardware.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>
   Installation can be performed from a bootable USB device, such as a memory
   stick or USB optical drive. The exact procedure may differ from model to
   model, depending on how the individual device is configured.
  </para>
  <para>
   The &rpi; 3 Model B+ is shipped pre-configured to boot from USB devices and
   no additional steps should be required.
  </para>
  <para>
   Depending on whether this has previously been done on a particular unit, the
   older &rpi; 3 Model B may require additional configuration to boot from USB.
   The procedure is described on the &rpi; Foundation Web site:
   <link xlink:href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/documentation/hardware/raspberrypi/bootmodes/msd.md"/>
  </para>

 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Network Booting the &rpi;
  </title>
  <para>
   Due to the hardware's lack of on-board firmware, network-booting the &rpi;
   using PXE is more complex than with more conventional computers.
  </para>
  <para>
   The process of setting up a PXE boot server for &x86; and &arm; is described
   in the &suse; Best Practices document <link
    xlink:href="&dsc-sbp;/all/html/SBP-Multi-PXE-Install/index.html"><citetitle>How
     to Set Up a Multi-PXE Installation Server</citetitle></link>.
  </para>
  <para>
   The &rpi; Foundation publishes information on how to PXE boot one &rpi; from
   another &rpi;:
   <link xlink:href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/documentation/hardware/raspberrypi/bootmodes/net_tutorial.md"/>
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>For More Information</title>
  <para>
   For more information, consult the following resources:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     &sls; 15 SP1 Release Notes
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      For more information about hardware compatibility, supported options and
      functionality when running on &rpi; hardware, consult the relevant
      section of the &sls; Release Notes:
     </para>
     <para>
      <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/aarch64/SUSE-SLES/15-SP1/#fate-325731"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     &rpiquick;
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <link xlink:href="&dsc-sles;/html/SLES-rpi-quick/art-rpiquick.html"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     &opensuse; Hardware Compatibility List: &rpi; 3
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The &opensuse; project also has information about installing and configuring
      &rpi; hardware. Much of this also applies to &sle;.
     </para>
     <para>
      See <link xlink:href="https://en.opensuse.org/HCL:Raspberry_Pi3"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     Das U-Boot
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      More information about <literal>Das U-Boot</literal> boot loader can
      be found on the project's GitHub page at
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/u-boot/u-boot"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect2>

</sect1>
