<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="docker.dockerizing.application" xml:lang="en">
	<title>Dockerizing Applications</title>
	<para>
	Docker is a technology that can help you to minimize resources used to run or build your applications. There are several types of applications that are suitable to run inside a docker container like daemons, web pages or applications that expose ports for communication. You can use docker for automation of building processes by adding the build process into a docker image and then running containers based on that image.
	</para> 
	<para>
	Running your application inside a docker container provides you with the following advantages:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			You can minimize the runtime environment of the application as you can add to the application docker image just the required processes and apllications.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			The image with your application is portable across machines also with different linux host systems.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			You can share the image of your application by using a repository.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			You can use different version of required packages in the container than the host system uses.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			You can run several instances of the same application that are completely independent on each other.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>
	Using docker for building of applications provides the following features:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			You can prepare a complete building image.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>
	The following sections provides you with examples and tips how to dockerize your applications.
	</para>
	<sect1 xml:id="">
		<title></title>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
