<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.working.with.containers" xml:lang="en">
	<title>Working with Containers</title>
	<para>
	After you have created your images, you can start your containers based on that image. You can run an instance of the image by using the <command>docker run</command> command. The docker engine then creates and starts the container. The <command>docker run</command> takes several arguments that enables you to specify a wide range of arguments for your container: 
	</para>	
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			a container's name - it is recommended to name your container
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			specify a user to use in your container
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			define a mounting point
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			specify a particular hostname, etc.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>
	The container typically exits if its main process finishes. For example, if your container starts a particular application, as soon as you quit the application, the container exists. You can start the container again by running:
	</para>
	<screen>
	docker start -ai &lt;container name&gt;
	</screen>
	<para>
	You may need to remove unsused containers, you can achieve this by using:
	</para>
	<screen>
	docker rm &lt;container name&gt;
	</screen>	
	<sect1 xml:id="Linking.Containers">
		<title>Linking Containers</title>
		<para>
		Docker enables you to link containers together which allows for communication between containers on the same host server. If you use the standard networking model, you can link containers by using the <literal>--link</literal> option when running containers:
		</para>
		<para>
		At first create a container to link to:
		</para>
		<screen>
		docker run -d --name sles sles12 /bin/bash
		</screen>
		<para>
		Now create a container that will link to the <emphasis>sles</emphasis> container:
		</para>
		<screen>
		docker run --link sles:sles sles12 /bin/bash
		</screen>
		<para>
		The container that links to <emphasis>sles</emphasis> has been defined environment variables that enables connecting to the linked container.
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
