<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="docker.building.images" xml:lang="en">
	<title>Creating Custom Images</title>
	<!-- KIWI is used to build a docker image from scratch, not to build an image derived from some base image. Please verify that. -->
	<para>
	For creating your custom image you need a base docker image of &sles;. There are two possible ways how you can obtain the &sles; base image:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>	
	<listitem>
			<para>
			You can build your own base docker image by using <link xlink:href="https://doc.opensuse.org/projects/kiwi/doc/#sec.introduction.whatiskiwi">KIWI</link>. For more details please refer to the <xref linkend="Building_Base_Images_KIWI"/>.
			</para>			
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			You can use any of the pre-built &sles; images. Please refer to the <xref linkend="Customizing_Pre-build_Images"/> for a procedure of obtaining these images. 
			</para>
		</listitem>		
	</itemizedlist>
	 <note>
	 	<title>No &sles; Images in Docker Hub</title>
	 	<para>
	 	Usually you can pull a variety of  base docker images from the <link xlink:href="https://hub.docker.com/">docker hub</link> but that does not apply for &sles;. Currently we cannot distribute &sles; images for Docker because there is no way to associate an End-User License Agreement (EULA) to a Docker image. <literal>sle2docker</listeral> enables you to import pre-build &sles; images that you can use for creating base &sles; images.
	 	</para>
	 </note>
	 <para>
	 After you obtain your base docker image, you can update the image by using a dockerfile (usually placed to the build directory). Then use the standard docker building tool to create your custom image:
	 </para>
	 <screen>
	 docker build <emphasis>path_to_build_directory</emphasis>
	 </screen>
	 <para>
	 For more options please refer to the <link xlink:href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/commandline/build/">official docker documentation</link>.
	 </para>
	 
	<sect1 xml:id="Building_Base_Images_KIWI">
		<title>Building Base &sles; Images with KIWI</title>
		<para>
		Pre-built images do not have repositories configured. But when the Docker host has an SLE subscription that provides access to the product used in the image, Zypper will automatically have access to the right repositories. 
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 xml:id="Building_Pre-build_Images">
	<title>Building from Pre-built &sles; Images</title>
	<para>
	You can install pre-built images of &sles; by using zypper:
	</para>	
	<screen>
	sudo zypper in sles11sp3-docker-image sles12-docker-image
	</screen>
	<para>
	Pre-built images do not have repositories configured. But when the Docker host has an SLE subscription that provides access to the product used in the image, Zypper will automatically have access to the right repositories.
	</para>
	<para>
	After the pre-built images are installed, you need to list them using <literal>sle2docker</literal> to get a proper image name:
	</para>
	<screen>
	sle2docker list
	</screen>
	<para>
	Now you need to activate the pre-built images:
	</para>
	<screen>
	sle2docker activate <emphasis>PRE-BUILT_IMAGE_NAME</emphasis>
	</screen>
	<para>
	After successful activation, <literal>sle2docker</literal> will display the name of the docker image. You can customize the docker image as described in the <xref linkend="Customizing_SLES_Images"/>.
	</para>
	<sect2 xml:id="Customizing_SLES_Images">
	<title>Customizing &sles; Docker Images </title>
	 <para>
	 The pre-built images do not have any repository configured. They contain a <link xlink:href="https://github.com/SUSE/container-suseconnect">zypper service</link> that contacts either the SUSE Customer Center (SCC) or your Subscription Management Tool (SMT) server, according to the configuration of the SLE host that runs the Docker container. The service obtains the list of repositories available for the product used by the Docker image.
	 </para>
	 <para>
	 You do not need to add any credentials to the Docker image because the machine credentials are automatically injected into the container by the docker daemon. They are injected inside of the <literal>/run/secrets</literal> directory. The same applies to the <filename>/etc/SUSEConnect</filename> file of the host system, which is automatically injected into the <filename>/run/secrets</filename> directory. 
	 </para>
	 <note>
    <title>Credentials and Security</title>
    <para>
     The contents of the <filename>/run/secrets</filename> directory are
     never committed to a Docker image, hence there is no risk of your
     credentials leaking.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
   To obtain the list of repositories use the following command: 
   </para>
   <screen>zypper ref -s</screen>
   <para>
    It will automatically add all the repositories to your container. For
    each repository added to the system a new file is going to be created
    under <command>/etc/zypp/repos.d</command>. The URLs of these
    repositories include an access token that automatically expires after 12
    hours. To renew the token call the <command>zypper ref -s</command>
    command. It is secure to commit these files to a Docker image.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you want to use a different set of credentials, place a custom
    <filename>/etc/zypp/credentials.d/SCCcredentials</filename> file inside
    of the Docker image. It contains the machine credentials that have the
    subscription you want to use. The same applies to the
    <filename>SUSEConnect</filename> file: to override the file available on
    the host system that is running the Docker container, add a custom
    <filename>/etc/SUSEConnect</filename> file inside of the Docker image.
   </para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
