<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.gnomeuser.start">
 <title>Getting Started with the &gnome; Desktop</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
   </dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  This section describes the conventions, layout, and common tasks of the
  &gnome; desktop as implemented in your product.
 </para>
 <para>
  &gnome; is an easy-to-use graphical interface that can be customized to meet
  your needs and personal preferences.
  This section describes the default configuration of &gnome;.
  If you or your system administrator modify the defaults, some aspect might be
  different, such as appearance or key combinations.
 </para>
 <note>
 <title>Included Session Configurations</title>
  <para>
   <!-- Does this need profiling for SLE? - sknorr, 2015-09-10 -->
   Some versions of &sle; ship with as many as three different
   session configurations based on &gnome;. These are &gnome;, &gnome; Classic,
   and &slea; Classic.
   The version described here is the default configuration of &sled;
   called &slea; Classic.
  </para>
 </note>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.login">
  <title>Logging In</title>
  <para>
   In general, all users must authenticate&mdash;unless
   <guimenu>Auto Login</guimenu> is enabled for a specific user.
   In this case, a particular user will be logged in automatically when the
   system starts.
   This can save some time, especially if a computer is used by a single person.
   It may impact account security.
   Auto Login can be enabled or disabled during installation or at any time
   using the &yast; User and Group Management module.
   For more information, refer to <xref linkend="cha.y2.userman"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   If your computer is running in a
   network environment and you are not the only person using the machine,
   you are usually prompted to enter your user name and password when you
   start the system.
   <phrase os="sled"> If you did not set up the system and
   user account yourself, check with your system administrator for your user
   name and password.</phrase>
  </para>

  <remark>screenshot useful... -- sknorr, 2015-09-10</remark>

  <procedure>
   <title>Normal Login</title>
   <step>
    <remark>Not ideal... -- sknorr, 2015-09-10</remark>
    <para>If your name is listed, click it.</para>
    <para>If your name is not listed, click <guimenu>Not listed?</guimenu>.
     Then enter your user name and click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter your password and click <guimenu>Sign in</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.gnome.switchsession">
   <title>Switching the Session Type Before Logging In</title>
   <para>
    If you want to try one of the additional &gnome; session configurations or
    try another desktop environment, follow the steps below.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      On the login screen, click your user name or enter it, as you normally
      would.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To change the session type, click the cog wheel icon.
      A menu appears.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      From the menu, choose one of the entries.
      Depending on your configuration there may be different choices,
      but the default selection is as follows.
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>&gnome;</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         A &gnome; 3 configuration that is very close to the upstream design.
         It focuses on interrupting users as little as possible.
         However, starting applications and switching between them works
         differently from many other desktop operating systems.
         It uses a single panel at the top of the screen.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>&gnome; Classic</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         A &gnome; 3 configuration that is designed to appeal to former users of
         &gnome; 2.
         The desktop has two panels, one at the top and another at the bottom.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>IceWM</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         A very basic desktop designed to use little resources.
         It can be used as a fallback, if other options do not work or are slow.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>&slea; Classic <emphasis>(default)</emphasis></term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         The default &sle; desktop, designed to appeal to users of older
         versions of &sle; and users of Microsoft* Windows*.
         This desktop is a &gnome; 3 configuration and uses a single panel
         that is placed at the bottom of the screen.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Enter your password into the input field, then click
      <guimenu>Sign In</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    After switching to another session type once, the chosen session will become
    your default session. To switch back, repeat the steps above.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec.gnome.loginassistance">
   <title>Assistive Tools</title>
   <para>
    In the top right corner, there are status icons and the assistive
    technologies menu. By clicking the status icons, open a menu that allows
    you to set the sound volume and restart or power off the machine.
   </para>
  </sect2>

 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.desktop">
  <title>Desktop Basics</title>

  <remark>Screenshot ... -- sknorr, 2015-09-10</remark>

  <para>
   The &gnome; desktop appears after you first log in. The &gnome; desktop
   appears with a panel at the bottom with following elements. From left to
   right, the panel features the following elements:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Applications menu</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> in the left corner to open a
      menu with all the installed programs. These are classified under
      different categories for a better overview. Sub-items open
      automatically as soon as you place the mouse above them.
     </para>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Activities Overview</guimenu> in the bottom part of
      the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu to open Activities Overview
      where you can start programs and manage those already running.
     </para>
     <para>
      The Activity Overview is described further in
      <xref linkend="sec.gnome.start.activities"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Places menu</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Places</guimenu> further to the right to open a menu
      containing important directories (such as your personal directory or
      the Download directory), show content of connected storage media and
      establish a connection to another computer (connection to server).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Task switcher</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      All applications currently open on the desktop (on the active
      workspace) appear in the middle part of the panel. You can bring
      these applications to the foreground by clicking their names.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Notification indicator <emphasis>(not always visible)</emphasis></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <!-- Sadly, upstream uses "Notifications" together with "Message Tray,"
           trying to keep consistent with them here. - sknorr, 2015-09-10 -->
      When there are notifications, for example, for new chat or e-mail messages
      or concerning system updates, an indicator will appear.
      The indicator is a blue circle with the number of available notifications
      displayed in the middle.
      Click the indicator to open the Message Tray where you can interact with
      all the notifications.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Workspace switcher</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This menu lets you choose a workspace (also called a virtual desktop) to
      work on.
      This feature can help you work with many windows.
      For example, you could move windows needed for one project to workspace 1
      and windows needed for another project to workspace 2.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Date and time</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The current day of the week and time are shown to the right from the
      workspace switcher.
      Click it to open a menu where you can access a calendar and
      adjust date and time settings.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Status icons</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      In the right corner of the panel, icons showing the current status of
      the network connection, sound volume and power/battery status are
      displayed.
     </para>
     <para>
      Click the icons to open a menu where you can adjust sound volume,
      display brightness, network connection, and power settings.
      Click the name to display the options for logging out or for switching to
      another user.
     </para>
     <para>
      The three icons in the lower part of the menu allow you to, from left
      to right, open the &gnome; settings dialog, lock the screen, and power
      off or restart your computer.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.gnome.start.activities">
   <title>Activities Overview</title>
   <para>
    Activities Overview is a full screen mode that comprises
    all the ways in which you can switch from one activity to another.
    It shows previews of all open windows and icons for favorite and running
    applications.
    It also integrates searching and browsing functionality.
   </para>
   <sect3>
    <title>Opening the Activities Overview</title>
    <para>
     There are multiple ways to open the Activities Overview:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Open the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu on the bottom panel and
       choose <guimenu>Activities Overview</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Press <keycap function="meta"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Forcefully move the mouse cursor to the top left corner
       (the so-called <emphasis>hot corner</emphasis>).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </sect3>
   <sect3>
    <title>Using the Activities Overview</title>
    <remark>screenshot useful -- sknor, 2015-09-10</remark>
    <para>
     In the following, the most important parts of the Activities Overview are
     explained.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Dash</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The Dash is the bar positioned on the center left.
        It contains favorite applications and all applications with open
        windows.
        If you move the mouse pointer over one of the icons, &gnome; will
        display the name of the corresponding application nearby.
        A light glow indicates that the application is running and has at least
        one open window.
       </para>
       <para>
        Right-clicking an icon opens a menu which offers
        different actions depending on the associated program.
        Using <guimenu>Add to Favorites</guimenu>, you can place the
        application icon permanently in Dash.
        To remove a program icon from Dash, select
        <guimenu>Remove from Favorites</guimenu>.
        To rearrange an icon, use the mouse to drag it to a new position.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Search box</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        On the top, there is a search box that you can use to find applications,
        settings and files in your home directory.
       </para>
       <para>
        To search, you do not need to click the search box.
        You can begin typing directly after opening Activity Overview.
        Search starts immediately, you do not need to press
        <keycap function="enter"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Workspace selector</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        On the right, there is an overview of available workspaces.
        To switch to the selected desktop, click the preview of it.
       </para>
       <para>
        To move a window from one workspace to another, drag a window preview
        from one one workspace preview to another.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.gnome.start.startprograms">
   <title>Starting Programs</title>
   <para>
    To start a program, you have several options:
   </para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      In the bottom panel, click <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> and choose the
      desired program from the hierarchical menu.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Open the Activities Overview by pressing <keycap function="meta"/>.
      Now click an application icon or search for an application.
      If you don't know the exact application name, you can search for generic
      category names such as <quote>image editor</quote>.
     </para>
     <para>
      Further information about the activities overview can be found in
      <xref linkend="sec.gnome.start.activities"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you know the exact command to start the program, you can press
      <keycombo><keycap function="alt"/><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>, enter
      the command into the dialog and press <keycap function="enter"/>.
     </para>
     <para>
      Note that the only button displayed in the window is labeled
      <guimenu>Close</guimenu> and will indeed close the window.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnomeuser.start.logout">
  <title>Pausing or Finishing Your Session</title>

  <para>
   When you have finished using the computer, there are multiple ways finish the
   session.
   Which one is right in a given situation depends on how long you will be away
   and whether you are worried about energy consumption, among other things.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Locking the Computer</title>
      <para>
       Pause your session, but keep the computer on.
       Make sure that nobody can look at or change your work while you are
       away on a break.
       Other users can log in and work in the meantime.
       Other users can shut down the computer, but a prompt will warn
       them that you are still logged in.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Logging Out</title>
      <para>
       Finish the current session, but leave the computer on, so other users
       can log in.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Shutting Down</title>
      <para>
       Finish the current session and turn off the computer.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Restarting</title>
      <para>
       Finish the current session and restart the computer.
       Restarting is necessary to apply some system updates.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Suspending the Computer</title>
      <para>
       Pause your session and put the computer in a state where it consumes
       a minimal amount of energy.
       Suspend mode can be configured to lock your screen, so nobody can
       look at or change your work.
       Waking up the computer is generally much quicker than a full
       computer start.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <para>
      This mode is also known as suspend-to-RAM, sleep or standby mode.
     </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.gnomeuser.start.login.lock">
   <title>Locking the Screen</title>
   <para>
    To lock the screen, click the status icons on the right of the main
    panel and click the padlock icon.
   </para>
   <para>
    When you lock your screen, at first a curtain with a clock will appear,
    after some time turns black.
    To unlock the screen, move the mouse or press a key to display the locked
    screen dialog.
    Enter your password, then press <keycap function="enter"/> to unlock the
    screen.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.gnomeuser.start.logout.logout">
   <title>Logging Out or Switching Users</title>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the status icons on the right of the main panel to open the
      menu.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click your user name.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select one of the following options:
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Log Out</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Logs you out of the current session and returns you to the Login
         screen.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Switch User</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Suspends your session, allowing another user to log in and use the
         computer.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.gnomeuser.start.logout.restart">
   <title>Restarting or Shutting Down the Computer</title>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the status icons on the right of the main panel to open the
      menu.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the power off icon in the lower right part of the menu.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select one of the following options:
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Power Off</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Logs you out of the current session, then turns off the computer.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Restart</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Logs you out of the current session, then restarts the computer.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.gnomeuser.start.suspend">
   <title>Suspending the Computer</title>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the status icons on the right of the main panel to open the
      menu.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Hold <keycap function="alt"/> pressed.
      The power off icon in the lower right part of the menu turns into a pause
      icon.
      Click the pause icon.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

 </sect1>
</chapter>
