<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.gnome.accessibility">
 <title>Assistive Technologies</title>
 <info>
      <abstract>
        <para>
    The &gnome; desktop includes assistive technologies to support users with
    various impairments and special needs, and to interact with common
    assistive devices. This chapter describes several assistive technology
    applications designed to meet the needs of users with physical
    disabilities like low vision or impaired motor skills.
   </para>
      </abstract>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
        </dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec.general.accessibility.enable">
  <title>Enabling Assistive Technologies</title>

  <para>
   To configure accessibility features, open the &gnome; Settings dialog (for
   example using <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
   <guimenu>System Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu></menuchoice>)
   and click <guimenu>Universal Access</guimenu>. Each assistive feature is
   enabled separately using this dialog.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you need a more direct access to individual assistive features, check
   <guimenu>Always Show Universal Access Menu</guimenu> in the
   <guimenu>Universal Access</guimenu> dialog. A new menu will appear on the
   bottom panel.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.general.accessibility.visual">
  <title>Visual Impairments</title>

  <para>
   In the <guimenu>Seeing</guimenu> section of the
   <guimenu>Universal Access</guimenu> dialog, you can enable features that
   help people with impaired vision.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Turning on <guimenu>High Contrast</guimenu> enables high contrast black
     and white icons in the &gnome; desktop.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Turning on <guimenu>Large Text</guimenu> enlarges the font used in the
     user interface.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Turning on <guimenu>Zoom</guimenu> enables a screen magnifier. You can
     set the desired magnification and magnifier behavior, including color
     effects.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If the <guimenu>Screen Reader</guimenu> is turned on, any UI element or
     text that receives keyboard focus is read aloud.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If the <guimenu>Sound Keys</guimenu> are turned on, a sound is played
     whenever <keycap>Num Lock</keycap> or <keycap>Caps Lock</keycap> are
     turned on.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.general.accessibility.hearing">
  <title>Hearing Impairments</title>

  <para>
   In the <guimenu>Hearing</guimenu> section of the
   <guimenu>Universal Access</guimenu> dialog, you can enable features
   helping people with impaired hearing.
  </para>

  <para>
   If the <guimenu>Visual Alerts</guimenu> are turned on, a window title or
   the entire screen is flashed when an alert sound occurs.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.general.accessibility.mobility">
  <title>Mobility Impairments</title>

  <para>
   In the <guimenu>Typing</guimenu> and <guimenu>Pointing and
   Clicking</guimenu> sections of the <guimenu>Universal Access</guimenu>
   dialog, you can enable features that help people with mobility
   impairments.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If the <guimenu>Screen Keyboard</guimenu> is turned on, a virtual
     keyboard appears whenever you need to enter text. You can use the screen
     keyboard by clicking the virtual keys.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Typing Assist</guimenu> to open a dialog where you can
     enable various features that make typing easier.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Sticky Keys</guimenu> allows you to type key combinations one
       key at a time rather than having to hold down all of the keys at once.
       For example, the <keycombo>
       <keycap function="alt"/><keycap function="tab"/></keycombo> shortcut
       switches between windows.
      </para>
      <para>
       With sticky keys turned off, you need to hold
       down both keys at the same time. With sticky keys turned on, press
       <keycap function="alt"/> and then <keycap function="tab"/> to do the
       same.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Turn on <guimenu>Slow Keys</guimenu> if you want a delay between pressing
       a key and the letter being displayed on the screen. This means that you
       need to hold down each key you want to type for a little while before it
       appears. Use slow keys if you accidentally press several keys at a time
       when you type, or if you find it difficult to press the right key on the
       keyboard first time.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Turn on <guimenu>Bounce Keys</guimenu> to ignore key presses that are
       rapidly repeated.
       This can help, for example, if you have hand tremors which cause you
       to press a key multiple times when you only want to press it once.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Turn on <guimenu>Mouse Keys</guimenu> to control the mouse pointer using
       the numeric keypad on your keyboard.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Click Assist</guimenu> to open a dialog where you can
     enable various features that make clicking easier: simulated secondary
     click and hover click.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Turn on <guimenu>Simulated Secondary Click</guimenu> to activate the
       secondary click (usually the right mouse button) by holding down the
       primary button for a predefined <guimenu>Acceptance delay</guimenu>. This
       is useful if you find it difficult to move your fingers individually on
       one hand, or if your pointing device only has a single button.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Turn on <guimenu>Hover Click</guimenu> to trigger a click by hovering
       your mouse pointer over an object on the screen. This is useful if you
       find it difficult to move the mouse and click at the same time. If this
       feature is turned on, a small Hover Click window opens and stays above
       all of your other windows. You can use this to choose what sort of click
       should happen when you hover. When you hover your mouse pointer over a
       button and do not move it, the pointer gradually changes color. When it
       has fully changed color, the button will be clicked.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>For More Information</title>
  <para>You can find further information in the &gnome; help, which is also available
   online at
   <link xlink:href="https://help.gnome.org/users/gnome-help/3.12/a11y.html.en">https://help.gnome.org/users/gnome-help/3.12/a11y.html.en</link>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
