<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-gnome-settings">
 <title>Customizing Your Settings</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  You can change the way the &gnome; desktop looks and behaves to suit your own
  personal tastes and needs. Some possible changes of settings are:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Keyboard and mouse configuration, as described in
    <xref linkend="sec-gnome-settings-hardware-keyboard"/> and
    <xref linkend="sec-gnome-settings-hardware-mouse"/>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Desktop background, as described in
    <xref linkend="sec-gnome-settings-look-deskback"/>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Sounds, as described in <xref linkend="sec-gnome-settings-hardware-audio"/>
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  These settings and others can be changed in the &gnome;
  <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> dialog.  It focuses on look and feel,
  personal settings and preferences of your &gnome; desktop.
  </para>

  <para>
   To change some system-wide settings, you need to use &yast; instead. This is
   the case for administrator settings (including most of the hardware, the
   graphical user interface, Internet access, security settings, user
   administration, software installation and system updates and
   information). For information about using &yast;, refer to the integrated
   &yast; help texts or to the <phrase os="sles;sled"><xref
   linkend="book-sle-deployment"/></phrase><phrase os="osuse"><xref
   linkend="book-opensuse-startup"/></phrase>.
  </para>

  <para>
   To access the GNOME settings dialog, right-click the desktop and choose
   <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <sect1 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-look-deskback">
   <title>Changing the Desktop Background</title>
   <para>
    The desktop background is the image or color that is applied to your
    desktop. You can also customize the image shown when the screen is locked.
   </para>
   <para>
    To change the desktop background or the lock screen:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Right-click the desktop and choose <guimenu>Change Background</guimenu>.
     </para>
<!--<informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="preferences_background.png" width="45%"
         format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="preferences_background.png" width="45%"
         format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>-->
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose <guimenu>Background</guimenu> or <guimenu>Lock Screen</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Wallpapers</guimenu>, <guimenu>Pictures</guimenu>, or
      <guimenu>Colors</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <para>
      Wallpapers are preconfigured images distributed with your system.
      Pictures are your own images from your <filename>Pictures</filename>
      directory (<filename>~/Pictures</filename>). Colors are predefined colors
      chosen by &gnome; developers.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose an option from the list.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      When you are satisfied with your choice, click <guimenu>Select</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-lang">
   <title>Configuring Language Settings</title>
   <para>
    &productname; can be configured to use any of several languages. The
    language setting determines the language of dialogs and menus and can also
    determine the keyboard and clock layout.
   </para>
   <para>
    To configure your language settings right-click the desktop and choose
    <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>. Now choose <guimenu>Region &amp;
    Language</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Here you can choose:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <guimenu>Language</guimenu>. Choose a language from the list and confirm
      with <guimenu>Done</guimenu>. To make the change take effect, you need to
      restart the desktop afterwards.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <guimenu>Formats</guimenu>: To change the formats for date, number,
      currency and related options, choose a country from the list and confirm
      with <guimenu>Done</guimenu>. To make the change take effect, you need to
      restart the desktop afterwards.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <guimenu>Input sources</guimenu> (keyboard layout). Change your keyboard
      layout here or add another one. If you use more than one keyboard layout,
      you can switch keyboards by clicking the language code in the Activities
      Bar.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <note>
    <title>
     Settings Made Using <command>ibus-setup</command> Do Not Take Effect
    </title>
    <para>
     On GNOME, settings made using <command>ibus-setup</command> do not take
     effect. <command>ibus-setup</command> can only be
     used to configure IceWM. Instead, always use the
     <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> application:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To change input methods, use <guimenu>Region &amp; Language</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To change the key combination that switches between input methods, use
       <menuchoice> <guimenu>Devices</guimenu> <guimenu>Keyboard</guimenu>
       </menuchoice>. In there, choose the category <guimenu>Typing</guimenu>
       and the entry <guimenu>Switch to next input source</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </note>
</sect1>
   
<sect1 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-hardware-keyboard">
  <title>Configuring the Keyboard</title>
  <para>
      Refer to <xref linkend="sec-general-accessibility-mobility"/> for
      additional settings, such as key autorepetition and cursor blink rate,
      and accessibility features. To configure your
      keyboard layout, refer to <xref linkend="sec-gnome-settings-lang"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   To modify keyboard shortcuts right-click the desktop and choose
   <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>. Now choose <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Devices</guimenu> <guimenu>Keyboard</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
  </para>
  <figure xml:id="fig-gnome-settings-hardware-keyboard">
   <title>Keyboard Dialog</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="preferences_keyboard.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="preferences_keyboard.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Keyboard</guimenu> dialog shows the keyboard shortcuts that
   are configured for your system. To edit a key combination, click the entry
   you like to change. To set a new key combination, press the respective
   keys. To disable a shortcut, press <keycap function="backspace"/> instead.
  </para>
 </sect1>

   <sect1 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-xmodmap">
       <title>Using XCompose to Type Special Characters</title>
       <para>GNOME supports fast input source (keyboard layout) switching 
           (<xref linkend="sec-gnome-settings-lang"/>). However, if you are using
           <command>xmodmap</command> to create custom keymaps, it may not
           work correctly when you switch between multiple input sources. For 
           example, you have two input sources, English and German. Your
           <command>xmodmap</command> commands work fine in the first input
           source you select, but when you switch to the second input source
           the same <command>xmodmap</command> commands produce incorrect output.
            <command>xmodmap</command> is an older protocol and does not have 
            full view of the keyboard layout, so in more complex situations it 
            causes errors.
        </para>
        <para>
            An alternative method is to use <command>xcompose</command> to assign 
            special symbols to sequences of key presses. This should work 
            with any input source. Install <command>xcompose</command>
            by installing the <literal>libX11-devel</literal> package.
        </para>
        <para>            
            Next, assign a compose key with the Tweaks tool in Activities. You
            will press this key in sequence with one or two additional keys 
            to print a special character. The keys must be pressed in the correct
            sequence, starting with the compose key.
         </para>
         <para>
            Navigate to 
            <menuchoice><guimenu>Keyboard &amp; Mouse</guimenu>
            <guimenu>Compose Key</guimenu></menuchoice> and select your command
            key (<xref linkend="fig-gnome-settings-keyboard-compose"/>).
        </para>
          <figure xml:id="fig-gnome-settings-keyboard-compose">
   <title>Enabling the Compose Key in Tweaks</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="tweaks-compose.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="tweaks-compose.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
      Next, create a <filename>~/.XCompose</filename> file. This is the default 
      per-user configuration file. Enter your 
      keymappings in this file, like this example:
   </para>
   <screen>include "%L"

&lt;Multi_key> &lt;a> : "α"
&lt;Multi_key> &lt;b> : "β"
&lt;Multi_key> &lt;exclam>  : "¡"</screen>
        
    <para>
        <literal>include "%L"</literal> includes the default compose file
        for your locale, for example 
        <filename>/usr/share/X11/locale/en_US.UTF-8</filename>.
    </para>
    <para>
        The remaining lines specify the compose key, the other keypresses, and the 
        symbols they are intended to print. After you 
        make changes to your compose file, you must log out of your session and 
        log back in to activate the changes.
    </para>
    <para>
        Your key assignments are case-sensitive. 
        <filename>~/.XCompose</filename> overrides the system files. Use the 
        compose file for your locale to see what is already configured, and to
        copy symbols from it into your personal compose file. (These files
        may have a lot of whitespace at the beginning; they're not empty so keep 
        scrolling.) As always, watch out for conflicts with the other keymaps 
        on your system.
    </para>
    <para>
        For additional information see <command>man xcompose</command>.
    </para>
  </sect1> 
 
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-hardware-bluetooth">
  <title>Configuring Bluetooth Settings</title>
  <para>
   <remark>taroth 2016-05-25: FIXME - need to check this on a laptop</remark>
   The Bluetooth module lets you set the visibility of your machine over
   Bluetooth and connect to available Bluetooth devices. To configure Bluetooth
   connectivity, follow these steps:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Right-click the desktop and choose <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>. Now choose
     <guimenu>Bluetooth</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To use Bluetooth, turn the <guimenu>Bluetooth</guimenu> switch on.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To make your computer visible over Bluetooth, turn the
     <guimenu>Visibility</guimenu> switch on. The computer will start
     searching for other visible Bluetooth devices in the vicinity and display
     any found devices in the <guimenu>Devices</guimenu> list. At first, the
     list may be empty.
    </para>
    <note>
     <title>Temporary Visibility</title>
     <para>
      The <guimenu>Visibility</guimenu> switch is meant to be used only
      temporarily. You only need to turn it on for the initial setup of a
      connection to a Bluetooth device. After the connection has been
      established, turn off the switch.
     </para>
    </note>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the device you want to connect, turn on Bluetooth connectivity and
     visibility, too.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If the desired device has been found and is shown in the list, click it
     to establish a connection to it.
    </para>
    <para>
     You will be asked whether the PINs of the two devices match.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If the PINs match, confirm this on <emphasis>both</emphasis> your
     computer and the device.
    </para>
    <para>
     The pairing is now established. On your computer, the device in the list
     is shown as <guimenu>Connected</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <textobject role="description">
       <phrase>Connect bluetooth</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="bluetooth_connect.png" width="95%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="bluetooth_connect.png" width="90%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
     Depending on the device type, it will now be available in other
     applications, for example as a storage device in &nautilus;, or a sound
     device in playback applications.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   To connect to a paired Bluetooth device, select the device in the list. In
   the dialog that appears, turn the <guimenu>Connection</guimenu> switch on.
   You can send files to the connected device by using the <guimenu>Send
   Files</guimenu> button. If you are connected to a device such as a mobile
   phone, you can use it as a network device by activating the appropriate
   option.
  </para>
  <para>
   To remove a connected device from the list on your computer, click
   <guimenu>Remove Device</guimenu> and confirm your choice. To completely
   remove the pairing, you also need to do so on your device.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-hardware-power">
  <title>Configuring Power Settings</title>
  <para>
   Settings available in this dialog depend on your hardware. In the following
   we describe options that are typically available when using a laptop. On a
   workstation, many of the described options are not available.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Right-click the desktop and choose <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>. Now choose
     <guimenu>Power</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the upper part of the dialog the current state of the battery is
     displayed.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Power Saving</guimenu> section of the dialog, set the
     <guimenu>Screen Brightness</guimenu>. You can also set whether to dim or
     blank the screen after or turn off wireless networking a period of
     inactivity.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Suspend and Power Button</guimenu> section of the dialog,
     configure a time after which the computer is set to do an
     <guimenu>Automatic Suspend</guimenu>. You may set diff
    </para>
    <para>
     You can also set the action performed when the power button is pressed.
     Choose <guimenu>Hibernate</guimenu> to use a mode where the computer
     turns off completely but saves your running session to the hard disk.
     Alternatively, choose <guimenu>Suspend</guimenu> or
     <guimenu>Nothing</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-hardware-mouse">
  <title>Configuring the Mouse and Touchpad</title>
  <para>
   To modify mouse and touchpad options, right-click the desktop and choose
   <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>. Now choose <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Devices</guimenu> <guimenu>Mouse &amp; Touchpad</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>.
  </para>
  <figure xml:id="fig-gnome-settings-hardware-mouse">
   <title>Mouse and Touchpad Settings Dialog</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="preferences_mouse.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="preferences_mouse.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>General</guimenu> section of the dialog, you can set the
     <guimenu>Primary button</guimenu> orientation (left or right).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Mouse</guimenu> section of the dialog, use <guimenu>Mouse
     Speed</guimenu> to adjust the sensitivity of the mouse pointer. With
     <guimenu>Natural Scrolling</guimenu> you can set the direction in which
     the content moves, when scrolling with the mouse. When natural scrolling
     is turned off, the content moves <emphasis>up</emphasis> when pushing the
     scroll wheel <emphasis>down</emphasis>. When natural scrolling is turned
     on, the content moves in the same direction as the mouse wheel.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Touchpad</guimenu> section of the dialog, you can turn
     the touchpad on and off. Use <guimenu>Touchpad Speed</guimenu> to adjust
     the sensitivity of the touchpad pointer. You can also disable the
     touchpad while typing and enable clicks by tapping the touchpad.
    </para>
    <para>
     With <guimenu>Natural Scrolling</guimenu> you can set the direction in
     which the content moves, when scrolling with two fingers. When natural
     scrolling is turned on, the content moves in the same directions as your
     fingers. When natural scrolling is turned off, the content moves in the
     opposite direction.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To test your settings, click <guimenu>Test Your Settings</guimenu> and
     try the pointing device.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   For configuration of mouse accessibility options, refer to the
   <xref linkend="sec-general-accessibility-mobility"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-hardware-printer">
  <title>Installing and Configuring Printers</title>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Printers</guimenu> dialog lets you connect to any available
   local or remote CUPS server and configure printers.
  </para>
  <para>
   To start the Printers module, right-click the desktop and choose
   <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>. Now choose <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Devices</guimenu> <guimenu>Printers</guimenu> </menuchoice>. For
   detailed information, refer to <xref linkend="cha-gnome-print"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-hardware-screen">
  <title>Configuring Screens</title>
  <para>
   To specify resolution and orientation for your screen or to configure
   multiple screens, right-click the desktop and choose <guimenu>Display
   Settings</guimenu>. The configuration options available in this dialog
   depend on whether you have a single or a multiple monitor setup.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-hardware-screen-single">
   <title>Changing Settings: Single Monitor Setup</title>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gnome-settings-hardware-screen-single">
    <title>Single Monitor Settings Dialog</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="preferences_screen_single.png" width="100%"
                 format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="preferences_screen_single.png" width="80%"
                 format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Orientation</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If you use a monitor which can change its orientation, you need to
       adjust the display before turning the monitor. Use
       <guimenu>Orientation</guimenu> to do this. Choose the orientation your
       monitor supports, close the selection box and click
       <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>. You have 20 seconds to <guimenu>Revert
       Settings</guimenu>, otherwise they will automatically be applied.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Resolution</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To change the screen resolution, click
       <guimenu>Resolution</guimenu>. Choose a new value, close the selection
       box and click <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>. You have 20 seconds to
       <guimenu>Revert Settings</guimenu>, otherwise they will automatically be
       applied.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Night Light</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If you are working in a dark environment, your eyes can easily be
       strained by the monitor. To prevent this, change the screen's color
       palette to a warmer tone by turning on <guimenu>Night
       Light</guimenu>. Under <guimenu>Schedule</guimenu> you can automate this
       setting by specifying at which time <guimenu>Night Light</guimenu>
       should be turned on and off.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-hardware-screen-multi">
   <title>Changing Settings: Multiple Monitor Setup</title>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gnome-settings-hardware-screen-multi">
    <title>Single Monitor Settings Dialog</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="preferences_screen.png" width="100%"
                 format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="preferences_screen.png" width="80%"
                 format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <para>
    In case you have a multiple monitor setup, identify each monitor by the
    number displayed in its upper left corner.
   </para>

   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Display Mode</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Choose how to use the monitors. With <guimenu>Join Displays</guimenu>
       you get a single desktop that stretches across all
       monitors. <guimenu>Mirror</guimenu> displays the same content on each
       monitor. <guimenu>Single Display</guimenu> deactivates all monitors but
       the one chosen.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Display Arrangement</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Drag and Drop the monitor pictograms to order them so they match your
       physical setup. This is especially important when using joint displays,
       to ensure you can move from monitor to monitor in the correct order. You
       can also set the primary display here. This is the display that shows
       GNOME's activity bar.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Monitor Configuration</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To configure orientation and resolution for each monitor, select a
       monitor by clicking its pictogram or its tab. For further instructions
       refer to <xref linkend="sec-gnome-settings-hardware-screen-single"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-hardware-audio">
  <title>Configuring Sound Settings</title>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Sound</guimenu> tool lets you manage sound devices and set the
   sound effects. In the top part of the dialog, you can select the general
   output volume or turn the sound off completely.
  </para>
  <para>
   To open the sound settings, right-click the desktop and choose
   <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>. Now choose <guimenu>Sound</guimenu>.
  </para>
  <figure>
   <title>Configuring Sound Settings</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="sound_devices.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="sound_devices.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-hardware-audio-dev">
   <title>Configuring Sound Devices</title>
   <para>
    Use the <guimenu>Output</guimenu> tab to select the device for sound
    output. Below the list, choose the sound device setting you prefer, for
    example balance.
   </para>
   <para>
    Use the <guimenu>Input</guimenu> tab to set the input device volume or to
    mute the input temporarily. If you have more than one sound device, you
    can also select a default device for audio input in the <guimenu>Choose a
    device for sound input</guimenu> list.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-hardware-audio-effects">
   <title>Configuring Sound Effects</title>
   <para>
    Use the <guimenu>Sound Effects</guimenu> tab to configure whether and how
    you want sound to be played when message boxes appear.
   </para>
   <para>
    Specify the volume at which the sound effects will be played under
    <guimenu>Alert volume</guimenu>. You can also turn the effects on and off.
   </para>
   <para>
    Choose a sound of your choice under <guimenu>Choose an alter
    sound</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <!--
     Only works as root and therefore makes little sense to document here

  <sect1 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-personal-password">
   <title>Changing Your Password</title>
   <para>
    For security reasons, it is a good idea to change your login password from
    time to time. To change your password:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guimenu>System
      Tools</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenu>Users</guimenu></menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the button labeled with dots next to <guimenu>Password</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the first text box, type your current password.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the next text box, type a new password.
     </para>
     <para>
      You can also click the cog wheel icon at the end of the text box to
      generate a random password.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Confirm your new password by typing it again in the last text box.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Change</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   </sect1>
   -->

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-prefapps">
  <title>Setting Default Applications</title>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     To change the default application for various common tasks such as
     browsing the Internet, sending mails or playing multimedia files,
     right-click the desktop and choose <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>. Now
     choose <menuchoice> <guimenu>Details</guimenu> <guimenu>Default
     Applications</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Default Applications</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="preferences_preferred_apps.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="preferences_preferred_apps.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     You can choose an application to handle Web, mail, calendar, music,
     videos or photographs. Select one of the available applications from the
     drop-down boxes for the task of your choice.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-gnome-settings-share">
  <title>Setting Session Sharing Preferences</title>
  <para>
   To open a configuration dialog for sharing files and allowing remote logins
   via ssh, right-click the desktop and choose <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>. Now
   choose <guimenu>Sharing</guimenu>.
  </para>
  <para>
   Before you can share anything, you need to turn on the switch in the upper
   part of the dialog. The switch also helps you if you quickly need to
   disable all sharing options.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To share files via the WebDAV protocol click <guimenu>File
     Sharing</guimenu> and enable this option. Optionally set a password
     required to access the files and choose a network from which others can
     access your files.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To enable logging in via SSH, click <guimenu>Remote Login</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    All the sharing screens contain an address which you can give to other
    users, so they can reach you. To copy a sharing address, click it and
    select <guimenu>Copy</guimenu>. You can then paste it into an e-mail or
    messaging software.
   </para>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
