<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
  ]>
<chapter id="cha.gnomeuser.start">
 <title>Getting Started with the GNOME Desktop</title>
 <para>
  This section describes the conventions, layout, and common tasks of the
  GNOME desktop as implemented in your product.
 </para>
 <para>
  GNOME is an easy-to-use graphical interface that can be customized to meet
  your needs and personal preferences. This section describes the default
  configuration of GNOME. If you or your system administrator modifies the
  defaults, some aspect might be different, such as appearance or key
  combinations.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.login">
  <title>Getting Started</title>
  <para>
   If more than one user account is configured on your computer, generally
   all users must authenticate&mdash;unless <guimenu>Auto Login</guimenu> is
   enabled for a specific user. Auto login lets a user automatically log in
   to the desktop environment when the system starts. This feature can be
   enabled or disabled during installation or at any time using the &yast;
   User and Group Management module. For more information, refer to
   <xref linkend="cha.y2.userman"/>. If your computer is running in a
   network environment and you are not the only person using the machine,
   you are usually prompted to enter your user name and password when you
   start the system.<phrase os="sled"> If you did not set up the system and
   user account yourself, check with your system administrator for your
   user name and password.</phrase>
  </para>
  <para>
   The GNOME desktop appears after you first log in. The GNOME desktop
   appears with a panel at the bottom with following elements:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <!--   <varlistentry>
    <term>Bottom Panel</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The desktop includes a panel at the bottom of the screen. All
      applications currently open on the desktop appear here. You can access
      these applications by clicking their name.
     <para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>-->
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Applications menu</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> in the left corner to open a menu
      with all the installed programs. These are classified under different
      categories for a better overview. Sub-items open automatically as soon
      as you place the mouse above them.
     </para>
     <para><!--just a link?-->
      Clicking <guimenu>Activities Overview</guimenu> in the bottom part
      of the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu takes you to the so-called
      Activities overview where you start programs and manage those already
      running. You also reach this view by placing the mouse pointer in the
      top left corner of the screen or pressing the <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
      key (also called the <guimenu>Super</guimenu> key). You return to the
      normal view by clicking <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> or pressing
      the <guimenu>Escape</guimenu> key.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Places menu</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Places</guimenu> further to the right to open a menu
      containing important directories (such as your personal directory or the
      Download directory), show content of connected data carriers and establish
      a connection to another computer (connection to server).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>The middle part of the panel</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      All applications currently open on the desktop (on the active
      workspace) appear in the middle part of the panel. You can access
      these applications by clicking their name.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Workspace menu</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The first menu on the right lets you choose a workspace
      (a virtual desktop) to work on.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Date and time</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The current date and time is shown to the right from the workspace
      menu. By clicking it, open a menu where you can access a calendar
      and adjust the date and time settings.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Status icons</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      In the right corner of the panel, icons showing the current status
      of the network connection, sound volume and power (battery) status
      are displayed.
     </para>
     <para>
      By clicking them, you open a menu where you can
      adjust the sound volume, the display brightness, the network
      connection, and the power settings. There is also the name of the
      current user. Click the name to display the options for logging
      out or for switching to another user.
     </para>
     <para>
      The three icons in the lower part of the menu allow you to,
      from left to right, open the GNOME settings dialog, lock the
      screen, and power off or restart your computer.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <sect2 id="sec.gnome.start.activities">
   <title>Activities Overview</title>
   <para>
    Activities overview is a special mode that dedicates a full screen to all
    the different ways in which the user can switch from doing one thing (an
    activity) to doing something else. It shows previews of all the windows
    the user has open and the user's favorite and running applications. It
    also integrates search and browse functionality.
   </para>
   <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Activities Overview</title>
    <para>
     There are three ways to activate the activities overview:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Open the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu on the bottom panel
       and choose <guimenu>Activities Overview</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Press the <guimenu>Windows</guimenu> key (also called the
       <guimenu>Super</guimenu> key).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </sect3>
   <sect3>
    <title>Using the Activities Overview</title>
    <para>
     The activities overview contains three important parts:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       On the left, there is a favorite bar. It contains favorite applications
       as well as the running applications with open windows. If you hover
       over one of the icons with the mouse pointer, GNOME will tell you the
       name of the pertaining application. A light glow indicates that the
       application is running and (at least) one window is open.
       Right-clicking an icon opens a small menu which offers different
       actions depending on the associated program. With Add to Favorites, you
       can place the application icon permanently in Dash. To remove a program
       icon from Dash, select Remove from Favorites. If you want to rearrange
       an icon in the dock, hold the left mouse button pressed above it and
       then drag it to its new position.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       On the top, there is a search box. If you cannot find what you are
       looking for or when things need to get done quickly, the small search
       box on the  top will help. As soon as you enter a term there, GNOME
       will show all the matching applications and system settings. By the
       way, you do not need to clickthe search box first, you can begin typing
       directly.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       On the right, there is an overview of active virtal desktops.
       Click to switch to a selected virtual desktop.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.gnome.start.startprograms">
   <title>Starting Programs</title>
   <para>
    To start a program, you have several options:
   </para>
   <para>
    Click <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> in the bottom
    panel and choose the desired program from the hierarchical menu.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you know the exact command to start the program, you can press
    <keycombo><keycap function="alt"/><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>,
    enter the command into the dialog and press <keycap function="enter"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can also start the program using the activities view. You can reach
    this view by placing the mouse pointer in the top left corner of the
    screen or pressing the <guimenu>Windows</guimenu> key (also called the
    <guimenu>Super</guimenu> key). Now you have two options. Either click
    the program icon in the bar on the left edge of the screen, or enter
    a term into the search box in the upper part of the activities view.
    You can use the name of the desired program or try any meaningful
    keywords, such as <literal>image</literal> or <literal>photo</literal>
    in the case you need an image editor.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="sec.gnome.start.login">
  <title>Logging In and Selecting a Desktop</title>

  <para>
   If more than one user account is configured on your computer, generally
   all users must authenticate&mdash;unless <guimenu>Auto Login</guimenu> is
   enabled for a specific user. Auto login lets a user automatically log in
   to the desktop environment when the system starts. This feature can be
   enabled or disabled during installation or at any time using the &yast;
   User and Group Management module. For more information, refer to
   <xref linkend="cha.y2.userman"/>. If your computer is running in a
   network environment and you are not the only person using the machine,
   you are usually prompted to enter your user name and password when you
   start the system.<phrase os="sled"> If you did not set up the system and
   user account yourself, check with your system administrator for your
   user name and password.</phrase>
  </para>

  <para>
   In the login screen, click your user name, enter your password and
   click <keycap function="enter"/> to log in. If your name is not listed,
   click <guimenu>Not listed?</guimenu> and enter your user name, password
   and click <keycap function="enter"/> to log in.
  </para>
  
  <para>
   In the top right corner, there are status icons and the assistive
   technologies menu. By clicking the status icons, open a menu that
   allows you to set the sound volume and restart or power off the machine.
  </para>
   
  <!-- <sect2 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.login.switch">
   <title>Switching the Desktop Environment</title>
   <para>
    If you have installed other desktop environments beside GNOME, use the
    following instructions to switch the desktop environment.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Computer</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Logout</guimenu> <guimenu>Log Out</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose a desktop from the <guimenu>Session</guimenu> menu.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Type your user name, then press <keycap function="enter"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Type your password, then press <keycap function="enter"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>-->

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.login.lock">
   <title>Locking Your Screen</title>
   <para>
    To lock the screen, click the status icons on the right of the main panel and
    click the lock icon.
   </para>
   <para>
    When you lock your screen, a screen saver starts, locking the screen. To
    unlock the screen, move your mouse or press a key to display the locked
    screen dialog. Enter your password, then press
    <keycap function="enter"/> to unlock the screen.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.logout">
  <title>Logging Out</title>
  <para>
   When you have finished using the computer, you can log out (leaving the
   system running), restart or shut down the computer. If your system
   provides power management you can also suspend your computer, making the
   next session start much faster than with a complete reboot.
  </para>
  <sect2 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.logout.logout">
   <title>Logging Out or Switching Users</title>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the status icons on the right of the main panel to open the menu.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click your user name.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select one of the following options:
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Log Out</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Logs you out of the current session and returns you to the Login
         screen.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Switch User</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Suspends your session, allowing another user to log in and use the
         computer.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.logout.restart">
   <title>Restarting or Shutting Down the Computer</title>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the status icons on the right of the main panel to open the menu.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the power off icon in the lower right part of the menu.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select one of the following options:
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Power Off</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Logs you out of the current session, then turns off the computer.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Restart</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Logs you out of the current session, then restarts the computer.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Suspend</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Puts your computer in a temporary state that conserves minimal
         power (<quote>Suspend to RAM</quote>). The state of your session is
         preserved, however, including all applications you have running and
         all documents you have open.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Hibernate</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Suspends your session, using no power until the computer is
         restarted (<quote>Suspend to Disk</quote>). The state of your
         session is preserved, however, including all applications you have
         running and all documents you have open.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
