<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!--PM's doc requirements:
 Data encryption (partially NEW)
	1.High level information for end-users
	2.Basic configuration details
-> which application(s)? GNOME Passwords and Keys?
	Yes, I am still pushing very hard for an unified solution here. Feature
	302530 is pretty central to my idea here.
	http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/FedoraCryptoConsolidation

 @maintainer: GNOME Passwords and Keys are mentioned here,
 please update - not sure where to mention the certificate store - might
 go to new file security_certificatestore.xml
-->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.gnome.crypto">
 <title>Passwords and Keys: Signing and Encrypting Data</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
   </dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  The &gnome; Passwords and Keys program is an important component
  of the encryption infrastructure on your system. With the help of this
  program, you can create and manage PGP and SSH keys, import and export PGP
  and SSH keys, share your keys with others, back up your keys and keyring,
  cache your passphrase, and encrypt and decrypt the clipboard.
 </para>
 <para>
  Start the program by choosing <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
  <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu> <guimenu>Passwords and Keys</guimenu>
  </menuchoice>
 </para>
 <figure pgwide="0">
  <title>Password and Keys Main Window</title>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="seahorse_main.png" width="73%" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="seahorse_main.png" width="73%" format="png"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.crypto.sign_encrypt">
  <title>Signing and Encryption</title>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Signing</title>
   <para>
    Attaching electronic signatures to pieces of information, such as
    e-mail messages or software to prove its origin. To keep someone
    else from writing messages using your name, and to protect both you and
    the people you send them to, you should sign your mails. Signatures help
    you check the sender of the messages you receive and distinguish
    authentic messages from malicious ones.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <para>
   Software developers sign their software so that you can check the
   integrity. Even if you get the software from an unofficial server, you
   can verify the package with the signature.
  </para>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Encryption</title>
   <para>
     You might also have sensitive information you want to protect from other
     parties. Encryption helps you transform data and
     make it unreadable for others. This is important for companies so they
     can protect internal information as well as their employees' privacy.
   </para>
  </formalpara>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="cha.gnome.crypto.gen_key">
  <title>Generating a New Key Pair</title>

  <para>
   To exchange encrypted messages with other users, you must first generate
   your own pair of keys. It consists of two parts:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Public Key</title>
     <para>
      This key is used for encryption.
      Distribute it to your communication partners, so they can use it to
      encrypt files or messages for you.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Private Key</title>
     <para>
      This key is used for decryption.
      Use it to make encrypted files or messages from others (or yourself)
      legible again.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <important>
   <title>Access to the Private Key</title>
   <para>
    If others gain access to your private key, they will be able to decrypt
    files and messages intended only for you.
    Never grant others access to your private key.
   </para>
  </important>

  <sect2 xml:id="cha.gnome.crypto.gen_key.openpgp">
   <title>Creating OpenPGP Keys</title>
   <para>
    OpenPGP is a non-proprietary protocol for encrypting e-mail with the use
    of public-key cryptography based on PGP. It defines standard formats for
    encrypted messages, signatures, private keys, and certificates for
    exchanging public keys.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu> <guimenu>Passwords and Keys</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guimenu>New</guimenu></menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select <guimenu>PGP Key</guimenu> and click
      <guimenu>Continue</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Specify your full name and e-mail address.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Advanced key options</guimenu> to specify the following
      advanced options for the key.
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Comment</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         An optional comment.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Encryption Type</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Specifies the encryption algorithms used to generate your keys.
         <guimenu>DSA ElGamal</guimenu> is the recommended choice because it
         lets you encrypt, decrypt, sign, and verify as needed. Both
         <guimenu>DSA (sign only)</guimenu> and <guimenu>RSA (sign
         only)</guimenu> allow only signing.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Key Strength</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Specifies the length of the key in bits. The longer the key, the
         more secure it is (provided a strong passphrase is used)
         Keep in mind that performing any operation with a longer key requires
         more time than it does with a shorter key. Acceptable values are
         between 1024 and 4096 bits. At least 2048 bits are recommended.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Expiration Date</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Specifies the date at which the key will cease to be usable for
         performing encryption or signing operations. You will need to
         either change the expiration date or generate a new key or subkey
         after this amount of time passes. Sign your new key with your old
         one before it expires to preserve your trust status.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Create</guimenu> to create the new key pair.
     </para>
     <para>
      The <guimenu>Passphrase for New PGP Key</guimenu> dialog opens.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Specify the passphrase twice for your new key, then click
      <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <para>
      When you specify a passphrase, use the same practices you use when you
      create a strong password.
      <!-- The main difference between a password and a
      passphrase is that spaces are valid characters in a passphrase. -->
      <!-- I see no real proof for this: Some people argue that
      spaces are bad because of badly written scripts, but well-written
      software should generally be fine. Some people say that they have been
      using spaces in their Linux passwords forever and never had a problem.
      Some people argue it is bad for security, as spaces are the single most
      common character in naturally occurring text. - sknorr, 2015-09-21 -->
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="cha.gnome.crypto.gen_key.ssh">
   <title>Creating Secure Shell Keys</title>
   <para>
    Secure Shell (SSH) is a method of logging in to a remote computer to
    execute commands on that machine. SSH keys are used in key-based
    authentication system as an alternative to the default password
    authentication system. With key-based authentication, there is no need
    to manually type a password to authenticate.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu> <guimenu>Passwords and Keys</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>New</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select <guimenu>Secure Shell Key</guimenu>, then click
      <guimenu>Continue</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Specify a description of what the key is to be used for.
     </para>
     <para>
      You can use your e-mail address or any other reminder.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Optionally, click <guimenu>Advanced key options</guimenu> to specify
      the following advanced options for the key.
     </para>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Encryption Type</title>
      <para>
       Specifies the encryption algorithms used to generate your keys.
       Select <guimenu>RSA</guimenu> to use the Rivest-Shamir-Adleman (RSA)
       algorithm to create the SSH key. This is the preferred and more
       secure choice. Select <guimenu>DSA</guimenu> to use the Digital
       Signature Algorithm (DSA) to create the SSH key.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Key Strength</title>
      <para>
       Specifies the length of the key in bits. The longer the key, the more
       secure it is (provided a strong passphrase is used), but keep in mind
       that performing any operation with a longer key requires more time
       than it does with a shorter key. Acceptable values are between 1024
       and 4096 bits. At least 2048 bits is recommended.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Just Create Key</guimenu> to create the new key, or
      click <guimenu>Create and Set Up</guimenu> to create the key and set
      up another computer to use for authentication.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Specify the passphrase for your new key, click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>,
      then repeat.
     </para>
     <para>
      When you specify a passphrase, use the same practices you use when you
      create a strong password.
      <!-- The main difference between a password and a
      passphrase is that spaces are valid characters in a passphrase. -->
      <!-- I see no real proof for this: Some people argue that
      spaces are bad because of badly written scripts, but well-written
      software should generally be fine. Some people say that they have been
      using spaces in their Linux passwords forever and never had a problem.
      Some people argue it is bad for security, as spaces are the single most
      common character in naturally occurring text. - sknorr, 2015-09-21 -->
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="cha.gnome.crypto.modify_key">
  <title>Modifying Key Properties</title>

  <para>
   You can modify properties of existing OpenPGP or SSH keys.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="cha.gnome.crypto.modify_key.openpgp">
   <title>Editing OpenPGP Key Properties</title>
   <para>
    The descriptions in this section apply to all OpenPGP keys.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu> <guimenu>Passwords and Keys</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Double-click the PGP key you want to view or edit.
<!--(or select the key,
      then click <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> in toolbar).-->
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use the options on the <guimenu>Owner</guimenu> tab to add a photo to
      the key or to change the passphrase associated with the key.
     </para>
     <para>
      Photo IDs allow a key owner to embed one or more pictures of
      themselves in a key. These identities can be signed like normal user
      IDs. A photo ID must be in JPEG format. The recommended size is
      120×150 pixels.
     </para>
     <para>
      If the chosen image does not meet the required file type or size,
      Passwords and Keys can resize and convert it on the fly
      from any image format supported by the GDK library.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>Names and Signatures</guimenu> tab to add a user ID
      to a key.
     </para>
     <para>
      See
      <xref linkend="cha.gnome.crypto.modify_key.openpgp.add_user" xrefstyle="HeadingOnPage"/>
      for more information.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>Details</guimenu> tab, which contains the following
      properties:
     </para>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Key ID:</title>
      <para>
       The Key ID is similar to the Fingerprint, but the Key ID contains
       only the last eight characters of the fingerprint. It is generally
       possible to identify a key with only the Key ID, but sometimes two
       keys might have the same Key ID.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Type:</title>
      <para>
       Specifies the encryption algorithm used to generate a key. DSA keys
       can only sign. ElGamal keys are used to encrypt.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Strength:</title>
      <para>
       Specifies the length, in bits, of the key. The longer the key, the
       more security it provides. However, a long key will not compensate
       for the use of a weak passphrase.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Fingerprint:</title>
      <para>
       A unique string of characters that exactly identifies a key.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Created:</title>
      <para>
       The date the key was created.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Expires:</title>
      <para>
       The date the key can no longer be used (a key can no longer be used
       to perform key operations after it has expired). Changing a key's
       expiration date to a point in the future re-enables it. A good
       general practice is to have a master key that never expires and
       multiple subkeys that do expire and are signed by the master key.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Override Owner Trust:</title>
      <para>
       Here you can set the level of trust in the owner of the key. Trust is
       an indication of how sure you are of a person's ability to correctly
       extend the Web of trust. When you are faced with a key you have not
       signed, the validity of that person's key will be determined based on
       the signatures they have collected and how well or not you trust the
       people who have made those signatures.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Export Complete Key:</title>
      <para>
       Exports the key to a file.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Subkeys:</title>
      <para>
       See
       <xref linkend="cha.gnome.crypto.modify_key.openpgp.edit_subkey" xrefstyle="HeadingOnPage"/>
       for more information.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <informalfigure pgwide="0">
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="seahorse_editpgpkey.png" width="56%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="seahorse_editpgpkey.png" width="56%" format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Close</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <sect3 xml:id="cha.gnome.crypto.modify_key.openpgp.add_user">
    <title>Adding a User ID</title>
    <para>
     User IDs allow multiple identities and e-mail addresses to be used with
     the same key. Adding a user ID is useful, for example, when you want to
     have an identity for your job and one for your friends. They take the
     following form:
    </para>
<screen>Name (<replaceable>comment</replaceable>) &lt;<replaceable>e-mail address</replaceable>&gt;</screen>
    <procedure>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu><guimenu>Passwords and
       Keys</guimenu></menuchoice>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Double-click the PGP key you want to view or edit.
<!--(or select the key,
       then click <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> in the toolbar).-->
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click the <guimenu>Names and Signatures</guimenu> tab, then click
       <guimenu>Add Name</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Specify a name in the <guimenu>Full Name</guimenu> field.
      </para>
      <para>
       You must enter at least five characters in this field.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Specify an e-mail address in the <guimenu>E-Mail Address</guimenu>
       field.
      </para>
      <para>
       Your e-mail address is how most people will locate your key on a key
       server or other key provider. Make sure it is correct before
       continuing.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       In the <guimenu>Key Comment</guimenu> field, specify additional
       information that will display in the name of your new ID.
      </para>
      <para>
       This information can be searched for on key servers.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>Close</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="cha.gnome.crypto.modify_key.openpgp.edit_subkey">
    <title>Editing OpenPGP Subkey Properties</title>
    <para>
     Each OpenPGP key has a single master key used to sign only. Subkeys are
     used to encrypt and to sign as well. In this way, if your subkey is
     compromised, you do not need to revoke your master key.
    </para>
    <procedure>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu> <guimenu>Passwords and Keys</guimenu>
       </menuchoice>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Double-click the PGP key you want to edit.
<!--(or select the key, then
       click <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> in the toolbar).-->
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click the <guimenu>Details</guimenu> tab, then click
       <guimenu>Subkeys</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Use the button to on the left of the dialog to add, delete, expire,
       or revoke subkeys.
      </para>
      <informalfigure pgwide="0">
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
         <imagedata fileref="seahorse_subkeys.png" width="53%" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
         <imagedata fileref="seahorse_subkeys.png" width="53%" format="png"/>
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      <para>
       Each subkey has the following information:
      </para>
      <formalpara>
       <title>ID:</title>
       <para>
        The identifier of the subkey.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Type:</title>
       <para>
        Specifies the encryption algorithm used to generate a subkey. DSA
        keys can only sign, ElGamal keys are used to encrypt, and RSA keys
        are used to sign or to encrypt.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Created:</title>
       <para>
        Specifies the date the key was created.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Expires:</title>
       <para>
        Specifies the date the key can no longer be used.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Status:</title>
       <para>
        Specifies the status of the key.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Strength:</title>
       <para>
        Specifies the length, in bits, of the key. The longer the key, the
        more security it provides. However, a long key will not compensate
        for the use of a weak passphrase.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>Close</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="cha.gnome.crypto.modify_key.ssh">
   <title>Editing Secure Shell Key Properties</title>
   <para>
    The descriptions in this section apply to all SSH keys.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu> <guimenu>Passwords and Keys</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Double-click the Secure Shell key you want to view or edit.
<!--(or select
      the key, then click <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> in the toolbar).-->
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use the options on the <guimenu>Key</guimenu> tab to change the name
      of the key or the passphrase associated with the key.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>Details</guimenu> tab, which contains the following
      properties:
     </para>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Algorithm:</title>
      <para>
       Specifies the encryption algorithm used to generate a key.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Strength:</title>
      <para>
       Indicates the length in bits of a key. The longer the key, the more
       security it provides. However, a long key does not make up for the
       use of a weak passphrase.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Location:</title>
      <para>
       The location where the private key has been stored.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Fingerprint:</title>
      <para>
       A unique string of characters that exactly identifies a key.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Export Complete Key:</title>
      <para>
       Exports the key to a file.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <informalfigure pgwide="0">
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="seahorse_editsshkey.png" width="56%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="seahorse_editsshkey.png" width="56%" format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Close</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="cha.gnome.crypto.import_key">
  <title>Importing Keys</title>

  <para>
   Keys can be exported to text files.
   These files contain human-readable text at the beginning and at the end
   of a key.
   This format is called an ASCII-armored key.
  </para>

  <para>
   To import keys:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu> <guimenu>Passwords and Keys</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Import</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select a file containing at least one ASCII-armored public key.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Open</guimenu> to import the key.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   You can also paste keys inside Passwords and Keys:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select an ASCII-armored public block of text, then copy it to the
     clipboard.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu> <guimenu>Passwords and Keys</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> <guimenu>Paste</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="cha.gnome.crypto.export_key">
  <title>Exporting Keys</title>

  <para>
   To export keys:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu> <guimenu>Passwords and Keys</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the keys you want to export.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Export</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Specify a file name and location for the exported key.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Save</guimenu> to export the key.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   You can also export keys to the clipboard in an ASCII-armored block of
   text:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu> <guimenu>Passwords and Keys</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the keys you want to export.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> <guimenu>Copy</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="cha.gnome.crypto.sign_key">
  <title>Signing a Key</title>

  <para>
   Signing another person's key means that you are giving trust to that
   person. Before signing a key, carefully check the key's fingerprint to
   ensure that the key really belongs to that person.
  </para>

  <para>
   Trust is an indication of how sure you are of a person's ability to
   correctly extend the Web of trust. When you are faced with a key you have
   not signed, the validity of that person's key will be determined based on
   the signatures they have collected and how much you trust the
   people who have made those signatures. By default, an unknown key will
   require three signatures with marginal trust value or one fully trusted
   signature.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu> <guimenu>Passwords and Keys</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the key you want to sign from the <guimenu>My Personal
     Keys</guimenu> or <guimenu>Other Keys</guimenu> tabs.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Sign</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select how carefully the key has been checked, then indicate if the
     signature should be local to your keyring, and if your signature can be
     revoked
    </para>
    <informalfigure pgwide="0">
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="seahorse_signkey.png" width="55%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="seahorse_signkey.png" width="55%" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Sign</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 os="osuse" id="cha.gnome.crypto.nautilus">
  <title>File Manager Integration</title>
  <!-- Required package nautilus-extension-seahorse is not present on SLE
       - sknorr, 2015-09-21 -->

  <para>
   Passwords and Keys integrates with &nautilus;.
   You can encrypt, decrypt, sign, and verify files, as well as import
   public keys from the file manager window without launching Passwords and
   Keys.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>Enabling File Manager Integration</title>
   <para>
    The package <systemitem>nautilus-extension-seahorse</systemitem> has to be
    installed to enable file manager integration.
   </para>
  </note>

  <sect2 id="cha.gnome.crypto.nautilus.encrypt">
   <title>Encrypting Files From &nautilus;</title>
   <procedure>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      In &nautilus;, right-click the files you want to encrypt.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select <guimenu>Encrypt</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select the people (recipients) you want to encrypt the file to, then
      click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      If prompted, specify the passphrase of your private key, then click
      <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="cha.gnome.crypto.nautilus.sign">
   <title>Signing Files From &nautilus;</title>
   <procedure>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      In &nautilus;, right-click the files you want to sign.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select <guimenu>Sign</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      Select a signer, then click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step performance="required">
     <para>
      If prompted, specify the passphrase of your private key, then click
      <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="cha.gnome.crypto.nautilus.decrypt">
   <title>Decrypting Files From &nautilus;</title>
   <para>
    To decrypt an encrypted file in &nautilus;, simply double-click the file
    you want to decrypt.
   </para>
   <para>
    If prompted, specify the passphrase of your private key.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="cha.gnome.crypto.nautilus.verify">
   <title>Verifying Signatures From &nautilus;</title>
   <para>
    To verify files, simply double-click the detached signature file.
    Detached signature file names often have a <filename>.sig</filename>
    extension.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="cha.gnome.crypto.prefs.keyrings">
  <title>Password Keyrings</title>

  <para>
   You can use password keyring preferences to create or remove keyrings, to
   set the default keyring for application passwords or to change the unlock
   password of a keyring. To create a new keyring, follow these steps:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu> <guimenu>Passwords and Keys</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>New</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Password Keyring</guimenu> </menuchoice>, then click
     <guimenu>Continue</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter a new name for the keyring and click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Set and confirm a new <guimenu>Password</guimenu> for the keyring and
     click <guimenu>Create</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   To change the unlock password of an existing keyring, click the keyring
   in the <guimenu>Passwords</guimenu> tab and click <guimenu>Change
   Password</guimenu>. You need to provide the old password to be able to
   change it.
  </para>

  <para>
   To change the default keyring for application passwords, click the
   keyring in the <guimenu>Passwords</guimenu> tab and click <guimenu>Set as
   Default</guimenu>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="cha.gnome.crypto.prefs.servers">
  <title>Key Servers</title>

  <para>
   You can keep your keys up-to-date by synchronizing keys periodically with
   remote keyservers. Synchronizing will ensure that you have the latest
   signatures made on all of your keys, so that the Web of trust will be
   effective.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu> <guimenu>Passwords and Keys</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu> </menuchoice>, then click the
     <guimenu>Key Servers</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
    <informalfigure pgwide="0">
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="seahorse_keyservers.png" width="66%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="seahorse_keyservers.png" width="66%" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
     Passwords and Keys provides support for HKP and LDAP
     keyservers.
    </para>
    <formalpara>
     <title>HKP Key Servers:</title>
     <para>
      HKP key servers are ordinary Web-based key servers, such as the popular
      <literal>hkp://pgp.mit.edu:11371</literal>, also accessible at
      <link xlink:href="http://pgp.mit.edu">http://pgp.mit.edu</link>.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
     <title>LDAP Key Servers:</title>
     <para>
      LDAP key servers are less common, but use the standard LDAP protocol to
      serve keys. ldap://keyserver.pgp.com is a good LDAP server.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
    <para>
     You can <guimenu>Add</guimenu> or <guimenu>Remove</guimenu> key servers
     to be used using the buttons on the left. To add a new key server, set
     its type, host and port, if necessary.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Set whether you want to automatically publish your public keys and
     which keyserver to use. Set whether you want to automatically retrieve
     keys from key servers and whether to synchronize modified keys with
     keyservers.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Close</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="cha.gnome.crypto.prefs.sharing">
  <title>Key Sharing</title>

  <para>
   Key Sharing is provided by DNS-SD, also known as Bonjour or Rendezvous.
   Enabling key sharing adds the local Passwords and Keys users'
   public key rings to the remote search dialog. Using these local key
   servers is generally faster than accessing remote servers.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Utilities</guimenu> <guimenu>Passwords and Keys</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu> </menuchoice>, then click the
     <guimenu>Key Servers</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Automatically synchronize modified keys with key
     servers</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Close</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
