<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 version="5.0"
 xml:id="cha-gnome-accessibility">
 <title>Assistive technologies</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    The &gnome; desktop provides built-in assistive technologies to support users with
    disabilities and facilitate interaction with common assistive devices. This chapter describes several assistive technology
    applications designed to meet the needs of users with physical disabilities
    like low vision or impaired motor skills.
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-general-accessibility-enable">
  <title>Enabling assistive technologies</title>

  <para>
   To configure accessibility features, open the <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>
   dialog by right-clicking the desktop and choosing
   <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>. In the navigation pane, select
   <guimenu>Accessibility</guimenu>. Each assistive feature can be enabled
   separately.
  </para>

  <para>
   To directly access individual assistive features, enable the
   <guimenu>Accessibility Menu</guimenu>. This will display an icon resembling a person in the top bar, providing quick
   access to accessibility settings.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-general-accessibility-visual">
  <title>Visual assistance</title>

  <para>
   In the <guimenu>Seeing</guimenu> section of the
   <guimenu>Accessibility</guimenu> settings, you can enable features that
   help people with impaired vision.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Turning on <guimenu>High Contrast</guimenu> increases color contrast
     of foreground and background interface elements.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Turning on <guimenu>Reduce Animation</guimenu> reduces animations in the user interface to reduce motion.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Turning on <guimenu>Large Text</guimenu> increases the size of all text in the user interface.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     By customizing the <guimenu>Cursor Size</guimenu>, you can make it easier to see the mouse pointer.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If the <guimenu>Sound Keys</guimenu> are turned on, a beep will sound when 
     <keycap>Num Lock</keycap> or <keycap>Caps Lock</keycap> are turned on or off.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The <guimenu>Overlay Scrollbars</guimenu> option uses scrollbars that overlay 
     the content and automatically hide.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If the <guimenu>Screen Reader</guimenu> is turned on, the screen reader reads 
     displayed text as you move the focus.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-general-accessibility-hearing">
  <title>Hearing assistance</title>

  <para>
   In the <guimenu>Hearing</guimenu> section of the
   <guimenu>Accessibility</guimenu> dialog, you can enable features helping
   people with impaired hearing.
  </para>

  <para>
   If the <guimenu>Visual Alerts</guimenu> are turned on, a window title or the
   entire screen is flashed when an alert sound occurs for the respective
   application.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-general-accessibility-mobility">
  <title>Keyboard and mouse</title>

  <para>
   In the <guimenu>Typing</guimenu> and <guimenu>Pointing and
   Clicking</guimenu> sections of the <guimenu>Accessibility</guimenu>
   dialog, you can enable features that help people with mobility
   impairments.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Typing</guimenu> section, when <guimenu>Screen Keyboard</guimenu> 
     is turned on, an on-screen keyboard appears at the bottom of the screen when you next have the
     opportunity to type.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>On-screen keyboard</title>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="gnome_onscreen_kbd.png" width="100%"
        />
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="gnome_onscreen_kbd.png" width="80%"
        />
       </imageobject>
       <textobject role="description">
         <phrase>Screen keyboard showing on-screen typing with numbers, symbols and layout controls</phrase>
       </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </figure>

    <para>To enter numbers and symbols,
     press the <guimenu>?123</guimenu> button first. More symbols are available
     if you press the <guimenu>=/&lt;</guimenu> button. To return to the
     alphabetic keyboard, press the <guimenu>ABC</guimenu> button.
    </para>
    <para>To temporarily hide the keyboard, press the button with the arrow
     down icon. The keyboard is shown again automatically in the next
     situation where you can use it. To change your keyboard layout or change
     <guimenu>Region &amp; Language</guimenu> settings, press the button
     with the flag icon.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Enable by Keyboard</guimenu> allows you to turn accessibility 
     features on or off using keyboard shortcuts.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Under <guimenu>Cursor Blinking</guimenu>, you can configure if and at which
     speed the cursor blinks in text boxes (for example, in a terminal).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Blink Speed</guimenu> is an adjustable slider to set how quickly 
     the cursor blinks, ranging from Slow to Fast.
    </para>
    </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Test Entry</guimenu> is a field where you can test cursor behavior.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Repeat Keys</guimenu> lets you configure if and when a key is
       repeated when it is pressed for a longer time. You can either turn this
       feature <guimenu>Off</guimenu> or configure a <guimenu>Delay</guimenu> and
       the <guimenu>Speed</guimenu> by which keys are repeated.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Sticky Keys</guimenu> allows you to type key combinations one
       key at a time rather than having to hold down all keys at once.
       For example, the <keycombo>
       <keycap function="alt"/><keycap function="tab"/></keycombo> shortcut
       switches between windows.
      </para>
      <para>
       With sticky keys turned off, you need to hold down both keys at the same
       time. With sticky keys turned on, press <keycap function="alt"/> and
       then <keycap function="tab"/> to do the same.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Turn on <guimenu>Slow Keys</guimenu> if you want a delay between
       pressing a key and the letter being displayed on the screen. This means
       that you need to hold down each key you want to type for a little while
       before it appears. Use slow keys if you accidentally press several keys
       at a time when you type, or if you find it difficult to press the right
       key on the keyboard first time.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Turn on <guimenu>Bounce Keys</guimenu> to ignore key presses that are
       rapidly repeated. This can help, for example, if you have hand tremors
       which cause you to press a key multiple times when you only want to
       press it once.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
    <para>
    The <guimenu>Pointing &amp; Clicking</guimenu> section includes:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
         <guimenu>Mouse Keys</guimenu>: When enabled, it allows users to control the 
         mouse pointer using the numeric keypad on the keyboard.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <guimenu>Locate Pointer</guimenu>: When enabled, it reveals the pointer 
         location by pressing left <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <guimenu>Double-Click Delay</guimenu> is a slider adjustment that lets 
         users set how quickly they need to click twice for a double-click to 
         register, ranging from Short to Long.
        </para>
       </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
        In the <guimenu>Click Assist</guimenu> section, you can enable 
        <guimenu>Simulated Secondary Click</guimenu> to activate the
       secondary click (usually the right mouse button) by holding down the
       primary button. This is useful if you find it difficult to move your fingers
       individually on one hand, or if your pointing device only has a single
       button.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Turn on <guimenu>Hover Click</guimenu> to trigger a click by hovering
       your mouse pointer over an object on the screen. This is useful if you
       find it difficult to move the mouse and click at the same time. If this
       feature is turned on, a small hover click window opens and stays above
       all your other windows. You can use this to choose what sort of click
       should happen when you hover. When you hover your mouse pointer over a
       button and do not move it, the pointer gradually changes color. When it
       has fully changed color, the button will be clicked.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-general-accessibility-zoom">
  <title>Zoom</title>
  <para>
   In the <guimenu>Zoom</guimenu> section of the
   <guimenu>Accessibility</guimenu> dialog, you can enable features 
   that help people with visual impairments.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <guimenu>Desktop Zoom</guimenu> allows you to magnify the entire screen.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The <guimenu>Magnifier</guimenu> section offers detailed configuration options, including <guimenu>Magnifier View</guimenu>,
      <guimenu>Screen Area</guimenu> and <guimenu>Follow Behavior</guimenu>.
     </para>
     </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The <guimenu>Crosshairs</guimenu> section includes options like <guimenu>Overlap Mouse Cursor</guimenu>,
      <guimenu>Thickness</guimenu> and <guimenu>Length</guimenu> sliders and <guimenu>Color</guimenu>.     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <guimenu>Color Filters</guimenu> offers the <guimenu>Inverted</guimenu> option to 
      invert colors in the magnifier region, and <guimenu>Brightness</guimenu>, 
      <guimenu>Contrast</guimenu> and <guimenu>Color</guimenu> options to adjust color effects. 
     </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
