<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
  ]>
<chapter id="cha.gnomeuser.start">
 <title>Getting Started with the GNOME Desktop</title>
 <para>
  This section describes the conventions, layout, and common tasks of the
  GNOME desktop as implemented in your product.
 </para>
 <para>
  GNOME is an easy-to-use graphical interface that can be customized to meet
  your needs and personal preferences. This section describes the default
  configuration of GNOME. If you or your system administrator modifies the
  defaults, some aspect might be different, such as appearance or keyboard
  shortcuts.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.login">
  <title>Getting Started</title>
  <para>
   If more than one user account is configured on your computer, generally
   all users must authenticate&mdash;unless <guimenu>Auto Login</guimenu> is
   enabled for a specific user. Auto login lets a user automatically log in
   to the desktop environment when the system starts. This feature can be
   enabled or disabled during installation or at any time using the &yast;
   User and Group Management module. For more information, refer to
   <xref linkend="cha.y2.userman"/>. If your computer is running in a
   network environment and you are not the only person using the machine,
   you are usually prompted to enter your username and password when you
   start the system.<phrase os="sled"> If you did not set up the system and
   user account yourself, check with your system administrator for your
   username and password.</phrase>
  </para>
  <para>
   The GNOME desktop appears after you first log in. The GNOME desktop
   appears with a panel at the bottom with following elements:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <!--   <varlistentry>
    <term>Bottom Panel</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The desktop includes a panel at the bottom of the screen. All
      applications currently open on the desktop appear here. You can access
      these applications by clicking on their name.
     <para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>-->
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Applications menu</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Click on <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> in the left corner to open a menu
      with all the installed programs. These are classified under different
      categories for a better overview. Sub-items open automatically as soon
      as you place the mouse above them.
     </para>
     <para><!--just a link?-->
      Clicking on <guimenu>Activities Overview</guimenu> in the bottom part
      of the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu takes you to the so-called
      ctivities overview where you start programs and manage those already
      running. You also reach this view by placing the mouse pointer in the
      top left corner of the screen or pressing the <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
      key (also called the <guimenu>Super</guimenu> key). You return to the
      normal view by clicking on <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> or pressing
      the <guimenu>Escape</guimenu> key.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Places menu</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Click on <guimenu>Places</guimenu> more to the right to open a menu
      containing important folders (such as your personal folder or the
      Download folder), show content of connected data carriers and establish
      a connection to another computer (connection to server).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>The middle part of the panel</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      All applications currently open on the desktop (on the active
      workspace) appear in the middle part of the panel. You can access
      these applications by clicking on their name.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Workspace menu</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The first menu on the right lets you choose a workspace
      (a virtual desktop) to work on.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Date and time</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The current date and time is shown to the right from the workspace
      menu. By clicking on it, open a menu where you can access a calendar
      and adust the date and time settings.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Status icons</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      In the right corner of the panel, icons showing the current status
      of the network connection, sound volume and power (battery) status
      are displayed.
     </para>
     <para>
      By clicking on them, you open a menu where you can
      adjust the sound volume, the display brightness, the network
      connection, and the power settings. There is also the name of the
      current user. Click on the name to display the options for logging
      our or for switching to another user.
     </para>
     <para>
      The three icons in the lower part of the menu allow you to,
      from left to right, open the GNOME settings dialog, lock the
      screen, and power off or restart your computer.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <sect2>
   <title>Activities Overview</title>
   <para>
    Activities overview is a special mode which dedicates a full screen to all
    the different ways in which the user can switch from doing one thing (an
    activity) to doing something else. It shows previews of all the windows
    the user has open and the user's favorite and running applications. It
    also integrates search and browse functionality.
   </para>
   <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Activities Overview</title>
    <para>
     There are three ways to activate the acttivities overview:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Open the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu on the bottom panel
       and choose <guimenu>Activities Overview</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Place the mouse pointer in the top left corner of the screen.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Press the <guimenu>Windows</guimenu> key (also called the
       <guimenu>Super</guimenu> key).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Starting Programs</title>
   <para>
    To start a program, you have several options:
   </para>
   <para>
    First you can just click on <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> in the bottom
    panel and choose the desired program from the hierarchical menu.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you know the exact command to start the program, you can press
    <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>,
    enter the command into the dialog and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can also start the program using the activities view. You can reach
    this view by placing the mouse pointer in the top left corner of the
    screen or pressing the <guimenu>Windows</guimenu> key (also called the
    <guimenu>Super</guimenu> key). Now you have two options. Either click on
    the program icon in the bar on the left edge of the screen, or enter
    a term into the search box in the upper part of the activities view.
    You can use the name of the desired program or try any meaningful
    keywords, such as <literal>image</literal> or <literal>photo</literal>
    in the case you need an image editor.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Managing Windows</title>
   <para></para>
   <!--FIXME-->
  </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
  <title>Logging In and Selecting a Desktop</title>

  <para>
   If more than one user account is configured on your computer, generally
   all users must authenticate&mdash;unless <guimenu>Auto Login</guimenu> is
   enabled for a specific user. Auto login lets a user automatically log in
   to the desktop environment when the system starts. This feature can be
   enabled or disabled during installation or at any time using the &yast;
   User and Group Management module. For more information, refer to
   <xref linkend="cha.y2.userman"/>. If your computer is running in a
   network environment and you are not the only person using the machine,
   you are usually prompted to enter your username and password when you
   start the system.<phrase os="sled"> If you did not set up the system and
   user account yourself, check with your system administrator for your
   username and password.</phrase>
  </para>

  <para>
   The program managing the login process is specific to the desktop
   environment installed on your system. For GNOME, it is GDM.
  </para>

  <para>
   In the login window of the GDM you can <guimenu>Suspend</guimenu>,
   <guimenu>Restart</guimenu> or <guimenu>Shut Down</guimenu> your machine.
   Enter a username and a password each followed by
   <keycap function="enter"/> to log in to the system. The login screen
   offers several login options. For example, you can select the language of
   your session so that text that appears in the interface is presented in
   that language. To change the desktop defaults prior to logging in, use
   the menus in the panel.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Language Menu</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Select a language for your session.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Keyboard Menu</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Select a keyboard layout for your session.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Session Menu</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Select the desktop to run during your session. If other desktops are
      installed, they appear in the list.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Domain Menu</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you authenticate against an Active Directory server, choose the
      Windows* Domain to which you want to log in. For all other
      authentication methods, choose <guimenu>Local Login</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Display Settings Menu</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Change display settings such as resolution and refresh rate here.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Access Preferences</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Configure the use of assistive technologies using this menu. For
      details please refer to <xref linkend="cha.gnome.accessibility"/> .
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.login.session">
   <title>Session Management</title>
   <para>
    A <emphasis>session</emphasis> is the period of time that you are
    actively logged in. During a session, you can use applications, print,
    browse the Web and so on.
   </para>
   <para>
    After your username and password are authenticated, the Session Manager
    starts. The Session Manager lets you save certain settings from each
    session. It also lets you save the state of your most recent session and
    return to that session the next time you log in.
   </para>
   <para>
    The Session Manager can save and restore the following settings:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Appearance and behavior settings, such as fonts, colors, and mouse
      settings.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Applications that you were running. such as a file manager or an &ooo;
      program.
     </para>
     <tip>
      <para>
       You cannot save and restore applications that Session Manager does
       not manage. For example, if you start the Vi editor from the command
       line in a terminal window, Session Manager cannot restore your
       editing session.
      </para>
     </tip>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.login.switch">
   <title>Switching the Desktop Environment</title>
   <para>
    If you have installed other desktop environments beside GNOME, use the
    following instructions to switch the desktop environment.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Computer</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Logout</guimenu> <guimenu>Log Out</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose a desktop from the <guimenu>Session</guimenu> menu.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Type your username, then press <keycap function="enter"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Type your password, then press <keycap function="enter"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.login.lock">
   <title>Locking Your Screen</title>
   <para>
    To lock the screen, you can do either of the following:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Computer</guimenu> <guimenu>Lock
      Screen</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If the <guimenu>Lock</guimenu> button is present on a panel, click it.
     </para>
     <para>
      To add the <guimenu>Lock</guimenu> button to a panel, right-click the
      panel, then click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Add to Panel</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Lock Screen</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    When you lock your screen, a screen saver starts, locking the screen. To
    unlock the screen, move your mouse or press a key to display the locked
    screen dialog. Enter your password, then press
    <keycap function="enter"/> to unlock the screen.
   </para>
   <para>
    For information on configuring your screen saver see
    <xref linkend="sec.gnome.settings.look.ssaver"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.logout">
  <title>Logging Out</title>

  <para>
   When you are finished using the computer, you can log out (leaving the
   system running), restart or shut down the computer. If your system
   provides power management you can also suspend your computer, making the
   next session start much faster than with a complete reboot.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.logout.logout">
   <title>Logging Out or Switching Users</title>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Computer</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Logout</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select one of the following options:
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Log Out</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Logs you out of the current session and returns you to the Login
         screen.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Switch User</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Suspends your session, allowing another user to log in and use the
         computer.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.logout.restart">
   <title>Restarting or Shutting Down the Computer</title>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Computer</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Shutdown</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select one of the following options:
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Shutdown</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Logs you out of the current session, then turns off the computer.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Restart</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Logs you out of the current session, then restarts the computer.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Suspend</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Puts your computer in a temporary state that conserves minimal
         power (<quote>Suspend to RAM</quote>). The state of your session is
         preserved, however, including all applications you have running and
         all documents you have open.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Hibernate</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Suspends your session, using no power until the computer is
         restarted (<quote>Suspend to Disk</quote>). The state of your
         session is preserved, however, including all applications you have
         running and all documents you have open.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.basics">
  <title>Desktop Basics</title>

  <para>
   As with other common desktop products, the main components of the GNOME
   desktop are icons that link to files, folders, or programs, as well as
   the panel at the bottom of the screen (similar to the Task Bar in
   Windows). Double-click an icon to start its associated program.
   Right-click an icon to access additional menus and options. You can also
   right-click any empty space on the desktop to access additional menus for
   configuring or managing the desktop itself.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>GNOME Desktop</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="gnome_desktop.png" format="PNG" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="gnome_desktop.png" format="png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   By default, the desktop features two key icons: your personal Home folder
   and a trash can for deleted items. Other icons may also be present on the
   desktop, such as icons representing devices on your computer. If you
   double-click your Home folder, the Nautilus file manager starts and
   displays the contents of your home directory (where your personal files
   and configurations are stored). For more information about using
   Nautilus, see <xref linkend="sec.gnomeuser.start.nautilus"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Right-clicking an icon displays a menu that offers file operations such
   as copying, cutting or renaming. Selecting <guimenu>Properties</guimenu>
   from the menu displays a configuration dialog. On the
   <guimenu>Basic</guimenu> tab, you can change the name of the icon as well
   as the icon itself (by clicking on it and selecting a file with a
   different one). Various information about the object represented by the
   icon is also shown here. The <guimenu>Emblems</guimenu> tab lets you add
   up to four graphically descriptive symbols to the icon. The
   <guimenu>Permissions</guimenu> tab lets you set access permissions for
   the selected files. The <guimenu>Notes</guimenu> tab lets you manage
   comments. The menu for the trash can also features the <guimenu>Empty
   Trash</guimenu> option, which deletes its contents. Icons representing
   folders also feature the <guimenu>Share</guimenu> tab which lets you
   share that folder with other users. Learn more about this in
   <xref linkend="sec.gnome.network.smbshare"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   A link is a special type of file that points to another file or folder.
   When you perform an action on a link, the action is performed on the file
   or folder to which the link points. However, when you delete a link, you
   delete only the link file and not the file that the link is referencing.
  </para>

  <para>
   To create a desktop link to a folder or a file, access the object in
   <link linkend="sec.gnomeuser.start.nautilus">File Manager</link> by
   right-clicking the object and then clicking <guimenu>Make Link</guimenu>.
   Drag the link from the File Manager window and drop it onto the desktop.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.basics.icons">
   <title>Default Desktop Icons</title>
   <para>
    To remove an icon from the desktop, simply drag it onto the trash can.
    The Home icon cannot be removed.
   </para>
   <warning>
    <para>
     Be careful with this option - if you move folder or file icons to the
     trash can and you empty the trash can, the actual data is deleted. If
     the icons only represent links to a file or to a directory, only the
     links are deleted.
    </para>
   </warning>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.basics.desktopmenu">
   <title>Desktop Menu</title>
   <para>
    Right-clicking an empty spot on the desktop displays a menu with various
    options. Click <guimenu>Create Folder</guimenu> to create a new folder.
    Create a launcher icon for an application with <guimenu>Create
    Launcher</guimenu>. Provide the name of the application and the command
    for starting it, then select an icon to represent it. To create a new
    document from a template click <guimenu>Create Doucument</guimenu>.
    Align the desktop icons by name with <guimenu>Clean Up by
    Name</guimenu>. With <guimenu>Keep Aligned</guimenu> checked, icons are
    always arranged in a grid. You can also change the desktop background
    with this menu or open a terminal window.
   </para>
   <figure>
    <title>GNOME Desktop Menu</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gnome_menu.png" format="PNG" width="28%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gnome_menu.png" format="png" width="28%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.basics.panel">
   <title>Bottom Panel</title>
   <para>
    The desktop includes a panel across the bottom of the screen. The bottom
    panel contains the <guimenu>main menu</guimenu> (similar to the Start
    menu in Windows*), the taskbar showing the icons of all applications
    currently running as well as easy access to applications and applets. If
    you click the name of a program in the taskbar, the program's window is
    moved to the foreground. If the program is already in the foreground, a
    mouse click minimizes it. Clicking a minimized application reopens the
    respective window to foreground status.
   </para>
   <figure>
    <title>GNOME Bottom Panel</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="bottompanel.png" format="PNG" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="bottompanel.png" format="png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    Access additional workspaces through virtual desktops. For example, you
    can open applications in different workspaces and use them on their own
    desktops without the clutter from other applications.
   </para>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>Show Desktop</guimenu> icon is on the right side of the
    bottom panel. This icon minimizes all program windows and displays the
    desktop. Or, if all windows are already minimized, it reopens them.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you right-click an empty spot in the panel, a menu opens, offering
    the options listed in the following:
   </para>
   <table rowsep="1">
    <title>Panel Menu Options</title>
    <tgroup cols="2">
     <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="28*"/>
     <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="72*"/>
     <thead>
      <row rowsep="1">
       <entry colname="1">
        <para>
         Option
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>
         Description
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row rowsep="1">
       <entry colname="1">
        <para>
         <guimenu>Add to Panel</guimenu>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>
         Opens a menu of applications and applets that can be added to the
         panel.
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row rowsep="1">
       <entry colname="1">
        <para>
         <guimenu>Properties</guimenu>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>
         Modifies the properties for selected panel. Using the
         <guimenu>Orientation</guimenu> property, you can move the panel to
         a different place of the screen.
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row rowsep="1">
       <entry colname="1">
        <para>
         <guimenu>Delete This Panel</guimenu>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>
         Removes the panel, along with all panel settings, from the desktop.
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row rowsep="1">
       <entry colname="1">
        <para>
         <guimenu>New Panel</guimenu>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>
         Creates a new panel and adds it to the desktop.
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row rowsep="1">
       <entry colname="1">
        <para>
         <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>
         Opens the Help Center.
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row rowsep="0">
       <entry colname="1">
        <para>
         <guimenu>About Panels</guimenu>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>
         Opens information window about the panel application.
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </table>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.basics.panel_add">
   <title>Adding Applets and Applications to the Panel</title>
   <para>
    You can add applications and applets to the bottom panel for quick
    access. An applet is a small program, while an application is usually a
    more robust stand-alone program. Adding applets puts useful tools where
    you can easily access them.
   </para>
   <para>
    The GNOME desktop comes with many applets. You can see a complete list
    by right-clicking the bottom panel and selecting <guimenu>Add to
    Panel</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <figure>
    <title>Add to Panel Dialog Box</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="add_to_panel.png" format="PNG" width="65%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="add_to_panel.png" format="png" width="65%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    Some useful applets include the following:
   </para>
   <table rowsep="0">
    <title>Some Useful Applets</title>
    <tgroup cols="2">
     <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="33*"/>
     <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="67*"/>
     <thead>
      <row rowsep="1">
       <entry colname="1">
        <para>
         Applet
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>
         Description
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row rowsep="0">
       <entry colname="1">
        <para>
         Dictionary Look up
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>
         Look up a word in an online dictionary.
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row rowsep="0">
       <entry colname="1">
        <para>
         Force Quit
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>
         Terminate an application. This is especially useful if you want to
         terminate an application that is no longer responding.
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row rowsep="0">
       <entry colname="1">
        <para>
         Search for Files
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>
         Find files, folders, and documents on the computer.
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row rowsep="0">
       <entry colname="1">
        <para>
         Sticky Notes
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>
         Create, display, and manage sticky notes on your desktop.
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row rowsep="0">
       <entry colname="1">
        <para>
         Traditional Main Menu
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>
         Access programs from a menu like the one in previous versions of
         GNOME. This is especially useful for people who are accustomed to
         earlier versions of GNOME.
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row rowsep="0">
       <entry colname="1">
        <para>
         Weather Report
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>
         Display current weather information for a specified city.
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </table>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
