<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
  ]>
<preface id="pre.gnome.about">
 <title>About This Guide</title>
 <para>
  This manual introduces you to the GNOME graphical desktop environment as
  implemented in &productnamereg;, and shows you how to configure it to meet
  your personal needs and preferences. It also introduces you to several
  programs and services. It is intended for users who have some experience
  using a graphical desktop environment such as Macintosh*, Windows*, or
  other Linux desktops.
 </para>
 <para>
  The manual is divided into two parts:
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Introduction</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Get to know your GNOME desktop and learn how to cope with basic and
     daily tasks using the central GNOME applications, as well as various
     small utilities. Get an overview of the possibilities that GNOME offers
     for modifying and individualizing the desktop according to your needs
     and wishes. Learn how to use assistive technologies to improve
     accessibility in case of vision or mobility impairment.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Connectivity, Files and Resources</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Find vital information concerning the management and exchange of data
     on your system: how to share files on the network and how to use an
     integrated collaboration environment, how to effectively search for
     data, and how to manage printers and back up your data.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>&libo;</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Introduces the &libo; suite, including Writer, Calc, Impress, Base,
     Draw, and Math.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Information Management</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Get to know the e-mailing and calendaring software provided by your
     product. Learn how to use protected information transfer by signing and
     encrypting your documents or mails.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Communication and Collaboration</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Stay in contact with others and communicate via network connections
     using Instant Messaging or Voice over IP.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Internet</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Search for information on the Web with browsers combining the latest
     browsing and security technologies. Make use of file transfer clients
     to transfer data from the Internet.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Graphics</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Get to know GIMP, an image manipulation program that meets the needs of
     both amateurs and professionals.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Multimedia</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Get introduced to your desktop's applications for playing
<!-- music and-->
     movies. Learn how to create data or audio CDs and DVDs for archiving
     your data.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <para>
  Many chapters in this manual contain links to additional documentation
  resources. These include additional documentation that is available on the
  system as well as documentation available on the Internet.
 </para>
 <para>
  For an overview of the documentation available for your product and the
  latest documentation updates, refer to
  <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/doc"/> or to the following section.
 </para>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  href="common_intro_available_doc_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  href="common_intro_feedback_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  href="common_intro_typografie_i.xml"/>
</preface>
