<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.gnome.network" lang="en">
 <title>Accessing Network Resources</title>
 <para>
  From your desktop, you can access files and directories or certain
  services on remote hosts or make your own files and directories available
  to other users in your network. &productnamereg; offers the following ways
  of accessing and creating network shared resources.
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Network Browsing</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Your file manager, Nautilus, lets you browse your network for shared
     resources and services. Learn more about this in
     <xref
      linkend="sec.gnome.network.accshare"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Sharing Folders in Mixed Environments</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Using Nautilus, configure your files and folders to share with other
     members of your network. Make your data readable or writable for users
     from any Windows or Linux workstation. Learn more about this in
     <xref linkend="sec.gnome.network.smbshare"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Managing Windows Files</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &productname; can be configured to integrate into an existing Windows
     network. Your Linux machine then behaves like a Windows client. It
     takes all account information from the Active Directory domain
     controller, just as the Windows clients do. Learn more about this in
     <xref linkend="sec.gnome.network.ad.data"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Configuring and Accessing a Windows Network Printer</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You can configure a Windows network printer through the GNOME Control
     Center. Learn how to configure this in
     <xref linkend="sec.gnome.network.ad.printer"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.network.connect">
  <title>Connecting to Your Network</title>

  <para>
   You can connect to a network with wired and wireless connections. To view
   your network connection status, click <guimenu>Computer</guimenu>. In the
   <guimenu>Status</guimenu> area of the main menu, the
   <guimenu>Network</guimenu> icon shows your network connection status.
   Click the icon to open the &yast; Network Settings module. You can use
   this module to configure your network setup method or to edit your
   network card configuration. Refer to <xref linkend="sec.basicnet.yast"/>
   for details.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.network.general">
  <title>General Notes on File Sharing and Network Browsing</title>

  <para>
   Whether and to which extent you can use file sharing and network browsing
   on your machine and in your network highly depends on the network
   structure and on the configuration of your machine. Before setting up
   either of them, contact your system administrator to make sure that your
   network structure supports this feature and to check whether your
   company's security policies permit it.
  </para>

  <para>
   Network browsing, be it SMB browsing for Windows shares or SLP browsing
   for remote services, relies heavily on the machine's ability to send
   broadcast messages to all clients in the network. These messages and the
   clients' replies to them enable your machine to detect any available
   shares or services. For broadcasts to work effectively, your machine must
   be part of the same subnet as all other machines it is querying. If
   network browsing does not work on your machine or the detected shares and
   services do not meet with your expectations, contact your system
   administrator to ensure that you are connected to the appropriate subnet.
  </para>

  <para>
   To allow network browsing, your machine needs to keep several network
   ports open to send and receive network messages that provide details on
   the network and the availability of shares and services. The standard
   &productname; is configured for tight security and has a firewall that
   protects your machine against the Internet. To adjust the firewall
   configuration, you would either need to ask your system administrator to
   put your interface into the internal zone or to tear down the firewall
   entirely (depending on your company's security policy). If you try to
   browse a network with a restrictive firewall running on your machine,
   Nautilus warns you that your security restrictions are not allowing it to
   query the network.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.network.accshare">
  <title>Accessing Network Shares</title>

  <para>
   Networking workstations can be set up to share folders. Typically, files
   and folders are marked to allow users remote access. These are called
   <emphasis>network shares</emphasis>. If your system is configured to
   access network shares, you can use your file manager to access these
   shares and browse them just as easily as if they were located on your
   local machine. Your level of access to the shared folders (whether
   read-only or write access, as well) is dependent on the permissions
   granted to you by the owner of the shares.
  </para>

  <para>
   To access network shares, open Nautilus and click
   <guimenu>Network</guimenu> from the <guimenu>Places</guimenu> pane.
   Nautilus displays the servers and networks that you can access.
   Double-click on a server or network to access its shares. You might be
   required to authenticate to the server by providing a username and
   password. Common network shares are SFTP accessible resources (SSH File
   Transfer Protocol) or Windows shares.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Network File Browser</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="network_browser.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="network_browser.png" width="70%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnomeuser.start.network.shares.add">
   <title>Adding a Network Place</title>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Computer</guimenu> <guimenu>Nautilus File
      Browser</guimenu> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Connect to
      Server</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
     <figure>
      <title>Connect to Server dialog box</title>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="connect_server_a.png" format="PNG" width="50%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="connect_server_a.png" format="png" width="50%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </figure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select a service type, then specify the required information for your
      type of service.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To bookmark the connection, check <guimenu>Add Bookmark</guimenu> and
      enter its name.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Connect</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.network.smbshare">
  <title>Sharing Folders</title>

  <para>
   Sharing and exchanging documents is a must-have in corporate
   environments. Nautilus offers you file sharing, which makes your files
   and folders available to both Linux and Windows users.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnome.network.sharingcomputer">
   <title>Enabling Sharing on the Computer</title>
   <para>
    Before you can share a folder, you must enable sharing on your computer.
    To enable sharing:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start &yast; from the main menu.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Enter the &rootuser; password.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Network Services</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Windows Domain Membership</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Allow Users to Share Their Directories</guimenu>, then
      click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.gnome.network.sharingfolder">
   <title>Enabling Sharing for a Folder</title>
   <para>
    To configure file sharing for a folder:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Open Nautilus.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Right-click a folder, then select <guimenu>Sharing Options</guimenu>
      from the context menu.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="folder_sharing_1_a.png" width="35%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="folder_sharing_1_a.png" width="35%" format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select <guimenu>Share this folder</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      If you want other people to be able to write to the folder, select
      <guimenu>Allow other people to write in this folder</guimenu>. To
      allow access for people without a user account check <guimenu>Guest
      Access</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Create Share</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      If the folder does not already have the permissions that are required
      for sharing, a dialog appears. Click <guimenu>Add the permissions
      automatically</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    The folder icon changes to indicate that the folder is now shared.
   </para>
   <important>
    <title>Samba Domain Browsing</title>
    <para>
     Samba domain browsing only works if your system's firewall is
     configured accordingly. Either disable the firewall entirely or assign
     the browsing interface to the internal firewall zone. Ask your system
     administrator about how to proceed.
    </para>
   </important>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.network.ad.data">
  <title>Managing Windows Files</title>

  <para>
   With your &productname; machine being an Active Directory client, you can
   browse, view and manipulate data located on Windows servers. The
   following examples are just the most prominent ones:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Browsing Windows Files with Nautilus</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use Nautilus' network browsing features to browse your Windows data.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Viewing Windows Data with Nautilus</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use Nautilus to display the contents of your Windows user folder just
      as you would for displaying a Linux directory. Create new files and
      folders on the Windows server.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Manipulating Windows Data with GNOME Applications</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Many GNOME applications allow you to open files on the Windows server,
      manipulate them and save them back to the Windows server.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Single-Sign-On</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      GNOME applications, including Nautilus, support Single-Sign-On. This
      means that to access other Windows resources, such as Web servers,
      proxy servers or groupware servers like MS Exchange, you do not need
      to reauthenticate. Authentication against all these is handled
      silently in the background using the username and password you
      provided on login.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   To access your Windows data using Nautilus, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open Nautilus and click <guimenu>Network</guimenu> in the Places pane.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Double-click <guimenu>Windows Network</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Double-click the icon of the workgroup containing the computer you want
     to access.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the computer’s icon (and authenticate if prompted to do so) and
     navigate to the shared folder on that computer.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   To create folders in your Windows user folder using Nautilus, proceed as
   you would when creating a Linux folder.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.gnome.network.ad.printer">
  <title>Configuring and Accessing a Windows Network Printer</title>

  <para>
   Being part of a corporate network and authenticating against a Windows
   Active Directory server, you can access corporate resources such as
   printers. GNOME allows you to configure printing from your Linux client
   to a Windows network printer.
  </para>

  <para>
   To configure a Windows network printer for use through your Linux
   workstation, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the GNOME Control Center from the main menu by clicking
     <menuchoice> <guimenu>Computer</guimenu> <guimenu>Control
     Center</guimenu> <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Printing</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>New</guimenu> <guimenu>Printer</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Windows Printer via SAMBA</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open the SMB Browser with <guimenu>Browse</guimenu> and select a
     workgroup, a server and the printer. Either enter the authentication
     credentials or choose to be prompted for authentication each time when
     accessing the printer. Click <guimenu>Forward</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Choose the printer's manufacturer and the printer model from the list
     and select a driver. The one that is marked with
     <guimenu>recommended</guimenu> normally produces the best results.
     Proceed with <guimenu>Forward</guimenu> and provide a name, a
     description and a location for the printer. Click
     <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Adding a printer requires &rootuser; privileges, so you must enter the
     &rootuser; password as the final step to adding it.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   To print to the Windows network printer configured above, select it from
   the list of available printers.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
