<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:novdoc-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN"
 "novdocx.dtd"
[
 <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "IGNORE">
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entities;
]>
<?provo dirname="security/"?>
<!--
FIXME:

* new rationale/ABOUT:
  - encourage investigative hardening
  - more focus on method and strategy - ask questions first, answer when question is sane.
  - add cyclic restart of procedure as a main argument: security as a process, not a state
* remove occurrences of EAL4+
* add chapter about reference to Common Criteria
  - evaluated configuration
  - value-add by evaluation
* fine-tuning, removal of some chapters
* sle11-sp2 specifics
  - pseudo filesystems: debugfs, tmpfs, procfs, sysfs
  - AppArmor


-->
<book lang="en" id="book.hardening">
 <bookinfo>
  <title><emphasis>Security and Hardening Guide</emphasis></title>
  <productname>&productname;</productname>
  <productnumber>&productnumber;</productnumber>
  <date><?dbtimestamp format="B d, Y"?></date>
  <titleabbrev>Security and Hardening</titleabbrev>
  <xi:include href="common_copyright_gfdl.xml"
	      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    &abstract_hardening;
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </bookinfo>
 <preface id="pre.hardening.about">
  <title>About This Guide</title>
  <para>
   The &productname; Security and Hardening Guide deals with the particulars
   of installation and set up of a secure &productname; server and
   additional post-install processes required to further secure and harden
   that installation. Security and hardening elements and procedures are
   best applied to a server both during installation and post-installation
   and aim to improve the fitness of the system for the purposes demanded by
   its administrator.
  </para>
  <para>
   This guide supports administrator in making security related choices
   and decisions. The individual steps and procedures should be seen as
   proposals, not as strict rules. In many cases, you will have to
   evaluate the usefulness of measures for your organization yourself.
  </para>
  <para>
   The objective is to improve the security value of the system.
   Definitions about the meaning of the term security vary, but we want to
   settle on one that is both simple and abstract:
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis>A good system does what it is expected to do, and it does it
   well.</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis>A secure system is a good system that does nothing
   else.</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   The focus of this guide lies on doing <quote>nothing else</quote>.
   The Linux system is constructed in such way that security
   policies are enforced. These policies are (fairly generic and incomplete
   list):
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     DAC (Discretionary Access Control): File and directory permissions,
     as set by <command>chmod</command> and <command>chown</command>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Privileged ports: TCP and UDP ports 0-1023 as well as raw sockets are
     only to the super user.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Other privileged operations: loading kernel modules,
     configuring network interfaces, all security relevant
     settings of the Linux kernel. These are operations that can only be done by
     the root user, that is the user with the user ID 0.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   Attacking a system means to attempt to overcome (for example, circumvent or break)
   these privilege boundaries in a way that the administrator of the system
   or the programmer of the corresponding subsystem has not taken into
   account.
  </para>
  <para>
   A hardened system raises the bar for the attacker to make
   the system do what they want by reducing the area that the
   system exposes to the attacker (often called attack surface), and by
   mitigating the risk that exists for the system if a part of it fails to
   handle untrusted input safely, thereby allowing actions within the
   context of this part of the system that were not intended by the
   programmer.
  </para>
  <para>
   Security is about decisions, and whenever security is in (apparent)
   opposition to function, these decisions become trade-offs. While it can
   be argued that all systems should be set up to be as securely as
   possible, some levels of security and hardening may very well be overkill
   in some cases. Each system's operational environment has its own security
   requirements derived from business drivers or regulatory compliance
   mandates (for example, SOX, HIPAA, PCIDSS) and an effective business
   requirements analysis should be performed in order to determine the right
   level of security and hardening to be applied to a server or defined as
   part of a baseline server build.
  </para>
  <para>
   As a final note before we begin: You may encounter individual
   requirements in regulatory compliance frameworks that may not make sense
   from a technical perspective, or they do not serve the purpose of
   improving security. It may be a productive attitude to simply implement
   what is required, but whenever there is a contradiction to security, an
   informed discussion in the documentation serves the overall purpose of
   your regulative compliance framework much more than blindly obeying the
   specifications. Please feel encouraged to dispute list items that you
   think are counterproductive.
  </para>
  <sect1 id="pre.hardening.about.assumptions">
   <title>Assumptions and Scope</title>

<!--
   <note>
    <para>
     As we go through this guide – we derive base assumptions from those
     provided from the EAL configuration. However, very few real-world
     environments provide for such a riskfree design constraint set. As
     such it can be considered that the EAL environment includes a generally
     cooperative usership with medium attack expertise and potential for
     individual users, and that the system runs physically protected in an
     untrusted network that can be considered hostile.
    </para>
   </note>
-->

   <para>
    While in most cases in this document reference will be made to a single
    server target or host, the scope can generally be applied to more than
    one machine. We generally assume that the security target can cover one
    or more systems running &productname;.
   </para>

   <para>
    We explicitly do <emphasis>not</emphasis> make any assumptions about the
    hostility of the network that the systems are connected to, or the
    cooperative nature of the users that leverage the services provided by
    the systems.
   </para>

   <para>
    In turn, this means that you partially define your context on your own
    when reading through this document. You will need to broaden the meaning
    of individual portions to adopt it to your environment. In some cases,
    such as the use case of a server that is exposed to the Internet, this
    document may even be insufficient or incomplete; however, it may still
    serve as a good starting point on your journey towards an increased
    level of confidence that your system will behave like you want it to.
   </para>

   <para>
    About trust: Trust relationships exist among all systems that
    participate in networked transactions. In this way, the trust relationship
    between the people that use the systems is transported across these
    systems. The chain that is formed by your trust relationships is only as
    strong as the weakest link. If we further assume that not all your
    problems are between keyboards and chairs, then it is up to the designer
    of the network of systems to watchguard the trust relationships. It is
    good practice to graphically visualize the trust relationships with the
    services in a schematic overview or map of your network. Generally, it
    is up to the owner of a resource to enforce the policies imposed on that
    resource; this would usually be the server that provides the resource.
    The client that opens a connection to request the resource can only be
    made responsible for the actions that it performs. This refers to the
    action of opening the connection to start with, but to nothing else as
    such.
   </para>

   <para>
    The case of hostile users is special and unique: The Human Resources
    department may be able to solve some of your security problems in your
    computing environment at least as well as some technical measures can.
    Please make sure that the necessary regulations in your environment fit
    your needs, and that they back your intentions instead of obstructing
    them if you need to work around a missing support from your HR
    department (and your management).
   </para>

   <para>
    Persons that have administrative privileges on a system are
    automatically considered trusted.
   </para>

   <para>
    A Linux system - without any additional security frameworks such as
    SELinux - is a single level security system: From a security policy
    perspective there is only the superuser (root) and non-privileged users.
    System users are non-root user IDs that have access to files specific to
    their purpose. All system user identities are inaccessible for local or
    networked users!) The separation of (systems-) administrative duties is
    complicated by this simplicity. Some tools however help: Make use of
    sudo(8) for administrative tasks, but be aware that once the privilege
    boundary is crossed, a program running with root privileges does not
    enforce any file access policies for non-privileged users any more.
    vi(1) that runs as root can read and write to any file in the system.
   </para>

   <para>
    Another tool to mitigate the risk of abuse or accidental misuse of
    administrative privileges is NetIQ's Privileged User Manager product.
    More information is available here:
   </para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink
       url="https://www.netiq.com/products/privileged-user-manager/"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

<!--
    It is not intended to
    address the needs of an Internet-connected server, or the case where
    services are to be provided to potentially hostile users. Further
    network security design and requirements would be required in such an
    instance and cover multi-layered firewalls / DMZ setups / etc.
   </para>

   <para>
    It is also assumed that all network cabling <emphasis>must</emphasis> be
    secured and protected from tapping and any other modifications. A secure
    network is assumed for this configuration because detailed examination
    of cryptographic protocols is beyond the scope of this document.
   </para>

   <note>
    <para>
     Note: Again – these assumptions are a bit <quote>idyllic</quote>.
     Evaluation of the threat environment would define the need for
     crypto-supported services. Also a tap-safe network infrastructure might
     be a requirement based on the type of threats defined.
    </para>
   </note>
-->

   <para>
    Physical security of the server is another assumption made here, where
    the server is protected from theft and manipulation by unauthorized
    persons. A common sobering thought amongst security professionals is the
    <quote>ten-second Denial of Service</quote>: Unplug the wires and
    reboot the server. Physical security must be ensured and physical access
    must be controlled. Otherwise, all assumptions about at least the
    availability of these systems are void.
   </para>

   <note>
    <title>Cryptography</title>
    <para>
     The use of cryptography to protect the confidentiality of transactions
     with the services that your system provides is generally encouraged.
     The need to implement cryptographic enhancements is strongly dependent on the
     operational environments of all participating systems. Keep in
     mind that you need to verify all of the possible security benefits that
     cryptography can provide, for all of your services, and
     that these benefits are not delivered automatically just by turning on
     the <quote>encrypt</quote> option of your service (if you can enjoy the
     idyllic situation where encryption is available as a button to check):
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Confidentiality</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Protection against reading the content of a
        transaction
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Privacy</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Protection against knowing that a transaction exists, and some
        properties that it may have, such as size, identities of involved
        parties, their presence, ...
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Integrity</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Protection against alteration of content. Be aware that cryptography
        does not automatically provide this kind of protection.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Authenticity</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Protection against identity fraud. Cryptography that does not know
        about identities of participating entities cannot deliver this
        value. If an encrypted data connection to your server can articulate
        integrity, then the server may provide authenticity
        of the content, but the cryptographic part cannot.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
     Keep in mind that encryption of data for confidentiality purposes can
     merely reduce the size of the data to protect from the actual size to
     the size of the key that is used to encrypt the data. This results in a
     key exchange problem for encrypted transactions, and in a key
     management problem for encrypted data storage. Since data is
     (typically, there are exceptions!) processed in clear, you need your
     vault unlocked while data within is being worked with. The encryption
     of such data on the file system or block device layer helps against the
     theft of the system, but it does not help the confidentiality of the
     data while the system is running.
    </para>
   </note>

<!--
    Also, all components in the network such as routers,
    switches and hubs that are used for communication are assumed to pass
    the user data reliably and without modification. Translations on
    protocol elements (for example NAT) are allowed just as long as those
    modifications don't lead to situations where data or information is
    routed to something other than the intended recipient system. Also, be
    aware that data passed to another system leaves the control of the
    sending system; therefore the protection of that data against
    unauthorized access needs to be enforced by the receiving system.

    *DUH* This is no statement about the obligation of the server to guard the data and the policy!
    -->

   <para>
    If you want to implement a consistent security policy covering multiple
    hosts on a network then organizational procedures
    <emphasis>must</emphasis> ensure that all those hosts can be trusted and
    are configured with compatible security configurations enforcing an
    organization wide security policy. Isolation of groups of systems that
    maintain data of the same trust domain can provide an adequate means of
    control; ultimately, the access controls to these systems, both for end
    users and for other systems, need to be carefully designed, configured,
    inspected and monitored.
   </para>

<!--
   <important>
    <para>
     If any connection is established with a system that is outside of the
     customer's control, enforcement of security policies for information
     passed to that system is not possible. Systems outside of the customer
     realm of control should also be considered beyond the scope of this
     document – or at least the configuration prescribed.
    </para>
   </important>
-->

   <important>
    <title>Trusting Data</title>
    <para>
     Data can only be trusted to the degree that is associated with the
     domain it comes from. If data leaves the domain in which security
     policies can be enforced, it should consequently be
     associated with the trust of the target domain.
    </para>
   </important>

   <para>
    For a review of industry best practices on security, the development of
    sound security processes, controls, development, reviews and audit
    practices and incident management, you can review a public RFC (request
    for comments). RFC 2196 is the ongoing work of the world-wide community
    and individual security and process experts. You can review it online
    here: <ulink url="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc2196.html"/>. An RFC is an
    open and living document that invites comments and review.
    Enhancements and improvements are welcomed; you will find instructions
    on where to send those suggestions within the document itself.
   </para>

   <para>
    This guide provides initial guidance on how to set up and secure a
    &productname; installation but it is not intended to be the only
    information required for a system administrator to learn how to operate
    Linux securely. Assumptions are made within this guide that the reader
    has knowledge and understanding of operating security principles in
    general, and of Linux administrative commands and configuration options
    in particular. Upon reaching this section of the document, we believe
    that the willingness of the reader to learn can be safely assumed.
   </para>

<!-- It is strongly advised that a
    customer organization that wants to operate their systems in the
    resultant secure configurations have their administrators trained in
    operating system security principles, &sle; security functions,
    properties and configuration. &suse; has developed ATT (Advanced
    Technical Training) courses for &productname; security and advanced
    administration. Courses range from introductory to advanced and are the
    basis for two of the leading &suse; and industry Linux certifications,
    the Certified Linux Professional and the Certified Linux Engineer.
   </para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink
       url="http://www.novell.com/training/certinfo/clp/roadmap_10.html"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink
       url="http://www.novell.com/training/certinfo/cle/roadmap_10.html"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

   <para>
    A common security axiom is <quote>Trust ... No One!</quote> or
    <quote>trust only those who have something considerable to
    lose...</quote>. While it is important that every organization can trust
    their system administrators not to deliberately undermine the security
    of the system, we will cover system configuration, including audit
    functions, which can be used to make users accountable for their
    actions. However, it is necessary to point out that an administrator may
    be able to stop the audit subsystem and reconfigure it such that his
    actions no longer get audited. Well trained and trustworthy
    administrators are therefore a key element for the secure operation of
    the system.
   </para>

   <para>
    Much of the configuration information outlined in this guide is provided
    in compliance with the requirements defined for &suse; to acquire the
    EAL Common Criteria certifications and is information a system
    administrator should use when installing, configuring, and operating the
    system to meet certified levels of security. To get an understanding of
    the differing levels you can visit the Common Criteria website or for
    more succinct reference – wikipedia.
   </para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="http://www.commoncriteriaportal.org/"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="http://www.commoncriteriaportal.org/"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_Criteria"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="http://www.commoncriteriaportal.org/"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

   <para>
    As a major portion of the hardened setup guidance has been placed here,
    and some has been modified, access to the original <quote>Common
    Criteria EAL4+ Evaluated Configuration Guide for &sls; on IBM
    Hardware</quote>” by Klaus Weidner can be found on the &productname;
    shipping DVD. You can find the package that contains the unedited
    version on the DVD in the /suse/noarch/ directory. The package name
    (which needs to be installed as part of the EAL criteria hardening) is
    <systemitem
     class="resource">certification-sles-ibm-eal4.rpm</systemitem>.
    Once installed, a pdf and other forms of the configuration guide can be
    found on the system in
    <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/certification-sles-ibm-eal4/</filename>.
   </para>

   <para>
    You can also find a copy of this documentation in a variety of formats
    on the &suse; FTP site. You can also find different CAPP certification
    efforts (with different sponsors HP and IBM) from various &productname;
    versions 8, 9 and 10:
   </para>

   <para>
    <ulink
     url="ftp://anonymous@ftp.suse.com/pub/projects/security/CommonCriteria/"/>
   </para>

   <para>
    A final note of merit, the EAL 4+ (augmented) certification explicitly
    defines the hardware platform used to achieve the certification, and as
    such it could be argued that any variation on the hardware platform
    could ostensibly invalidate the certification itself. While this could
    be argued to the <quote>letter of the law</quote>, the practical and
    pragmatic reality is that a CC EAL certification is referenced in the
    industry to provide a level of intrinsic trust for
    companies wishing to implement an operating system or technology. Minor
    modifications to the hardware reference platform should not be
    considered a risk.
   </para>

   <note>
    <para>
     Note: The specific hardware configuration constraint is merely due to
     the way the EAL certification process is run – sponsored by a third
     party, as is the hardware.
    </para>
   </note>

   <para>
    As the EAL levels go up so do the intrinsic costs associated with
    garnering a particular level of certification for the vendor who makes
    the product. Upper level EAL certifications have real monetary costs in
    addition to considerable labor and research/design efforts. While it may
    be considered that an EAL 6 or 7 certification on an operating system
    would garner more revenue due to its demonstrated security capabilities,
    it isn't guaranteed nor even something most consumers would require.
    Most commercially available operating systems are rated at EAL 4 today,
    and very specialized OSes garner an EAL 5 or higher typically by
    extensive planning (from the start) and use security kernels
    designed for a specific purpose. Another commonly heard description of a
    <quote>secure system</quote> is one that is disconnected, powered-off,
    buried 10 feet underground and covered with cement... and of course, if
    followed, that system would be of very little value to anyone. System
    security and the <quote>usefulness</quote> of a particular system is a
    constant balancing act. Using sound and pragmatic logic to determine the
    value of the system and/or the data it protects or serves can help
    determine the level of system protections one should or even should
    <emphasis>not</emphasis> apply to it.
   </para>

-->
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec.content_hardening">
  <title>Contents of this Book</title>
  <para>
    <xref linkend="part.setup_for_eal"/>
    contains a reference to Common Criteria and &productname;.
    <xref linkend="part.sec_prot"/>
    contains more general system security and service protection schemes.
   </para>

<!--
   <note>
    <para>
     Please keep in mind that we use the EAL/CC evaluation guide as a means
     to describe a variety of services that can be hardened, processes that
     can or should be followed, operational functionality of &productname;,
     components, pieces and parts. Together, the eal script that can be run
     should never be considered the be-all-end-all method to harden or
     secure a &productname; system... it is merely a tool used here to
     facilitate discussion and learning. A beginning, perhaps – but not an
     end.
    </para>
   </note>
-->
  </sect1>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="common_intro_available_doc_i.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="common_intro_feedback_i.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="common_intro_typografie_i.xml"/>
 </preface>
 <part id="part.setup_for_eal">
  <title>Common Criteria</title>
  <chapter id="cha.setup_for_eal.intro">
   <title>Overview and rationale</title>
   <abstract>
    <para>
     <remark>sknorr, 2014-07-14: update necessary, we are past Q2/2012</remark>
     Common Criteria certificates have been published for every major
     release of the &productname; since version 8. In Q2/2012, the
     &productname; 11 Service Pack 2 is expected to receive a Common
     Criteria v3.1 OSPP EAL4+ certificate. As of the time of writing of this
     document, the evaluation is progressing, while the product is under
     development at the same time.
    </para>
   </abstract>
   <sect1 id="sec.setup_for_eal.intro.generic">
    <title>What is the Common Criteria certification?</title>

    <para>
     Common Criteria is the best known and most widely used methodology to
     evaluate and measure the security value of an IT product. The
     methodology aims to be independent, as an independent laboratory
     conducts the evaluation, which a certification body will certify
     afterwards. Security Functional Requirements (SFR) are summarized in
     so-called Protection Profiles (PP), which allows the comparison of
     security functions of different products if the definition of the
     Security Target (ST) (which typically makes use of a reference to the
     PP if one exists that fits the purpose of the product) and the
     Evaluation Assurance Levels are comparable.
    </para>

    <para>
     A clear definition of security in IT products is
     challenging. Security should be considered a process that never ends,
     not a static condition that can be met or not. A Common Criteria
     certificate (below EA7) does not make a clear statement about error
     proneness of the system (while many of the flaws that exist
     specifically in operating systems are security-relevant), but it adds
     an important value to the product that cannot be described with the
     presence of technology alone: That someone has independently inspected
     the design of the system in such way that is corresponds to the claims
     that are made, and that explicit care has been taken in producing and
     maintaining the product. In an environment where the product is
     reliably shielded from any kind of attacker, the only remaining attack
     vector is the vendor of the system.
    </para>

    <para>
     The certificate states a degree of maturity of both the product with
     its security functions and the processes of the company that has
     designed, built and engineered the product, and that will maintain the
     product across its life cycle. As such, Common Criteria aims to be
     fairly holistic with its approach to take everything into account that
     is relevant for the security of an IT product.
    </para>

    <para>
     The Evaluation Assurance Level (EAL) shall denote the degree of
     confidence that the product fulfills the described claims. The levels
     are from 1 through 7:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       EAL1: Functionally tested
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       EAL2: Structurally tested
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       EAL3: Methodically tested and checked
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       EAL4: Methodically designed, tested and reviewed
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       EAL5: Semiformally designed and tested
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       EAL6: Semiformally verified design and tested
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       EAL7: Formally verified design and tested
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
     While EAL1 only provides basic assurance for products to meet security
     requirements, EAL2 to 4 are medium assurance levels. EAL5-EAL7 describe
     medium-to-high and high assurance; EAL4 is expected to be the highest
     level of assurance that a product can have if it has not been designed
     from the start to achieve a higher level of assurance.
    </para>

    <para>
     All commonly known General Purpose/Utility Computing
     operating systems have been awarded a Common Criteria certificate at
     EAL4. A "+" after the assurance level denotes an augmentation to the
     EAL, an addition that is useful for the articulation of security value,
     but formally not needed at the corresponding EAL.
    </para>

    <para>
     <remark>sknorr, 2014-07-08: it might be better to use an
       entity instead of hardcoding SLES..?</remark>
     The &productname; version 8 was the first Linux system to achieve EAL3+
     (Augmentation: Basic Flaw Remediation) in 2003; Version 9 of SLES was
     the first Linux based operating system to reach EAL4+ in 2004. More
     certifications and recertifications have followed targeting SLES 9 and
     SLES 10-SP1, until the &productname; version 11 Service Pack 2 was
     evaluated in 2011/2012.
    </para>

    <para>
     The Common Criteria evaluations inspect a specific configuration of the
     product in an evaluated configuration.
     <remark>sknorr, 2014-07-08: better use an xref here...</remark>
     The
     <quote>Administrator's Guide</quote> is a document that comes with a
     Common Criteria certified product and describes the individual steps
     that need to be taken to install and configure the product to a state
     like it was evaluated.
    </para>

    <para>
     Very often, the evaluated configuration is used as a reference for the
     secure installation of the &productname;. It is however incorrect to
     understand the evaluated configuration as a hardened configuration: the
     removal of setuid bits and the prescription of administrative
     procedures after installation is there to reach a specific
     configuration that is sane, but this process is clearly insufficient
     for a hardening claim.
    </para>

    <para>
     Earlier versions of this document have contained a substantial part
     that links to Common Criteria evaluated configurations. For the purpose
     of clarity and to avoid confusion, this version drafted for the
     &productname; version 11 Service Pack 2 has these chapters removed.
    </para>

    <para>
     Instead, this guide recommends the lecture the documentation that comes
     with the Common Criteria certificate to understand the Common Criteria
     evaluation of &productname; in general, the security functions that are
     in place within the operating system and how these security functions
     are relevant for the mitigation of threats. The High Level Design
     documentation encompasses the design specifics of the &productname;:
     Authentication mechanisms, access controls, audit subsystem and system
     logs, just to name a few of them. The accumulated knowledge contained
     in the documentation allows decision making for hardening purposes at
     an informed level - find it at
     <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/security/"/>
    </para>

    <para>
     Apart from the valuable documentation that comes with the Common
     Criteria effort, the following manual pages may be of greater interest
     to the inclined reader:
    </para>

    <para>
     <quote>pam(8), pam(5)</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
     <quote>apparmor(7)</quote> and referred manpages
    </para>

    <para>
     <quote>rsyslogd(8), syslog(8), syslogd(8), </quote>
    </para>

    <para>
     <quote>fstab(5), mount(8), losetup(8), cryptsetup(8)</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
     <quote>haveged(8), random(4)</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
     <quote>ssh(1), sshd(8), ssh_config(5), sshd_config(5), ssh-agent(1),
     ssh-add(1), ssh-keygen(1)</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
     <quote>cron(1), crontab(5), at(1), atd(8)</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
     <quote>systemctl(1), daemon(7), systemd.unit(5),
      systemd.special(5), kernel-command-line(7), bootup(7),
      systemd.directives</quote>
    </para>

<!--
    <para>
     The purpose of this part is to provide security configuration and
     hardening recommendations for the &sle; operating system. The guidance
     provided here should be applicable to all versions of the product from
     9 on, however many of the components are available (generally) in
     version 10 and later. Much of the content in this guide has been
     presented elsewhere as part of the base configuration details used to
     achieve the Common Criteria EAL 4+ certification. Where it will differ
     is in describing the addition of services and applications outside of
     the EAL 4+ scope. These descriptions will still focus on the security
     and hardening of these additions. However, due to the strict nature of
     the Common Criteria certification some services, and certainly third-party
     applications, could not be included.
    </para>

    <para>
     Attempts will be made to point out any differences applicable between
     &productname; version variants. Recommended settings for the basic
     operating system are provided, as well as for many commonly used
     services that the system can host in a network environment. Also, as
     there are security measures that can only be applied (easily) during a
     fresh installation, this document will begin with guidance as if the
     system is a new install of &productname; 10 SP2 version. As of
     publication, &productname; 11 has just shipped. As Linux itself
     continues to grow, change, improve exponentially as a secure operating
     system, this guide attempts to cover many different versions of
     &productname;. You may note some differences depending on the version
     you are using. If known, any thing presented here that is subject to
     change based on &productname; versioning will be noted. Any
     enhancements (pertaining to security) with the newest &productname; 11
     releases will also be called out.
    </para>

    <para>
     Audience: The guide is intended for partners, consultants and technical
     specialists with some decent Linux background and basic system
     administration experience. Readers are assumed to possess basic system
     administration skills for Unix-like systems, as well as some
     familiarity with &suse; documentation and administration
     conventions.
    </para>

    <para>
     Some instructions within this guide may be complex. Directions should
     be followed completely and with understanding of their effects in order
     to avoid serious adverse implications to the system and its security.
    </para>

    <para>
     Additional discussion, information and examples will be included at
     various points to help further the understanding of a given topic. For
     example, due to the complex nature of the Pluggable Authentication
     Modules and architecture, extra attention will be placed on its
     discussion so that the native flexibility can be understood. For a more
     exhaustive understanding of all of the security components it is highly
     recommended to read the individual man pages (even the <quote>see
     also</quote> page references at the bottom of an individual man page)
     and to seek other on-line resources or documentation. The next section
     describes guiding principles and assumptions used in the document. It
     will also describe some of the base services for an EAL 4+ build.
    </para>

    <para>
     Later sections will augment the security and hardening processes for
     other services and more generalized procedures, but these will be
     separated from the EAL 4+ content as they may not be qualified as part
     of the certified configuration. This does NOT mean that they are not
     <quote>secure</quote>, only that they were not part of the defined
     target of evaluation that garnered the Common Criteria certification.
    </para>
-->
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.setup_for_eal.intro.principals">
    <title>Generic Guiding Principles</title>

    <para>
     The following guiding principles motivate much of the advice in this
     guide, and security processes in general, and should also influence any
     configuration decisions that are not explicitly covered.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Use Data Encryption Whenever Possible</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <remark>sknorr, 2014-07-08: Use xrefs...</remark>
        Please refer to the "About... " section of this guide. In
        "Assumptions", the limitations of cryptography are briefly outlined.
       </para>
       <para>
        Please be aware that cryptography is certainly useful, but only for
        the specific purposes that it is good for. It is not a generic
        recipe for better security in a system, its use may even impose
        additional risk on the system. Make informed decisions about the use
        of cryptography, and feel obliged to have a reason for your
        decisions, no matter if they are for or against cryptography. A
        false sense of security is normally more harmful than the weakness
        itself.
<!--
        Data transmissions over wired or wireless networks are susceptible
        to passive monitoring. If it is possible to encrypt these
        transmissions, and practical, it should be done. Even if the realm
        of control is exclusively on a local network, encryption should
        still be considered and implemented, especially authentication data
        like ID and passwords. Networks of machines with &productname;
        can and should be configured such that no
        unencrypted authentication data is ever transmitted between
        machines.
    -->
        &productname; supports encryption for generic network connections
        (the openssl command, stunnel), for remote login (openssh, man
        ssh(1)), for generic file encryption (gpg), for entire file systems
        at block layer (dm_crypt, cryptsetup) and for VPN (IPsec, openvpn).
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Minimal Package Installation</term>
      <listitem>
<!--
       <para>
        The easiest way to avoid vulnerabilities in software is NOT to
        install it! &productname; allows for careful management of the set
        of software packages installed on a system via the &yast; Software
        Management interface and the RPM package manager.
       </para>
   -->
       <para>
        Generally, an RPM software package consists of the package's meta
        data that is written to the RPM database upon installation, the
        package's files and directories and scripts that are being executed
        before and after installation and uninstallation.
       </para>
       <para>
        If the package does NOT contain
       </para>
       <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          setuid- or setgid bits on any of the installed files
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          group- or world-writeable files or directories
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          a service that is activated upon installation/activated by
          default.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </orderedlist>
       <para>
        then the said package generally does not impose any security risk to
        the system. Under the above condition, the package is merely a
        collection of files, and their use shall not be automatically
        assumed if you do not have any local users on your system. Since the
        installation of such packages does not have any influence on the
        security value of the system, the uninstallation of them should
        not either.
       </para>
       <para>
        However, a fairly simple reason to keep to a minimal set of packages
        in your installation is that something that is not present cannot
        get used. Binaries not installed cannot be executed.
       </para>
       <para>
        A straight forward way of keeping to a minimal set of packages
        begins with the installation of the system. You can start the
        installation of your system by deselecting all packages and then
        select only those that you wish to use. As an example, the selection
        of the apache2-mod_perl package in &yast; would automatically cause
        all packages to be selected for installation that are needed for the
        Apache package to operate. In many cases, dependencies have been
        artificially cut down to be able to handle the system's dependency
        tree more flexibly. You should be safe if you chose the minimal
        system, and build the dependency tree from there with your (leaf)
        package selection.
       </para>
<!--
       <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          A setuid program is a binary that runs with the privileges of the
          binary file owner and not the privileges of the user who executes
          the program.
          Packages that include setuid programs may provide local attackers
          a potential path to privilege escalation. For this reason, setuid
          bits should be avoided, or the setuid bits should be removed unless
          explicitly required (example: passwd(1)).
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Packages that include network services may give this opportunity
          to network-based attackers. There are only two packages in &productname;
          that contain or provide network services and that are active by
          default after the installation: the openssh package (sshd secure shell daemon)
          and the rpcbind package (rpcbind, RPC portmapper, needed for NFS client
          mounts).
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Packages that include programs which are predictably executed by
          local users (for example after graphical login) may provide opportunities
          for Trojan horses or other attack code to be run undetected.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          The number of software packages installed on a system can almost
          always be significantly pruned to include only the software for
          which there is an environmental or operational need.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </orderedlist>
 -->
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Service Isolation - Run Different Services on Separate
      Systems</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Whenever possible, a server should be dedicated to serving exactly
        one service or application. This limits the number of other services
        that could be compromised in the event an attacker is able to
        successfully exploit a software flaw in one service (assuming that
        flaw allows access to others).
       </para>
       <para>
        This point can lead to healthy and robust dialog on
        system sizing and even further to consolidation or virtualization.
        The intent with this guidance is to reduce the fault domain and risk
        where possible.
       </para>
       <para>
        The use of AppArmor for services that are provided on a system is an
        effective means of containment. Please refer to the AppArmor
        documentation on your system to learn more. <command>man
        apparmor</command> is a good starting point.
       </para>
       <para>
        The use of virtualization technology with &kvm; or with &xen; is
        supported with the &productname; version 11. While virtualization is
        generally designed for server consolidation purposes, its usefulness
        for service isolation is another good argument. Please be aware that
        the capability of the hypervisor to separate virtual machines is not
        higher or stronger than the Linux kernel's capability to separate
        processes and their address spaces. The granularity at which
        virtualization technology tackles separation may however come with
        its benefits, being resource-hungry and somewhat clumsy on the other
        hand.
       </para>
       <note>
        <para>
         Virtualization technology cannot match or substitute the separation
         strength that is given by running services on different physical
         machines!
        </para>
       </note>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       System fingerprinting and backups
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        In the case of the suspicion of an attack against the system,
        nothing can provide more comfort than
       </para>
       <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          a backup
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          a fingerprint of your system to detect modifications
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          having done your homework.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </orderedlist>
       <para>
        Several tools exist on &productname; 11 which can be effectively
        used for the detection of unknown, but yet successful attacks. These
        tools come at the cost of relatively little configuration effort,
        but with the benefit of being able to actually know
        what has been changed in your system.
       </para>
       <para>
        In particular, the use of
        <systemitem class="resource">AIDE</systemitem> is strongly
        encouraged. <systemitem class="resource">AIDE</systemitem>, when run
        for initialization, creates a hash database of all files in the
        system that are configured. This allows to verify the integrity of
        all catalogued files at a later time.
       </para>
       <note>
        <para>
         You need to copy the hash database that AIDE creates to a place
         that is unaccessible for potential attackers. Otherwise, the
         attacker may modify the integrity database after planting a
         backdoor, thereby defeating the purpose of the integrity
         measurement.
        </para>
       </note>
       <note>
        <para>
         An attacker may have planted a backdoor in the kernel. This has an
         entire variety of consequences: Apart from being very hard to
         detect, the kernel-based backdoor can effectively remove all traces
         of the system compromise to the degree that system alterations are
         almost invisible. By consequence, an integrity check needs to be
         done from a rescue system (or any other system where an independent
         system runs, and the target system's file systems are mounted
         manually).
        </para>
       </note>
       <note>
        <para>
         Security is a lively process. Essentially, in this context, this
         means that the application of security updates invalidates the
         integrity database. <command>rpm <option>-qlv packagename</option></command> lists the
         files that are contained in a package. Generally spoken, the RPM
         subsystem is very powerful with the data that it maintains, and
         that is accessible with the <option>--queryformat</option>
         commandline option. A differential update of integrity database
         with the changed files becomes more manageable with some
         fine-grained utilisation of RPM.
        </para>
       </note>
       <para>
        A fast and directly accessible backup adds distinct confidence about
        the integrity of your system and can substitute an integrity check
        such as described above with AIDE. It is important, though, that the
        backup mechanism/solution has adequate versioning support so that
        you can trace changes in the system. As an example: The installation
        times of packages (<command>rpm <option>-q</option> <option>--queryformat='%{INSTALLTIME}
        %{NAME}\n'</option> packagename</command> must correspond to the changed files
        in the backup's logs.
       </para>
       <note>
        <para>
         Make it an integral part of your security routine to verify
         that your backups work.
        </para>
       </note>
<!--

       <para>
        and the <systemitem class="resource">seccheck</systemitem> cron script
        this guide recommends and discusses the use of
        iptables for host-based firewalling (although, in general, usage of
        the &susefirewall; and configuring it with &yast; is easier and
        actually uses iptables), &aa; or SELinux (preview in &productname;
        11) for protection against vulnerable services, and a logging and
        auditing (<systemitem class="daemon">syslog-ng</systemitem> and
        <systemitem
         class="daemon">auditd</systemitem>)
        infrastructure for detection of problems. Also included in
        &productname; are some security specific tools that improve the
        general security, monitoring and reporting capabilities. Tools such
        as ,
         and
        <systemitem class="resource">nessus</systemitem>.
       </para>
-->
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect1>
<!--
   <sect1 id="sec.setup_for_eal.intro.usage">
    <title>Guide Usage</title>

    <para>
     In using this guide you should keep the following points in mind:
    </para>

    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Sectioning Order and Section Cohesion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Just a general caution, each section might build on information and
        recommendations discussed in prior sections. It is wise to read each
        section to gain complete understanding (if possible) as the
        instructions/recommendations should never be applied to a system
        blindly. Relevant examples and descriptions may occur after the
        instructions for a particular action.
       </para>
       <para>
        There are two distinct sections for the system set up, system-level
        installation/configuration and service-level
        installation/configuration. The system-level recommendations should
        be applied to all hosts; however service-level guidance may or may
        not be applicable. In the case of services, you will apply the
        guidance if the machine is either a server or a client for that
        service, and ensure that the service is disabled (or as previously
        mentioned, the package removed from the system) according to the
        instructions provided if the machine is neither a server nor a
        client.
       </para>
       <para>
        Also, as mentioned previously, the first sections describe an EAL 4+
        installation and setup. As additional services are added, they may
        be outside of the EAL 4+ base installation and configuration
        (<quote>certified target of evaluation</quote>) yet should not be
        considered 'non-secure'. Additional content depth, recommendations
        and examples will be included to provide for increased flexibility
        in securing and hardening system implementations.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Testing and Fingerprinting</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Each component and recommendation should be tested. In the Delivery
        Guide, guidance was described for a prototype and lab environment.
        This is where testing should occur. Overall, any recommendations
        made here should always be tested in a non-production environment
        before deployment. This test environment should simulate the setup
        in which the system will be deployed as closely as possible.
       </para>
       <para>
        Fingerprinting is the process of storing a 'picture' of a system so
        it can be referenced and compared later to prove its integrity has
        not been compromised. Details will be given in this guide for the
        use of <systemitem class="resource">AIDE</systemitem> (the Advanced
        Intrusion Detection Environment). It is used as an example, but the
        fingerprinting guidance is sound. There are several third-party
        providers of system integrity and audit solutions. However,
        <systemitem class="resource">AIDE</systemitem> is included with
        &productname;, is OpenSource, and fairly easy to implement. In the
        event of a system breach, having a system fingerprint can prove
        invaluable when it comes to forensic analysis.
       </para>
       <note>
        <para>
         NOTE: Earlier versions of &productname;
         included<systemitem class="resource"> TripWire</systemitem>.
        </para>
       </note>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Root Shell Environment Assumed</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Most of the actions listed in this document are written with the
        assumption that they will be executed by the &rootuser; user running
        the /bin/bash shell. Any commands preceded with a hash mark (#)
        assume that the administrator will execute the commands as
        &rootuser;, in other words, they will be applied via the usage of
        sudo whenever possible (or use su to gain root privileges if sudo
        cannot be used).
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Reboots / Restarts</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        A system restart or reboot might be required after some actions in
        order to complete the reconfiguration of the system. Attempts will
        be made to mention when a reboot is explicitly required. However, in
        some cases, changes will not take effect until a reboot is
        performed. In order to ensure that changes are applied properly and
        to test functionality, it is always a good practice to reboot the
        system after applying a set of recommendations from this guide if a
        reboot is specified.There are only few system changes that
        require a reboot.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Hardware Preparation</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If possible, BIOS passwords should be enabled. They are no
        guarantee, but are decent protection from low-level hardware
        configuration changes. Physical access must be controlled to ensure
        that the BIOS 'clear' hardware-jumpers could not be manipulated on
        the motherboard to bypass this protection.
       </para>
       <note>
        <para>
         The caveat to this is that a BIOS passwords can also be problematic
         or detrimental. If physical access/safety can be assured – you
         may opt to refrain from their usage. Booting from a forensics or
         rescue image may not be possible – in the event of a system
         failure or break in – if a BIOS password preempts a boot.
        </para>
       </note>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>System User Requirements</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The assumption is made that the hardened host will reside in a
        friendly environment, one with cooperative and
        security-minded users. Users who will use the system responsibly to
        fulfill their tasks.
       </para>
       <para>
        Note that system availability is not addressed in this guide, and a
        malicious user could disable a server through resource exhaustion,
        denial-of-service attacks or like methods. High availability is
        addressed in other playbooks and can be at the server or service
        level. Of particular interest to many &productname; customers is the
        fact that high-availability tools are included and supported with
        the &productname; distributions (&productname; 10 and higher) either
        in the base distribution or included as add-ons.
       </para>
       <para>
        A set of baseline user account requirements are prescribed here in
        accordance with the EAL 4+ evaluation. These requirements are not
        exhaustive, yet provide a minimum level of trusted security for a
        user environment. Other requirements may be necessary depending on
        other policy constraints like SOX, auditing, etc.
       </para>
       <para>
        The requirements for users specifically include:
       </para>
       <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
         <term>Prescribed Usage / Access Control</term>
         <listitem>
          <para>
           User accounts <emphasis>must</emphasis> be assigned only to those
           users with a need to access the data protected by
           the system. These users <emphasis>must</emphasis> be sufficiently
           trustworthy not to abuse those privileges. Again, the concept of
           domain control needs to be considered. Once data
           leaves a system the system has no control and cannot prevent that
           data from being intentionally redistributed to unauthorized third
           parties by an authorized user.
          </para>
         </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
         <term>Granted Trust</term>
         <listitem>
          <para>
           All users of the system <emphasis>must</emphasis> be sufficiently
           skilled to understand the security implications of their actions,
           and <emphasis>must</emphasis> understand and follow a base set of
           security guidelines. There is a baseline set of these
           requirements in a later section. Appropriate training
           <emphasis>must</emphasis> be available to ensure this. Further,
           best practices suggest some sort of User/Acceptable Use policy be
           maintained and logged. As part of many auditing standards, these
           types of policies are required to be signed and stored before
           access is granted to systems including host access, remote
           access, Internet access, etc.
          </para>
         </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
       </variablelist>
       <para>
        Normally it is part the responsibility of system administrators to
        verify that these requirements are met, and to be available to users
        if they need help in maintaining the security of their data.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.setup_for_eal.intro.host_security">
    <title>Host Security Functions</title>

    <para>
     This section summarizes the security functions that were covered by the
     EAL 4+ certified evaluation. Refer to the appropriate sections for
     information on configuring, using, and managing any of these functions.
     Further examples and details may be provided in later sections if that
     detail is granular and out-of-scope of the base evaluation. All section
     numbers referenced in this guide will correspond directly with those in
     the native <quote>Common Criteria EAL4+ Evaluated Configuration Guide
     for &suse; LINUX Enterprise Server on IBM Hardware</quote> for clarity,
     however this synchronization will not begin until section 2.2 (EAL 4+
     Installation). Also note that more detail (for clarity-sake) will be
     provided in this guide. When in doubt, refer to man pages, the Internet
     or check other references. There is a wealth of information available
     in the topic of *nix system security or computer
     security in general. A list of sources will be included
     in an appendix of this guide.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="sec.setup_for_eal.intro.host_security.auth">
     <title>Identification and Authentication</title>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Pluggable Authentication Module (PAM)</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <xref linkend="cha.setup_for_eal.securing.background.pam"/> will
         describe PAM and its usage. Extra details will be provided on PAM
         'stacks' and how to extend PAM to meet your usage requirements. PAM
         documentation is located on the system in
         <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/pam/</filename> and you can check
         the pam man page with <command>man 8 pam</command>.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>loginRequired</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         The setup and configuration of system logins will be covered in
         <xref linkend="cha.setup_for_eal.securing.background.login_defs"/>.
         Also refer to the <literal>login</literal> and
         <literal>login.defs</literal> man pages for additional information.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>OpenSSH</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         OpenSSH is used by default in &productname; and its usage and setup
         are described in
         <xref
          linkend="cha.setup_for_eal.securing.background.ssh"/>
         and the <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem>,
         <command>ssh</command>, <literal>sshd_config</literal> man pages.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><systemitem class="daemon">vsftpd</systemitem>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         The Very Secure FTP daemon is discussed in
         <xref
          linkend="cha.setup_for_eal.securing.background.ftp"/>
         and the <systemitem class="daemon">vsftpd</systemitem> and
         <literal>vsftpd.conf</literal> man pages. Usage of FTP may not be a
         service that is required in all host configurations, but it was
         part of the EAL 4+ configuration test.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><command>su</command>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         The usage of the <command>su</command> command is prescribed
         <xref
          linkend="sec.setup_for_eal.operating.root"/> in.
         Further details can be found in the <command>su</command> man page.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.setup_for_eal.intro.host_security.audit">
     <title>Audit</title>
     <para>
      The audit subsystem has changed considerably from version to version
      of &productname; with updates being made at both the kernel and
      user-space. In recent updates to &productname; 10 SP2, more features
      and functionality has been introduced furthering the capabilities and
      configuration possibilities. The audit subsystem has distinct
      components for event detection and configuration, proxy handling, and
      reporting. Details will be covered in
      <xref
       linkend="sec.setup_for_eal.monitoring.audit"/>. You
      should also refer to the
      <systemitem class="daemon">auditd</systemitem> man page, whose
      <quote>SEE ALSO</quote> section points to the remaining audit
      subsystem man pages (for example <literal>auditd.conf</literal>,
      <systemitem class="daemon">audispd</systemitem>,
      <command>ausearch</command>, <command>aureport</command> and
      <command>auditctl</command>).
     </para>
     <para>
      Additional information will be covered in later chapters. The audit
      subsystem is very powerful and flexible. Many customers choose to
      purchase third-party products for audit event tracking and reporting
      when a detailed knowledge of the Linux Auditing System might have
      satisfied their needs with no additional costs.
     </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.setup_for_eal.intro.host_security.access">
     <title>Discretionary Access Control</title>
     <para>
      Discretionary access control will be covered in
      <xref
       linkend="sec.setup_for_eal.user.acl"/>. Further, System V
      interprocesses communication objects (for example message queues, semaphore
      sets and shared memory segments) and security permissions and
      processes will be covered in
      <xref
       linkend="sec.setup_for_eal.operating.sysv_memory"/>.
     </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.setup_for_eal.intro.host_security.object_reuse">
     <title>Object Reuse</title>
     <para>
      According to the &productname; High Level Design document, the kernel
      automatically ensures that new objects (disk files, memory, IPC) do
      not contain any traces of previous contents. The design has even been
      enhanced in the latest editions of &productname; to include further
      security enhancements in the kernel and user-space.
     </para>
     <para>
      Some examples include:
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Randomization:</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Better address space randomization is available for binaries
         compiled with PIE support (-fPIE). Randomizations include the
         address where the binary is mapped and the head start address.
         Stack and mmap areas are already randomized for all other binaries.
         Randomization is typically an anti-worm measure, not typically an
         anti-overflow solution.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Fstack-protection</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         fstack-protector runtime stack overrun heuristics are now enabled
         for all packages in the SLE11 code base.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.setup_for_eal.intro.host_security.manage">
     <title>Security Management and System Protection</title>
     <para>
      These topics will be covered as complete chapters. General operation
      and system management will be covered in
      <xref
       linkend="cha.setup_for_eal.operating"/> and system
      monitoring, logging and audit will be handled in
      <xref
       linkend="cha.setup_for_eal.monitoring"/>.
     </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.setup_for_eal.intro.host_security.communication">
     <title>Secure Communication</title>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>stunnel</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Encryption methods and secure communications are expansive topics.
         The EAL 4+ evaluation guide, the usage of stunnel was described to
         provide a universal SSL tunnel for applications or services. In
         <xref
          linkend="sec.setup_for_eal.operating.stunnel"/> the
         specifics will be covered. See also the <literal>stunnel</literal>
         man page.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>SSH System Operation Procedures for Secure Systems</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <xref
          linkend="cha.setup_for_eal.securing.background.ssh"/>
         will cover the configuration and usage of SSH with further details
         available within the <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem>,
         <command>ssh</command>, <literal>sshd_config</literal> man pages.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </sect2>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.setup_for_eal.intro.events">
    <title>Overview of Security Relevant Events</title>

    <para>
     The audit subsystem is intended to be the central interface for
     collecting and viewing the record of security relevant events. Formerly
     called the Linux Audit Subsystem (LauS). It was developed by &suse; for
     &productname; 9 (Open Sourced and released under GPL) to attain a CC
     EAL 4 certificate. Since then it has been reworked, renamed simply
     audit, and adopted upstream into the kernel and is now common to the
     2.6 kernel.
    </para>

    <para>
     The events being monitored by default in the evaluated configuration
     include:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       All authentication done through the PAM library, including the
       identity and location (where available) of the user and the success
       or failure result.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Any use of <command>su</command> to change identity. All actions done
       as part of a su session are marked in the audit record along with the
       original user's login user ID.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The addition, change or deletion of any users or groups.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Any changes and/or change attempts to the contents of any security
       critical files.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Any changes to the access permissions or ownership of any files or
       IPC (interprocess communication) objects.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Changes to or new binding network ports and accepting connections.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
     Details will be covered in
     <xref linkend="cha.setup_for_eal.monitoring"/>.
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.setup_for_eal.intro.events.sle11">

    <title>&productname; 11 Enhancements</title>

    <para>
     As previously mentioned in the section above, there have been some
     variations in capabilities as the &productname; operating system has
     matured from version to version, service pack to service pack in some
     instances. Even the included binaries themselves in &productname; 11
     have included security enhancements during compilation as improvements
     have been developed. Here are some examples:
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Randomization and Enhanced fstack-protection&mdash;see
       <xref
        linkend="sec.setup_for_eal.intro.host_security.object_reuse"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>D_FORTIFY_SOURCE</literal> flag enabled at compilation time
       – provides compile-time and runtime based overflow protection and
       format string checking. This was included in SLE 10 as well.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A new &yast; module for Audit. This will ease the setup and
       configuration of the audit modules as part of the Linux Audit
       Framework (CAPP/EAL capable in SLE10SP2 and certified as of
       SLE10SP1).
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Several &aa; enhancements.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       PolicyKit – this allows for more fine-grained access controls for
       administration access. Enables limited/reduced root access for some
       configuration tasks.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Additional code and design reviews/improvements by the &suse;
       Security Team – securing new features.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
   </sect1>

-->
  </chapter>
 </part>
 <part id="part.sec_prot">
  <title>General System Security and Service Protection Methods</title>
  <chapter id="cha.sec_prot.intro">
   <title>Introduction</title>
   <para>
    In <xref linkend="part.setup_for_eal"/> we covered the Common Criteria
    EAL 4+ certified installation and setup that was sponsored by IBM for a
    select subset of hardware. This certified build is a
    great first step for customers wishing to build a secure and hardened
    base system, yet might not address all of the services and software
    specifics that many customers would be interested in.
   </para>
   <para>
    This next part will present a more general view and
    give recommendations and guidance for &productname; system
    security. Some topics may seem repeated here (from the previous part)
    yet the context is very different. More detail will be provided in some
    sections and certainly some more general examples for a greater number
    of services.
   </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="cha.sec_prot.general">
   <title>Linux Security in General</title>
   <para>
    This portion of the guide will only give basic recommendations
    instead of strict rules. The procedures and examples here should
    give you the ability to apply security enhancement techniques to a
    wider variety of server-based services and programs.
   </para>
   <para>
    Some of the subjects of this chapter have been discussed before.
    However, in many cases, you will find more details and explanations
    in this chapter. Some of the general topics are:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Physical Security – Protection of the server from environmental
      threats (people, places, things).
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Security Policies and Procedures – Server life cycle management,
      disk/media reclamation, backup and archive security.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Systems Monitoring – Procedures around event
      notification/management.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Systems Automation – Mechanisms and/or procedures for automatic
      security measures. Heuristics, account control, security reporting and
      remediation, automated shutdown, etc.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Systems Management – Methods to obtaining packages, verification and
      signing keys, patching procedures and recommendations.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Securing Network – Addition programs, ports and service wrappers –
      iptables, tcpwrappers, services.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Remote Access – extra SSH information and key federation. CA
      integration.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Common Services – mail, NFS and automount.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Securing the Kernel and Init Process – parameters, systemd targets, and boot scripts.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Access Control – user/groups/permissions.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Password Security and Warnings – Proper setup of passwords, banners
      and <systemitem class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Miscellaneous Security – Assorted security settings and
      miscellany.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Resources – Web links, documentation and example references, HOWTOs
      and general information, product links.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    The sections will again be organized by a topical hierarchy for
    continuity-sake. Refer to the main table of contents for easy reference.
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>Typography</title>
    <para>
     <remark>sknorr, 2014-07-07: Update this chapter to use &amp;prompt.user;
       and &amp;prompt.root;, instead of the hand-rolled symbology below.
     </remark>
     The following examples will show the <literal>&gt;</literal> symbol to
     denote a <quote>normal</quote> user (without &rootuser; privileges) and
     also the <literal>#</literal> will denote commands run as the
     <quote>&rootuser;</quote> user.
    </para>
   </note>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.physical">
    <title>Physical Security</title>

    <para>
     Physical security should be one of the utmost concerns. Linux
     production servers should be in locked
     data centers where only people have access that have passed security checks.
     Depending on the environment and circumstances, you can also
     consider boot loader passwords.
    </para>
    <para>Additionally, consider questions like:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>Who has direct physical access to the host?</para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>Of those that do, should they?</para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>Can the host be protected from tampering and should it be?</para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
     The amount of physical security needed on a particular system depends
     on the situation, and can also vary widely by available funds.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.physical.locks">
     <title>System locks</title>
     <para>
      Most server racks in data centers include a locking
      feature. Usually this will be a hasp/cylinder lock on the front of the
      rack that allows you to turn an included key to a locked or unlocked
      position – granting or denying entry. Cage locks can help prevent
      someone from tampering or stealing devices/media from the servers, or
      opening up the cases and directly manipulating/sabotaging the
      hardware. Preventing system reboots or the booting from alternate
      devices is also important (for example CD/DVDs/USB drives/etc.).
     </para>
     <para>
      Some servers also have case locks. These locks can do different things
      according to the designs of the system vendor and construction. Many
      systems are designed to self-disable if attempts are made to open the
      system without unlocking. Others have device covers that will not let
      you plug in or unplug new keyboards or mice. While locks are sometimes
      a useful feature, they are usually lower quality and easily defeated
      by attackers with ill intent.
     </para>
    </sect2>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.bios">
    <title>Locking down the BIOS</title>

    <para>
     The BIOS (Basic Input/Output System) is the lowest level of
     software/firmware that dictates system configuration and low-level
     hardware. &grub;, &elilo; and other Linux boot loaders access the BIOS
     to determine how to boot the host. Other hardware types
     (&ipseries;/&zseries;) that run Linux also have low-level
     software/firmware. Typically the BIOS can be configured to help prevent
     attackers from being able to reboot the host and manipulate the system.
    </para>

    <para>
     Most BIOS varieties allow the setting of a boot password. While this
     does not provide a high level of security (a BIOS can be reset, removed
     or modified – assuming case access), but it can be another deterrent.
    </para>

    <para>
     Many BIOS capabilities have other various security settings –
     checking with the system vendor, the system documentation or examine
     the BIOS during a system boot.
    </para>

    <important>
     <title>Booting when a BIOS Password is Set</title>
     <para>
      If a system host has been set up with a boot password, the host will
      not boot up unattended (for example a system reboot, power failure, etc.).
      This is the trade-off/risk.
     </para>
    </important>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.bootloader">
    <title>Security via the Boot Loaders</title>

    <para>
     Linux boot loaders, like &grub; (used by default in &productname;) and
     &elilo; (optional), can also have a boot passwords set.
     <remark condition="clarity">
      2014-02-10 - fs: FIXME: Is the following still true with ELILO?
     </remark>
     &elilo; has the
     password and restricted settings. The password setting requires a
     password at boot time, and the restricted setting requires a boot-time
     password only if you specify different boot options (such as single )
     at the &elilo; prompt.
    </para>

    <para>
     &grub; also provides a password feature, so that only
     administrators can start the interactive operations (i.e. editing menu
     entries and entering the command-line interface).

     <remark condition="clarity">
      2014-02-10 - fs: FIXME: Is the following still true with GRUB 2?
     </remark>

     If a password is
     specified, &grub; will disallow any interactive control until you press
     the key <keycap>P</keycap> or <keycap>E</keycap> and enter a correct
     password.
    </para>

    <para>
     You can refer to the &grub; and &elilo; man pages for examples.
    </para>

    <para>
     It is very important to keep in mind that when setting these passwords
     they will obviously need to be remembered! Also, enabling these passwords
     might merely slow an intrusion, not necessarily prevent it.  Again,
     someone could boot from a removable device, and mount your root
     partition.  If you are using BIOS-level security as well as a boot
     loader, it is a good practice to disable the ability to boot from
     removable devices in your computer's BIOS, and then also
     password-protecting the BIOS itself.
    </para>

    <para>
     Also keep in mind that the boot loader configuration files will need to be
     protected by changing their mode to <literal>600</literal> (read/write
     for &rootuser; only), or others will be able to read your passwords or
     hashes!
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.seccheck">
    <title>Verifying Security Action with seccheck</title>

    <para>
     Verifying Security Action Items. It is highly recommended to have scripts
     in place which can verify that security actions or procedures have been
     run. Even the best systems administrators can make errors or forget
     something. If you have a small or large Linux installation or
     environment, you should consider the use of the seccheck scripts.
    </para>

    <para>
     seccheck is the &suse; Security Checker. It is a set of several
     shellscripts designed to check the local security of the system on a
     regular basis. There are three main scripts that are executed at
     different time intervals. They are <literal>security-daily,</literal>
     <literal>security-weekly</literal> and
     <literal>security-monthly</literal>. At installation these scripts all
     have schedule entries that get placed in cron that determine when they
     run. Although cron scheduling is the default behavior, this can be
     controlled via configuration settings (see next section). The daily
     script runs at midnight, and if changes are detected since the last run
     (the night before), an e-mail noting the differences will be sent. The
     weekly script runs every Monday at 1:00 am, and only if changes to the
     last run (the week before) are found, a mail with the differences will
     be sent. The monthly script runs every on every 1st of the month and
     sends the full last daily and weekly report via e-mail.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.seccheck.config">
     <title>Seccheck Configuration</title>
     <para>
      Please note that you can change the receiver of the seccheck mails
      from root to anyone else if you add an entry like this one to
      <filename>/etc/sysconfig/seccheck</filename>:
     </para>
<screen>SECCHK_USER="firewall" # exchange firewall is an admin user's account name</screen>
     <para>
      Please also note that the <envar>START_SECCHK</envar> variable from
      <filename>/etc/sysconfig/seccheck</filename> controls whether the
      security check will be run from cron. (It's ignored, if you call
      <command>security-control</command> manually.)
     </para>
     <para>
      The following daily checks are done:
     </para>
     <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
       <colspec colname="c1"/>
       <colspec colname="c2"/>
       <tbody>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           <filename>/etc/passwd</filename> check
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           length/number/contents of fields, accounts with same uid accounts
           with uid/gid of 0 or 1 beside root and bin
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           <filename>/etc/shadow</filename> check
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           length/number/contents of fields, accounts with no password
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           <filename>/etc/group</filename> check
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           length/number/contents of fields
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           user root checks
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           secure umask and <envar>PATH</envar>
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           <filename>/etc/ftpusers</filename>
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           checks if important system users are put there
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           <filename>/etc/aliases</filename>
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           checks for mail aliases which execute programs
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           <filename>.rhosts</filename> check
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           checks if users' <filename>.rhosts</filename> file contain +
           signs
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           homedirectory
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           checks if homedirectories are writable or owned by someone else
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           dot-files check
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           checks many dot-files in the home directories if they are writable
           or owned by someone else
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           mailbox check
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           checks if user mailboxes are owned by user and unreadable
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           NFS export check
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           exports should not be exported globally
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           NFS import check
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           NFS mounts should have the <option>nosuid</option> option set
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           promisc check
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           checks if network cards are in promiscious mode
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           list modules
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           just lists loaded modules
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           list sockets
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           just lists open ports
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">
          <para>
           Weekly Checks are as follows:
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           password check
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           runs john to crack the password file, user will get an e-mail
           notice to change his password asap
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           RPM md5 check
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           checks for changed files via RPM's MD5 checksum feature
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           suid/sgid check
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           lists all suid and sgid files
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           exec group write
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           lists all executables which are group/world-writeable
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           writable check
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           lists all files which are world-writeable (including executables)
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           device check
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           lists all devices
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
       </tbody>
      </tgroup>
     </informaltable>
     <important>
      <para>
       For the weekly seccheck password check to work, the <quote>john the
       ripper</quote> package needs to be installed yet could be considered
       a security risk in itself. It's important to understand the operation
       of john. Normally it will be used only to send notice of weak
       passwords to users as an e-mail as part of the weekly seccheck cron
       job. Since <quote>john</quote> would need to be installed separately,
       it is recommended to weigh the benefits and risks before doing so.
      </para>
     </important>
     <para>
      Additional monthly checks are also run, however the key difference is
      mainly that the monthly file is not a diff like the
      daily/weekly ones but the full reports in one file.
     </para>
    </sect2>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.retiring">
    <title>Retiring Linux Servers with Sensitive Data</title>

    <para>
<!-- As mentioned in <xref linkend="sec.setup_for_eal.operating.mount"/> -->
     Security policies usually contain some procedures for the treatment of
     storage media that is going to be retired or disposed of. Disk and media
     wipe procedures are frequently prescribed as is complete
     destruction of the media. You can find several free tools on the
     Internet. A search of <quote>dod disk wipe utility</quote> will yield
     several variants. To retire servers with sensitive data, it is important
     to ensure that data cannot be recovered from the hard disks.  To ensure
     that all traces of data are removed, a wipe utility can be used. Some of
     these tools can even be operated from a bootable removable device and
     remove data according to the U.S. Department of Defense (DoD)
     standards. Note that many government agencies specify their own standards
     for data security. Some standards are stronger than others, yet may
     require more time to implement. DiskSanitizer is just one
     of many that you can find. This utility is shareware and available to
     download at <ulink url="http://freshmeat.net/projects/disksanitizer"/>.
     <remark>sknorr, 2014-07-08: Freshmeat became Freecode, and Freecode
       was closed. In other words, this project seems to have
       become inaccessible. DBAN might be an alternative, but its page seems to
       have turned into an infomercial for Blancco (commercial).
       (http://sourceforge.net/projects/dban/)
     </remark>
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.backups">
    <title>Backups</title>

    <para>
     If your system is compromised, backups can be used to restore a
     prior system state. When bugs or accidents occur, backups can also
     be used to compare the current system against an older version.
     For production
     systems, it is very important to take some backups off-site for cases
     like disasters (for example off-site storage of tapes/recordable media, or
     off-site initiated).
    </para>

    <para>
     For legal reasons, some firms and organizations must be careful about
     backing up too much information and holding it too long. If your
     environment has a policy regarding the destruction of old paper files,
     you might have to extend this policy to Linux backup tapes as well.
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.partitions">
    <title>Disk Partitions</title>

    <para>
     Servers should have separate partitions for at least
     <filename>/</filename>, <filename>/boot</filename>,
     <filename>/usr</filename>, <filename>/var</filename>,
     <filename>/tmp</filename>, and <filename>/home</filename>. You don't
     want that for example logging and temporary space under
     <filename>/var</filename> and <filename>/tmp</filename> fill up the
     root partition. Third-party applications should be on separate
     file systems as well, for example under <filename>/opt</filename>.
    </para>

    <para>
     Review <xref linkend="part.setup_for_eal"/>. To repeat: It is important
     to understand the need to separate the partitions that could impact a
     running system (for example, log files filling up
     <filename>/var/log</filename> are a good reason to separate
     <filename>/var</filename> from the <filename>/</filename> partition).
     Another thing to keep in mind is that you will likely need to leverage
     LVM or another volume manager or at the very least the
     extended partition type to work around the limitations of primary
     partitions (4 partitions).
    </para>

    <para>
     Another capability in &productname; is encrypting a partition or even a
     single folder or file as a container. Please refer to
     <xref linkend="cha.security.cryptofs"/> for details.
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.firewall">
    <title>Firewall (iptables)</title>

    <para>
     iptables will not be covered in detail in this guide. Most
     companies use hardware based firewalls to protect their servers in a
     production network. This is strongly recommended for secure
     environments. &productname; also includes &susefirewall; which
     is a wrapper for iptables and is enabled by default as a simple and
     layered protection.
    </para>

    <para>
     If you are also interested in Linux stateful firewalls using iptables,
     there are several many guides on the Internet. See the Appendix for
     resources. For lots of iptables tutorials and examples, see
     <ulink url="http://www.linuxguruz.com/iptables/"/>. An overview is also
     available at <xref linkend="sec.security.firewall.iptables"/>.
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.kernel">
    <title>Security Features in the Kernel</title>

    <para>
     The following list shows tunable kernel parameters you can use to
     secure your Linux server against attacks. Some of them are defaults
     already within the SLE distributions. To check the current status of
     any of these settings, you can query the kernel
     (<filename>/proc/sys/...</filename> contents). For example, the Source
     Routing setting is located in the
     <filename>/proc/sys/net/ipv4/conf/all/accept_source_route</filename>
     file. Simply cat the contents of a file to see how the current running
     kernel is setup.
    </para>

    <para>
     For each tunable kernel parameter shown, the change to the entry that
     needs to be affected can be modified or added to the
     <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename> configuration file to make the
     change persistent after a reboots.
    </para>

    <para>
     You can get a list of current kernel settings by using the command:
    </para>

<screen>sysctl -a</screen>

    <para>
     It is even a very good idea to store the output of the kernel settings
     (for comparison or reference) by redirecting the output of the sysctl
     command to a file, for example
    </para>

<screen>sysctl -A &gt; /root/sysctl.settings.store</screen>

    <para>
     Because &productname; includes, by default, security-focused kernel
     tuning parameters, you will find the existing
     <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename> file to be sparsely populated.
     You may choose to use the above mentioned <quote>catalog</quote> method
     of storing the complete gamut of kernel settings and then
     choose those parameters you want to be reset at reboot. You
     can place these in the <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename> file or
     they can be inserted immediately (into the running kernel) by running
     the command <command>sysctl <option>-p</option></command> or they will
     be picked up upon a reboot.
    </para>

    <para>
     Many third-party applications like Oracle, SAP, DB2, Websphere, etc.
     recommend changing kernel parameters to ensure high performance for I/O
     or CPU processing. Having a full list of current settings can be
     helpful for reference.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.kernel_syn_cookie">
     <title>Enable TCP SYN Cookie Protection (default in &productname; 11)</title>
     <para>
      A SYN Attack is a denial of service attack that
      consumes all the resources on a machine. Any server that is connected
      to a network is potentially subject to this attack. To enable TCP SYN
      Cookie Protection, edit the <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename> file
      and ensure the following line and value exists:
     </para>
<screen>net.ipv4.tcp_syncookies = 1</screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.route">
     <title>Disable IP Source Routing (default in &productname; 11)</title>
     <para>
      Source Routing is used to specify a path or route through the network
      from source to destination. This feature can be used by network people
      for diagnosing problems. However, if an intruder was able to send a
      source routed packet into the network, then he could intercept the
      replies and your server might not know that it's not communicating
      with a trusted server.
     </para>
<screen>net.ipv4.conf.all.accept_source_route = 0</screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.icpm_redirect">
     <title>Disable ICMP Redirect Acceptance</title>
     <para>
      ICMP redirects are used by routers to tell the server that there is a
      better path to other networks than the one chosen by the server.
      However, an intruder could potentially use ICMP redirect packets to
      alter the host's routing table by causing traffic to use a path you
      didn't intend. To disable ICMP Redirect Acceptance, edit the
      <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename> file and add the following line:
     </para>
<screen>net.ipv4.conf.all.accept_redirects = 0</screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.ip_spoofing">
     <title>Enable IP Spoofing Protection (default in &productname; 11)</title>
     <para>
      IP spoofing is a technique where an intruder sends out packets which
      claim to be from another host by manipulating the source address. IP
      spoofing is very often used for denial of service attacks. For more
      information on IP Spoofing, I recommend the article <citetitle>IP
      Spoofing: Understanding the basics</citetitle>.
     </para>
<screen>net.ipv4.conf.all.rp_filter = 1</screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.icpm_ignore">
     <title>Enable Ignoring to ICMP Requests</title>
     <para>
      If you want or need Linux to ignore <command>ping</command> requests,
      edit the <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename> file and add the
      following line:
     </para>
<screen>net.ipv4.icmp_echo_ignore_all = 1</screen>
     <para>
      This cannot be done in many environments, as even some monitoring
      systems use a rudimentary ICMP (ping) to determine the health of the
      device on the network (or at least its ability to respond).
     </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.broadcast">
     <title>Enable Ignoring Broadcasts Request (default in &productname; 11)</title>
     <para>
      If you want or need Linux to ignore broadcast requests...
     </para>
<screen>net.ipv4.icmp_echo_ignore_broadcasts = 1</screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.errormsg">
     <title>Enable Bad Error Message Protection (default in &productname; 11)</title>
     <para>
      To alert you about bad error messages in the network...
     </para>
<screen>net.ipv4.icmp_ignore_bogus_error_responses = 1</screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.logging">
     <title>Enable Logging of Spoofed Packets, Source Routed Packets, Redirect Packets</title>
     <para>
      To turn on logging for Spoofed Packets, Source Routed Packets, and
      Redirect Packets, edit the <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename> file
      and add the following line:
     </para>
<screen>net.ipv4.conf.all.log_martians = 1</screen>
     <note>
      <para>
       Because of the way &productname; is set up (with syslog) for network event
       tracking, keep in mind that this can cause a large amount of messages
       to be logged.
      </para>
     </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.add_random">
     <title>Virtual Address Space Randomization</title>
     <para>
      Starting with the 2.6.x kernel releases, Linux uses the address-space
      randomization technique to mitigate buffer overflows. For more
      information, see:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <ulink
      url="http://searchopensource.techtarget.com/tip/1,289483,sid39_gci1144658,00.html"/>
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <ulink url="http://lwn.net/Articles/121845/"/>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.aa">
    <title>&aa;</title>

    <para>
     Included with &productname;, &aa; is an application security tool
     designed to provide an easy-to-use security framework for your
     applications. &aa; proactively protects the operating system and
     applications from external or internal threats, even zero-day attacks,
     by enforcing good behavior and preventing even unknown application
     flaws from being exploited. &aa; security policies, called "profiles",
     completely define what system resources individual applications can
     access, and with what privileges. A number of default profiles are
     included with &aa;, and using a combination of advanced static analysis
     and learning-based tools, &aa; profiles for even very complex
     applications can be deployed successfully in a matter of hours.
    </para>

    <para>
     &aa; consists of:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A kernel module, shipped with the &productname; kernel, which enforces
       the security profiles.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A collection of RPMs, also shipped with &productname; that provides:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         A set of &aa; profiles for numerous programs that ship with
         &productname;
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Tools to create and manage new and existing &aa; profiles
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         A &yast; user interface to manage reports and notification of
         security events
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Documentation about the &aa; tools
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
     It is best to reboot a system after completing installation, so that
     &aa; can confine all system daemons.
    </para>

    <para>
     The &aa; quick-start and administrative guides are available online
     here:
    </para>

    <para>
     <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/documentation/apparmor/"/>
    </para>

    <para>
     For additional details and step-by-step instructions on the usage and
     configuration of &aa; you can also refer to
     <xref linkend="part.apparmor"/>.
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.selinux">
    <title>SELinux</title>

    <para>
     SELinux is an advanced technology for securing Linux systems. It is included
     with <quote>basic enablement</quote> in &productname; 11, and included
     with some other distributions by default. Hardening Linux using SELinux
     technology, on its own, warrants its own security HOWTO and is out of
     scope for this guide. <citetitle>SELinux: NSA's Open Source
     Security Enhanced Linux</citetitle> contains a very good description of its
     setup and usage. As part of the <quote>basic enablement</quote>,
     SELinux will not be officially supported, but packages have now been
     added to &productname; 11 to enable its usage with minimal effort.
     While &aa; is much easier to use and has a similar feature set, knowing
     both will most certainly be beneficial.
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.remote">
    <title>FTP, <command>telnet</command>, and <command>rlogin</command> (rsh)</title>

    <para>
     The programs/protocols of FTP, <command>telnet</command>, and
     <command>rlogin</command> (rsh) are normally vulnerable to
     eavesdropping, which is one of the main reasons why secure alternatives
     such as <command>ssh</command>, <command>scp</command> or
     <command>sftp</command> should be used instead. It is highly
     recommended not to run the insecure services. Due to the high risk,
     this guide does not cover these services (other than vsftp). It would
     also be a good idea (and part of our guidance, see next section) not to
     have FTP and Telnet server RPMs installed on the system. Note that the
     EAL 4+ evaluation had vsftp installed. The <quote>vs</quote> stands for
     <quote>very secure</quote> - which is a differentiator here when
     compared to normal ftp.
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.remove_packs">
    <title>Removing Unnecessary Software Packages (RPMs)</title>

    <para>
     A very important step in securing a Linux system is to determine the
     primary function(s) or role(s) of the Linux server. Strive for a
     deterministic and specific view of what is installed and running on the
     system. Otherwise, it can be difficult to understand what needs to be
     secured and securing these Linux systems can prove
     ineffective. Therefore, it is critical to look at the default list
     of software packages and remove any unnecessary packages or
     packages that do not comply with your defined security policies.
    </para>

    <para>
     Doing this will result in fewer packages that require updates and
     will simplify maintenance efforts when security alerts and patches
     are released. It is a best practice not to install, among others,
     development packages or desktop software packages (for example, an
     X Server) on production servers. If you do not need them, you should
     also uninstall, for example, the Apache web server or Samba file
     sharing server.
    </para>

    <important>
     <title>Requirements of Third-party Installers</title>
     <para>
      Many third-party vendors like Oracle and IBM require
      a desktop environment and development libraries to run installers.
      To avoid this from having an impact on the security of their
      production servers, many organizations work around this by creating
      a silent installation (response file) in a development lab.
     </para>
    </important>

    <para>
     Also, other packages like FTP and Telnet daemons should not be
     installed as well unless there is a justified business reason for it
     (again, <command>ssh</command>, <command>scp</command> or
     <command>sftp</command> should be used as replacements).
    </para>

    <para>
     One of the first action items should be to create a Linux image that
     <emphasis>only</emphasis> contains RPMs needed by the system and
     applications, and those needed for maintenance and troubleshooting
     purposes. A good approach is to start with a minimum list of RPMs and
     then add packages as needed. This process is time-consuming but
     usually worth the effort.
    </para>

    <note>
     <title>Just Enough Operating System (JeOS)</title>
     <para>
      The &suse; Appliance Program includes a component called JeOS
      (Just Enough Operating System). JeOS has a very
      small footprint and can be customized to fit the specific needs of
      a system developer. Main uses
      of JeOS are for hardware/software appliance or virtual machine
      development. Key benefits of JeOS are efficiency, higher performance,
      increased security and simplified management.
     </para>
    </note>

    <para>
     To generate a list of all installed RPMs - use the following command:
    </para>

<screen>rpm -qa</screen>

    <para>
     To retrieve details about a particular RPM (from the RPM itself), run:
    </para>

<screen>rpm -qi <replaceable>package_name</replaceable></screen>

    <para>
     To check for and report potential conflicts and dependencies when
     deleting an RPM, run:
    </para>

<screen>rpm -e --test <replaceable>package_name</replaceable></screen>

    <para>
     This can be very useful, as running the removal command without a
     test can often yield a mass of complaints and require
     manual recursive dependency hunting.
    </para>

    <remark condition="clarity">
     2011-07-12 - fs: The following seems to be a bit out of context...
    </remark>

    <para>
     For information on performing &ay; installations and how to build an
     image, see <xref linkend="book.autoyast"/>.
<!-- &ay;
     develovers keep the &ay; documentation up to date and lists
     enhancements and differences between shipping versions of &ay; on
     ... [tbd] -->
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.patching">
    <title>Patching Linux Systems</title>

    <para>
     Building an infrastructure for the purpose of patch management is
     another very important part of a proactive and secure production Linux
     environment.
    </para>

    <para>
     It is recommended to have a written security policy and procedure to
     handle Linux security updates and issues. For example, a security
     policy should detail the time frame for assessment, testing, and roll
     out of patches. Network related security vulnerabilities should get the
     highest priority and should be addressed immediately within a short
     time frame. The assessment phase should occur within a testing lab, and
     initial roll out should occur on development systems first
    </para>

    <para>
     A separate security log should detail what Linux security notices have
     been received, when patches have been researched and assessed, when
     patches have been applied etc.
    </para>

    <para>
     At this time &suse; releases their patches in three categories, security,
     recommended and optional. There are a few options that can be used to
     keep systems patched, up to date and secure. Each individual system can
     register and then retrieve updates via the &suse; Update website using the
     included &yast; tool – &yast; Online Update. &suse; has also created the
     &smtool; (&smt;), an efficient way to maintain a local repository of
     available/released patches/updates/fixes that systems can then pull from
     (reducing Internet traffic). &suse; also offers &susemgr; for the
     maintenance, patching, reporting and centralized management of Linux
     systems, not just &suse;, but other distributions as well.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.patching.you">
     <title>&yast; Online Update</title>
     <para>
      On a per-server basis, installation of important updates and
      improvements is possible using the &yast; Online Update tool. Current
      updates for the &sle; family are available from the product specific
      update catalogs containing patches. Installation of updates and
      improvements is accomplished using &yast; and selecting
      <guimenu>Online Update</guimenu> in the <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
      Group. All new patches (except the optional ones) that are currently
      available for your system will already be marked for installation.
      Clicking <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> will then automatically install
      these patches.
     </para>
     <para>
      After installation is complete, click the <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>
      button. The system will be patched, current and up-to-date.
     </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.patching.auto">
     <title>Automatic Online Update</title>
     <para>
      &yast; also offers the possibility to set up an automatic update.
      Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Software</guimenu> <guimenu> Automatic
      Online Update</guimenu></menuchoice>. Configure a Daily or a Weekly
      update. Some patches, such as kernel updates, require user
      interaction, which would cause the automatic update procedure to stop.
      Check <guimenu>Skip Interactive Patches</guimenu> for the update
      procedure to proceed automatically.
     </para>
     <para>
      In this case, run a manual Online Update from time to install patches
      that require interaction.
     </para>
     <para>
      When <guimenu>Only Download Patches</guimenu> is checked, the patches
      are downloaded at the specified time but not installed. They must be
      installed manually. The patches are downloaded to the rug cache
      directory, <filename>/var/cache/zmd/web</filename>, by default. Use
      the command <command>rug get-prefs cache-directory</command> to get
      the current rug cache directory
     </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.patching.zlm">
     <title>ZENworks Linux Management (ZLM)</title>
     <para>
      ZENworks Linux Management lets you install, remove, and roll back
      software on your Linux devices. This is done through the use of
      bundles, which are collections of one or more software (RPM) packages.
      ZENworks automatically resolves dependencies for any software packages
      it is installing.
     </para>
     <para>
      When you assign a bundle to a device, it is automatically installed on
      the device. If you want to give the device's user the choice of
      whether to install a software package, you can use catalogs. A catalog
      is simply a group of bundles that appears in the ZENworks Linux
      Management Software Updater client on the device; the user must
      initiate installation of any of the bundles in the catalog.
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>ZLM - Policy-Based Device Management</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         ZENworks Linux Management provides a number of policies to help you
         manage the &sled;, Evolution&trade; e-mail client, Epiphany Web
         browser, and several other software applications. Policies enable
         you to provide consistent operating system and application
         configuration settings for your devices. You can lock the
         configuration settings so that users cannot change them.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>ZLM - Automated Install and Imaging</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         ZENworks Linux Management includes a service called Preboot
         Services that enables you to perform tasks on devices before their
         operating systems boot up. Using Preboot Services, you can
         automatically or manually do the following to a Linux device when
         it boots up:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
          <para>
           Run scripted installations on the device, such as &ay; and
           kickstart.
          </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
           Run ZENworks imaging scripts on the device.
          </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
           Make an image of the device's hard drives and other storage
           devices.
          </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
           Restore an image to the device.
          </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
           Apply an existing image to multiple devices.
          </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
           Update the device's BIOS.
          </para>
         </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
         To accomplish these tasks automatically, there simply needs to be a
         PXE (Preboot Execution Environment) enabled on device targets, and
         to have prebootable tasks configured and assigned to the devices .
         Then, the devices can automatically implement these tasks when they
         boot. Or, to manually implement the tasks, devices can be
         configured to require user intervention during bootup.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>ZLM - Remote Management</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         ZENworks Linux Management provides the ability to use ZENworks
         Control Center (ZCC) to remotely manage devices by using a
         graphical Web interface.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>ZLM - Inventory Collection</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         ZENworks Linux Management can gather extensive software and
         hardware inventory for all managed devices, and it also enables you
         to create and export custom reports.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>ZLM - Features Specific to Dell PowerEdge Servers</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         By combining ZENworks Linux Management capabilities with the Dell
         OpenManage toolkit capabilities, it is possible to manage Dell
         PowerEdge servers right out of the box through the entire server
         life cycle.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.patching.smt">
     <title>&smtool; - &smt;</title>
     <para>
      The &smtool;for &sle; goes one step further than the Online Update
      process by establishing a proxy system with repository and
      registration targets. This helps customers centrally manage software
      updates within the firewall on a per-system basis, while maintaining
      their corporate security policies and regulatory compliance.
     </para>
     <para>
      The downloadable &smt;
      (<ulink
       url="http://download.suse.com/"/>)
      &smt; is integrated with &ncc;
      (<ulink
       url="&sccurl;"/>) and
      provides a repository and registration target that is synchronized
      with it. This can be very helpful in tracking entitlements in large
      deployments. The &smt; maintains all the capabilities of &ncc;, while
      allowing a more secure centralized deployment. It is included with
      every &sle; subscription and is therefore fully supported.
     </para>
     <para>
      The &smt; provides an alternative to the default configuration, which
      requires opening the firewall to outbound connections for each device
      to receive updates. That requirement often violates corporate security
      policies and can be seen as a threat to regulatory compliance by some
      organizations. Through its integration with &ncc;, the &smt; ensures
      that each device can receive its appropriate updates without the need
      to open the firewall, and without any redundant bandwidth
      requirements.
     </para>
     <para>
      The &smt; also enables customers to locally track their &sle; devices
      (that is servers, desktops, or Point of Service terminals) throughout
      their enterprise. Now they can easily determine how many entitlements
      are in need of renewal at the end of a billing cycle without having to
      physically walk through the data center to manually update
      spreadsheets.
     </para>
     <para>
      The &smt; informs the &sle; devices of any available software updates.
      Each device then obtains the required software updates from the &smt;.
      The introduction of the &smt; improves the interaction among &sle;
      devices within the network and simplifies how they receive their
      system updates. The &smt; enables an infrastructure for several
      hundred &sle; devices per instance of each installation (depending on
      the specific utilization profile). This offers more accurate and
      efficient server tracking.
     </para>
     <para>
      In a nutshell, the &smtool; for &sle; provides customers with:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Assurance of firewall and regulatory compliance
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Reduced bandwidth usage during software updates
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Full support under active subscription from &suse;
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Maintenance of existing customer interface with &ncc;
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Accurate server entitlement tracking and effective measurement of
        subscription usage
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Automated process to easily tally entitlement totals (no more
        spreadsheets!)
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Simple installation process that automatically synchronizes server
        entitlement with &ncc;
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.ports">
    <title>Securing the Network - Open Network Ports Detection</title>

    <para>
     Securing a server requires that you know what it is serving; what
     services are running. Default server installations may have services
     running that aren't self apparent and open network ports that they are
     using. So, one of the most important tasks is to detect and close
     network ports that are not needed. To get a list of listening network
     ports (TCP and UDP sockets), you can use the <command>netstat</command>
     service run the following command:
    </para>

<screen>netstat -tulp</screen>

    <para>
     Be aware that <command>netstat</command> output can be wider than a
     default terminal screen. If the screen is too narrow, the options
     described above will likely cause the output to wrap and be less
     legible.
    </para>

    <para>
     Below is an example of output from the above command:
    </para>

<screen>
Proto Recv-Q Send-Q Local            Foreign         State   PID/Program
                    Address          Address                 name
tcp   0      0      *:auth           *.*             LISTEN  2328/xinetd
tcp   0      0      local[...].:smtp *.*             LISTEN  2360/sendmail:acce
tcp   0      0      *:ssh            *.*             LISTEN  2317/sshd</screen>

    <para>
     From the output above you can see that three tcp-based services are
     running and listening: xinetd, sendmail, and sshd. Sendmail should not
     be configured to listen for incoming network connections unless the
     server running it is a designated as a mail or relay server. Running a
     port scan from another server will be able to confirm that, but make
     sure to obtain proper permissions to scan/probe a machine on a
     production network.
    </para>

    <important>
     <para>
      Some organizations consider port scans without permission a security
      offense.
     </para>
    </important>

    <para>
     Using the nmap tool, just such a probe/scan can be run:
    </para>

<screen>&wsI;:~ # nmap -sTU <replaceable>remote_host</replaceable>
Starting nmap 3.70 ( http://www.insecure.org/nmap/ ) at 2004-12-10 22:51 CST
Interesting ports on &wsII; (&wsIIip;):
(The 3131 ports scanned but not shown below are in state: closed)
PORT     STATE         SERVICE
22/tcp   open          ssh
113/tcp  open          auth

Nmap run completed -- 1 IP address (1 host up) scanned in 221.669 seconds
     </screen>

    <para>
     Note that running the <command>nmap</command> command can take quite a
     while (in this example almost 4 minutes) depending on the options used.
     If you remove the UDP port scan (leave out the <option>-U</option>
     option), then <command>nmap</command> will finish the port scan nearly
     immediately. Running it on a local machine will also make it complete
     quickly. The results of <command>nmap</command> can vary widely and
     might not show all listening network sockets depending on the status of
     the &susefirewall; (or other) and if it has been setup to block any
     ports.
    </para>

    <para>
     From the sample run above, you see that the
     <systemitem
      class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem> daemon is
     listening on port auth (port 113) for <literal>IDENT</literal> (for
     more information on this service, see
     <xref
      linkend="sec.sec_prot.general.disable_xinetd_services"/>).
     You can also see that sendmail is not listening for remote incoming
     network connections.
    </para>

    <para>
     Another method (safer) to list all of the TCP and UDP sockets to which
     programs are listening (on a host) is to use the lsof command – which
     lists open files :
    </para>

<screen>&wsI;:~ # lsof -i -n | egrep 'COMMAND|LISTEN|UDP'
COMMAND  PID   USER   FD   TYPE    DEVICE SIZE/OFF NODE NAME
sshd     2317  root   3u   IPv6    6579   0t0      TCP *:ssh (LISTEN)
xinetd   2328  root   5u   IPv4    6698   0t0      TCP *:auth (LISTEN)
sendmail 2360  root   3u   IPv4    6729   0t0      TCP 127.0.0.1:smtp (LISTEN)</screen>
   </sect1>

   <!--taroth 2014-03-18: disabling section completely since systemd does not really
    have the concept of  disabling stuff in a specific runlevel/target-->

    <!--<sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.disable_services">
    <title>Disabling Runlevel Services</title>

    <para>
     One of the most important tasks is the removal of any network services
     from a systems start-up (init) process that are not needed. On &suse;
     systems you can list all services which are started at boot time using
     the following command:
    </para>

    <screen>systemctl -t service list-units</screen>

    <para>
     This command will list any service that has been enabled to start at
     any of the 7 init levels. 0 through 6 and also S (single user). Notice
     there may be quite a few services enabled on a given host, but many
     runlevel services (Stand-Alone Services) might not be for network
     related services. There are some services that are only run during the
     boot process. Make sure NOT to disable any runlevel services that are
     needed by the system to run smoothly. For example, many of these type
     of services will begin with a prefix of <literal>boot</literal>.
    </para>

    <para>
     Some examples of Runlevel System Services which you may or may not want
     to enable (check &yast; <guimenu>System Services (Runlevels)</guimenu>
     module for a complete list):
    </para>

    <table>
     <title><systemitem class="service">init</systemitem> Services and their Descriptions - Examples</title>
     <tgroup cols="2">
      <thead>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Service Name
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Description of Service
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          syslog
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          important for syslog services
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          netfs
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          needed only if there are NFS shares that should be mounted at boot
          time
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          network
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          important for starting network interfaces (for example eth0, eth1,
          bonding,...)
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          random
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          used for the system entropy pool
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          atd
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          needed if the at(1) service is used instead of cron
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          apmd
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Advanced Power Management (APM) daemon is used for laptops and
          some desktops
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          isdn
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          needed if ISDN is being used
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          iptables
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          needed if Netfilter (iptables) Firewall is being used
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          ip6tables
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          needed if ip6tables Firewall is being used
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          pcmcia
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          not needed on servers - needed for laptops
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          irqbalance
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            important for distributing interrupts across all CPUs
           </para>
          </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          sendmail
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          needed if Sendmail is used - Procmail should be used which is more
          secure
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          autofs
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          needed if automounter is used - production applications should not
          be dependent on automounter
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          sshd
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          important for logins via SSH
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          portmap
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          needed if for example NFS is being used
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          nfslock
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          needed if NFS shares are mounted
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          nfs
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            needed if server runs the NFS server
           </para>
          </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          mdmonitor
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          needed only if software RAID is being used
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          crond
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          important for running cron jobs
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          xinetd
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          needed if xinetd services are being used, see /etc/xinetd.d/ for
          list of services
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          cups
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          needed if CUPS is used for the printing system
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          rhnsd
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          needed if server should connect to RHN to check for software
          updates etc.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          sysstat
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          needed to reset system statistics logs
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          audit
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          needed only if Linux Audit Subsystem (LAuS) should run for
          collecting system call audit records
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          psacct
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          needed only if kernel process accounting information is needed
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          smartd
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          important for monitoring disk problems if hard disks support SMART
          technology
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          netdump
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            important if kernel oops data and memory dumps should be sent to
            a Netdump server for server crashes
           </para>
          </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>
     The init (start/stop) scripts of all the runlevel services are found in
     the <filename>/etc/init.d</filename> directory. For example, if you
     don't know what the atd service does, go to
     <filename>/etc/init.d</filename> and open the file
     <filename>atd</filename>. And in the script look for lines that start
     programs. In the <systemitem class="daemon">atd</systemitem> script the
     <literal>startproc $ATD_BIN $ATD_ARGS</literal> line starts the
     process <systemitem class="daemon">atd</systemitem>. Now
     having the name of the program that is started by this service, you can
     check the online pages of <systemitem class="daemon">atd</systemitem>
     by running <command>man atd</command>. This will help you to find out
     more about a system service.
    </para>

    <para>
     To permanently disable for example the service nfs, run:
    </para>

<screen>&prompt.root;systemctl disable nfs.service</screen>

    <para>
     To immediately disable the service nfs, execute:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;systemctl stop nfs.service</screen>

   </sect1>-->
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.disable_xinetd_services">
    <title><systemitem class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem> Services - Disabling</title>

    <para>
     The <systemitem class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem> daemon is a
     replacement for inetd, the Internet services daemon. It monitors the
     ports for all network services configured in
     <filename>/etc/xinetd.d</filename>, and starts the services in response
     to incoming connections. To check if
     <systemitem
       class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem> is enabled and running, execute:
    </para>
<screen>&wsI;:~ # ls/etc/chkconfig --list xinetd</screen>
<!--taroth 2014-02-13: not sure what the expected result is:
       xinetd 0:off 1:off 2:off 3:on 4:on 5:on 6:off-->
    <!--taroth 2014-03-18: systemd - according to fcrozat, xinetd is *not*
    managed by systemd, so let's keep the rc*command here for now...
    <screen>&wsI;:~ # systemctl is-enabled xinetd.service; echo $?</screen>
     <para>A value of <literal>0</literal> indicates that the service is enabled,
     <literal>1</literal> indicates that it is disabled.</para>-->
    <para>
     To check the current status of the
     <systemitem class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem> service, execute:
    </para>
<screen>&wsI;:~# /etc/init.d/xinetd status
Checking for service xinetd: xinetd (pid 2619) is running..</screen>
    <para>or just: <command>rcxinetd status</command></para>
    <!--taroth 2014-03-18: systemd - according to fcrozat, xinetd is *not*
     managed by systemd, so let's keep the rc*command here for now...
<screen>&prompt.root;systemctl status xinetd.service</screen>-->


    <para>
     If <systemitem class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem> is active, it is very
     important to see which services are active and being controlled by
     <systemitem class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem>. The following command
     will list all services configured in <filename>/etc/xinetd.d</filename>
     and whether <systemitem class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem> monitors the
     ports for these services:
    </para>

<!--taroth 2014-03-18: systemd - according to fcrozat no change here, as systemd
 does not manage xinetd-->
<screen>&wsI;:~ # chkconfig -/-list | awk '/xinetd based services/,/""/'
xinetd based services:

  chargen:     off
  chargen-udp: off
  cups-lpd:    off
  cvs:         off
  daytime:     off
  daytime-udp: off
  discard:     off
  discard-udp: off
  echo:        off
  echo-udp:    off
  netstat:     off
  rsync:       off
  sane-port:   off
  servers:     off
  services:    off
  svnserve:    off
  swat:        off
  systat:      off
  tftp:        on
  time:        off
  time-udp:    off
  vnc:         off</screen>

    <para>
     To get a list of only active services for which xinetd monitors the
     ports, you could run (where the <option>-v</option> option of grep does
     an inverse-match) :
    </para>
    <!--taroth 2014-03-18: systemd - according to fcrozat no change here, as systemd
     does not manage xinetd-->
<screen>&wsI;:~ # chkconfig --list | awk '/xinetd based services/,/""/' | grep -v off
xinetd based services:

  tftp:        on</screen>

    <para>
     In the above example you can see that the
     <systemitem
       class="resource">telnet-server</systemitem> package
     is not installed on the system. If the Telnet Server package
     <systemitem
       class="resource">telnet-server</systemitem> would be
     installed, it would show up on the list whether it is active.
     Here is an example how to disable a service. Assuming the
     <systemitem
       class="service">tftp</systemitem> service is active,
     run the following commands to disable it and to see how the telnet
     service entries are being updated:
    </para>
 <remark>taroth 2014-02-13: FIXME: SYSTEMD: @file-maintainer: "translate" command to systemd and add new output</remark>
<screen>&wsI;:~ # chkconfig -l tftp
xinetd based services:

  tftp:        on
&wsI;:~ # cat /etc/xinetd.d/tftp | grep disable
      disable = no
&wsI;:~ # chkconfig tftp off
&wsI;:~ # chkconfig --list tftp
xinetd based services:

  tftp:        off
&wsI;:~ # cat /etc/xinetd.d/tftp | grep disable
      disable = yes</screen>

    <para>
     For the TFTP service it would be better to remove the package from the
     system since removal is always safer than just disabling (when
     possible):
    </para>

<screen>rpm -e tftp</screen>

    <sect2
      id="sec.sec_prot.general.disable_xinetd_services.inventory">
     <title>Inventory <systemitem class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem> services</title>
     <para>
      It is important to investigate <emphasis>all</emphasis> active
      <systemitem class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem> services and to disable
      them (or remove their packages) if they are not needed. To find out
      what a service does, here is a viable approach. Using the
      <systemitem
       class="service">tftp</systemitem> service as an
      example and assuming its function is unknown and it is listed as an
      active service. Execute the following commands:
     </para>
<screen>&wsI;:~ # grep " server" /etc/xinetd.d/tftp
  server = /usr/sbin/in.tftpd
  server_args = -s /tftpboot</screen>
     <para>
      To read the manual:
     </para>
<screen>&wsI;:~ # man in.tftpd
TFTPD(8)               System Manager's Manual              TFTPD(8)



NAME
       tftpd - IPv4 Trivial File Transfer Protocol server

SYNOPSIS
       in.tftpd [options...]  directory...

DESCRIPTION
       tftpd  is  a  server  for the Trivial File Transfer Protocol.
       The TFTP protocol is extensively used to support remote boot-
       ing  of  diskless devices.  The server is normally started by
       inetd, but can also run stand-alone.
[...]</screen>
     <para>
      To determine what package supplies the in.tftpd binary:
     </para>
<screen>&wsI;:~ # rpm -qf /usr/sbin/in.tftpd
tftp-0.48-101.16</screen>
     <para>
      To get a description of TFTP and its usage, etc:
     </para>
<screen>&wsI;:~ # rpm -qi tftp-0.48-101.16| awk '/Description/,/""/'
Description :
The Trivial File Transfer Protocol (TFTP) is normally used only for
booting diskless workstations and for getting or saving network
component configuration files.</screen>
     <para>
      To get a list of what files are installed via the TFTP package (RPM),
      execute the rpm command with the following options:
     </para>
<screen>&wsI;:~ # rpm -ql tftp-0.48-101.16
/etc/xinetd.d/tftp
/usr/bin/tftp
/usr/sbin/in.tftpd
/usr/share/doc/packages/tftp
/usr/share/doc/packages/tftp/README
/usr/share/doc/packages/tftp/README.security
/usr/share/doc/packages/tftp/sample.rules
/usr/share/man/man1/tftp.1.gz
/usr/share/man/man8/in.tftpd.8.gz
/usr/share/man/man8/tftpd.8.gz</screen>
     <para>
      This example described what could be done to find out information
      about services (specifically ones started by
      <systemitem
        class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem>) even if an
      online manual didn't exist for the binary
      <filename>in.ftpd</filename>. This example yielded a man page – but
      you may not always find one. The RPM commands in the example are very
      commonly used for a variety of reasons. It is also possible to use the
      &yast; software management interface to retrieve all of the resultant
      information – however having a knowledge of RPM command syntax can
      save quite a bit of time. Again to disable the TFTP service, execute
      the following command:
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;systemctl disable tftp.service</screen>
     <para>
      The <systemitem class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem> daemon is quite
      flexible and has many features. Here are just a few functionalities of
      <systemitem class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem>:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Access control for TCP, UDP, and RPC services.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Access limitations based on time.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Provides mechanisms to prevent DoS attacks.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
     <para>
      For more specific information on Xinetd, review the documentation and
      usage examples at the xinetd website:
      <ulink
      url="http://www.xinetd.org/"/> and also for some xinetd
      usage tutorials:
      <ulink url="http://www.macsecurity.org/resources/xinetd/tutorial.shtml"/>
     </para>
    </sect2>
   </sect1>
   <!--taroth 2014-02-13: FIXME: systemd, commenting for now, as this section
    needs rewrite (/etc/inittab and runlevels no longer exist):

   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.inittab">
    <title>Reviewing Inittab and Boot Scripts</title>
<remark></remark>
    <para>
     The inittab file located in <filename>/etc/inittab</filename> contains
     a running <quote>tab</quote> (table) or list of which processes are to
     be started at bootup during normal system operation. Some third-party
     vendors will install an entry there to ensure the initialization and
     start-up of dependent services. For example Oracle places cluster services
     start-up entries here to ensure they start at boot time. It is
     important to review this file and verify all entries (in the
     <filename>/etc/inittab</filename>) are appropriate in your environment.
    </para>

    <para>
     It is <emphasis>highly</emphasis> recommended to trap the <keycombo>
     <keycap function="control"/> <keycap function="alt"/>
     <keycap function="delete"/> </keycombo> key sequence in order to
     prevent accidental reboots. The following command uses the sed string
     processor to find the <literal>ca::ctrlaltdel</literal> string and add
     a <literal>#</literal> symbol to the front of it. This will comment-out
     the whole line – thereby disabling the entry:
    </para>

<screen>sed -i 's/\(ca::ctrlaltdel:\)/#\1/g' /etc/inittab</screen>

    <para>
     It is generally recommended to make the default runlevel of a
     production system set to <literal>3</literal> - which means, multiuser
     <emphasis>with</emphasis> networking but <emphasis>without</emphasis>
     graphics. In other words – the X subsystem should not be running. It
     uses server compute cycles and is generally not needed. In this case,
     it should be removed – if not used. Setting the default runlevel is
     normally done via &yast; at time of installation – or by using the
     <guimenu>System Services (Runlevel)</guimenu> tool in &yast;. This tool
     will set the inittab for you, or you can make the modification manually
     (ensuring <literal>id:3:initdefault</literal> is in the inittab):
    </para>

<screen>&wsI;:~ # grep ':initdefault' /etc/inittab
id:3:initdefault:</screen>

    <para>
     To have changes in <filename>/etc/inittab</filename> become effective
     immediately, you can tell init to re-examine the
     inititab like this:
    </para>

<screen>telinit q</screen>

    <para>
     Reviewing the System Services tool in &yast; is a great way to
     determine what will be started on a system. The <guimenu>System
     Services (Runlevel)</guimenu> tool has a normal and
     <guimenu>Expert</guimenu> mode. Switch to <guimenu>Expert</guimenu> to
     see some of the boot services. These can be important for things like
     multipath, etc.
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.restrict_access">
    <title>Restricting System Access from Servers and Networks</title>

    <para>
     Normally a firewall is used to protect a server from other servers and
     networks – or to protect an environment from the server itself.
     However, you can also protect a server or more accurately, an
     individual service using a TCP wrapper (which is a function of
     <systemitem
      class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem> – already
     discussed above).
    </para>

    <para>
     The <systemitem class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem> super server that
     comes with &productname; provides a built-in TCP wrapper functionality.
     This can be used to specifically define network services to accept or
     deny incoming connections from specified hosts and networks. The TCP
     wrappers implements access control through the use of two files,
     <filename>/etc/hosts.allow</filename> and
     <filename>/etc/hosts.deny</filename>. Note that the
     <filename>hosts.allow</filename> file takes precedence over the
     <filename>hosts.deny</filename> file. And you may want to change the
     permissions on the two configuration files since they are both world
     readable. An important difference between the security provided by a
     TCP wrapper versus the use of netfilter (iptables) is that netfilter
     works at the network layer (layer 2) and can provide security before
     the traffic goes up the stack to the application layers. The trade-off
     however is that a TCP wrapper allows for the use of a
     banner - or a welcome message (per service) and some
     other things. It is best to know what an organization requires – so
     the best recommendation can be made.
    </para>

    <para>
     Generally, a best-practice strategy is to block all incoming requests
     by default, and allow only specific hosts or networks to connect.
     This is commonly called <quote>deny all, permit few</quote>. To
     use this strategy, edit the
     <filename>/etc/hosts.deny</filename> file and add the following line:
    </para>

<screen>ALL: ALL</screen>

    <para>
     Then, in order to accept incoming SSH connections from specific hosts
     (for example nodes <systemitem class="systemname">sles-ha1</systemitem>,
     <systemitem class="systemname">sles-ha2</systemitem> and
     <systemitem
      class="systemname">sles-ha3</systemitem>, modify the
     <filename>/etc/hosts.allow</filename> file and add the following line:
    </para>

<screen>sshd: sles-ha1 sles-ha2 sles-ha3</screen>

    <para>
     To accept incoming SSH connections from all servers from a specific
     network, add the name of the subnet to
     <filename>/etc/hosts.allow</filename>. Adjust the entry like this:
    </para>

<screen>sshd: sles-ha1 sles-ha2 sles-ha3 .network.&exampledomain;</screen>

    <para>
     Remember, each service can be defined separately. In order to accept
     incoming portmap connections from the host at IP address
     <literal>192.168.0.1</literal> and from the subnet
     <literal>192.168.5</literal>, the following modification can be made to
     <filename>/etc/hosts.allow</filename>:
    </para>

<screen>portmap: 192.168.0.1 192.168.5.</screen>

    <para>
     To accept connections from all servers on the subnet named
     .network.&exampledomain; but not from host
     badhost.network.&exampledomain;, add the following line to the
     <filename>/etc/hosts.allow</filename> file:
    </para>

<screen>ALL: .network.&exampledomain; EXCEPT badhost.network.&exampledomain;</screen>

    <para>
     Here are other examples that show some features of TCP wrapper: If you
     just want to restrict ssh connections without configuring or using
     <filename>/etc/hosts.deny</filename>, you can add the following entries
     to <filename>/etc/hosts.allow</filename>:
    </para>

<screen>sshd: rac1cluster rac2cluster rac3cluster
sshd: ALL: DENY</screen>

    <para>
     The version of TCP wrapper that comes with &productname; also supports
     the extended options documented in the <literal>hosts_options</literal>
     man page. Here is an example how an additional program can be spawned
     in for example the <filename>/etc/hosts.allow</filename> file:
    </para>

<screen>sshd: ALL : spawn echo "Login from %c to %s" | mail -s "Login Info for %s" log@loghost</screen>

    <para>
     For information on the % expansions, see <command>man
     hosts_access</command>.
    </para>

    <para>
     The TCP wrapper is quite flexible. And
     <systemitem class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem> provides its own set of
     host-based and time-based access control functions. You can even tell
     <systemitem class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem> to limit the rate of
     incoming connections. Various documentations about the
     <systemitem
      class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem> super daemon on
     the Internet and should be considered recommended reading. Just
     remember the trade-offs between a TCP wrapper and the &susefirewall;
     (netfilter/iptables).
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.ssh">
    <title>Securing SSH</title>

    <para>
     Many network services like telnet, rlogin, and rsh are vulnerable to
     eavesdropping which is one of several reasons why SSH should be used
     instead. The &productname; default configuration for SSH meets the
     security requirements for many environments. However, there are a few
     parameters in <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</filename> that you may
     want to change.
    </para>

    <para>
     The section on Restricting System Access from Servers and Networks
     shows how direct logins can be disabled for shared and system accounts
     including root. But it's prudent to disable direct root logins at the
     SSH level as well.
    </para>

<screen>PermitRootLogin no</screen>

    <para>
     Also ensure to have privilege separation enabled where the daemon is
     split into two parts. With privilege separation a small part of the
     code runs as root and the rest of the code runs in a chroot jail
     environment.
    </para>

<screen>UsePrivilegeSeparation yes</screen>

    <para>
     Since SSH protocol version 1 is not as secure you may want to limit the
     protocol to version 2 only:
    </para>

<screen>Protocol 2</screen>

    <para>
     You may also want to prevent SSH from setting up TCP port and X11
     forwarding if you don't need it:
    </para>

<screen>AllowTcpForwarding no
X11Forwarding no</screen>

    <para>
     Ensure the StrictModes directive is enabled which checks file
     permissions and ownerships of some important files in the user's home
     directory like <filename>~/.ssh</filename>,
     <filename>~/.ssh/authorized_keys</filename> etc. If any checks fail,
     the user won't be able to login.
    </para>

<screen>StrictModes yes</screen>

    <para>
     Ensure that all host-based authentications are disabled. These methods
     should be avoided as primary authentication.
    </para>

<screen>IgnoreRhosts yes
HostbasedAuthentication no
RhostsRSAAuthentication no</screen>

    <para>
     Disable sftp if it's not needed (by commenting it out with the
     <literal>#</literal>):
    </para>

<screen>#Subsystem sftp /usr/lib/misc/sftp-server</screen>

    <para>
     After changing any directives make sure to restart the
     <systemitem
      class="daemon">sshd</systemitem> daemon:
    </para>

<screen>/etc/init.d/sshd restart</screen>
   </sect1>-->
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.postfix">
    <title>Securing Postfix</title>

    <para>
     Postfix is a replacement for Sendmail and has several security
     advantages over Sendmail. Postfix is the default mail system in
     &productname; and consists of several small programs that each performs
     their own small task – most of these programs run in a chroot jail.
     This is another reason why Postfix is recommended over Sendmail.
    </para>

    <para>
     Linux servers that are not dedicated mail or relay servers should not
     accept external e-mails. However, it is important for production
     servers to send local e-mails to a relay server – some security
     setups (for example the seccheck scripts) can be configured to send e-mails to
     someone other than &rootuser;, even off the local system.
    </para>

    <para>
     Verify the following parameters in
     <filename>/etc/postfix/main.cf</filename> are set to ensure that
     Postfix accepts only local e-mails for delivery (look towards the
     bottom of the file as the top portion is mostly commented-out example
     entries and explanations):
    </para>

<screen>mydestination = $myhostname, localhost.$mydomain, localhost
inet_interfaces = localhost</screen>

    <para>
     The <literal>mydestination</literal> parameter lists all domains to
     receive e-mails for. The <literal>inet_interfaces</literal> parameter
     specifies the network to listen on. After reconfiguring Postfix, a
     restart of the mail system is necessary:
    </para>

<screen>&prompt.root;systemctl restart postfix.service</screen>

    <para>
     Verify that Postfix is still listening for network requests (incoming)
     by running one of these commands from another host:
    </para>

<screen>nmap -sT -p 25 <replaceable>remote_host</replaceable>
telnet &lt;remote_host&gt; 25</screen>

    <note>
     <para>
      Running these commands on the local host will provide inaccurate
      results since Postfix is supposed to accept connections from the local
      node – use an external host for correct results.
     </para>
    </note>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.nfs">
    <title>Filesystems: Securing NFS</title>

    <para>
     NFS (Network File System) allows servers to share files over a network.
     But like all network services using NFS involves risks.
    </para>

    <para>
     Here are some basic rules:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       NFS should not be enabled if not needed.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If NFS is truly needed, use a TCP wrapper to restrict. remote access
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Ensure to export only to those hosts that really need access.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use a fully qualified domain name to diminish any spoofing attempts.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Export only as read-only whenever possible.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use NFS only over TCP.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
     If you don't have shared directories to export, then ensure that the
     NFS service is <emphasis>not</emphasis> enabled nor running on the
     system:
    </para>

    <para>
     Check the nfs service status:
    </para>

<screen>&wsI;:~ # systemctl status nfsserver.service
<!--Checking for kernel based NFS server:
idmapd                                                    running
mountd                                                    unused
statd                                                     unused
nfsd                                                      unused--></screen>

    <para>
     Check the current targets:
    </para>
<!--taroth 2014-02-13: commenting due to systemd-->
<!--<screen>&wsI;:~ # chkconfig -l nfsserver
nfsserver 0:off 1:off 2:off 3:off 4:off 5:off 6:off</screen>-->

    <screen>&wsI;:~ #  ls /etc/systemd/system/*.wants/nfsserver.service</screen>
     <!--taroth 2014-02-13: not sure what the expected result is?
      maybe ls: cannot access /etc/systemd/system/*.wants/nfsserver.service: No such file or directory
      -->

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.nfs.start">
     <title>Enabling and Starting NFS Server</title>
     <para>
      If NFS must be used, it can be activated using the following commands
      on &productname; or more simply and securely with the &yast; plug-in
      (ncurses). Access it directly from command line with <command>yast
      nfs-server</command> or <command>yast nfs-client</command> – or
      manually:
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;systemctl enable nfs.service
systemctl start nfs.service</screen>
     <para>
      Portmapper information:
     </para>
<screen>&wsI;:~ # rpcinfo -p <replaceable>server</replaceable>
   program vers proto   port
    100000    2   tcp    111  portmapper
    100000    2   udp    111  portmapper
    100003    2   udp   2049  nfs
    100003    3   udp   2049  nfs
    100003    2   tcp   2049  nfs
    100003    3   tcp   2049  nfs
    100005    1   udp    623  mountd
    100005    1   tcp    626  mountd
    100005    2   udp    623  mountd
    100005    2   tcp    626  mountd
    100005    3   udp    623  mountd
    100005    3   tcp    626  mountd</screen>
     <para>
      If you run it from an "untrusted" server or network, you should get
      the following output:
     </para>
<screen>&wsI;:~ # rpcinfo -p <replaceable>server</replaceable>
No remote programs registered.</screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.nfs.export">
     <title>Exporting NFS File Systems</title>
     <para>
      To allow a client access to a filesystem or directory, the
      <filename>/etc/exports</filename> serves as the access control list.
      To give the network "network.&exampledomain;" read-only access to
      <filename>/pub</filename>, the entries in
      <filename>/etc/exports</filename> would look like as follows:
     </para>
<screen>
      /pub *.network.&exampledomain;(ro,sync)
     </screen>
     <para>
      It is very important <emphasis>not</emphasis> to give write access to
      NFS clients if not absolutely needed! Entries in
      <filename>/etc/exports</filename> are exported read-only
      (<option>ro</option> option) by default. To allow servers
      <systemitem
       class="systemname">sles-ha1</systemitem>,
      <systemitem
       class="systemname">sles-ha2</systemitem> and
      <systemitem
       class="systemname">sles-ha3</systemitem> read-write
      access to the <filename>/data/MYSQL</filename> directory, the entries
      in <filename>/etc/exports</filename> would look like as follows:
     </para>
<screen>/data/MYSQL sles-ha1.&exampledomain;(rw,sync) sles-ha2.&exampledomain;(rw,sync) sles-ha3.&exampledomain;(rw,sync)
     </screen>
     <para>
      Note that the options <emphasis>must not</emphasis> be separated from
      the host names or networks with whitespace(s). Also, fully qualified
      domain names should <emphasis>always</emphasis> be used to diminish
      spoofing attempts. All entries in <filename>/etc/exports</filename>
      are exported with the <option>root_squash</option> option (<quote>root
      squashing</quote>) by default. This means that a root user on a client
      machine does not have root privileges (root access) to root-owned
      files on exported NFS filesystems/directories. It is not recommended
      to turn <quote>root squashing</quote> off using the
      <option>no_root_squash</option> option! After you have made all your
      entries in <filename>/etc/exports</filename>, you can export all
      filesystems/directories using the following command:
     </para>
<screen>exportfs -a</screen>
     <para>
      To unexport all shared filesystems/directories, run:
     </para>
<screen>exportfs -ua</screen>
     <para>
      To see all shared filesystems/directories, run:
     </para>
<screen>&wsI;:~ # showmount -e localhost
Export list for localhost:

/pub *.network.&exampledomain;/data/MYSQL
sles-ha1.&exampledomain;,sles-ha2.&exampledomain;,sles-ha3.&exampledomain;</screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.nfs.tcp">
     <title>Using NFS over TCP</title>
     <para>
      If you need NFS, it is recommended to use NFS only over TCP since NFS
      over UDP is not secure. All 2.4 and later kernels support NFS over TCP
      on the client side. Server support for TCP appears in later 2.4
      kernels and beyond.In order to mount a shared directory using NFS over
      TCP, it is necessary to use the <option>proto=tcp</option> mount
      option:
     </para>
<screen>mount -o proto=tcp <replaceable>server_name</replaceable>:/pub /usr/local/pub
     </screen>
     <para>
      Verify that the target directory, in this case
      <filename>/usr/local/pub</filename>, exists on the client:
     </para>
     <para>
      &wsI;:~ # mount [...] <replaceable>server_name</replaceable>:/pub on
      /usr/local/pub type nfs (rw,proto=tcp,addr=&nfsip;)
     </para>
     <para>
      To have the shared directory mounted on the client at boot time, use
      the <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> file. For the above example, the
      <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> entry could look like this:
     </para>
<screen><replaceable>server_name</replaceable>:/pub /usr/local/pub nfs rsize=8192,wsize=8192,timeo=14,intr,tcp 0 0
     </screen>
    </sect2>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.scp">
    <title>Copying Files Using SSH Without Providing Login Prompts</title>

    <para>
     This example is needed in some cases in order to enable files to be
     copied over the network using ssh without providing an interactive
     login prompt. This allows trusted hosts to be set up – an example of
     federation.
    </para>

    <para>
     SSH can allow a forced command using the <quote>command</quote> option.
     Using this option it is possible to disable scp (secure copy) and
     enforce every passed ssh command to be ignored. On the server side
     where you want to retrieve the file from, add the following entry to
     the beginning of the SSH key in the
     <filename>~/.ssh/authorized_keys2</filename> file (the
     <filename>~</filename> represents a particular users
     home directory – &rootuser;'s home directory is
     <filename>/root</filename> – other users typically reside in
     <filename>/home/<replaceable>username</replaceable></filename>):
    </para>

<screen>command="/bin/cat ~/&lt;file_name&gt;" ssh-dss XXXYYYzzZ1122AAbbCC...{etc}
     </screen>

    <para>
     To copy now the file from the remote server, run the following command:
    </para>

    <para>
     ssh <replaceable>user</replaceable>@<replaceable>server</replaceable>
     <replaceable>local_file</replaceable>
    </para>

    <para>
     Since <command>/bin/cat</command> is run on the server side, its output
     has to be redirected to the local file.
    </para>

    <para>
     Another approach is to replace the <command>/bin/cat</command>
     (referenced above) with your own script that checks the passed SSH
     commands by reading the environment variable
     <envar>$SSH_ORIGINAL_COMMAND</envar>. For example:
    </para>

<screen>#!/bin/ksh
 if [[ $SSH_ORIGINAL_COMMAND = "File1" ||
       $SSH_ORIGINAL_COMMAND = "File2" ]]
 then
     /bin/cat $SSH_ORIGINAL_COMMAND
 else
     echo "Invalid file name!"
     exit 1
 fi</screen>

    <para>
     So you replace the <command>/bin/cat</command> portion with the script
     name in <filename>~/.ssh/authorized_keys2</filename>, and run the
     following command to copy <filename>Foo1</filename>:
    </para>

<screen>ssh <replaceable>user</replaceable>@<replaceable>server</replaceable> Foo1 &gt; <replaceable>local_file</replaceable></screen>

    <para>
     To copy <filename>Foo 2</filename>, run:
    </para>

<screen>ssh <replaceable>user</replaceable>@<replaceable>server</replaceable> Foo2 &gt; <replaceable>local_file</replaceable></screen>

    <para>
     With the modifications above, every other variety of passed parameters
     will return errors.
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.check_perms">
    <title>Checking File Permissions and Ownership</title>

    <para>
     The following sections deal with some of the ways in which the default
     permissions and file settings can be modified to enhance the security
     of a host. It is important to note that the use of the default
     &productname; utilities like <command>seccheck</command> - can be run
     to lock down and improve the general file security and user
     environment. However, it is beneficial to understand how to modify
     these things.
    </para>

    <para>
     &productname; hosts include 3 defaults settings for file permissions:
     <filename>permissions.easy</filename>,
     <filename>permissions.secure</filename>, and
     <filename>permissions.paranoid</filename>, all located in the
     <filename>/etc</filename> directory. The purpose of these files is to
     define special permissions, such as world-writeable directories or, for
     files, the setuser ID bit (programs with the setuser ID bit set do not
     run with the permissions of the user that has launched it, but with the
     permissions of the file owner, in most cases &rootuser;).
    </para>

    <para>
     Administrators can use the file
     <filename>/etc/permissions.local</filename> to add their own settings.
     The easiest way to implement one of the default permission rule-sets
     above is to use the <guimenu>Local Security</guimenu> module in &yast;.
    </para>

    <para>
     Each of the following topics will be modified by a selected rule-set,
     but the information is important to understand on its own.
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.umask">
    <title>Default umask</title>

    <para>
     The <command>umask</command> (user file-creation mode mask) command is
     a shell built-in command which determines the default file permissions
     for newly created files. This can be overwritten by system calls but
     many programs and utilities make use of <command>umask</command>. By
     default, &suse; sets <command>umask</command> to <literal>022</literal>.
     You can modify this by changing the value in
     <filename>/etc/profile</filename>.
    </para>

    <para>
     The <command>id</command> command will print out the current user
     identity information. Example from a non-root prompt:
    </para>

<screen>&wsI;:~ > id
uid=1000(ne0) gid=100(users) groups=16(dialout),33(video),100(users)</screen>

    <para>
     And to determine the active umask – use the umask command:
    </para>

<screen>&wsI;:~ > umask
0022</screen>

    <para>
     Now for comparison sake – the same commands from the root user:
    </para>

<screen>&wsI;:~ # id
uid=0(root) gid=0(root) groups=0(root)
&wsI;:~ # umask
0022</screen>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.s-bit">
    <title>SUID/SGID Files</title>

    <para>
     When the SUID (set user ID) or SGID (set group ID) bits are set on an
     executable, it executes with the UID or GID of the owner of the
     executable rather than that of the person executing it. This means
     that, for example, all executables that have the SUID bit set and are
     owned by root are executed with the UID of root. A good example is the
     passwd command that allows ordinary users to update the password field
     in the /etc/shadow file which is owned by root.
    </para>

    <para>
     But SUID/SGID bits can be misused when the SUID/SGID executable has a
     security hole. Therefore, you might want to search the entire system
     for SUID/SGID executables and document it. For example, ensure that
     code developers don't set SUID/SGID bits on their programs if it's not
     an absolute requirement. Very often you can use workarounds like
     removing just the executable bit for world/others. However, a better
     approach is to change the design of the software if possible.
    </para>

    <para>
     To search the entire system for SUID or SGID files, you can run the
     following command:
    </para>

<!-- fs 2011-10-17:
    This and the following find examples should probably also exclude /sys
-->

<screen>find / -path /proc -prune -o -type f -perm +6000 -ls</screen>

    <para>
     The <option>-prune</option> option in this example is used to skip the
     /proc filesystem.
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.filepermissions">
    <title>World-Writeable Files</title>

    <para>
     World-writeable files are a security risk since it allows anyone to
     modify them. Additionally, world-writeable directories allow anyone to
     add or delete files. To locate world-writeable files and directories,
     you can use the following command:
    </para>

<screen>find / -path /proc -prune -o -perm -2 ! -type l -ls</screen>

    <para>
     The <option>! -type l</option> parameter skips all symbolic links since
     symbolic links are always world-writeable. However, this is not a
     problem as long as the target of the link is not world-writeable, which
     is checked by the above find command.
    </para>

    <para>
     World-writeable directories with sticky bit such as the
     <filename>/tmp</filename> directory do not allow anyone except the
     owner of a file to delete or modify it in this directory. The sticky
     bit makes files stick to the user who created it and it prevents other
     users from deleting and renaming the files. Therefore, depending on the
     purpose of the directory world-writeable directories with sticky are
     usually not an issue. An example is the <filename>/tmp</filename>
     directory:
    </para>

<screen>&wsI;:~ > ls -ld /tmp
drwxrwxrwt 18 root root 16384 Dec 23 22:20 /tmp</screen>

    <para>
     The <literal>t</literal> mode, which denotes the sticky bit, allows
     files to be deleted and renamed only if the user is the owner of this
     file or the owner of the directory.
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.orphaned">
    <title>Orphaned or Unowned Files</title>

    <para>
     Files not owned by any user or group might not necessarily be a
     security problem in itself. However, unowned files could pose a
     security problem in the future. For example, if a new user is created
     and the new users happens to get the same UID as the unowned files
     have, then this new user will automatically become the owner of these
     files.
    </para>

    <para>
     To locate files not owned by any user or group, use the following
     command:
    </para>

<screen>find / -path /proc -prune -o -nouser -o -nogroup</screen>
   </sect1>
   <!-- ============================================================== -->
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.removable_media">
    <title>Restricting Access to Removable Media</title>
    <!-- fate#312966 -->
    <para>
     In some environments it is required to restrict access to removable
     media such as USB storage or optical devices.  The tools coming
     with the <systemitem>udisks2</systemitem> package help with such a
     configuration.
    </para>
    <procedure>
     <step>
    <para>
     In <filename>/usr/share/polkit-1/rules.d/</filename>, create a rules
     file similar to:
    </para>
<screen>// Allow users in group 'mmedia_all' to mount/unmount all type of drives
// Allow users in group 'mmedia_removable' to mount/umount USB storage drives
// Allow users in group 'mmedia_optical' to mount/unmount Optical drives
polkit.addRule(function(action, subject) {
if (/^org\.freedesktop\.udisks2\.filesystem-.*mount.*$/.test(action.id) &amp;&amp;
action.lookup("drive.removable") == "true") {
if (subject.isInGroup("mmedia_all")) {
return polkit.Result.YES;
}
else {
if (/.*optical.*/.test(action.lookup("drive.removable.media"))) {
if (subject.isInGroup("mmedia_optical"))
return polkit.Result.YES;
}
else if (/.*floppy.*/.test(action.lookup("drive.removable.media"))) {
return polkit.Result.NO;
}
else if (action.lookup("drive.removable.bus") == "usb") {
if (subject.isInGroup("mmedia_removable"))
return polkit.Result.YES;
}
return polkit.Result.NO;
}
}
});</screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Restart <systemitem>udisks2</systemitem>:
      </para>
      <screen>systemctl restart udisks2.service</screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Restart <systemitem>polkit</systemitem>
      </para>
      <screen>systemctl restart polkit.service</screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       In &yast;, click <menuchoice><guimenu>Security and
       Users</guimenu><guimenu>User and Group
       Management</guimenu><guimenu>Groups</guimenu></menuchoice> to
       create the three groups <literal>mmedia_all</literal>,
       <literal>mmedia_optical</literal>, and
       <literal>mmedia_removable</literal>.  Then add the users to these
       groups as wanted.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect1>
   <!-- ============================================================== -->
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.accounts">
    <title>Various Account Checks</title>

    <para/>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.accounts.unlocked">
     <title>Unlocked Accounts</title>
     <para>
      It is important that all system and vendor accounts that are not used
      for logins are locked.To get a list of unlocked accounts on your
      system, you can check for accounts that do <emphasis>not</emphasis>
      have an encrypted password string starting with <literal>!</literal>
      or <literal>*</literal> in the <filename>/etc/shadow</filename> file.
      If you lock an account using <command>passwd
      <option>-l</option></command>, it will put a <literal>!!</literal> in
      front of the encrypted password, effectively disabling the password.
      If you lock an account using <command>usermod
      <option>-L</option></command>, it will put a <literal>!</literal> in
      front of the encrypted password. Many system and shared accounts are
      usually locked by default by having a <literal>*</literal> or
      <literal>!!</literal> in the password field which renders the
      encrypted password into an invalid string. Hence, to get a list of all
      unlocked (encryptable) accounts, run (<command>egrep</command> is used
      to allow use of regular-expressions):
     </para>
<screen>egrep -v '.*:\*|:\!' /etc/shadow | awk -F: '{print $1}'</screen>
     <para>
      Also make sure all accounts have a <literal>x</literal> in the
      password field in <filename>/etc/passwd</filename>. The following
      command lists all accounts that do not have a <literal>x</literal> in
      the password field:
     </para>
<screen>grep -v ':x:' /etc/passwd</screen>
     <para>
      A <literal>x</literal> in the password fields means that the password
      has been shadowed, i.e. the encrypted password has to be looked up in
      the <filename>/etc/shadow</filename> file. If the password field in
      <filename>/etc/passwd</filename> is empty, then the system will not
      lookup the shadow file and it will not prompt the user for a password
      at the login prompt.
     </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.accounts.unused">
     <title>Unused Accounts</title>
     <para>
      All system or vendor accounts that are not being used by users,
      applications, by the system or by daemons should be removed from the
      system. You can use the following command to find out if there are any
      files owned by a specific account:
     </para>
<screen>find / -path /proc -prune -o -user <replaceable>account</replaceable> -ls</screen>
     <para>
      The <option>-prune</option> option in this example is used to skip the
      /proc filesystem. If you are sure that an account can be deleted, you
      can remove the account using the following command:
     </para>
<screen>userdel -r <replaceable>account</replaceable></screen>
     <para>
      Without the <option>-r</option> option userdel will not delete the
      user's home directory and mail spool
      (<filename>/var/spool/mail/<replaceable>user</replaceable></filename>).
      Note that many system accounts have no home directory.
     </para>
    </sect2>
   </sect1>
   <!--taroth 2014-03-19: systemd - commenting because according to fcrozat
    this hack is needed anymore, booting in single mode in
    systemd requires root password
    <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.single_user">
    <title>Single User Mode Password for &rootuser;</title>

    <para>
     &suse; includes the following entry in the
     <filename>/etc/inittab</filename> file to ensure that a root password
     is required for Single User Mode logins:
    </para>

<screen>~~:S:respawn:/sbin/sulogin</screen>

    <note>
     <para>
      This works well and will even restart the sulogin if terminated, but
      it can be easily circumvented!
     </para>
    </note>

    <para>
     The &grub; prompt can accept parameters allowing the execution of an
     alternate program – like the Bash shell (for example
     <option>init=/bin/bash</option>). This will place you at a root shell
     prompt without a password. This further enhances the need to password
     protect the &grub; boot loader.
<!-\- (as discussed in
     <xref linkend="cha.setup_for_eal.securing.background.boot"/>) -\->
     </para>
   </sect1>-->
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.pw_aging">
    <title>Enabling Password Aging</title>

    <para>
     Password expirations are a general best practice&mdash;but might need
     to be excluded for some system and shared accounts (for example Oracle, etc.).
     Expiring password on those accounts could lead to system outages if the
     application account expires.
    </para>

    <para>
     Typically a corporate policy should be developed that dictates
     rules/procedures regarding password changes for system and shared
     accounts. However, normal user account passwords should expire
     automatically. The following example shows how password expiration can
     be setup for individual user accounts.
    </para>

    <para>
     The following files and parameters in the table can be used when a new
     account is created with the <command>useradd</command> command.
     Settings such as these are stored for each user account in the
     <filename>/etc/shadow</filename> file. If using the &yast; tool
     (<guimenu>User and Group Management</guimenu>) to add users, the
     settings are available on a per-user basis. Here are the various
     settings&mdash;some of which can also be system-wide (for example modification
     of <filename>/etc/login.defs</filename> and
     <filename>/etc/default/useradd</filename>):
    </para>

    <informaltable>
     <tgroup cols="3">
      <tbody>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          <filename>/etc/login.defs</filename>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          <literal>PASS_MAX_DAYS</literal>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Maximum number of days a password is valid.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          <filename>/etc/login.defs</filename>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          <literal>PASS_MIN_DAYS</literal>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Minimum number of days before a user can change the password since
          the last change.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          <filename>/etc/login.defs</filename>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          <literal>PASS_WARN_AGE</literal>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Number of days when the password change reminder starts.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          <filename>/etc/default/useradd</filename>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          <literal>INACTIVE</literal>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Number of days after password expiration that account is disabled.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          <filename>/etc/default/useradd</filename>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          <literal>EXPIRE</literal>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          Account expiration date in the format YYYY-MM-DD.
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <note>
     <para>
      Users created prior to these modifications will not be affected.
     </para>
    </note>

    <para>
     Ensure that the above parameters are changed in the
     <filename>/etc/login.defs</filename> and
     <filename>/etc/default/useradd</filename> files. Review of the
     <filename>/etc/shadow</filename> file will show how these settings get
     stored after adding a user.
    </para>

    <para>
     To create a new user account, execute the following command:
    </para>

<screen>useradd -c "<replaceable>Test User</replaceable>" -g <replaceable>users</replaceable><replaceable>test</replaceable></screen>

    <para>
     The <option>-g</option> option specifies the primary group for this
     account:
    </para>

<screen>&wsI;:~ # id <replaceable>test</replaceable>
uid=509(test) gid=100(users) groups=100(users)</screen>

    <para>
     The settings in <filename>/etc/login.defs</filename> and
     <filename>/etc/default/useradd</filename> are recorded for the test
     user in the <filename>/etc/shadow</filename> file as follows:
    </para>

<screen>&wsI;:~ # grep <replaceable>test</replaceable> /etc/shadow
test:!!:12742:7:60:7:14::</screen>

    <para>
     Password aging can be modified at any time by use of the
     <command>chage</command> command. To disable password aging for system
     and shared accounts, you can run the following chage command:
    </para>

<screen>
     chage -M 99999 <replaceable>system_account_name</replaceable></screen>

    <para>
     To get password expiration information:
    </para>

<screen>chage -l <replaceable>system_account_name</replaceable></screen>

    <para>
     For example:
    </para>

<screen>&wsI;:~ # chage -l <replaceable>test</replaceable>
Minimum: 7
Maximum: 60
Warning: 7
Inactive: 14
Last Change: Jan 11, 2011
Password Expires: Mar 12, 2011
Password Inactive: Mar 26, 2011
Account Expires: Never</screen>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.pw_strength">
    <title>Stronger Password Enforcement</title>

    <para>
     On an audited system it is important to restrict people from using
     simple passwords that can be cracked too easily. However, if the
     passwords being enforced are too strong, people will write them down.
     Strong passwords that are written down are not much safer than weak
     passwords. Some will argue that strong passwords protect you against
     dictionary attacks and those type of attacks can be defeated by locking
     accounts after a few failed attempts. However, this is not always an
     option. If set up like this, locking system accounts could bring down
     your applications and systems which would be nothing short of a denial
     of service attack – another issue.
    </para>

    <para>
     At any rate, it is important to practice effective password management
     safety. Most companies require that passwords have at the very least a
     number, another alpha character, and one upper case letter. Policies
     vary – but maintaining a balance between password strength/complexity
     and management is sometimes difficult.
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.general.pam">
    <title>Leveraging an Effective PAM stack</title>

    <para>
     Linux-PAM (Pluggable Authentication Modules for Linux) is a suite of
     shared libraries that enable the local system administrator to choose
     how applications authenticate users.
    </para>

    <para>
     It is strongly recommended to familiarize oneself with the capabilities
     of PAM – and how this architecture can be leveraged to provide the
     best authentication setup for an environment. This
     configuration can be done once – and implemented across all systems
     (a standard) or can be enhanced for individual hosts (enhanced security
     – by host / service / application). The key is to realize how
     flexible the architecture is and how incredibly flexible it is.
    </para>

    <para>
     To learn more about the PAM architecture – you can find PAM
     documentation on a &productname; system in the
     <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/pam</filename> directory (in a
     variety of formats).
    </para>

    <para>
     The following discussions are examples of how to modify the default PAM
     stacks&mdash;specifically around password policies&mdash;for example password
     strength, password re-use and account locking. While these are only a
     few of the possibilities, they serve as a good start and demonstrate
     PAM's flexibility.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.pam.pw_strength">
     <title>Password Strength</title>
     <para>
      &productname; can leverage the
      <systemitem
       class="library">pam_cracklib</systemitem> library
      to test for weak passwords – and to suggest using a stronger one if
      it determines obvious weakness. The following parameters represent an
      example or policy that could be part of a corporate password policy or
      something required due to audit constraints.
     </para>
     <para>
      The PAM libraries follow a defined flow. In
      most cases, the best way to design the perfect stack is to consider
      all of the requirements and policies and draw out a flow chart.
     </para>
     <table>
      <title>Sample rules/constraints for password enforcement</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
       <tbody>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           <systemitem class="library">pam_cracklib.so</systemitem>
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           <literal>minlen=8</literal>
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           Minimum length of password is 8
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           <systemitem class="library">pam_cracklib.so</systemitem>
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           <literal>lcredit=-1</literal>
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           Minimum number of lower case letters is 1
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           <systemitem class="library">pam_cracklib.so</systemitem>
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           <literal>ucredit=-1</literal>
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           Minimum number of upper case letters is 1
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           <systemitem class="library">pam_cracklib.so</systemitem>
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           <literal>dcredit=-1</literal>
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           Minimum number of digits is 1
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry>
          <para>
           <systemitem class="library">pam_cracklib.so</systemitem>
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           <literal>ocredit=-1</literal>
          </para>
         </entry>
         <entry>
          <para>
           Minimum number of other characters is 1
          </para>
         </entry>
        </row>
       </tbody>
      </tgroup>
     </table>
     <para>
      To set up these password restrictions, use the
      <command>pam-config</command> tool and specify the parameters you want
      to configure. For example, the minimum length parameter could be
      modified like this:
     </para>
<screen>pam-config --cracklib-minlen=8</screen>
     <para>
      The other parameters are : <option>--cracklib-lcredit=-1</option>,
      <option>--cracklib-ucredit=-1</option>,
      <option>--cracklib-dcredit=-1</option>, etc.
     </para>
     <para>
      Now verify that the new password restrictions work for new passwords.
      Simply login to a non-root account and change the password using the
      <command>passwd</command> command. Note that the above requirements
      are not enforced if you run the <command>passwd</command> command
      under root.
     </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.pam.pw_previous">
     <title>Restricting Use of Previous Passwords</title>
     <para>
      The <systemitem>pam_unix2</systemitem> module parameter remember can
      be used to configure the number of previous passwords that cannot be
      reused. And the <systemitem>pam_cracklib</systemitem> module parameter
      <literal>difok</literal> can be used to specify the number of
      characters that must be different between the old and the new
      password.
     </para>
     <para>
      The following example describes how to implement password restrictions
      on a system so that a password cannot be reused for at least 6 months
      and that at least 3 characters must be different between the old and
      new password.
     </para>
     <para>
      Recall that in the section
      <xref
       linkend="sec.sec_prot.general.pw_aging"/> we set
      <literal>PASS_MIN_DAYS</literal> to <literal>7</literal>, which
      specifies the minimum number of days allowed between password changes.
      Therefore, if <systemitem>pam_unix2</systemitem> is configured to
      remember <literal>26</literal> passwords, then the previously used
      passwords cannot be reused for at least 6 months (26*7 days).
     </para>
     <para>
      Here is an example of an enhanced pam stack. It is possible to edit
      the <filename>/etc/pam.d/common-auth</filename> file to add/change
      modules used and how they react. Consider the following
      <systemitem>pam_cracklib</systemitem> and
      <systemitem>pam_unix2</systemitem> arguments&mdash;keeping in mind how
      the pam rules are processed:
     </para>
<screen>auth        required      pam_env.so
auth        sufficient    pam_unix2.so likeauth nullok
auth        required      pam_deny.so
account     required      pam_unix2.so
account     sufficient    pam_succeed_if.so uid &lt; 100 quiet
account     required      pam_permit.so
password    requisite     pam_cracklib.so retry=3 minlen=8 lcredit=-1
                             ucredit=-1 dcredit=-1 ocredit=-1 difok=3
password    sufficient    pam_unix2.so nullok use_authtok md5 shadow
                             remember=26
password    required      pam_deny.so
session     required      pam_limits.so
session     required      pam_unix2.so</screen>
     <note>
      <title><filename>/etc/security/opasswd</filename></title>
      <para>
       If the /etc/security/opasswd doesn't exist, create the file.
      </para>
<screen>&wsI;:~ # ls -l /etc/security/opasswd
-rw------- 1 root root 0 Dec 8 06:54 /etc/security/opasswd</screen>
     </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.general.pam.lock_accounts">
     <title>Locking User Accounts After Too Many Login Failures</title>
     <para>
      It is not generally recommend that a host automatically locks system
      and shared accounts after too many failed login or su attempts. This
      could lead to outages if the application's account gets locked due to
      too many login failures like in this example for an Oracle shared
      account:
     </para>
<screen>&wsI;:~ # su oracle -c id
su: incorrect password</screen>
     <para>
      This could be an easy target for a denial of service attack. The
      following example shows how to lock only individual user accounts
      after too many failed su or login attempts. Add the following two
      lines to the <filename>/etc/pam.d/common-auth</filename>:
     </para>
<screen>auth      required      pam_tally.so onerr=fail no_magic_root
[...]
auth      required     pam_tally.so per_user deny=5 no_magic_root reset
     </screen>
     <para>
      The first added line counts failed login and failed su attempts for
      each user. The default location for attempted accesses is recorded in
      <filename>/var/log/faillog</filename>.
     </para>
     <para>
      The second added line specifies to lock accounts automatically after
      <literal>5</literal> failed login or su attempts
      (<literal>deny=5</literal>). The counter will be reset to 0 (reset) on
      successful entry if
      <literal>deny=<replaceable>n</replaceable></literal> was not exceeded.
      But you don't want system or shared accounts to be locked after too
      many login failures (denial of service attack).
     </para>
     <para>
      It is also possible to add the
      <literal>lock_time=<replaceable>n</replaceable></literal> parameter,
      and then optionally the
      <literal>unlock_time=<replaceable>n</replaceable></literal> parameter.
      For example, setting the <literal>lock_time=60</literal> would deny
      access for 60 seconds after a failed attempt. The
      <literal>unlock_time=<replaceable>n</replaceable></literal> option
      would then allow access after n seconds after an account has been
      locked. If this option is used the user will be locked out for the
      specified amount of time after he exceeded his maximum allowed
      attempts. Otherwise the account is locked until the lock is removed by
      a manual intervention of the system administrator. See the
      <literal>pam_tally</literal> man page for more information.
     </para>
     <para>
      To exempt system and shared accounts from the
      <literal>deny=<replaceable>n</replaceable></literal> parameter, the
      per_user parameter was added to the module. The per_user parameter
      instructs the module <emphasis>not</emphasis> to use the
      <literal>deny=<replaceable>n</replaceable></literal> limit for
      accounts where the maximum number of login failures is set explicitly.
      For example:
     </para>
<screen>&wsI;:~ # faillog -u oracle -m -1
    Username   Failures  Maximum  Latest
    oracle     0         -1       Fri Dec 10 23:57:55 -0600 2005 on unknown</screen>
     <para>
      The faillog command with the option <option>-m -1</option> has the
      effect of not placing a limit on the number of failed
      logins&mdash;effectively disabling the option. To instruct the module
      to activate the <literal>deny=<replaceable>n</replaceable></literal>
      limit for this account again, run:
     </para>
<screen>faillog -u oracle -m 0</screen>
     <para>
      By default, the maximum number of login failures for each account is
      set to zero (0) which instructs pam_tally to leverage the
      <literal>deny=<replaceable>n</replaceable></literal> parameter. To see
      failed login attempts, run:
     </para>
<screen>faillog</screen>
     <para>
      To unlock a locked account (after too many login failures), use the
      <option>-r</option> option:
     </para>
<screen>faillog -u <replaceable>user</replaceable> -r</screen>
     <para>
      Make sure to test these changes (and <emphasis>any</emphasis> changes
      – for that matter) thoroughly on your system using ssh and su, and
      make sure the &rootuser; id does not get locked! To lock/unlock
      accounts manually, you can run one of the following commands:
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Locking</term>
       <listitem>
<screen>passwd -l <replaceable>user</replaceable>
         usermod -L <replaceable>user</replaceable></screen>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Unlocking</term>
       <listitem>
<screen>passwd -u <replaceable>user</replaceable>
usermod -U <replaceable>user</replaceable></screen>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </sect2>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.dos">
    <title>Preventing Accidental Denial of Service</title>

    <para>
     Linux allows you to set limits on the amount of system resources that
     users and groups can consume. This is also very handy if bugs in
     programs cause them to use up too much resources (for example memory leaks),
     slow down the machine, or even render the system unusable. Incorrect
     settings can allow programs to use too many resources which may make
     the server unresponsive to new connections or even local logins (for example
     if a program uses up all available file handles on the host). This can
     also be a security concern if someone is allowed to consume all system
     resources and therefore cause a denial of service attack – either
     unplanned or worse, planned. Setting resource limits for users and
     groups may be an effective way to protect systems, depending on the
     environment.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.dos_restrict_ressources">
     <title>Example for Restricting System Resources</title>
     <para>
      The following example demonstrates the practical usage of setting or
      restricting system resource consumption for an Oracle user account.
      For a list of system resource settings, see
      <filename>/etc/security/limits.conf</filename> or <command>man
      limits.conf</command>.
     </para>
     <para>
      Most shells like Bash provide control over various resources (for example the
      maximum allowable number of open file descriptors or the maximum
      number of processes) that are available on a per/user basis. To
      examine all current limits in the shell execute:
     </para>
<screen>ulimit -a</screen>
     <para>
      For more information on <command>ulimit</command> for the Bash shell,
      examine the Bash man pages.
     </para>
     <important>
      <title>Setting Limits for SSH Sessions</title>
      <para>
       Setting "hard" and "soft" limits might not behave as expected when
       using an SSH session. To see valid behavior it may be necessary to
       login as root and then su to the id with limits (for example, <literal>oracle</literal> in these
       examples). Resource limits should also work assuming the application
       has been started automatically during the boot process. It may be
       necessary to set UsePrivilegeSeparation in /etc/ssh/sshd_config to
       "no" and restart the SSH daemon (rcsshd restart) if it seems that the
       changes to resource limits are not working (via SSH). However this is
       not generally recommended – as it weakens a systems security.
      </para>
     </important>
     <para>
      In this example, a change to the number of file handles or open files
      that the user <literal>oracle</literal> can use is made by editing
      <filename>/etc/security/limits.conf</filename> as &rootuser; making
      the following changes:
     </para>
<screen>oracle           soft    nofile          4096
oracle           hard    nofile          63536</screen>
     <para>
      The soft limit in the first line defines the number of
      file handles (open files) that the
      <systemitem
       class="username">oracle</systemitem> user will have
      after login. If the user sees error messages about running out of file
      handles, then the user can increase the number of file handles like in
      this example up to the hard limit (in this example
      63536) by executing:
     </para>
<screen>ulimit -n 63536</screen>
     <para>
      You can set the soft and hard limits
      higher if necessary.
     </para>
     <note>
      <para>
       It is important to be judicious with the usage of ulimits –
       allowing a "hard" limit for <quote>nofile</quote> for a user that
       equals the kernel limit (<filename>/proc/sys/fs/file-max</filename>)
       is very bad! If the user consumes all the available file handles –
       the system will not be able to initiate new logins as accessing
       (opening) PAM modules which are required for performing a login will
       not be possible.
      </para>
     </note>
     <para>
      You also need to ensure that <literal>pam_limits</literal> is
      configured in <filename>/etc/pam.d/common-auth</filename>, or in an
      individual service (like SSH, su, login, telnet, etc.) config:
     </para>
     <simplelist>
      <member><filename>/etc/pam.d/sshd</filename> (for SSH)</member>
      <member><filename>/etc/pam.d/su</filename> (for su)</member>
      <member><filename>/etc/pam.d/login</filename> (local logins and telnet)</member>
     </simplelist>
     <para>
      If you don't want to enable it for all logins, there is a specific PAM
      module that will read the
      <filename>/etc/security/limits.conf</filename> file. Entries in pam
      configuration directives will have entries like:
     </para>
<screen>session     required      /lib/security/pam_limits.so
session     required      /lib/security/pam_unix.so</screen>
     <para>
      It is important to note that changes are not immediate and require a
      new login session:
     </para>
<screen>&wsI;:~ # su – oracle
&wsI;:~ > ulimit -n
4096</screen>
     <para>
      Note that these examples are specific to the Bash shell -
      <command>ulimit</command> options are different for other shells. The
      default limit for the user <literal>oracle</literal> is
      <literal>4096</literal>. To increase the number of file handles
      the user <literal>oracle</literal> can use to
      <literal>63536</literal>, do:
     </para>
<screen>&wsI;:~ # su – oracle
&wsI;:~ > ulimit -n
4096
&wsI;:~ > ulimit -n 63536
&wsI;:~ > ulimit -n
63536</screen>
     <para>
      Making this permanent requires the addition of the setting,
      <literal>ulimit -n 63536</literal>, (again, for Bash) to the users
      profile (<filename>~/.bashrc</filename> or
      <filename>~/.profile</filename> file) which is the user start-up file
      for the Bash shell on &productname; (to verify your shell run: echo
      <envar>$SHELL</envar>). To do this you could simply type (or
      copy/paste – if you are reading this on the system) the following
      commands for the Bash shell of the user <literal>oracle</literal>:
     </para>
<screen>&wsI;:~ # su - oracle
&wsI;:~ > cat &gt;&gt; ~oracle/.bash_profile &lt;&lt; EOF
ulimit -n 63536
EOF</screen>
    </sect2>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.banners">
    <title>Displaying Login Banners</title>

    <para>
     In many cases, it is necessary to place a banner on login screens
     on all servers for legal/audit policy reasons and to deter
     intruders etc.
    </para>

    <para>
     If you want to print a legal banner after a user logs in using SSH,
     local console etc., you can leverage the <filename>/etc/motd</filename>
     (motd = message of the day) file. The file exists on &suse; – however
     it is empty. Simply add content to the file that is applicable/required
     by the organization.
    </para>

    <note>
     <title>Banner Length</title>
     <para>
      Try to keep the content to a single page (or less) – as it will
      scroll the screen if it does not fit.
     </para>
    </note>

    <para>
     For SSH you can edit the <quote>Banner</quote> parameter in the
     <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</filename> file which will then
     appropriately display the banner text before the login prompt. For
     local console logins you can edit the <filename>/etc/issue</filename>
     file which will display the banner before the login prompt. For GDM, you
     could make the following changes to require a user to acknowledge the
     legal banner by selecting <guimenu>Yes</guimenu> or <guimenu>No</guimenu>. Edit the
     <filename>/etc/gdm/PreSession/Default</filename> file and add the
     following lines at the beginning of the script:
    </para>

<screen>if ! gdialog --yesno '\n<replaceable>This system is classified...</replaceable>\n' 10 10; then
    sleep 10
    exit 1;
fi</screen>

    <para>
     The <replaceable>This system is classified...</replaceable>
     test should be replaced with the valid text. It is important to
     note that this dialog will not prevent a login from progressing. The
     existence of a <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu> button is merely incidental.
     <remark>sknorr, 2014-04-08: Do the second and third sentence make
       sense together? They seem to be either contradictory or
       unrelated.
     </remark>
    </para>
   </sect1>
   <sect1 id="sec.sec_prot.misc">
    <title>Miscellaneous</title>

    <para/>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.misc.aide">
     <title>Host-Based Linux Monitoring and Intrusion Detection</title>
     <para>
      Before you place a host into production or even on a network, consider
      the use of an system integrity checker – like
      <command>seccheck</command> (already discussed in
      <xref
       linkend="sec.sec_prot.general.seccheck"/>)&mdash;so in
      the event of unauthorized changes, notifications can happen. Also
      consider the use of an intrusion detection environment, like AIDE –
      the Advanced Intrusion Detection Environment.
     </para>
     <para>
      AIDE is a GPL licensed and open source intrusion detection system. It
      could be considered a system fingerprinting mechanism.
      AIDE works by creating a database containing information about the
      files on your system. The database is created from rules laid out in
      the configuration file aide.conf. When AIDE is run, this database is
      referenced to check for changes (or created for the first time).
      Assuming a comparison check is being run, any changes not permitted by
      the configuration file are reported.
     </para>
     <para>
      By leveraging AIDE&mdash;storing a copy of the host's database in a
      secure location&mdash;and comparing it (on a scheduled basis or as
      part of a forensic effort), system integrity/insurance can be a matter
      of heuristics and procedure. If an intruder compromises your system
      you the comparison effort will enable an administrator or security
      officer to know what has changed on the host. The initial database
      should be created as a final step – <emphasis>before</emphasis> a
      system gets deployed into production.
     </para>
     <para>
      It is outside the scope of this article to cover Linux Monitoring and
      detailed Intrusion Detection systems (IDS) or solutions – however
      there is a plethora of information of configuring AIDE or other
      solutions and many informative articles on the web.
     </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.misc.account_utils">
     <title>Connect Accounting Utilities</title>
     <para>
      Here is a list of commands you can use to get data about user logins:
     </para>
     <formalpara>
      <title><command>who</command></title>
      <para>
       Shows a listing of currently logged-in users.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title><command>w</command></title>
      <para>
       Shows who is logged on and what they are doing.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title><command>last</command></title>
      <para>
       Shows a list of last logged-in users, including login time, logout
       time, login IP address, etc.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title><command>lastb</command></title>
      <para>
       Same as <command>last</command>, except that by default it shows a
       log of the file <filename>/var/log/btmp</filename>, which contains
       all the bad login attempts.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title><command>lastlog</command></title>
      <para>
       This command reports data maintained in
       <filename>/var/log/lastlog</filename>, which is a record of the last
       time a user logged in.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title><command>ac</command></title>
      <para>
       Prints out the connect time in hours on a per-user basis or daily
       basis etc. This command reads <filename>/var/log/wtmp</filename>.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title><command>dump-utmp</command></title>
      <para>
       Converts raw data from /var/run/utmp or
       <filename>/var/log/wtmp</filename> into ASCII-parseable format.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <para>
      Also check the <filename>/var/log/messages</filename> file, or the output
      of <command>journalctl</command> if no logging facility is running. See
      <xref linkend="cha.journalctl"/> for more information on
      the &systemd; journal.
     </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sec_prot.misc.other">
     <title>Other</title>
     <para>
      Finally, the following couple items might not be (specifically)
      security related, but misconfiguration can cause many problems – and
      should be reviewed:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Resolver (<filename>/etc/hosts</filename>,
        <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename>,
        <filename>/etc/nsswitch.conf</filename>).
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        NTP configuration (<filename>/etc/ntp.conf</filename>).
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
   </sect1>
  </chapter>
 </part>
</book>
