<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha.addon_creator"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Creating Add-on Products With &addoncreator;</title>
 <info>
      <abstract>
        <para>
    An add-on is a special designed media, usually a CD or DVD, to extend
    &productname; with your product. The &addoncreator; was developed
    to support customers and partners and simplify third-party software
    distribution for all &suse; products.
   </para>
        <para>
    To be able to use the &addoncreator; you need to install the package
    <systemitem class="resource">yast2-add-on-creator</systemitem> from the
    &sdk;. The SDK is an add-on product for &sle; and is available for
    download from <link xlink:href="http://download.suse.com/"/>. Search for
    <literal>&sle; Software Development Kit</literal>.
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
        </dm:bugtracker>
      </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.addon_creator.creating">
  <title>Creating Images</title>

  <para>
   To create an image of an add-on product, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start &yast; and open the <guimenu>Add-on Creator</guimenu> module.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If you have not created an add-on before, click <guimenu>Create an
     Add-on from the Beginning</guimenu> to start. Alternatively, you may
     create the add-on based on an existing add-on product.Specify the path
     to the directory containing the data&mdash;this may also be a
     mounted iso image or a CD/DVD.
    </para>
    <para>
     In case you have already created an add-On, the window shows a list of
     all existing add-ons. You may <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> or
     <guimenu>Delete</guimenu> them. Choose <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to create
     a new one.
    </para>
    <para>
     This tutorial explains how to <guimenu>Create an Add-on from the
     Beginning</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the name (<guimenu>Add-on Product Label</guimenu>) and the
     version of your add-on and provide additional information:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Under <guimenu>Required Product</guimenu> choose the &suse; Linux
       product for which to create the add-on.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Select the path to a directory containing the add-on product
       packages.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Optionally, choose the path to a directory containing RPM packages
       from the <guimenu>Required Product</guimenu>. Typically, these
       packages originate in the required product (already chosen) and are
       not part of the add-on itself, but other packages from the add-on
       depend on them. These packages will not be added to the add-on
       product, but can be used to create patterns.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Each installation media contains a content file and a product file
     defining the add-on product. Use this dialog to provide the data for
     both files. Select an entry and choose <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> to set
     or change a value. Alternatively, double-click an entry. See
     <guimenu>Help</guimenu> for more information and possible values.
    </para>
    <para>
     To import values from an existing content or product file, choose the
     respective <guimenu>Import</guimenu> button.
    </para>
    <para>
     You need to at least enter values for <guimenu>Product
     architectures</guimenu>, <guimenu>Product name</guimenu> and
     <guimenu>Vendor name</guimenu> of the content file. Proceed with
     <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter or change the package descriptions on the next screen. Use
     <guimenu>Add Language</guimenu> to insert a new language and add
     translated descriptions (this step is optional). You may also
     <guimenu>Import</guimenu> existing package descriptions.
    </para>
    <para>
     Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Optionally, add patterns in the next step. With patterns you can group
     your RPM packages. Use <guimenu>New</guimenu> to add a new pattern name
     and change the respective attributes in the list below. Check
     <guimenu>Required Pattern</guimenu> for patterns that will
     automatically be selected for installation when installing the add-on
     product.
    </para>
    <para>
     Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Provide a path to the output directory. If you rather want to create an
     iso image, check <guimenu>Create ISO Image</guimenu> and provide a file
     name. Select <guimenu>Create Changelog</guimenu> to create a file
     containing the changelog entries of all packages included in your
     product. Additionally, you can modify the workflow and add files:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use <guimenu>Configure Workflow</guimenu> to enter files to customize
       your product workflow. This way you can, for example, insert
       additional dialogs with options into the add-on installation process
       that are needed for the correct product operation. See
       <guimenu>Help</guimenu> for more information.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use <guimenu>Optional Files</guimenu> to the following files to your
       add-on product:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
        <term><guimenu>info.txt</guimenu>
        </term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          A text file containing general information about the add-on
          product.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term><guimenu>License Files</guimenu>
        </term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Add files containing license information in various languages. The
          files are named
          <literal>license.<replaceable>LANGUAGE</replaceable></literal>,
          for example <filename>license.en_US</filename>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>README Files</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Add README files with a name of your choice.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>
       Enter the content of the files in the respective text boxes.
       Alternatively, <guimenu>Import</guimenu> the content from an existing
       file.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Sign your add-on product with your &gpg; key to provide evidence of
     the origin of your product. If you do not have a key, create one first
     and enter the respective passphrase twice.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Check your settings in the configuration summary and proceed with
     <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>. Choose the <guimenu>Back</guimenu> buttons
     to change a setting.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.addon_creator.structure">
  <title>Add-on Structure</title>

  <para>
   An add-on product contains the following files and directories:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename>ARCHIVES.gz</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Contains information about all packages included (the output of
      <command>rpm -qil</command> for each package). This file is compressed
      with gzip.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename>Changelog</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Contains all the changes of the RPM files ordered by date of change.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename>content</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The content file created during the add-on setup.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename>content.asc</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The &gpg; signature file.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename>content.key</filename>,
      <filename>gpg-pubkey-<replaceable>NUMBER</replaceable>.asc</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The public &gpg; key.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename>INDEX.gz</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A list of all RPM files. This file is compressed with gzip.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename>ls-lR.gz</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A list of all files and directories of the add-on product medium. This
      file is compressed with gzip.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename>media.<replaceable>N</replaceable>/</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Contains files with basic information about the add-on media set. The
      directory is numbered, so <filename>media.1/</filename> is for the
      first add-on medium (for example DVD1). Additional media have a
      consecutive number.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename>suse/</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Contains sub directories with architecture-specific information.
      Exceptions are <filename>noarch/</filename> for
      architecture-independent packages, and <filename>src/</filename> for
      source packages. Proprietary software packages are stored under
      <filename>nosrc/</filename>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
