<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!-- FIXME:
     fs 2014-05-12: local smt servers are recognized automatically after
                    having registered - can be chosen from list
                    or Cancel to use default server
     fs 2014-05-12: Performing Installation tabs:
                    * Slideshow (default)
                    * Details
                    * Release Notes
-->


<chapter id="cha.inst">
 <title>Installation with &yast;</title>
 <abstract>
  <para os="sles">
   After your hardware has been prepared for the installation of
   &productnamereg; as described in <xref linkend="part.archspec"/> and
   after the connection with the installation system has been established,
   you are presented with the interface of &productname;'s system assistant
   &yast;. &yast; guides you through the entire installation.
  </para>

  <para os="sled">
   Install your &productnamereg; system with &yast;, the central tool for
   installation and configuration of your system. &yast; guides you through
   the installation process of your system. If you are a first-time user of
   &productname;, you might want to follow the default &yast; proposals in
   most parts, but you can also adjust the settings as described here to
   fine-tune your system according to your preferences. Help for each
   installation step is provided by clicking <guimenu>Help</guimenu>.
  </para>
  <para>
   During the installation process, &yast; analyzes both your current system
   settings and your hardware components. Based on this analysis your system
   will be set up with a basic configuration including networking (provided
   the system could be configured using DHCP). To fine-tune the system after
   the installation has finished, start &yast; from the installed system. 
  </para>
 </abstract>
 
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.method">
  <title>Choosing the Installation Method</title>

  <para>
   After having selected the installation medium, determine the suitable
   installation method and boot option that best matches your needs:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry id="sec.i.yast2.source.cd">
    <term>Installing from the &productname; Media (DVD, USB)</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Choose this option if you want to perform a stand-alone installation
      and do not want to rely on a network to provide the installation data
      or the boot infrastructure. The installation proceeds exactly as
      outlined in <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.steps"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Installing from the LiveCD</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <remark condition="FIXME">
       2014-03-11 - fs: Check if true
      </remark>
      In order to install from a LiveCD, boot the live system from CD. In the
      running system, launch the installation routine by clicking the
      <guimenu>Install</guimenu> icon on the desktop. The installation will be
      executed in a window on the desktop. It is not possible to update an
      existing system with a LiveCD, you can only perform an installation from
      scratch.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry id="sec.i.yast2.source.net">
    <term>Installing from a Network Server</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Choose this option if you have an installation server available in your
      network or want to use an external server as the source of your
      installation data. This setup can be configured to boot from physical
      media (flash disk, CD/DVD, or hard disk) or configured to boot via
      network using PXE/BOOTP. Refer to <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.startup"/>
      for details.
     </para>
     <para>
      The installation program configures the network connection with DHCP and
      retrieves the location of the network installation source from the
      OpenSLP server. If no DHCP is available, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>F4
      Source</guimenu> <guimenu>Network Config</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Manual</guimenu></menuchoice> and enter the network data. On
      EFI systems modify the network boot parameters as described in <xref
      linkend="sec.i.yast2.bootscreen_uefi"/>.
     </para>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Installing from an SLP Server</title>
      <para>
       If your network setup supports OpenSLP and your network installation
       source has been configured to announce itself via SLP (described in
       <xref linkend="sec.deployment.remoteinst.instserver"/>), boot the
       system, press <keycap>F4</keycap> in the boot screen and select
       <guimenu>SLP</guimenu> from the menu. On EFI systems set the
       <literal>install</literal> parameter to
       <literal>install=slp:/</literal> as described in <xref
       linkend="sec.i.yast2.bootscreen_uefi"/>.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Installing from a Network Source without SLP</title>
      <para>
       If your network setup does not support OpenSLP for the retrieval of
       network installation sources, boot the system and press
       <keycap>F4</keycap> in the boot screen to select the desired network
       protocol (NFS, HTTP, FTP, or SMB/CIFS) and provide the server's address
       and the path to the installation media. On EFI systems modify the boot
       parameter <literal>install=</literal> as described in <xref
       linkend="sec.i.yast2.bootscreen_uefi"/>.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry os="sled">
    <term>Installing as a &sls; Add-on</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Choose this option if you want to install &productname; on top of
      &sls;. Install &sls;, register at the &scc; and choose the &sled;
      extension on the <guimenu>Extension Selection</guimenu> screen.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>


 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.startup">
  <title>System Startup for Installation</title>
  <para>
   The way the system is started for the installation depends on the
   architecture&mdash;system startup is different for PC (x86_64) or
   mainframe, for example. If you install &productname; as a &vmguest; on a
   &kvm; or &xen; hypervisor, follow the instructions for the x86_64
   architecture.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.start.ppc" arch="POWER" os="sles">
   <title>IBM &ppc;: Startup for Network Installation</title>
   <para>
    For IBM &ppc; platforms, the system is booted (IPL, Initial Program Load)
    as described in <xref linkend="cha.ppc.prep"/>. For a network
    installation, &sls; does not show a splash screen or a boot loader command
    line on these systems. During the installation load the kernel
    manually. &yast; starts with its installation screen as soon as a
    connection has been established to the installation system via VNC, X, or
    SSH. Because there is no splash screen or boot loader command line, kernel
    or boot parameters cannot be entered on the screen, but must be included
    in the kernel image using the <command>mkzimage_cmdline</command> utility.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.start.390" arch="zseries" os="sles">
   <title>IBM &zseries;: System Startup</title>
   <para>
    For IBM &zseries; platforms, the system is booted (IPL, Initial Program
    Load) as described in <xref linkend="sec.prep.ipling"/>. &productname;
    does not show a splash screen on these systems. During the installation,
    load the kernel, initrd, and parmfile manually. &yast; starts with its
    installation screen as soon as a connection has been established to the
    installation system via VNC, X, or SSH. Because there is no splash screen,
    kernel or boot parameters cannot be entered on screen, but must be
    specified in a parmfile (see <xref linkend="sec.appdendix.parm" />).
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.start.x86_64" arch="x86_64">
   <title>PC (x86_64): System Startup</title>
   <para>
    &productname; supports several different boot options from which you can
    choose, depending on the hardware available and on the installation
    scenario you prefer. Booting from the &productname; media is the most
    straightforward option, but special requirements might call for special
    setups:
   </para>
   <table id="tab.boot.opt">
    <title>Boot Options</title>
    <tgroup cols="2">
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>
	<para>
         Boot Option
	</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
	<para>
         Description
	</para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
	<para>
         DVD
	</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
	<para>
         This is the easiest boot option. This option can be used if the
         system has a local DVD-ROM drive that is supported by Linux.
	</para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
	<para>
         USB Mass Storage Device
	</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
	<para>
         In case your machine is not equipped with an optical drive, you can
         boot the installation image from a USB mass storage device such as a
         flash disk. To create a bootable USB storage device, you need to copy
         either the DVD or the Mini CD iso image to the device using the
         <command>dd</command> command (the USB device must not be mounted,
         all data on the device will be erased):
	</para>
	<screen>dd if=<replaceable>PATH_TO_ISO_IMAGE</replaceable> of=<replaceable>USB_STORAGE_DEVICE</replaceable> bs=4M</screen>
	<important>
         <title>Compatibility</title>
         <para>
          Note that booting from a USB Mass Storage Device is
          <emphasis>not</emphasis> supported on UEFI machines (this includes
          the complete ia64 architecture) and on the ppc64 architecture.
         </para>
	</important>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
	<para>
         PXE or BOOTP
	</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
	<para>
         Booting over the network must be supported by the system's BIOS or
         firmware, and a boot server must be available in the network. This
         task can also be handled by another &productname; system. Refer to
         <xref linkend="cha.deployment.remoteinst"/> for more
         information.
	</para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
	<para>
         Hard Disk
	</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
	<para>
         &productname; installation can also be booted from the hard disk. To
         do this, copy the kernel (<systemitem>linux</systemitem>) and the
         installation system (<systemitem>initrd</systemitem>) from the
         directory
         <filename>/boot/<replaceable>architecture</replaceable>/</filename>
         on the installation media to the hard disk and add an appropriate
         entry to the existing boot loader of a previous &productname;
         installation.
	</para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </table>
   
   <tip>
    <title>Booting from DVD on UEFI machines</title>
    <para>
     DVD1 can be used as a boot medium for machines equipped with UEFI
     (Unified Extensible Firmware Interface). Refer to your vendor's
     documentation for specific information. If booting fails, try to enable
     CSM (Compatibility Support Module) in your firmware.
    </para>
   </tip>
   
   <note>
    <title>Add-on Product Installation Media</title>
    <para>
     Media for add-on products (extensions or third-party products) cannot be
     used as stand-alone installation media. They can either be embedded as
     additional installation sources during the installation process (see <xref
     linkend="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.addon"/>) or be installed from the running
     system using the &yast; Add-on Products module (see <xref
     linkend="cha.add-ons"/> for details).
    </para>
   </note>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.bootscreen">
    <title>The Boot Screen on Machines Equipped with Traditional BIOS</title>
    <para>
     The boot screen displays a number of options for the installation
     procedure. <guimenu>Boot from Hard Disk</guimenu> boots the installed
     system and is selected by default, because the CD is often left in the
     drive. Select one of the other options with the arrow keys and press
     <keycap function="enter"/> to boot it. The relevant options are:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Installation</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	The normal installation mode. All modern hardware functions are
	enabled. In case the installation fails, see <xref
	linkend="sec.i.yast2.bootscreen.kernel"/> for boot options that
	disable potentially problematic functions.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Upgrade</guimenu></term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	FIXME
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Rescue System</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	Starts a minimal Linux system without a graphical user interface. For
	more information, see <xref
	linkend="sec.trouble.data.recover.rescue"/>. This option is not
	available on LiveCDs.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Check Installation Media</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	This option is only available when you install from media created from
	downloaded ISOs. In this case it is recommended to check the integrity
	of the installation medium. This option starts the installation system
	before automatically checking the media. In case the check was
	successful, the normal installation routine starts. If a corrupt media
	is detected, the installation routine aborts.
       </para>
       <warning>
	<title>Failure of Media Check</title>
	<para>
	 If the media check fails, your medium is damaged. Do not continue the
	 installation because installation may fail or you may loose your
	 data.  Replace the broken medium and restart the installation
	 process.
	</para>
       </warning>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Firmware Test</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	Starts a BIOS checker that validates ACPI and other parts of your
	BIOS. This option is not available on the
	LiveCDs.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Memory Test</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	Tests your system RAM using repeated read and write cycles. Terminate
	the test by rebooting. For more information, see
	<xref linkend="sec.trouble.install.noboot"/>. This
	option is not available on the LiveCDs.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    
    <figure>
     <title>The Boot Screen on Machines with a Traditional BIOS</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <textobject role="description">
       <phrase>The Boot Screen on Machines with a Traditional BIOS</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="i_y2_boot.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="i_y2_boot.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <para>
     Use the function keys indicated in the bar at the bottom of the screen to
     change the language, screen resolution, installation source or to add an
     additional driver from your hardware vendor:
    </para>
    
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><keycap>F1</keycap><guimenu>Help</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	Get context-sensitive help for the active element of the boot screen.
	Use the arrow keys to navigate, <keycap function="enter"/> to follow a
	link, and <keycap function="escape"/> to leave the help screen.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><keycap>F2</keycap><guimenu>Language</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	Select the display language and a corresponding keyboard layout for
	the installation. The default language is English (US).
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><keycap>F3</keycap><guimenu>Video Mode</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	Select various graphical display modes for the installation. By
	<guimenu>Default</guimenu> the video resolution is automatically
	determined using KMS (Kernel Mode Settings). If this setting does not
	work on your system, choose <guimenu>No KMS</guimenu> and, optionally,
	specify <literal>vga=ask</literal> on the boot command line to get
	prompted for the video resolution. Choose <guimenu>Text Mode</guimenu>
	if the graphical installation causes problems.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><keycap>F4</keycap><guimenu>Source</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	Normally, the installation is performed from the inserted installation
	medium. Here, select other sources, like FTP or NFS servers. If the
	installation is deployed on a network with an SLP server, select an
	installation source available on the server with this option. Find
	information about setting up an ipnstallation server with SLP at <xref
	linkend="sec.deployment.remoteinst.instserver"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry id="sec.i.yast2.bootscreen.kernel">
      <term><keycap>F5</keycap><guimenu>Kernel</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	If you encounter problems with the regular installation, this menu
	offers to disable a few potentially problematic functions. If your
	hardware does not support ACPI (advanced configuration and power
	interface) select <guimenu>No ACPI</guimenu> to install without ACPI
	support. <guimenu>No local APIC</guimenu> disables support for APIC
	(Advanced Programmable Interrupt Controllers) which may cause problems
	with some hardware. <guimenu>Safe Settings</guimenu> boots the system
	with the DMA mode (for CD/DVD-ROM drives) and power management
	functions disabled.
       </para>
       <para>
	If you are not sure, try the following options first:
	<guimenu>Installation&mdash;ACPI Disabled</guimenu> or
	<guimenu>Installation&mdash;Safe Settings</guimenu>. Experts can also
	use the command line (<guimenu>Boot Options</guimenu>) to enter or
	change kernel parameters.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><keycap>F6</keycap><guimenu>Driver</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	Press this key to notify the system that you have an optional driver
	update for &productname;. With <guimenu>File</guimenu> or
	<guimenu>URL</guimenu>, load drivers directly before the installation
	starts. If you select <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>, you are prompted to
	insert the update disk at the appropriate point in the installation
	process.
       </para>
       <tip>
	<title>Getting Driver Update Disks</title>
	<para>
	 Driver updates for &sle; are provided at
	 <ulink
	   url="http://drivers.suse.com/"/>. These drivers have
	 been created via the Partner Linux Driver Program.
	</para>
       </tip>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    

   </sect3>

   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.bootscreen_uefi">
    <title>The Boot Screen on Machines Equipped with UEFI</title>
    <para>
     UEFI (Unified Extensible Firmware Interface) is a new industry standard
     which replaces and extends the traditional BIOS. The latest UEFI
     implementations contain the <quote>Secure Boot</quote> extension, that
     prevents booting malicious code by only allowing signed boot loaders to
     be executed. See <xref linkend="cha.uefi"/> for more information.
    </para>
    <para>
     The boot manager &grub;, used to boot machines with a traditional BIOS,
     does not support UEFI, therefore &grub; is replaced with &elilo;. If
     Secure Boot is enabled, a &grub; UEFI module is used via an &elilo;
     compatibility layer. From an administrative and user perspective, both
     boot manager implementations behave the same and are referred to as
     <literal>&elilo;</literal> in the following.
    </para>

    <tip>
     <title>UEFI and Secure Boot are Supported by Default</title>
     <para>
      The installation routine of &sle; automatically detects if the machine
      is equipped with UEFI. All installation sources also support Secure
      Boot. If an EFI system partition already exists on dual boot machines
      (from a Microsoft Windows 8 installation, for example), it will
      automatically be detected and used. Partition tables will be written as
      GPT on UEFI systems.
     </para>
    </tip>

    <para>
     The boot screen displays a number of options for the installation
     procedure. Change the selected option with the arrow keys and press
     <keycap function="enter"/> to boot it. The relevant options are:
    </para>

    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Installation</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	The normal installation mode.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Upgrade</guimenu></term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	FIXME
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Rescue System</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	Starts a minimal Linux system without a graphical user interface. For
	more information, see
	<xref linkend="sec.trouble.data.recover.rescue"/>.
	This option is not available on LiveCDs.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Check Installation Media</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	This option is only available when you install from media created from
	downloaded ISOs. In this case it is recommended to check the integrity
	of the installation medium. This option starts the installation system
	before automatically checking the media. In case the check was
	successful, the normal installation routine starts. If a corrupt media
	is detected, the installation routine aborts.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    
    <figure>
     <title>The Boot Screen on Machines with UEFI</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <textobject role="description">
       <phrase>The Boot Screen on Machines with UEFI</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="i_y2_boot_uefi.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="i_y2_boot_uefi.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <para>
     &elilo; on &productname; does not support a boot prompt or function keys
     for adding boot parameters. By default, the installation will be started
     with American English and the boot media as the installation source. A DHCP
     lookup will be performed to configure the network. In order to change these
     defaults or to add additional boot parameters you need to edit the
     respective boot entry. Highlight it using the arrow keys and press
     <keycap>E</keycap>. See the on-screen help for editing hints (note that
     only an English keyboard is available at this time). The
     <guimenu>Installation</guimenu> entry will look similar to the following:
    </para>

    <screen>setparams 'Installation'

    set gfxpayload=keep
    echo 'Loading kernel ...'
    linuxefi /boot/x86_64/loader/linux install=
    echo 'Loading initial ramdisk ...'
    initrdefi /boot/x86_64/loader/initrd</screen>
    
    <para>
     Add space separated parameters to the end of the line starting with
     <literal>linuxefi</literal>. To boot the edited entry, press
     <keycap>F10</keycap>. If you access the machine via serial console, press
     <keycombo><keycap function="escape"/> <keycap>0</keycap></keycombo>. A
     complete list of parameters is available at <ulink
     url="https://en.opensuse.org/Linuxrc"/>. The most important ones are:
    </para>

    <table>
     <title>Installation Sources</title>
     <tgroup cols="2">
      <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="30*"/>
      <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="70*"/>
      <tbody>
       <row>
	<entry><para>CD/DVD (default)</para></entry>
	<entry><para><literal>install=cd:/</literal></para></entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>Hard disk</para></entry>
	<entry>
	 <para>
	  <literal>install=hd:/?device=<replaceable>sda/PATH_TO_ISO</replaceable></literal>
	 </para>
	</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>SLP</para></entry>
	<entry><para><literal>install=slp:/</literal></para></entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>FTP</para></entry>
	<entry>
	 <para>
	  <literal>install=ftp://<replaceable>&ftpname;/PATH_TO_ISO</replaceable></literal>
	 </para>
	</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>HTTP</para></entry>
	<entry>
	 <para>
	  <literal>install=http://<replaceable>&wwwname;/PATH_TO_ISO</replaceable></literal>
	 </para>
	</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>NFS</para></entry>
	<entry>
	 <para><literal>install=nfs:/<replaceable>PATH_TO_ISO</replaceable></literal></para>
	</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>SMB / CIFS</para></entry>
	<entry>
	 <para>
	  <literal>install=smb://<replaceable>PATH_TO_ISO</replaceable></literal>
	 </para>
	</entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </table>
    
    <table>
     <title>Network Configuration</title>
     <tgroup cols="2">
      <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="30*"/>
      <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="70*"/>
      <tbody>
       <row>
	<entry><para>DHCP (default)</para></entry>
	<entry><para>netsetup=dhcp</para></entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>Prompt for Parameters</para></entry>
	<entry>
	 <para>
	  <literal>netsetup=hostip,netmask,gateway,name server</literal>
	 </para>
	</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>Host IP address</para></entry>
	<entry>
	 <para><literal>hostip=&wsIip;</literal></para>
	 <para><literal>hostip=&wsIip;/24</literal></para>
	</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>Netmask</para></entry>
	<entry><para><literal>netmask=255.255.255.0</literal></para></entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>Gateway</para></entry>
	<entry><para><literal>gateway=&gateip;</literal></para></entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>Name Server</para></entry>
	<entry>
	 <para><literal>Nameserver=&dnsip;</literal></para>
	 <para><literal>Nameserver=&dnsip;,&dnsip118;</literal></para>
	</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>Domain Search Path</para></entry>
	<entry><para><literal>domain=&exampledomain;</literal></para></entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </table>
    
    <table>
     <title>Miscellaneous</title>
     <tgroup cols="2">
      <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="30*"/>
      <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="70*"/>
      <tbody>
       <row>
	<entry><para>Driver Updates: Prompt</para></entry>
	<entry><para><literal>dud=1</literal></para></entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>Driver Updates: URL</para></entry>
	<entry>
	 <para>
	  <literal>dud=ftp://<replaceable>&ftpname;/PATH_TO_DRIVER</replaceable></literal>
	 </para>
	 <para>
	  <literal>dud=http://<replaceable>&wwwname;/PATH_TO_DRIVER</replaceable></literal>
	 </para>
	</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>Installation Language</para></entry>
	<entry>
	 <para>
          <literal>Language=<replaceable>LANGUAGE</replaceable></literal>
	 </para>
	 <para>
	  Supported values for <replaceable>LANGUAGE</replaceable> are, among
	  others, <literal>cs_CZ</literal>, <literal>de_DE</literal>,
	  <literal>es_ES</literal>, <literal>fr_FR</literal>,
	  <literal>ja_JP</literal>, <literal>pt_BR</literal>,
	  <literal>pt_PT</literal>, <literal>ru_RU</literal>,
	  <literal>zh_CN</literal>, and <literal>zh_TW</literal>.
	 </para>
	</entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>Kernel: NO ACPI</para></entry>
	<entry><para><literal>acpi=off</literal></para></entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>Kernel: No Local APIC</para></entry>
	<entry><para><literal>noapic</literal></para></entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>Video: Disable KMS</para></entry>
	<entry><para><literal>nomodeset</literal></para></entry>
       </row>
       <row>
	<entry><para>Video: Start Installer in Text Mode</para></entry>
	<entry><para><literal>Textmode=1</literal></para></entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </table>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.start.parameters">
   <title>Boot Parameters for Advanced Setups</title>
   <para>
    In case you want to configure access to a local &smt; or
    <systemitem>supportconfig</systemitem> server for the installation, you
    can specify boot parameters that will be parsed by the installation
    routine to set up these services. The same is also true if you need IPv6
    support during the installation.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.start.parameters.smt">
    <title>Providing Data to Access an &smt; Server</title>
    <para>
     By default, updates for &productname; are delivered by the &scc;. If your
     network provides a so called &smt; server to provide a local update
     source, you need to equip the client with the server's URL. Client and
     server communicate solely via HTTPS protocol, therefore you also need to
     enter a path to the server's certificate if the certificate was not
     issued by a certificate authority. This information can either be entered
     at the boot prompt (as described here) or during the registration process
     as described in FIXME<!-- <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.cc.local" /> -->.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>regurl</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	URL of the &smt; server. This URL has a fixed format
	<literal>https://<replaceable>FQN</replaceable>/center/regsvc/</literal>. <replaceable>FQN</replaceable>
	needs to be a fully qualified host name of the &smt; server. Example:
       </para>
       <screen>regurl=https://smt.&exampledomain;/center/regsvc/</screen>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>regcert</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	Location of the &smt; server's certificate. Specify one of the
	following locations:
       </para>
       <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
         <term>URL</term>
         <listitem>
          <para>
           Remote location (HTTP, HTTPS or FTP) from which the certificate
           can be downloaded. Example:
          </para>
	  <screen>regcert=http://smt.&exampledomain;/smt-ca.crt</screen>
         </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
         <term>local path</term>
         <listitem>
          <para>
           Absolute path to the certificate on the local machine. Example:
          </para>
	  <screen>regcert=/data/inst/smt/smt-ca.cert</screen>
         </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
         <term>Interactive</term>
         <listitem>
          <para>
           Use <literal>ask</literal> to open a pop-up menu during the
           installation where you can specify the path to the certificate. Do
           not use this option with &ay;. Example
          </para>
	  <screen>regcert=ask</screen>
         </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
         <term>Deactivate certificate installation</term>
         <listitem>
          <para>
           Use <literal>done</literal> if either the certificate will be
           installed by an add-on product, or if you are using a certificate
           issued by an official certificate authority. Example:
          </para>
	  <screen>regcert=done</screen>
         </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
       </variablelist>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <warning>
     <title>Beware of Typing Errors</title>
     <para>
      Make sure the values you enter are correct. If
      <literal>regurl</literal> has not been specified correctly, the
      registration of the update source will fail. If a wrong value for
      regcert has been entered, you will be prompted for a local path to the
      certificate.
     </para>
     <para>
      In case regcert is not specified, it will default to
      <literal>http://<replaceable>FQN</replaceable>/smt.crt</literal> with
      <literal>FQN</literal> being the name of the SMT server.
     </para>
    </warning>
   </sect3>
   
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.start.parameters.supportconfigurl">
    <title>
     Configuring an Alternative Data Server for
     <systemitem>supportconfig</systemitem>
    </title>
    <para>
     The data that supportconfig (see <xref linkend="cha.adm.support"/> for
     more information) gathers is sent to the &ncc; by default. It is also
     possible to set up a local server to collect this data. If such a server
     is available on your network, you need to set the server's URL on the
     client. This information needs to be entered at the boot prompt.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>supporturl</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
	URL of the server. The URL has the format
	<literal>http://<replaceable>FQN</replaceable>/<replaceable>Path</replaceable>/</literal>
	<replaceable>FQN</replaceable> needs to be full qualified host name of
	the server, <replaceable>Path</replaceable> needs to be replaced with
	the location on the server. Example:
       </para>
       <screen>supporturl=http://support.&exampledomain;/supportconfig/data/</screen>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect3>

   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.start.parameters.ipv6">
    <title>Using IPv6 during the Installation</title>
    <para>
     By default you can only assign IPv4 network addresses to your machine.
     To enable IPv6 during installation, enter one of the following parameters
     at the bootprompt: 
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>ipv6=1</literal> (accept IPv4 and IPv6)
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>ipv6only=1</literal> (accept IPv6 only).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </sect3>

   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast.start.parameters.keys_users">
    <title>
     Disabling the Import of SSH Host Keys and Users from a Previous
     Installation
    </title>
    <para>
     If installing on a machine hosting a previous Linux installation, the SSH
     host keys from that installation will automatically imported into the
     &productname; setup by default. It is also possible to import users from
     that installation in the <guimenu>Create New User</guimenu> dialog.
    </para>
    <para>
     To disable these features, specify the <literal>ignore_features</literal>
     parameter at the bootprompt. Adding the (optional)
     <literal>ptoptions</literal> parameter ensures that the
     <literal>ignore_features</literal> parameter is only used for the
     installation and not appended to the Kernel command line in the installed
     system:  
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>ignore_features=import_ssh_keys
       ptoptions=ignore_features</literal> (do not import SSH host keys)
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>ignore_features=import_users
       ptoptions=ignore_features</literal> (disable user import dialog)
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>ignore_features=import_ssh_keys,import_users
       ptoptions=ignore_features</literal> (disable user import dialog)
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </sect3>
   
  </sect2>
 </sect1>


 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.steps">
  <title>The Installation Workflow</title>

  <para>
   The interactive installation of &productname; split into several steps
   listed below. For a description on how to perform non-interactive,
   automated installations, refer to <xref linkend="part.autoinstall"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   After starting the installation, &productname; loads and configures a
   minimal Linux system to run the installation procedure. To view the boot
   messages and copyright notices during this process, press
   <keycap function="escape"/>. On completion of this process, the &yast;
   installation program starts and displays the graphical installer.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>Installation without a Mouse</title>
   <para>
    If the installer does not detect your mouse correctly, use
    <keycap function="tab"/> for navigation, arrow keys to scroll, and
    <keycap function="enter"/> to confirm a selection. Various buttons or
    selection fields contain a letter with an underscore. Use
    <keycombo><keycap function="alt"/><keycap>Letter</keycap></keycombo>
    to select a button or a selection directly instead of navigating there
    with <keycap function="tab"/>.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <!-- Language, Keyboard and License Agreement -->
     <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.welcome" xrefstyle="HeadingOnPage"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <!-- Network Settings -->
     <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.network" xrefstyle="HeadingOnPage"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem arch="zseries" os="sles">
    <para>
     <!-- IBM System z: Hard Disk Configuration-->
     <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.s390.part" xrefstyle="HeadingOnPage"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <!-- SUSE Customer Center Registration -->
     <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.cc" xrefstyle="HeadingOnPage"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <!-- Extension Selection -->
     <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.addon" xrefstyle="HeadingOnPage"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <!-- Suggested Partitioning -->
     <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.partitioning" xrefstyle="HeadingOnPage"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <!-- Clock And Timezone -->
    <para>
     <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.timezone" xrefstyle="HeadingOnPage"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <!-- Create New User -->
    <para>
     <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.user" xrefstyle="HeadingOnPage"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <!-- Root Password -->
    <para>
     <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.user.root" xrefstyle="HeadingOnPage"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <!-- Installation Settings -->
    <para>
     <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.proposal" xrefstyle="HeadingOnPage"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <!-- Performing the Installation -->
    <para>
     <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.perform" xrefstyle="HeadingOnPage"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.welcome">
  <title>Language, Keyboard and License Agreement</title>

  <para>
   Start the installation of &productname; by choosing your language.
   Changing the language will automatically preselect a corresponding keyboard
   layout. Override this proposal by selecting a different keyboard layout
   from the drop-down box. The language selected here is also used to assume a
   time zone for the system clock. This setting can be modified later in the
   installed system as described in <xref linkend="cha.y2.lang"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Read the license agreement that is displayed beneath the language and
   keyboard selection thoroughly. Use <guimenu>License
   Translations</guimenu> to access translations. If you agree to the
   terms, check <guimenu>I Agree to the License Terms</guimenu> and click
   <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed with the installation. If you do not
   agree to the license agreement, you cannot install &productname;; click
   <guimenu>Abort</guimenu> to terminate the installation.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Language, Keyboard and License Agreement</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Language, Keyboard and License Agreement</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_welcome.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_welcome.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>


 
 

 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.s390.part" arch="zseries" os="sles">
  <title>IBM &zseries;: Disk Activation</title>

  <para>
   When installing on IBM &zseries; platforms, the language selection dialog
   is followed by a dialog to configure the attached hard disks. Select
   DASD, Fibre Channel Attached SCSI Disks (zFCP), or iSCSI for installation
   of &productname;. The DASD and zFCP configuration buttons are only
   available if the corresponding devices are attached. For instructions on
   how to configure iSCSI disks, refer to <xref linkend="bj4rqa5"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can also <guimenu>Change the Network Configuration</guimenu> in this
   screen by launching the <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu> dialog. Choose
   a network interface from the list and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> to
   change its settings. Use the tabs to configure DNS and routing. See <xref
   linkend="sec.basicnet.yast"/> for more details.
  </para>


  <remark condition="clarity">
   2014-06-05 - fs: Screenshot needs to be replaced by a version showing all 4
   options.
  </remark>

  <figure>
   <title>Disk Activation</title>
   <mediaobject>
      <textobject role="description">
       <phrase>Network Settings</phrase>
      </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_zseries_disk_activation.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_zseries_disk_activation.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

<!-- fs 2014-06-05:
     This does not seem to be possible anymore with SLE 12

  <tip>
   <title>Adding DASD or zFCP Disks at a Later Stage</title>
   <para>
    Adding DASD or zFCP disks is not only possible during the installation
    workflow, but also when the installation proposal is shown. To add disks
    at that stage, click <guimenu>Expert</guimenu> and scroll down. The DASD
    and zFCP entries are shown at the very bottom.
   </para>
   <para>
    After adding the disks, reread the partition table. Return to the
    installation proposal screen and choose <guimenu>Partitioning</guimenu>
    then select <guimenu>Reread Partition Table</guimenu>. This updates the
    new partition table.
   </para>
  </tip>

-->

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.s390.part.dasd">
   <title>Configuring DASD Disks</title>
   <para>
    After selecting <guimenu>Configure DASD Disks</guimenu>, an overview
    lists all available DASDs. To get a clearer picture of the available
    devices, use the text box located above the list to specify a range
    of channels to display. To filter the list according to such a range,
    select <guimenu>Filter</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <figure id="fig.s390_yast2.i_y2_sel_dasd">
    <title>IBM &zseries;: Selecting a DASD</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <textobject role="description">
      <phrase>IBM &zseries;: Selecting a DASD</phrase>
     </textobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata width="70%" fileref="s390_i_y2_sel_dasd.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata width="70%" fileref="s390_i_y2_sel_dasd.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    Specify the DASDs to use for the installation by selecting the
    corresponding entries in the list. Use <guimenu>Select All</guimenu> to
    select all DASDs currently displayed. Activate and make the selected DASDs
    available for the installation by selecting <menuchoice> <guimenu>Perform
    Action</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Activate</guimenu> </menuchoice>. To format the DASDs, select
    <menuchoice> <guimenu>Perform Action</guimenu> <guimenu>Format</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>. Alternatively or use the &yast; partitioner later as
    described in <xref linkend="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.s390.part.zfcp">
   <title>Configuring zFCP Disks</title>
   <para>
    To use zFCP disks for the &productname; installation, select
    <guimenu>Configure zFCP Disks</guimenu> in the selection dialog. This
    opens a dialog with a list of the zFCP disks available on the system. In
    this dialog, select <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to open another dialog in
    which to enter zFCP parameters.
   </para>
   <para>
    To make a zFCP disk available for the &productname; installation, choose
    an available <guimenu>Channel Number</guimenu> from the drop-down box.
    <guimenu>Get WWPNs</guimenu> (World Wide Port Number) and <guimenu>Get
    LUNs</guimenu> (Logical Unit Number) return lists with available WWPNs
    and FCP-LUNs, respectively, to choose from. When completed, exit the
    zFCP dialog with <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and the general hard disk
    configuration dialog with <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> to continue with the
    rest of the configuration.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

<sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.network">
  <title>Network Settings</title>
  <para>
   After booting into the installation, the installation routine is set
   up. During this setup, an attempt to configure at least one network
   interfaces with DHCP is made. In case this attempt fails, the
   <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu> dialog launches. Choose a network
   interface from the list and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> to change its
   settings. Use the tabs to configure DNS and routing. See <xref
   linkend="sec.basicnet.yast"/> for more details. <phrase arch="zseries">On
   IBM &zseries; this dialog does not start automatically. It can be started
   in the <guimenu>Disk Activation</guimenu></phrase> step.
  </para>
  <para>
   In case DHCP was successfully configured during installation setup, you can
   also access this dialog by clicking <guimenu>Network
   Configuration</guimenu> at the <guimenu>&scc; Registration</guimenu>
   step. It lets you change the automatically provided settings.
  </para>
  
  <figure>
   <title>Network Settings</title>
   <mediaobject>
      <textobject role="description">
       <phrase>Network Settings</phrase>
      </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_network.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_network.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.cc">
  <title>&scc; Registration</title>
  <para>
   To get technical support and product updates, you need to register and
   activate your product with the &scc;. Registering &productname; at this
   stage of the installation grants you immediate access to the update
   repository. This enables you to install the system with the latest updates
   and patches available. If you are offline or want to skip this step, select
   <guimenu>Skip Registration</guimenu>. You can register your system at any
   time later from the installed system. For detailed information about &scc;
   see FIXME.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>Network Configuration</title>
   <para>
    After booting into the installation, the installation routine is set
    up. During this setup, an attempt to configure all network interfaces
    with DHCP is made. In case DHCP is not available or if you want to
    modify the network configuration, click on <guimenu>Network
    Configuration</guimenu> in the upper right corner of the <guimenu>&scc;
    Registration</guimenu> screen. The &yast; module <guimenu>Network
    Settings</guimenu> opens. See <xref linkend="sec.basicnet.yast"/> for
    details.
   </para>
  </note>
  <figure>
   <title>&scc; Registration</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>&scc; Registration</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_scc.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_scc.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure> 
  <para>
   To register your system, provide the <guimenu>E-mail</guimenu> address
   associated with the &suse; account you or your organization uses to manage
   subscriptions. In case you do not have a SUSE account, yet, go to the &scc;
   home page (<ulink url="&sccurl;"/> to create one. Also enter
   the registration code you received with your copy of &productname;.
  </para>
  <para>
   Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to start the registration
   process. If one or more local registration servers are available on
   your network, you will be able to choose one of them from a
   list. Alternatively, choose <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu> to ignore the local
   registration servers and register with the default SUSE registration
   server.
  </para>
  <para>
   During the registration the online update channels will be added to your
   installation setup. When finished, you can choose whether to install the
   latest available package versions from the update channels. This ensures
   that &productname; is installed with the latest security updates
   available. If you choose <guimenu>No</guimenu>, all packages will be
   installed from the installation media. Proceed with
   <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.addon">
  <title>Extension Selection</title>
  <para>
   If you have successfully registered your system in the previous step, a
   list of available add-on products and extensions based on &productname; is
   shown. Otherwise this configuration step is skipped. <remark
   condition="clarity">2014-04-07 - fs: FIXME: bnc #870625</remark> It is also
   possible to configure add-on products from the installed system, see <xref
   linkend=" cha.add-ons"/> for details.
  </para>

  <remark condition="clarity">
   2014-04-03 - fs: As of beta 4 this is work in progress
  </remark>
 
  <para>
   The list contains free extensions for &productname;, such as the &sle; SDK
   and add-on products requiring a registration key that is liable to
   costs. Click an entry to see its description. Select an add-on or extension
   for installation by activating its check mark. This will add its repository
   from the &scc; server to your installation&mdash;no additional installation
   sources are required. Furthermore the installation pattern for the add-on
   product or extension is added to the default installation to ensure it gets
   installed automatically.
  </para>
  
  <note>
   <title>Available Extensions and Modules</title>
   <para>
    The amount of available extensions and modules depends on the registration
    server. A local registration server may only offer update repositories and
    no additional extensions at all.
   </para>
  </note>

  <tip>
   <title>&sled;</title>
   <para>
    As of &sle; 12, &sled; is not only available as a separate product, but
    also as an extension for &sls;. If you register at the &scc;, the &sled;
    extension can be selected for installation. Note that installing it
    requires a valid registration key.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <figure os="sles">
   <title>Extension Selection</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Extension Selection</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_extensions_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_extensions_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <figure os="sled">
   <title>Extension Selection</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Extension Selection</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_extensions_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_extensions_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to the <guimenu>Add-on Product</guimenu>
   dialog, where you can specify sources for additional Add-on products not
   available on the registration server.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you do not want to install add-ons, proceed with
   <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. Otherwise activate <guimenu>I would like to
   Install an Add-on Product</guimenu>. Specify the Media
   Type by choosing from CD, DVD, Hard Disk, USB Mass Storage, a
   Local Directory or a Local ISO Image. In case network access has been
   configured you can choose from additional remote sources such as HTTP, SLP,
   FTP, etc. Alternatively you may directly specify a URL. Check Download
   Repository Description Files to download the files describing the
   repository now. If deactivated, they will be downloaded after the
   installation starts. Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and insert a CD
   or DVD if required.
  </para>
  <para>
   Depending on the add-on's content it may be necessary to accept additional
   license agreements. If you have chosen an add-on product requiring a
   registration key, you will be asked to enter it at the <guimenu>Extension
   and Module Registration Codes</guimenu> page. Proceed with
   <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Add-on Product</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Add-on Product</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_addon.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_addon.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
  <tip>
   <title><quote>No Registration Key</quote> Error</title>
   <para>
    In case you have chosen a product in the <guimenu>Extension
    Selection</guimenu> dialog for which you do not have a valid
    registration key, choose <guimenu>Back</guimenu> until you see the
    <guimenu>Extension Selection</guimenu> dialog. Deselect the Add-on and
    proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. Add-on products can also be
    installed at any time later from the running system.
   </para>
  </tip>
  
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.partitioning">
  <title>Suggested Partitioning</title>
  <para>
   Define a partition setup for &productname; in this step. The installer
   creates a proposal for one of the available disks containing a root
   partition formatted with Btrfs (with snapshots enabled), a swap partition,
   and a home partition formatted with XFS. On hard disks smaller than 25 GB
   the proposal does not include a separate home partition. If one or more
   swap partitions have been detected on the available hard disks, these
   existing ones will be used (rather than proposing a new swap
   partition). You have several options to proceed:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Next</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To accept the proposal without any changes, click
      <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed with the installation workflow.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Edit Proposal Settings</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To adjust the proposal choose <guimenu>Edit Proposal
      Settings</guimenu>. It lets you switch to an LVM based proposal,
      adjust file systems for the proposed partitions and enlarge the swap
      partition, to enable suspend to disk. You can also disable Btrfs
      snapshots here.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Create Partition Setup</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use this option to move the proposal described above to a different
      disk. Select a specific disk from the list. If the chosen hard disk does
      not contain any partitions yet, the whole hard disk will be used for the
      proposal.  Otherwise, you can choose which existing partition(s) to
      use. <guimenu>Edit Proposal Settings</guimenu> lets you fine-tune the
      proposal. 
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Expert Partitioner</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To create a custom partition setup choose <guimenu>Expert
      Partitioner</guimenu>. The Expert Partitioner opens, displaying the
      current partition setup for all hard disks, including the proposal
      suggested by the installer. You can <guimenu>Add</guimenu>,
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>, <guimenu>Resize</guimenu>, or
      <guimenu>Delete</guimenu> partitions.
     </para>
     <para>
      You can also set up Logical Volumes (LVM), configure software RAID and
      device mapping (DM), encrypt Partitions, mount NFS shares and manage
      tmpfs volumes with the Expert Partitioner. To fine-tune settings such as
      the subvolume and snapshot handling for each Btrfs partition, choose
      <guimenu>Btrfs</guimenu>. For more information about custom partitioning
      and configuring advanced features, refer to
      <xref linkend="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert"/>
     </para>
     <warning>
      <title>Custom Partitioning on UEFI machines</title>
      <para>
       A UEFI machine <emphasis>requires</emphasis> an EFI system partition
       that must be mounted to <filename>/boot/efi</filename>. This partition
       must be formatted with the <literal>FAT</literal> file system.
      </para>
      <para>
       If an EFI system partition is already present on your system
       (for example from a previous Windows installation) use it by mounting
       it to <filename>/boot/efi</filename> without formatting it.
      </para>
     </warning>

     <note os="sles" arch="zseries">
      <title>IBM &zseries; Using Minidisks in z/VM</title>
      <para>
       If &productname; is installed on minidisks in z/VM, which reside on the
       same physical disk, the access path of the minidisks (/dev/disk/by-id/)
       is not unique, because it represents the ID of the physical disk. So if
       two or more minidisks are on the same physical disk, they all have the
       same ID.
      </para>
      <para>
       To avoid problems when mounting minidisks, always mount them either
       "by path" or "by UUID".
      </para>
     </note>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <note>
   <title>Supported Software RAID Volumes</title>
   <para>
    Installing to and booting from existing software RAID volumes is supported
    for Disk Data Format (DDF) volumes and Intel Matrix Storage Manager (IMSM)
    volumes. IMSM is also known by the following names:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Intel Rapid Storage Technology
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Intel Matrix Storage Technology
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Intel Application Accelerator / Intel Application Accelerator RAID
      Edition
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </note>
  
  <important os="sled">
   <title>Handling of Windows Partitions in Proposals</title>
   <para>
    In case the disk selected for the suggested partitioning proposal contains
    a large Windows FAT or NTFS partition, it will automatically be resized to
    make room for the &productname; installation. To avoid data loss it is
    strongly recommended to 
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      make sure the partition is not fragmented (run a defragmentation program
      from Windows prior to the &productname; installation)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      double-check the suggested size for the Windows partition is big enough
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      back up your data prior to the &productname; installation
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    To adjust the proposed size of the Windows partition, use the
    <guimenu>Expert Partitioner</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </important>
  
<!--

  <note arch="POWER">
   <title>Suggested Partitioning on IBM &ppc;</title>
   <para>
    An already existing boot partition is usually re-used by &yast; when
    making the partitioning proposal. This is not possible on IBM &ppc;.
   </para>
  </note>

-->
  
  <figure>
   <title>Partitioning</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Partitioning</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_partitioner.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_partitioner.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.timezone">
  <title>Clock and Time Zone</title>

  <para>
   In this dialog, select your region and time zone. Both are pre-selected
   according to the installation language. To change the preselected values,
   either use the map or the drop-down boxes for <guimenu>Region</guimenu> and
   <guimenu>Time Zone</guimenu>. When using the map, point the cursor at the
   rough direction of your region and left-click to zoom. Now choose your
   country or region by left-clicking.  Right-click to return to the world
   map.
  </para>

  <para>
   To set up the clock, choose whether the <guimenu>Hardware Clock is Set to
   UTC</guimenu>. If you run another operating system on your machine, such
   as Microsoft Windows, it is likely your system uses local time instead.
   If you only run Linux on your machine, set the hardware clock to UTC and
   have the switch from standard time to daylight saving time performed
   automatically.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Set the Hardware Clock to UTC</title>
   <para>
    The switch from standard time to daylight saving time (and vice versa)
    can only be performed automatically when the hardware clock (CMOS clock)
    is set to UTC. This also applies if you use automatic time
    synchronization with NTP, because automatic synchronization will only be
    performed if the time difference between the hardware and system clock
    is less than 15 minutes.
   </para>
   <para>
    Since a wrong system time can cause severe problems (missed backups,
    dropped mail messages, mount failures on remote file systems, etc.) it
    is strongly recommended to <emphasis>always</emphasis> set the hardware
    clock to UTC.
   </para>
  </important>

  <figure>
   <title>Clock and Time Zone</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Clock and Time Zone</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_timezone.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_timezone.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para arch="POWER;x86_64">
   If a network is already configured, you can configure time
   synchronization with an NTP server. Click
   <guimenu>Other Settings</guimenu> to either alter the NTP settings or to
   <guimenu>Manually</guimenu> set the time. See
   <xref linkend="cha.netz.xntp"/> for more information on configuring the
   NTP service. When finished, click <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to continue
   the installation.
  </para>

  <note arch="zseries" os="sles">
   <title>Time Cannot be Changed on IBM &zseries;</title>
   <para>
    Since the operating system is not allowed to change time and date
    directly, the <guimenu>Other Settings</guimenu> option is not available on
    IBM &zseries;.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.user">
  <title>Create New User</title>

  <para>
   Create a local user in this step. In case you do not want to configure any
   local users, for example when setting up a client on a
   network with centralized user authentication, skip this step by
   choosing <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and confirming the warning. Network user
   authentication can be configured at any time later in the installed system,
   refer to <xref linkend="cha.y2.userman"/> for instructions.
  </para>

  <para>
   After entering the first name and last name, either accept the proposal
   or specify a new <guimenu>User name</guimenu> that will be used to log
   in. Only use lowercase letters (a-z), digits (0-9) and the characters
   <literal>.</literal> (dot), <literal>-</literal> (dash) and
   <literal>_</literal> (underscore). Special characters as well as umlauts
   and accented characters are not allowed.
  </para>
  <para>
   Finally, enter a password for the user. Reenter it for confirmation (to
   ensure that you did not type something else by mistake). To provide
   effective security, a password should be at least six characters long and
   consist of uppercase and lowercase letters, digits and special characters
   (7-bit ASCII). Umlauts or accented characters are not allowed.
   Passwords you enter are checked for weakness. When entering a password
   that is easy to guess (such as a dictionary word or a name) you will see
   a warning. It is a good security practice to use strong passwords.
  </para>


  <important>
   <title>User Name and Password</title>
   <para>
    Remember both your user name and the password because they are needed
    each time you log in to the system.
   </para>
  </important>

  <figure>
   <title>Create New User</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Create New User</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_user.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_user.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   Three additional options are available:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Use this Password for the System Administrator</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If checked, the same password you have entered for the user will be
      used for the system administrator &rootuser;. This option is suitable
      for stand-alone workstations or machines in a home network that are
      administrated by a single user. When not checked, you are prompted for
      a system administrator password in the next step of the installation
      workflow (see <xref
       linkend="sec.i.yast2.user.root"/>).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Receive System Mail</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Checking this box sends messages created by the system services to the
      user. These are usually only sent to &rootuser;, the system
      administrator. This option is useful for the most frequently used
      account, because it is highly recommended to log in as &rootuser; only
      in special cases.
     </para>
     <para>
      The mails sent by system services are stored in the local mailbox
      <filename>/var/spool/mail/</filename><replaceable>username</replaceable>,
      where <replaceable>username</replaceable> is the login name of the
      selected user. To read e-mails after installation, you can use any
      e-mail client, for example KMail or Evolution.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Automatic Login</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option automatically logs the current user in to the system when
      it starts. This is mainly useful if the computer is operated by only
      one user. <phrase os="sles">For automatic login to work, the option
      must be explicitly enabled.</phrase>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <warning os="sled">
   <title>Automatic Login</title>
   <para>
    With the automatic login enabled, the system boots straight into your
    desktop with no authentication at all. If you store sensitive data on your
    system, you should not enable this option if the computer can also be
    accessed by others.
   </para>
  </warning>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.user.expert">
   <title>Expert Settings</title>
   <para>
    Click <guimenu>Change</guimenu> in the Create User dialog to import users
    from a previous installation (if present). Also change the password
    encryption type in this dialog.
   </para>
   <para>
    The default authentication method is <guimenu>Local
    (/etc/passwd)</guimenu>. If a former version of &productname; or another
    system using <filename>/etc/passwd</filename> is detected, you may
    import local users. To do so, check <guimenu>Read User Data from a
    Previous Installation</guimenu> and click <guimenu>Choose</guimenu>. In
    the next dialog, select the users to import and finish with
    <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    By default the passwords are encrypted with the SHA-512 hash
    function. Changing this method is not recommended unless needed for
    compatibility reasons. 
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.user.root">
  <title>Password for the System Administrator &rootuser;</title>
  <para>
   If you have not chosen <guimenu>Use this Password for the System
   Administrator</guimenu> in the previous step, you will be prompted to enter
   a Password for the System Administrator &rootuser;. Otherwise this
   configuration step is skipped.
  </para>
  <para>
   &rootuser; is the name of the superuser, or the administrator of the
   system. Unlike regular users (who may or may not have permission to access
   certain areas or execute certain commands on the system), &rootuser; has
   unlimited access to change the system configuration, install programs, and
   set up new hardware. If users forget their passwords or have other problems
   with the system, &rootuser; can help.  The &rootuser; account should only
   be used for system administration, maintenance, and repair. Logging in as
   &rootuser; for daily work is rather risky: a single mistake could lead to
   irretrievable loss of system files.
  </para>
  <para>
   For verification purposes, the password for &rootuser; must be entered
   twice. Do not forget the &rootuser; password. When entered, this password
   cannot be retrieved.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Password for the System Administrator &rootuser;</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Password for the System Administrator &rootuser;</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_root.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_root.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <tip>
   <title>Passwords and Keyboard Layout</title>
   <para>
    It is recommended to only use characters that are available on an English
    keyboard. In case of a system error or when you need to start your system
    in rescue mode a localized keyboard might not be available.
   </para>
  </tip>
  <para>
   The &rootuser; password can be changed any time later in the installed
   system. To do so run &yast; and start <menuchoice> <guimenu>Security and
   Users</guimenu>
   <guimenu>User and Group Management</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>.
  </para>
  <warning>
   <title>The root User</title>
   <para>
    The user &rootuser; has all the permissions needed to make changes to the
    system. To carry out such tasks, the &rootuser; password is required. You
    cannot carry out any administrative tasks without this password.
   </para>
  </warning>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal">
  <title>Installation Settings</title>

  <para>
   On the last step before the real installation takes place, you can alter
   installation settings suggested by the installer. To modify the
   suggestions, click on the respective headline. After having made changes to
   a particular setting, you are always returned to the Installation Settings
   window, which is updated accordingly.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Export Configuration</guimenu> option lets you save the
   current configuration to an XML file which can be used by &ay; for the
   automated installation of other machines.
  </para>

  <figure os="sles">
   <title>Installation Settings</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Installation Settings</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_summary_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_summary_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <figure os="sled">
   <title>Installation Settings</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>Installation Settings</phrase>
    </textobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_summary_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_summary_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <tip>
   <title>Existing SSH Host Keys</title>
   <para>
    If you install &productname; on a machine with one or more existing Linux
    installations, the installation routine automatically imports the SSH
    host key with the most recent access time from an existing installation.
   </para>
  </tip>

<!-- fs 2014-04-17
FIXME: Vanished in Beta 5, check if it will return
  <tip>
   <title>Restoring the Default Settings</title>
   <para>
    You can reset all changes to the defaults by clicking <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Change</guimenu> <guimenu>Reset to Defaults</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>. &yast; then shows the original proposal again.
   </para>
  </tip>
-->
 

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.sofware">
   <title><guimenu>Software</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    &productname; contains a number of software patterns for various
    application purposes. Click <guimenu>Software</guimenu> to open the
    <guimenu>Software Selection and System Tasks</guimenu> screen where you
    can modify the pattern selection according to your needs. Select a pattern
    from the list and see a description in the right-hand part of the
    window. Each pattern contains a number of software packages needed for
    specific functions (for example <phrase os="sled">Multimedia or Office
    software</phrase><phrase os="sles">Web and LAMP server or a print
    server</phrase>). For a more detailed selection based on software packages
    to install, select <guimenu>Details</guimenu> to switch to the &yast;
    Software Manager.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can also install additional software packages or remove software
    packages from your system at any later time with the &yast; Software
    Manager. For more information, refer to <xref linkend="cha.y2.sw"/>.
   </para>

   <figure os="sles">
    <title>Software Selection and System Tasks</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <textobject role="description">
      <phrase>Software Selection and System Tasks</phrase>
     </textobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="i_y2_software_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="i_y2_software_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <figure os="sled">
    <title>Software Selection and System Tasks</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <textobject role="description">
      <phrase>Software Selection and System Tasks</phrase>
     </textobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="i_y2_software_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="i_y2_software_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <note os="sles">
    <title>Graphical Desktop</title>
    <para>
     By default &productname; is installed with X Window and the GNOME desktop
     environment. If you do not need X Window, deselect the two respective
     patterns in the <guimenu>Software Selection and System Tasks</guimenu>
     screen. As an alternative to GNOME, the light-weight window manager IceWM
     can be installed. Select <guimenu>Details</guimenu> from the
     <guimenu>Software Selection and System Tasks</guimenu> screen and search
     for <literal>icewm</literal>.
    </para>
   </note>
   
   <tip os="sles" arch="zseries">
    <title>IBM &zseries;:  HW crypto support</title>
    <para>
     The HW crypto stack is not installed by default. To install it, select
     <guimenu>Sytem z HW crypto support</guimenu> in the <guimenu>Software
     Selection and System Tasks</guimenu> screen.
    </para>
   </tip>
         
   <tip id="ann.sec.i.yast2.proposal.sofware.language">
    <title>Adding Secondary Languages</title>
    <para>
     The language you selected with the first step of the installation will be
     used as the primary (default) language for the system. You can add
     secondary languages from within the <guimenu>Software</guimenu> dialog by
     choosing <menuchoice> <guimenu>Details</guimenu> <guimenu>View</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Languages</guimenu></menuchoice>. 
    </para>
   </tip>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.booting">
   <title><guimenu>Booting</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    The installer proposes a boot configuration for your system. Other operating
    systems found on your computer, such as Microsoft Windows or other Linux
    installations, will automatically be detected and added to the boot
    loader. However, &productname; will be booted by default. Normally, you
    can leave these settings unchanged. If you need a custom setup, modify
    the proposal according to your needs. For information, see
    <xref linkend="sec.grub2.yast2.config"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.firewall">
   <title><guimenu>Firewall and SSH</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    By default &susefirewall; is enabled on all configured network
    interfaces. To globally disable the firewall for this computer, click on
    <guimenu>Disable</guimenu> (not recommended).
   </para>
   <para>
    To enable remote access vi the secure shell (SSH), make sure the
    <literal>SSH service</literal> is enabled and the <literal>SSH
    port</literal> is open.
   </para>

   <note>
    <title>Firwall Settings</title>
    <para>
     If the firewall is activated, all interfaces are configured to be in the
     <quote>External Zone</quote>, where all ports are closed by default,
     ensuring maximum security. The
     only port you can open during the installation is port 22 (SSH), to allow
     remote access. All other services requiring network access (such as FTP,
     Samba, Web server, etc.) will only work after having adjusted the
     firewall settings. Refer to <xref linkend="cha.security.firewall"/> for
     more information. 
    </para>
   </note>

   <para>
    In case you are performing a remote administration over VNC, you can also
    configure whether the machine should be accessible via VNC even after the
    installation. Note that enabling VNC also requires to set the
    <guimenu>Default systemd Target</guimenu> to <guimenu>graphical</guimenu>.
   </para>
   
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.kdump" os="sles">
   <title><guimenu>Kdump</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    Using Kdump, you can save a dump of the kernel (in case of a crash) to
    analyze what went wrong. Use this dialog to enable and configure Kdump.
    Find detailed information at <xref
     linkend="cha.tuning.kexec"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.blacklist" os="sles" arch="zseries">
   <title>IBM &zseries;: Blacklist Devices</title>
   <para>
    In order to save memory, all channels for devices currently not in use,
    are blacklisted by default (each channel that is not blacklisted occupies
    approximately 50 kB of memory). To configure additional hardware in the
    installed system using channels which are currently blacklisted, run
    <menuchoice><guimenu>&yast;</guimenu> <guimenu>FIXME</guimenu>
    </menuchoice> to enable the respective channels first. 
    <remark condition="clarity">
     2014-06-05 - fs: What's the name of the yast module?
    </remark>
   </para>
   <para>
    To disable blacklisting, click <guimenu>disable</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.runlevel">
   <title><guimenu>Default systemd Target</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    &productname; can boot into two different targets (formerly known as
    <quote>runlevels</quote>). The <guimenu>graphical</guimenu> target starts
    a displaymanager, whereas the <guimenu>multi-user</guimenu> target
    starts the command line interface.
   </para>
   <para>
    The default target is <guimenu>graphical</guimenu>. In case you have not
    installed the <guimenu>X Window System</guimenu> patterns, you need to
    change it to <guimenu>multi-user</guimenu>. If the system should be
    accessible via VNC, you have to choose <guimenu>graphical</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.system">
   <title><guimenu>System</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    This screen lists all the hardware information the installer could obtain
    about your computer. When opened for the first time, the hardware
    detection is started. Depending on your system, this may take some
    time. Select any item in the list and click <guimenu>Details</guimenu> to
    see detailed information about the selected item. Use <guimenu>Save to
    File</guimenu> to save a detailed list to either the local file system or
    a removable device.
   </para>
   <para>
    Advanced users can also change the <guimenu>PCI ID Setup</guimenu> and
    Kernel Settings by choosing <guimenu>Kernel Settings</guimenu>. A screen
    with two tabs opens:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>PCI ID Setup</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Each kernel driver contains a list of device IDs of all devices it
       supports. If a new device is not in any driver's database, the device
       is treated as unsupported, even if it can be used with an existing
       driver. You can add PCI IDs to a device driver here. Only advanced
       users should attempt to do so.
      </para>
      <para>
       To add an ID, click Add and select whether to
       <guimenu>Manually</guimenu> enter the data, or whether to choose from a
       list. Enter the required data. The <guimenu>SysFS Dir</guimenu> is the
       directory name from <filename>/sys/bus/pci/drivers</filename>&mdash;if
       empty, the <guimenu>driver</guimenu> name is used as the directory
       name. Existing entries can be managed with <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> and
       <guimenu>Delete</guimenu>. 
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Kernel Settings</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Change the <guimenu>Global I/O Scheduler</guimenu> here. If
       <guimenu>Not Configured</guimenu> is chosen, the default setting for
       the respective architecture will be used. This setting can also be
       changed at any time later from the installed system. Refer to <xref
       linkend="cha.tuning.io"/> for details on I/O tuning.
      </para>
      <para>
       Also the <guimenu>Enable SysRq Keys</guimenu> here. These keys will let
       you issue basic commands (such as rebooting the system or writing
       kernel dumps) in case the system crashes. Enabling these keys is
       recommended when doing kernel development. Refer to <ulink
       url="http://www.kernel.org/doc/Documentation/sysrq.txt"/> for details.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.perform">
  <title>Performing the Installation</title>

  <para>
   After configuring all installation settings, click
   <guimenu>Install</guimenu> in the Installation Settings window to start
   the installation. Some software may require a license confirmation. If
   your software selection includes such software, license confirmation
   dialogs are displayed. Click <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to install the
   software package. When not agreeing to the license, click <guimenu>I
   Disagree</guimenu> and the software package will not be installed. In the
   dialog that follows, confirm with <guimenu>Install</guimenu> again.
  </para>

  <para>

   <!-- fs 2014-04-23:
     FIXME: Check if true
   -->

   The installation usually takes between 15 and 30 minutes, depending on the
   system performance and the selected software scope. After having prepared
   the hard disk and having saved and restored the user settings, the software
   installation starts. During this procedure a slide show introduces the
   features of &productname;. Choose <guimenu>Details</guimenu> to switch to
   the installation log or <guimenu>Release Notes</guimenu> to read important
   up-to-date information which was not available when the manuals were
   printed.
  </para>

  <note os="osuse">
   <title>Release Notes</title>
   <para>
    The release notes that can be viewed during this step are
    the ones printed on the installation CD. A newer version may be
    available on the Internet. When manually configuring network and
    Internet access as described in
    <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.network"/>, the latest version of
    the release notes will be displayed at the end of the installation.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   After the software installation has completed, the system reboots into the
   new installation where you can log in. To customize the system
   configuration or to install additional software packages, start &yast;. 
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.s390.inst.reipl" arch="zseries" os="sles">
   <title>IBM &zseries;: IPLing the Installed System</title>
   <para>
    In most cases, &yast; automatically reboots into the installed system on
    the IBM &zseries; platform. Known exceptions to this are installations
    where the boot loader resides on an FCP device in environments with
    LPAR on a machine older than z196 or with z/VM older than release 5.4. The
    boot loader gets written to a separate partition mountes as
    <filename>/boot/zipl/</filename>. 
   </para>
   <para>
    In cases where an automatic reboot is not possible, &yast; will show a
    dialog containing information about from which device to do an IPL.
    Accept the shutdown option and perform an IPL after the shutdown. The
    procedure varies according to the type of installation:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>LPAR Installation</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In the IBM &zseries; HMC, select <guimenu>Load</guimenu>, select
       <guimenu>Clear</guimenu>, then enter the loading address (the device
       address of the device containing the <filename>/boot/zipl</filename>
       directory with the boot loader). If using a zFCP disk as the boot
       device, choose <guimenu>Load from SCSI</guimenu> and specify the load
       address of your FCP adapter as well as WWPN and LUN of the boot
       device. Now start the loading process.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>z/VM Installation</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Log in to the VM guest (see <xref
       linkend="ex.prep.prep_ipl.vm.linux_guest.config"/> for the
       configuration) as <systemitem class="username">LINUX1</systemitem> and
       proceed to IPL the installed system:
      </para>
      <screen>IPL 151 CLEAR</screen>
      <para>
       <literal>151</literal> is an example address of the DASD boot device,
       replace this value with the correct address.
      </para>
      <para>
       If using a zFCP disk as the boot device, specify both the zFCP WWPN
       and LUN of the boot device before initiating the IPL. The parameter
       length is limited to eight characters. Longer numbers must be
       separated by spaces:
      </para>
      <screen>SET LOADDEV PORT 50050763 00C590A9 LUN 50010000 00000000 </screen>
      <para>
       Finally, initiate the IPL:
      </para>
      <screen>IPL FC00</screen>
      <para>
       <literal>FC00</literal> is an example address of the zFCP adapter,
       replace this value with the correct address.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.s390.inst.reipl.reconnect" arch="zseries" os="sles">
   <title>IBM &zseries;: Connecting to the Installed System</title>
   <para>
    After IPLing the system, establish a connection via VNC, SSH, or X to log
    in to the installed system. using either VNC or SSH is recommended.  To
    customize the system configuration or to install additional software
    packages, start &yast;.
   </para>
   
   <sect3 id="sec.s390.inst.reipl.reconnect.vnc">
    <title>Using VNC to Connect</title>
    <para>
     A message in the 3270&nbsp;terminal asks you to connect to the Linux
     system using a VNC client. This message is easily missed, however,
     because it is mixed with kernel messages and the terminal process might
     quit before you become aware of the message. If nothing happens for
     five minutes, try to initiate a connection to the Linux system using a
     VNC viewer.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you connect using a Java-capable browser, enter the complete URL,
     consisting of the IP address of the installed system along with the
     port number, in the following fashion:
    </para>
    <screen> http://&lt;IP of installed system&gt;:5801/ </screen>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.s390.inst.reipl.reconnect.ssh">
    <title>Using SSH to Connect</title>
    <para>
     A message in the 3270&nbsp;terminal asks you to connect to the Linux
     system with an SSH client. This message is easily missed, however,
     because it is mixed with kernel messages and the terminal process might
     quit before you become aware of the message.
    </para>
    <para>
     When the message appears, use SSH to log in to the Linux system as
     &rootuser;. If the connection is denied or times out, wait for the login
     timeout to expire, then try again (this time may vary depending on server
     settings).
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.s390.inst.reipl.reconnect.x">
    <title>Using X to Connect</title>
    <para>
     When IPLing the installed system, make sure that the X server used for
     the first phase of the installation is up and still available before
     booting from the DASD. &yast; opens on this X server to finish the
     installation. Complications may arise if the system is booted up but
     unable to connect to the X server in a timely fashion.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>


<!--
    <para>
     In <guimenu>Include for Convenience</guimenu>, select whether to send
     unsolicited additional information, such as your <guimenu>Hardware
     Profile</guimenu> or <guimenu>Optional Information</guimenu> when
     registering. This simplifies the registration process. Click on
     <guimenu>Details</guimenu> to get in-depth information about how the
     data will be collected. In order to obtain information about which data
     will be sent for your specific product, the Novell server will be
     connected. Upon this initial connect no data other than the ID of your
     product will be sent to the Novell servers.
    </para>
    <para>
     In order to become entitled for support, make sure to check
     <guimenu>Registration Code</guimenu>. You will be prompted to enter the
     code when proceeding with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. Find more
     information about the technical support at
     <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/support/programs/"/>.
    </para>
    <note>
     <title>Data Privacy</title>
     <para>
      No information is passed to anyone outside Novell. The data is used
      for statistical purposes and to enhance your convenience regarding
      driver support and your Web account. Find a link to the detailed
      privacy policy by clicking on <guimenu>Details</guimenu>. View the
      information transmitted in the log file at
      <filename>/root/.suse_register.log</filename>.
     </para>
    </note>
    <para>
     Apart from activating and registering your product, this module also
     adds the official update repositories to your configuration. These
     repositories provide fixes for known bugs or security issues which can
     be installed via an online update.
    </para>
    <para>
     To keep your repositories valid, select <guimenu>Regularly Synchronize
     with Customer Center</guimenu>. This option checks your repositories
     and adds newly available catalogs or removes obsolete ones. It does not
     affect manually-added repositories.
    </para>
    <para os="sled">
     In addition to the update repositories, two more catalogs with official
     drivers for ATI and NVidia graphics cards are added. &productname;
     ships with open source drivers for these cards, but the official
     drivers, provided directly by the graphics cards manufacturers, offer
     additional functionality. In order to add these repositories, you need
     to import their public &gpg; keys&mdash;these keys are used to ensure
     the repositories is provided by the owner of the catalog. Click
     <guimenu>Trust Key</guimenu> and then <guimenu>Import</guimenu> to add
     the catalog. Click <guimenu>Skip package</guimenu> and then
     <guimenu>Abort</guimenu> to prevent this specific repository from being
     added to your configuration.
    </para>
    <para>
     Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. A connection with the Novell
     server is established. Follow the on-screen instructions to finish the
     registration.
    </para>
    <tip>
     <title>Re-registering an Installed System with a Different Registration Code</title>
     <para>
      When you register a system in &ncc;, registration data is stored
      locally and in the &ncc; database. Although it is normally not
      necessary, there are corner cases which may require you to re-register
      an already installed machine with a different registration code. To do
      so, proceed with the following steps on the installed system:
     </para>
     <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Enter the following command as user &rootuser; to delete the
        installation data on the local machine:
       </para>
<screen>suse_register.pl \-\-erase-local-regdata</screen>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Next you need to remove the registered system from the &ncc;
        database. Go to <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/"/> in a browser and
        click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Support</guimenu> <guimenu>Customer
        Center</guimenu></menuchoice>. Log in and navigate to <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>My Systems</guimenu>
        <guimenu>System</guimenu></menuchoice>. Select the system and remove
        it by clicking on the dash sign in the bottom bar of the table.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Now you can re-register the machine with either
        <command>suse-register</command> or the &yast; module
        <guimenu>Online Update Configuration</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </orderedlist>
    </tip>
    <sect4 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.cc.local">
     <title>Local Registration Server</title>
     <para>
      If your organization provides a local registration server instead of
      using the &ncc;, you need to specify the server's URL. Client and
      server communicate solely via HTTPS protocol, therefore you also need
      to enter a path to the server's certificate if the certificate was not
      issued by a certificate authority. Open the dialog with <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> <guimenu>Local Registration
      Server</guimenu> </menuchoice>
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>Registration Server</guimenu>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         URL of the registration server. The URL has a fixed format
         <literal>https://<replaceable>FQN</replaceable>/center/regsvc/</literal>
         <replaceable>FQN</replaceable> has to be full qualified host name of
         the registration server. Example:
        </para>
<screen>https://smt.&exampledomain;/center/regsvc/</screen>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Server CA certificate location</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Location of the registration server's certificate. Specify one of
         the following locations:
        </para>
        <variablelist>
         <varlistentry>
          <term>URL</term>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            Remote location (http, https or ftp) from which the certificate
            can be downloaded. Example:
           </para>
<screen>http://smt.&exampledomain;/smt-ca.crt</screen>
          </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
          <term>local path</term>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            Absolute path to the certificate on the local machine. Example:
           </para>
<screen>/data/inst/smt/smt-ca.cert</screen>
          </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
          <term>Interactive</term>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            Use <literal>ask</literal> to open a pop-up menu where you can
            specify the path to the certificate. Do not use this option with
            &ay;. Example
           </para>
<screen>ask</screen>
          </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
          <term>Deactivate certificate installation</term>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            Use <literal>done</literal> if either the certificate will be
            installed by an add-on product, or if you are using a
            certificate issued by an official certificate authority.
            Example:
           </para>
<screen>done</screen>
          </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </sect4>
   </sect3>
-->

<!--
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode">
  <title>Installation Mode</title>

  <para>
   After a system analysis (where &yast; probes for storage devices and
   tries to find other installed systems on your machine) the available
   installation modes are displayed.<phrase os="osuse"> This step is skipped
   when installing from a LiveCD, since this medium only supports a new
   installation with automatic configuration.</phrase>
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>New installation</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Select this option to start a new installation from scratch.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Update</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Select this option to update an existing installation to a newer
      version. For more information about system update, see
      <xref
      linkend="cha.update.sle"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Repair Installed System</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Choose this option to repair a damaged system that is already
      installed. More information is available in
      <xref linkend="sec.trouble.data.recover"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <figure os="sled">
   <title>Installation Mode</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_mode_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_mode_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <figure os="sles">
   <title>Installation Mode</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_mode_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_mode_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para os="sled">
   By default, the automatic configuration is used when performing a new
   installation. In this mode the system automatically configures your
   hardware and the network, so the installation is performed with minimal
   user interaction. If necessary, you can change every configuration that
   is set up later in the installed system using &yast;. In repair mode the
   automatic configuration attempts to fix errors automatically. Deactivate
   <guimenu>Use Automatic Configuration</guimenu> if you prefer a manual
   configuration during the installation or to start the system's
   repair-process in expert mode.
  </para>

  <para>
   Check <guimenu>Include Add-On Products from Separate Media</guimenu> to
   include add-on products during the installation. An add-on product can
   include extensions, third-party products and drivers or additional
   software for your system<phrase os="osuse"> such as support for
   additional languages</phrase>.
  </para>

<!\-\- fs, 2011-08-10: Fate #312624 \-\->

  <tip>
   <title>Installing Product Patches from an SMT Server on Installation</title>
   <para>
    In case your organization provides the update channel for &productname;
    via an SMT server, it is possible to specify this channel as an Add-On
    product by entering its HTTP address. As a consequence, the system will
    be installed with the most current packages without having to apply the
    updates at the end of the installation.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
   Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed. If you selected to include an
   add-on product, proceed with
   <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.addon"/>, otherwise skip the next
   section and advance to <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.timezone"/>.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.addon">
   <title>Add-On Products</title>
   <para>
    Add-on products can be installed either from a local source (CD, DVD, or
    directory) or from a network source (HTTP, FTP, NFS, CIFS,...). When
    installing from a network source, you need to configure the network
    first (unless you are performing a network installation&mdash; in this
    case the existing network configuration is used). Choose <guimenu>Yes,
    Run the Network Setup</guimenu> and proceed as described in
    <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.network"/>. If the add-on product
    is available locally, select <guimenu>No, Skip the Network
    Setup</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and specify the product source. Source
    types available are <guimenu>CD</guimenu>, <guimenu>DVD</guimenu>,
    <guimenu>Hard Disk</guimenu>, <guimenu>USB Mass Storage</guimenu>, a
    <guimenu>Local Directory</guimenu> or a <guimenu>Local ISO
    Image</guimenu> (if no network was configured). If the add-on product is
    available on removable media, the system automatically mounts the media
    and reads its contents. If the add-on product is available on hard disk,
    choose <guimenu>Hard Disk</guimenu> to install from an unmounted hard
    drive, or <guimenu>Local Directory</guimenu>/<guimenu>Local ISO
    Image</guimenu> to install from the local file system. Add-on products
    may be delivered as a repository or as a set of RPM files. In the latter
    case, check <guimenu>Plain RPM Directory</guimenu>. Whenever a network
    is available, you can choose from additional remote sources such as
    HTTP, SLP, FTP, etc. It is also possible to specify a URL directly.
   </para>
   <para>
    Check <guimenu>Download Repository Description Files</guimenu> to
    download the files describing the repository now. If deactivated, they
    will be downloaded once the installation starts. Proceed with
    <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and insert a CD or DVD if required. Depending on
    the product's content it may be necessary to accept additional license
    agreements.
   </para>
   <para>
    It is also possible to configure add-on products later. Using add-on
    products on the installed system is described in
    <xref linkend="cha.add-ons"/>.
   </para>
   <tip>
    <title>Driver Updates</title>
    <para>
     You can also add driver update repositories via the Add-On Products
     dialog. Driver updates for &sle; are provided at
     <ulink
     url="http://drivers.suse.com/"/>. These drivers have been
     created via the Partner Linux Driver Program.
    </para>
   </tip>
   <sect3
    id="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.network">
    <title>Network Setup</title>
    <para>
     When invoking the network setup, &yast; scans for available network
     cards. If more than one network card is found, you must choose the card
     to configure from the list.
    </para>
    <para>
     If an ethernet network adapter is not already connected, a warning will
     open. Make sure the network cable is plugged in and choose
     <guimenu>Yes, Use It</guimenu>. If your network is equipped with a DHCP
     server, choose <guimenu>Automatic Address Setup (via DHCP)</guimenu>.
     To manually set up the network choose <guimenu>Static Address
     Setup</guimenu> and specify <guimenu>IP Address</guimenu>,
     <guimenu>Netmask</guimenu>, <guimenu>Default Gateway IP</guimenu>, and
     the <guimenu>DNS Server IP</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Some networks require the use of a proxy server to access the Internet.
     Tick the check box <guimenu>Use Proxy for Accessing the
     Internet</guimenu> and enter the appropriate specifications. Click
     <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to perform the network setup. The
     installation procedure will continue with the add-on products or
     repositories setup as described in
     <xref
      linkend="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.addon"/>.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.desktop" os="osuse">
  <title>Desktop Selection</title>

  <para>
   In &productname;, you can choose from various desktops. The major ones,
   <guimenu>KDE</guimenu> and <guimenu>GNOME</guimenu>, are powerful
   graphical desktop environments similar to Windows. Find information about
   these in the <xref linkend="book.kdeuser"/> and the
   <xref linkend="book.gnomeuser"/>.<phrase os="osuse"> This step is skipped
   when installing from a LiveCD, since this medium is already
   pre-configured to either use KDE or GNOME.</phrase>
  </para>

  <para>
   If you prefer a different desktop, choose <guimenu>Other</guimenu> for
   more options. The <guimenu>XFCE Desktop</guimenu> is a fast and
   lightweight desktop environment suitable for modest hardware. With
   <guimenu>Minimal X Window</guimenu>, install a graphical window manager
   that allows for running stand-alone X applications and console windows
   but does not provide the usual integrated desktop functionality. In
   <guimenu>Minimal Server Selection (Text Mode)</guimenu>, only console
   terminals are available.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.inst.sys_type">
   <title>Desktop Selection</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_sys_type.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_sys_type.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.server" os="sles">
  <title>Server Base Scenario</title>

  <para>
   In &productname;, you can choose from three base scenarios. The selected
   scenario affects the package selection.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Physical Machine</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Choose this scenario when installing on a <quote>real</quote> machine
      or a fully virtualized guest.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Virtual Machine</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Choose this scenario when installing a paravirtualized guest.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>XEN Virtualization Host</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Choose this scenario when installing on a machine that should serve as
      a XEN host.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <figure>
   <title>Server Base Scenario</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_server_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_server_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.partitioning" os="osuse">
  <title>Suggested Partitioning</title>

  <para>
   Define a partition setup for &productname; in this step. In most cases a
   reasonable scheme that can be accepted without change is proposed. If a
   hard disk containing only Windows FAT or NTFS partitions is selected as
   the installation target, &yast; proposes to shrink one of these
   partitions. Accept the proposal with <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and proceed
   with the installation. Experienced users can also customize the proposal
   or apply their own partitioning scheme.
  </para>

  <para>
   The proposed partitioning is <guimenu>Partition Based</guimenu> by
   default. If you prefer an <guimenu>LVM Based</guimenu> setup, check the
   respective option to automatically convert the proposal. Refer to
   <xref linkend="sec.yast2.system.lvm"/> for more information about the
   Logical Volume Manager (LVM).
  </para>

  <para>
   To make small changes in the proposal (like changing the file system type
   or encrypt partitions), select <guimenu>Edit Partition Setup</guimenu>
   and adjust the settings. See <xref linkend="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert"/>
   for instructions.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.inst.partitioning" os="osuse">
   <title>Suggested Partitioning</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_partitioning.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_partitioning.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <note arch="POWER">
   <title>Suggested Partitioning on IBM &ppc;</title>
   <para>
    An already existing boot partition is usually re-used by &yast; when
    making the partitioning proposal. This is not possible on IBM &ppc;.
   </para>
  </note>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.partitioning.disk">
   <title>Partitioning a Specific Disk</title>
   <para>
    If your machine contains more than one hard disk and you want to
    restrict the partitioning proposal to just one disk, choose
    <guimenu>Create Partition Setup</guimenu> and then select a specific
    disk from the list. If the chosen hard disk does not contain any
    partitions yet, the whole hard disk will be used for the proposal.
    Otherwise, you can choose which existing partition(s) to use. To add a
    separate partition for you personal data check <guimenu>Propose a
    Separate Home Partition</guimenu>. Instead of the default
    partition-based proposal, it is possible to <guimenu>Create an LVM Based
    Proposal</guimenu>. Choose two times <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed
    to the next step.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.partitioning.windows" os="sled;osuse">
    <title>Resizing a Windows Partition</title>
    <para>
     If the selected hard disk only contains a Windows FAT or NTFS
     partition, &yast; offers to delete or shrink this partition. If you
     select <guimenu>Delete Windows Completely</guimenu>, the Windows
     partition is marked for deletion and the space is used for the
     installation of &productname;.
    </para>
    <warning>
     <title>Deleting Windows</title>
     <para>
      If you delete Windows, all data will be lost beyond recovery as soon
      as the formatting starts.
     </para>
    </warning>
    <para>
     To <guimenu>Shrink the Windows Partition</guimenu>, you need to
     interrupt the installation and boot Windows to prepare the partition
     before shrinking it. For all Windows file systems, proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Deactivate a <literal>Virtual Memory</literal> file, if there is one.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Run <command>scandisk</command>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Run <command>defrag</command>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
     After these preparations, restart the &productname; installation. When
     you turn to the partitioning setup, proceed as before and select
     <guimenu>Shrink Windows Partition</guimenu>. After a quick check of the
     partition, the dialog for resizing the Windows partition opens.
    </para>
    <para>
     The bar graph shows how much disk space is currently occupied by
     Windows and how much space is still available. To change the proposed
     settings use the slider or the input fields to adjust the partition
     sizing.
    </para>
    <figure
     id="fig.yast2.inst_resize_ui-000">
     <title>Resizing the Windows Partition</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="i_y2_disk_resizer.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="i_y2_disk_resizer.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
     If you leave this dialog by selecting <guimenu>Next</guimenu>, the
     settings are stored and you are returned to the previous dialog. The
     actual resizing takes place later, before the hard disk is formatted.
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>Writing on NTFS Partitions</title>
     <para>
      By default, the Windows uses the NTFS file system.
      &productname; includes read and write access to the NTFS file system,
      but this feature has a few limitations. This means that you cannot
      read or write encrypted or compressed files. Furthermore, the Windows
      file permissions are not honored at the moment.<phrase os="osuse"> See
      <ulink
	url="http://en.opensuse.org/SDB:NTFS"/> for more
      information.</phrase>
     </para>
    </important>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.partitioning.custom">
   <title>Custom Partitioning</title>
   <para>
    Set up your own partitioning scheme by selecting <guimenu>Create
    Partition Setup</guimenu> and then <guimenu>Custom
    Partitioning</guimenu>. The Expert Partitioner opens, displaying the
    current partition setup. Expand the <guimenu>Hard Disks</guimenu> in the
    System View pane by clicking on the <guimenu>+</guimenu>, then click on
    one of the listed hard disks. Now you can <guimenu>Add</guimenu>,
    <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>, <guimenu>Resize</guimenu>, or
    <guimenu>Delete</guimenu> partitions. For more information about custom
    partitioning and configuring advanced features, refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert"/>
   </para>
   <warning>
    <title>Custom Partitioning on UEFI machines</title>
    <para>
     A UEFI machine <emphasis>requires</emphasis> an EFI system partition
     that must be mounted to <filename>/boot/efi</filename>. This partition
     must be formatted with the <literal>FAT</literal> file system.
    </para>
    <para>
     If an EFI system partition is already present present on your system
     (for example from a previous Windows installation) use it by mounting
     it to <filename>/boot/efi</filename> without formatting it.
    </para>
   </warning>
  </sect2>  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.partitioning.disk">
   <title>Partitioning a Specific Disk</title>
   <para>
    If your machine contains more than one hard disk and you want to
    restrict the partitioning proposal to just one disk, choose
    <guimenu>Create Partition Setup</guimenu> and then select a specific
    disk from the list. If the chosen hard disk does not contain any
    partitions yet, the whole hard disk will be used for the proposal.
    Otherwise, you can choose which existing partition(s) to use. To add a
    separate partition for you personal data check <guimenu>Propose a
    Separate Home Partition</guimenu>. Instead of the default
    partition-based proposal, it is possible to <guimenu>Create an LVM Based
    Proposal</guimenu>. Choose two times <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed
    to the next step.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.partitioning.windows" os="sled;osuse">
    <title>Resizing a Windows Partition</title>
    <para>
     If the selected hard disk only contains a Windows FAT or NTFS
     partition, &yast; offers to delete or shrink this partition. If you
     select <guimenu>Delete Windows Completely</guimenu>, the Windows
     partition is marked for deletion and the space is used for the
     installation of &productname;.
    </para>
    <warning>
     <title>Deleting Windows</title>
     <para>
      If you delete Windows, all data will be lost beyond recovery as soon
      as the formatting starts.
     </para>
    </warning>
    <para>
     To <guimenu>Shrink the Windows Partition</guimenu>, you need to
     interrupt the installation and boot Windows to prepare the partition
     before shrinking it. For all Windows file systems, proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Deactivate a <literal>Virtual Memory</literal> file, if there is one.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Run <command>scandisk</command>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Run <command>defrag</command>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
     After these preparations, restart the &productname; installation. When
     you turn to the partitioning setup, proceed as before and select
     <guimenu>Shrink Windows Partition</guimenu>. After a quick check of the
     partition, the dialog for resizing the Windows partition opens.
    </para>
    <para>
     The bar graph shows how much disk space is currently occupied by
     Windows and how much space is still available. To change the proposed
     settings use the slider or the input fields to adjust the partition
     sizing.
    </para>
    <figure
     id="fig.yast2.inst_resize_ui-000">
     <title>Resizing the Windows Partition</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="i_y2_disk_resizer.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="i_y2_disk_resizer.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
     If you leave this dialog by selecting <guimenu>Next</guimenu>, the
     settings are stored and you are returned to the previous dialog. The
     actual resizing takes place later, before the hard disk is formatted.
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>Writing on NTFS Partitions</title>
     <para>
      By default, the Windows uses the NTFS file system.
      &productname; includes read and write access to the NTFS file system,
      but this feature has a few limitations. This means that you cannot
      read or write encrypted or compressed files. Furthermore, the Windows
      file permissions are not honored at the moment.<phrase os="osuse"> See
      <ulink
	url="http://en.opensuse.org/SDB:NTFS"/> for more
      information.</phrase>
     </para>
    </important>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.partitioning.custom">
   <title>Custom Partitioning</title>
   <para>
    Set up your own partitioning scheme by selecting <guimenu>Create
    Partition Setup</guimenu> and then <guimenu>Custom
    Partitioning</guimenu>. The Expert Partitioner opens, displaying the
    current partition setup. Expand the <guimenu>Hard Disks</guimenu> in the
    System View pane by clicking on the <guimenu>+</guimenu>, then click on
    one of the listed hard disks. Now you can <guimenu>Add</guimenu>,
    <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>, <guimenu>Resize</guimenu>, or
    <guimenu>Delete</guimenu> partitions. For more information about custom
    partitioning and configuring advanced features, refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert"/>
   </para>
   <warning>
    <title>Custom Partitioning on UEFI machines</title>
    <para>
     A UEFI machine <emphasis>requires</emphasis> an EFI system partition
     that must be mounted to <filename>/boot/efi</filename>. This partition
     must be formatted with the <literal>FAT</literal> file system.
    </para>
    <para>
     If an EFI system partition is already present present on your system
     (for example from a previous Windows installation) use it by mounting
     it to <filename>/boot/efi</filename> without formatting it.
    </para>
   </warning>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.user" os="osuse;sled">
  <title>Create New User</title>

  <para>
   Create a local user in this step. Administrating local users is a
   suitable option for stand-alone workstations. If setting up a client on a
   network with centralized user authentication, click
   <guimenu>Change</guimenu> and proceed with the
   <xref
    linkend="sec.i.yast2.user.expert"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   After entering the first name and last name, either accept the proposal
   or specify a new <guimenu>Username</guimenu> that will be used to log in.
   Finally, enter a password for the user. Reenter it for confirmation (to
   ensure that you did not type something else by mistake). To provide
   effective security, a password should be between five and eight
   characters long. The maximum length for a password is 72 characters.
   However, if no special security modules are loaded, only the first eight
   characters are used to discern the password. Passwords are
   case-sensitive. Special characters (7-bit ASCII) and the digits 0 to 9
   are allowed. Other special characters like umlauts or accented characters
   are not allowed.
  </para>

  <para>
   Passwords you enter are checked for weakness. When entering a password
   that is easy to guess (such as a dictionary word or a name) you will see
   a warning. It is a good security practice to use strong passwords.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Username and Password</title>
   <para>
    Remember both your username and the password because they are needed
    each time you log in to the system.
   </para>
  </important>

  <figure os="osuse">
   <title>Create New User</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_user.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_user.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <figure os="sled">
   <title>Create New User</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_user_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_user_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   Three additional options are available:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Use this Password for the System Administrator</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If checked, the same password you have entered for the user will be
      used for the system administrator &rootuser;. This option is suitable
      for stand-alone workstations or machines in a home network that are
      administrated by a single user. When not checked, you are prompted for
      a system administrator password in the next step of the installation
      workflow (see <xref
       linkend="sec.i.yast2.user.root"/>).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Receive System Mail</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Checking this box sends messages created by the system services to the
      user. These are usually only sent to &rootuser;, the system
      administrator. This option is useful for the most frequently used
      account, because it is highly recommended to log in as &rootuser; only
      in special cases.
     </para>
     <para>
      The mails sent by system services are stored in the local mailbox
      <filename>/var/spool/mail/</filename><replaceable>username</replaceable>,
      where <replaceable>username</replaceable> is the login name of the
      selected user. To read e-mails after installation, you can use any
      e-mail client, for example KMail or Evolution.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Automatic Login</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option automatically logs the current user in to the system when
      it starts. This is mainly useful if the computer is operated by only
      one user. <phrase os="sles">For automatic login to work, the option
      must be explicitly enabled.</phrase>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <warning os="osuse;sled">
   <title>Automatic Login</title>
   <para>
    With the automatic login enabled, the system boots straight into your
    desktop with no authentication at all. If you store sensitive data on
    your system, you should not enable this option as long as the computer
    can also be accessed by others.
   </para>
  </warning>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.user.expert">
   <title>Expert Settings</title>
   <para os="osuse;sled">
    Click <guimenu>Change</guimenu> in the Create User dialog to set up
    network authentication or, if present, import users from a previous
    installation. Also change the password encryption type in this dialog.
   </para>
   <para os="sles">
    If network access was configured successfully during the previous steps
    of the installation, you can now choose from several user management
    options. If a network connection has not been configured, create local
    user accounts. You may also, if present, import users from a previous
    installation. Also change the password encryption type in this dialog.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can also add additional user accounts or change the user
    authentication method in the installed system. For detailed information
    about user management, see <xref linkend="cha.y2.userman"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The default authentication method is <guimenu>Local
    (/etc/passwd)</guimenu>. If a former version of &productname; or another
    system using <filename>/etc/passwd</filename> is detected, you may
    import local users. To do so, check <guimenu>Read User Data from a
    Previous Installation</guimenu> and click <guimenu>Choose</guimenu>. In
    the next dialog, select the users to import and finish with
    <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Access to the following network authentication services can be
    configured:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>LDAP</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Users are administered centrally on an LDAP server for all systems in
       the network. More information is available in
       <xref linkend="sec.security.ldap.yast.client"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>NIS</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Users are administered centrally on a NIS server for all systems in
       the network. See <xref linkend="sec.nis.client"/> for more
       information.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Windows Domain</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SMB authentication is often used in mixed Linux and Windows networks.
       <phrase os="sles"
        >Detailed information is available in
       <xref linkend="sec.samba.adnet"/></phrase> and
       <phrase
        os="sled;osuse"><xref linkend="sec.security.ad.config"/></phrase>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry os="sled">
     <term>eDirectory LDAP</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       eDirectory authentication is used in Novell networks.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    Along with user administration via <guimenu>LDAP</guimenu> and
    <guimenu>NIS</guimenu>, you can use Kerberos authentication. To use it,
    select <guimenu>Set Up Kerberos Authentication</guimenu>. For more
    information on Kerberos, refer to
    <xref
     linkend="cha.security.kerberos"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.user.root">
   <title>Password for the System Administrator &rootuser;</title>
   <para>
    If you have not chosen <guimenu>Use this Password for the System
    Administrator</guimenu> in the previous step, you will be prompted to
    enter a Password for the System Administrator &rootuser;. Otherwise this
    configuration step is skipped.
   </para>
   <para>
    &rootuser; is the name of the superuser, or the administrator of the
    system. Unlike regular users (who may or may not have permission to
    access certain areas or execute certain commands on the system),
    &rootuser; has unlimited access to change the system configuration,
    install programs, and set up new hardware. If users forget their
    passwords or have other problems with the system, &rootuser; can help.
    The &rootuser; account should only be used for system administration,
    maintenance, and repair. Logging in as &rootuser; for daily work is
    rather risky: a single mistake could lead to irretrievable loss of
    system files.
   </para>
   <para>
    For verification purposes, the password for &rootuser; must be entered
    twice. Do not forget the &rootuser; password. Once entered, this
    password cannot be retrieved.
   </para>
   <para>
    The &rootuser; can be changed any time later in the installed system. To
    do so run &yast; and start <menuchoice> <guimenu>Security and
    Users</guimenu> <guimenu>User and Group Management</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>.
   </para>
   <warning>
    <title>The root User</title>
    <para>
     The user &rootuser; has all the permissions needed to make changes to
     the system. To carry out such tasks, the &rootuser; password is
     required. You cannot carry out any administrative tasks without this
     password.
    </para>
   </warning>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.conf">
  <title>Configuration of the Installed System</title>

  <para>
   The system is now installed, but not yet configured for use. The
   hardware, the network and other services are not yet set
   up.<phrase os="osuse;sled"> If you follow the default installation path,
   the system will be automatically configured. If you have deselected the
   <guimenu>Automatic Configuration</guimenu>, the manual system
   configuration starts.</phrase>
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.auto" os="osuse;sled">
   <title>Automatic System Configuration</title>
   <para>
    Having rebooted, the system starts the Automatic Configuration. This
    routine attempts to configure your network and Internet access and sets
    up your hardware. This process does not need any interaction. You can
    change the settings made by Automatic Configuration at any time on the
    installed system with &yast;. Continue with
    <phrase os="osuse"><xref
      linkend="sec.i.yast2.conf.dm"/></phrase><phrase os="sled"><xref
      linkend="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.cc"/></phrase>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual">
   <title><phrase os="osuse;sled;">Manual </phrase>System Configuration</title>
   <para>
    Having rebooted, the system starts the manual configuration. If the
    configuration fails at one of the steps of this stage, it restarts and
    continues from the last successful step.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.root">
    <title>Password for the System Administrator <quote>root</quote></title>
    <para>
     &rootuser; is the name of the superuser, the administrator of the
     system. Unlike regular users, who may or may not have permission to
     execute administrative commands on the system, &rootuser; has unlimited
     command capacity, for instance changing the system configuration,
     installing programs, and setting up new hardware. If users forget their
     passwords or have other problems with the system, &rootuser; can help.
     The &rootuser; account should only be used for system administration,
     maintenance, and repair. Logging in as &rootuser; for daily work is
     rather risky: a single mistake could lead to the irretrievable loss of
     system files.
    </para>
    <para>
     For verification purposes, the password for &rootuser; must be entered
     twice. Do not forget the &rootuser; password. Once entered, this
     password cannot be retrieved.
    </para>
    <para>
     When typing passwords, the characters are replaced by dots, so you do
     not see the string you are typing. If you are unsure whether you have
     typed the correct string, use the <guimenu>Test Keyboard
     Layout</guimenu> field for testing purposes.
    </para>
    <para>
     &productname; can use the DES, MD5, or Blowfish encryption algorithms
     for passwords. The default encryption type is Blowfish. To change the
     encryption type, click <menuchoice><guimenu>Expert
     Options</guimenu><guimenu>Encryption Type</guimenu></menuchoice> and
     select the new type.
    </para>
    <para>
     The &rootuser; can be changed any time later in the installed system.
     To do so run &yast; and start <menuchoice> <guimenu>Security and
     Users</guimenu> <guimenu>User and Group Management</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.hostname">
    <title>Host name and Domain Name</title>
    <para>
     The hostname is the computer's name in the network. The domain name is
     the name of the network. A hostname and domain are proposed by default.
     If your system is part of a network, the hostname has to be unique in
     this network, whereas the domain name has to be common to all hosts on
     the network.
    </para>
    <para>
     In many networks, the system receives its name over DHCP. In this case
     it is not necessary to modify the proposed hostname and domain name.
     Select <guimenu>Change Hostname via DHCP</guimenu> instead. To be able
     to access your system using this hostname, even when it is not
     connected to the network, select <guimenu>Assign Hostname to Loopback
     IP</guimenu>. Do not enable this option when your machine provides
     network services. If you often change networks without restarting the
     desktop environment (e.g. when switching between different Wi-Fis), do
     not enable this option either, because the desktop system may get
     confused when the hostname in <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> changes.
    </para>
    <para>
     To change hostname settings at any time after installation, use &yast;
     <menuchoice><guimenu>Network Devices</guimenu><guimenu>Network
     Settings</guimenu></menuchoice>. For more information, see
     <xref linkend="sec.basicnet.yast.netcard"/>.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3
    id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.network">
    <title>Network Configuration</title>
    <tip arch="zseries" os="sles">
     <title>IBM &zseries;: Network Configuration</title>
     <para>
      For the IBM &zseries; platforms, a working network connection is
      needed at installation time to connect to the target system, the
      installation source, and the &yast; terminal controlling the process.
      The steps to set up the network are discussed in
      <xref
       linkend="sec.prep.netcfg"/>. The IBM &zseries; platforms
      only support the types of network interfaces mentioned there (OSA
      Ethernet, OSA Gigabit Ethernet, OSA Express Fast Ethernet, Escon, and
      IUCV). The &yast; dialog simply displays the interface with its
      settings as already configured. Just confirm this dialog to continue.
     </para>
    </tip>
    <para os="osuse;sled">
     If you are installing &productname; on a laptop computer,
     <guimenu>Interfaces Controlled by &nm;</guimenu> is enabled. &nm; is a
     tool that enables automatic connection with minimal user intervention.
     It is ideal for Wi-Fi and mobile computing. If you want to use the
     traditional method without &nm;, click <guimenu>Disable &nm;</guimenu>.
     Find detailed information about &nm; in <xref linkend="cha.nm"/>. If
     you are installing &productname; on any other type of machine, the
     traditional method without &nm; is selected by default. This
     configuration step also lets you configure the network devices of your
     system and make security settings, for example, for a firewall or
     proxy.
    </para>
    <para os="sles">
     By default, <guimenu>Traditional Method without &nm; Applet</guimenu>
     is enabled. If desired, you can also use &nm; to manage all your
     network devices. However, the traditional method is the preferred
     option for server solutions. Find detailed information about &nm; in
     <xref
      linkend="cha.nm"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The network can also be configured after the system installation has
     been completed. If you skip it now, your system is left offline unable
     to retrieve any available updates. To configure your network connection
     later, select <guimenu>Skip Configuration</guimenu> and click
     <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The following network settings can be configured in this step:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>General Network Settings</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Enable or disable the use of &nm; as described above. Also change
        the IPv6 support here. By default the IPv6 support is enabled. To
        disable it, click <guimenu>Disable IPv6</guimenu>. For more
        information about IPv6, see <xref linkend="sec.basicnet.ipv6"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Firewall</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        By default &susefirewall; is enabled on all configured network
        interfaces. To globally disable the firewall for this computer,
        click on <guimenu>Disable</guimenu>. If the firewall is enabled, you
        may <guimenu>Open</guimenu> the SSH port in order to allow remote
        connections via secure shell. To open the detailed firewall
        configuration dialog, click on <guimenu>Firewall</guimenu>. See
        <xref linkend="sec.security.firewall.SuSE.yast"/> for detailed
        information.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Services</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The CIM (Common Information Model) Server is started by default.
        Click <guimenu>Disable</guimenu> to prevent the server from starting
        automatically at boot time. <phrase os="sles">For more information
        on CIM services refer to <xref linkend="cha.wbem"/>.</phrase>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Network Interfaces</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        All network cards detected by &yast; are listed here. If you have
        already set up a network connection during the installation (as
        described in
        <xref
         linkend="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.network"/>) the card
        used for this connection is listed as <guimenu>Configured</guimenu>.
        A click on <guimenu>Network Interfaces</guimenu> opens the
        <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu> dialog, where you can change
        existing configurations, set up networks cards not configured yet,
        or add and configure additional cards.<phrase os="sled"> See
        <xref linkend="sec.internet.network"/> for checklists of
        configuration requirements for the various connection types and
        <xref linkend="sec.basicnet.yast.netcard"/> for configuration
        details.</phrase>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>DSL Connections</guimenu>, <guimenu>ISDN
        Adapters</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Modems</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If your computer is equipped with an internal DSL modem, an internal
        ADSL Fritz Card, an ISDN card or a modem, clicking on the respective
        headline opens the configuration dialog.
        <phrase>Refer to <xref linkend="cha.internet"/> for
        further information.</phrase>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>VNC Remote Administration</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        To enable remote administration of your machine via VNC, click
        <guimenu>VNC Remote Administration</guimenu>. Choose <guimenu>Allow
        Remote Administration</guimenu> in the following dialog and adjust
        your firewall settings accordingly.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Proxy</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If you have a proxy server controlling the Internet access in your
        network, configure the proxy URLs and authentication details in this
        dialog.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <tip>
     <title>Resetting the Network Configuration to the Default Values</title>
     <para>
      Reset the network settings to the original proposed values by clicking
      <menuchoice> <guimenu>Change</guimenu> <guimenu>Reset to
      Defaults</guimenu> </menuchoice>. This discards any changes made.
     </para>
    </tip>
    <sect4 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.network.internet">
     <title>Test Internet Connection</title>
     <para>
      After having configured a network connection, you can test it. For
      this purpose, &yast; establishes a connection to the &productname;
      server and downloads the latest release notes. Read them at the end of
      the installation process. A successful test is also a prerequisite for
      the automatic addition of the default repositories and for updating
      online.
     </para>
     <para>
      If you have multiple network interfaces, verify that the desired card
      is used to connect to the Internet. If not, click <guimenu>Change
      Device</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <para>
      To start the test, select <guimenu>Yes, Test Connection to the
      Internet</guimenu> and click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. In the following
      dialog, view the progress of the test and the results. Detailed
      information about the test process is available via <guimenu>View
      Logs</guimenu>. If the test fails, click <guimenu>Back</guimenu> to
      return to the network configuration to correct your entries.
     </para>
     <para>
      Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. If the test was successful, the
      official software repositories for &productname; and the update
      repository will be configured. Downloading the repository data for the
      first time may take some time.
     </para>
     <para>
      If you do not want to test the connection at this point, select
      <guimenu>No, Skip This Test</guimenu> then <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
      This also skips downloading the release notes,
      <phrase>configuring the customer center</phrase> and
      updating online. These steps can be performed any time after the
      system has been initially configured.
     </para>
    </sect4>
   </sect3>

   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.update">
    <title>Online Update</title>
    <para>
     If an Internet connection has been established, and updates are
     available, select whether to perform a &yast; online update. If there
     are any patched packages available on the servers, download and install
     them now to fix known bugs or security issues. For detailed
     instructions see <xref linkend="cha.onlineupdate.you"/>. Directives on
     how to perform an online update in the installed system are available
     at <xref linkend="sec.updater"/> or
     <xref
      linkend="cha.onlineupdate.you"/>. This step is skipped if
     no updates are available or no Internet connection has been
     established. Patches fixing security issues and recommended patches
     applying to your installation are automatically preselected. Click
     <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to install them and <guimenu>Next</guimenu>
     to proceed with the system configuration.
    </para>
    <important os="osuse">
     <title>Downloading Software Updates</title>
     <para>
      The download of updates might take quite some time, depending on the
      bandwidth of the Internet connection and the size of the update files.
      In case the patch system itself is updated, the online update will
      restart and download more patches after the restart. If the kernel was
      updated, the system will reboot before completing the configuration.
     </para>
    </important>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.servprop" os="sles">
    <title>Services Configuration</title>
    <para>
     After testing the Internet connection and downloading the first
     updates, a dialog opens in which to enable and configure three network
     services.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>CA Management</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The purpose of a CA (certificate authority) is to guarantee a trust
        relationship among all network services communicating with each
        other. Without a CA, you can secure server communications with SSL
        and TLS separately for each individual service. By default, a CA is
        created and enabled during the installation. Find details about the
        creation of a CA with &yast; in
        <xref linkend="cha.security.yast_ca"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>OpenLDAP Server</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        You can run an LDAP service on your host to have a central facility
        manage a range of configuration files. Typically, an LDAP server
        handles user account data, but with &productname; it can also be
        used for mail, DHCP, and DNS data. By default, an LDAP server is set
        up during the installation. If you decide against the use of an LDAP
        server, the &yast; mail server module does not work because it
        depends on LDAP functionality. However, you can still set up a mail
        server on your system with the help of the <guimenu>Mail Transfer
        Agent</guimenu> module. Find details about LDAP and its
        configuration with &yast; in <xref linkend="cha.security.ldap"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Services</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The CIM (Common Information Model) Server is started by default.
        Click <guimenu>Disable</guimenu> to prevent the server automatically
        stating at boot time. For more information on CIM services refer to
        <xref
	 linkend="cha.wbem"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
     If preferred, you can skip this configuration proposal for now. After
     the installation is finished, configure and start the same services
     with the help of &yast;.
    </para>
    <tip>
     <title>Resetting the Service Configuration to Defaults</title>
     <para>
      Restore the defaults by clicking <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Change</guimenu> <guimenu>Reset to Defaults</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>. This discards any changes made.
     </para>
    </tip>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.users" os="osuse;sled">
    <title>New Local User</title>
    <para>
     If no local user was created in step one, you can create one in this
     dialog. To create more users, manage groups, modify defaults for new
     users and set up network authentication, launch <guimenu>User
     Management</guimenu>. Refer to <xref linkend="cha.y2.userman"/> for
     more information about user management. To skip this step, click
     <guimenu>Next</guimenu> without entering any data.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.user_auth" os="sles">
    <title>User Authentication Method</title>
    <para>
     If network access was configured successfully during the previous steps
     of the installation, you can now choose from several user management
     options. If a network connection has not been configured, create local
     user accounts. You may also, if present, import users from a previous
     installation. Also change the password encryption type in this dialog.
    </para>
    <para>
     You can also add additional user accounts or change the user
     authentication method in the installed system. For detailed information
     about user management, see <xref
      linkend="cha.y2.userman"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The default authentication method is <guimenu>Local
     (/etc/passwd)</guimenu>. If a former version of &productname; or
     another system using <filename>/etc/passwd</filename> is detected, you
     may import local users. To do so, check <guimenu>Read User Data from a
     Previous Installation</guimenu> and click <guimenu>Choose</guimenu>. In
     the next dialog, select the users to import and finish with
     <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Manually enter local users by clicking <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. The New
     Local User dialog opens. After entering the first name and last name,
     either accept the proposal or specify a new <guimenu>Username</guimenu>
     that will be used to log in. Finally, enter a password for the user.
     Reenter it for confirmation (to ensure that you did not type something
     else by mistake). To provide effective security, a password should be
     between five and eight characters long. The maximum length for a
     password is 72 characters. However, if no special security modules are
     loaded, only the first eight characters are used to discern the
     password. Passwords are case-sensitive. Special characters (7-bit
     ASCII) and the digits 0 to 9 are allowed. Other special characters like
     umlauts or accented characters are not allowed.
    </para>
    <para>
     Passwords you enter are checked for weakness. When entering a password
     that is easy to guess, such as a dictionary word or a name, you will
     see a warning. It is a good security practice to use strong passwords.
    </para>
    <para>
     Two additional options are available:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Receive System Mail</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Checking this box sends messages created by the system services to
        the user. These are usually only sent to &rootuser;, the system
        administrator. This option is useful for the most frequently used
        account, because it is highly recommended to log in as &rootuser;
        only in special cases.
       </para>
       <para>
        The mails sent by system services are stored in the local mailbox
        <filename>/var/spool/mail/</filename><replaceable>username</replaceable>,
        where <replaceable>username</replaceable> is the login name of the
        selected user. To read e-mails after installation, you can use any
        e-mail client, for example KMail or Evolution.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Automatic Login</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        This option automatically logs the current user in to the system on
        startup. This is mainly useful if the computer is operated by only
        one user. <phrase os="sles">For automatic login to work, the option
        must be explicitly enabled.</phrase>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <warning>
     <title>Automatic Login</title>
     <para>
      With automatic login enabled, the system boots straight to your
      desktop with no authentication at all. If you store sensitive data on
      your system, you should not enable this option if the computer can
      also be accessed by others.
     </para>
    </warning>
    <para>
     Enter more users by calling the <guimenu>User Management</guimenu>
     module described in <xref linkend="cha.y2.userman"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     When using a network server for user authentication, access to the
     following services can be configured:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>LDAP</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Users are administered centrally on an LDAP server for all systems
        in the network. More information is available in
        <xref linkend="sec.security.ldap.yast.client"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>NIS</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Users are administered centrally on a NIS server for all systems in
        the network. See <xref linkend="sec.nis.client"/> for more
        information.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Windows Domain</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        SMB authentication is often used in mixed Linux and Windows
        networks. Detailed information is available in
        <xref linkend="sec.samba.adnet"/> and
        <xref
         linkend="sec.security.ad.config"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
     Along with user administration via <guimenu>LDAP</guimenu> and
     <guimenu>NIS</guimenu>, you can use Kerberos authentication. To use it,
     select <guimenu>Set Up Kerberos Authentication</guimenu>. For more
     information on Kerberos, refer to
     <xref
      linkend="cha.security.kerberos"/>.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.relnotes"
     >
    <title>Release Notes</title>
    <para>
     After completing the user authentication setup, &yast; displays the
     release notes. Reading them is recommended, because they contain
     important up-to-date information which was not available when the
     manuals were printed. If you successfully tested the Internet
     connection, read the most recent version of the release notes, as
     fetched from &productname;'s servers. Use <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Miscellaneous</guimenu> <guimenu>Release Notes</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> in &yast; or start the &suse; Help Center to view the
     release notes after installation.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.hardware">
    <title>Hardware Configuration</title>
    <para>
     At the end of the installation, &yast; opens a dialog for the
     configuration of <guimenu>Graphics Cards</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Printer</guimenu> <phrase os="sles">and
     <guimenu>Sound</guimenu></phrase><phrase
      os="sled"><guimenu>Sound</guimenu>
     and TV Card</phrase>. Click the individual components to start the
     hardware configuration. For the most part, &yast; detects and
     configures the devices automatically.
    </para>
    <tip arch="zseries" os="sles">
     <title>IBM &zseries;: Hardware Configuration</title>
     <para>
      On the IBM &zseries;, there is no display that would be supported by
      XFree. Accordingly, you do not find a <guimenu>Graphics
      Cards</guimenu> entry on these systems.
     </para>
    </tip>
    <para>
     You can skip any peripheral devices and configure them later, as
     described in <xref
      linkend="cha.y2.hw"/>. To skip the
     configuration, select <guimenu>Skip Configuration</guimenu> and click
     <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <tip>
     <title>Resetting Hardware Configuration to the Default Values</title>
     <para>
      You can cancel any changes to the hardware configuration by clicking
      <menuchoice> <guimenu>Change</guimenu> <guimenu>Reset to
      Defaults</guimenu> </menuchoice>. &yast; then shows the original
      proposal again.
     </para>
    </tip>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.complete">
    <title>Installation Completed</title>
    <para>
     After a successful installation, &yast; shows the Installation
     Completed dialog. In this dialog, select whether to clone your newly
     installed system for &ay;. To clone your system, select <guimenu>Clone
     This System for &ay;</guimenu>. The profile of the current system is
     stored in <filename>/root/autoyast.xml</filename>.
     <phrase os="sles">Cloning is selected by default.</phrase>
    </para>
    <para>
     &ay; is a system for installing one or more &productname; systems
     automatically without user intervention. &ay; installations are
     performed using a control file with installation and configuration
     data.<phrase os="sles">For detailed information, refer to
     <xref
       linkend="cha.deployment.autoinst"/>.</phrase> Finish the
     installation of &productname; with <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> in the
     final dialog.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.dm">
  <title>Graphical Login</title>

  <tip arch="zseries" os="sles">
   <title>IBM &zseries;: No Graphical Login</title>
   <para>
    The graphical login is not available on IBM &zseries; platforms.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
   &productname; is now fully installed and configured. Unless you enabled
   the automatic login function or customized the default target, you
   should see the graphical login on your screen in which to enter a
   username and password to log into the system. On single user systems with
   automatic login enabled, the desktop starts automatically.
  </para>

  <para os="sled;osuse">
   For a detailed information about the GNOME desktop environment, refer
   to the <xref linkend="book.gnomeuser"/>. This manual can be accessed via the
   <guimenu>Help</guimenu> in both GNOME.
  </para>
 </sect1>
-->
</chapter>
