<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.inst">
 <title>Installation with &yast;</title><indexterm id="idx.Installation_YaST2"
  class="startofrange">
 <primary>installing</primary>
 <secondary>&yast;, with</secondary></indexterm><indexterm id="idx.YaST2_Installation"
  class="startofrange">
 <primary>&yast;</primary>
 <secondary>installing with</secondary></indexterm><indexterm id="idx.Installation"
  class="startofrange">
 <primary>installation</primary></indexterm>
 <abstract>
  <para os="sles">
   After your hardware has been prepared for the installation of
   &productnamereg; as described in <xref linkend="part.archspec"/> and
   after the connection with the installation system has been established,
   you are presented with the interface of &productname;'s system assistant
   &yast;. &yast; guides you through the entire installation and
   configuration procedure.
  </para>

  <para os="osuse;sled">
   Install your &productnamereg; system with &yast;, the central tool for
   installation and configuration of your system. &yast; guides you through
   the installation process and the basic configuration of your system.
   During the installation and configuration process, &yast; analyzes both
   your current system settings and your hardware components and proposes
   installation settings based on this analysis. By default, &yast; displays
   an overview of all installation steps on the left hand side of the window
   and provides online help texts for each step. Click
   <guimenu>Help</guimenu> to view the help text.
  </para>

  <para os="osuse;sled">
   If you are a first-time user of &productname;, you might want to follow
   the default &yast; proposals in most parts, but you can also adjust the
   settings as described here to fine-tune your system according to your
   preferences. Many parts of the basic system configuration, such as user
   accounts or system language, can also be modified after the installation
   process.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.media" os="osuse">
  <title>Choosing the Installation Media</title><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>media</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   When installing &productname;, choose from several media available either
   online or in the retail box:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>DVD-retail</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      One DVD containing the &opensuse; distribution for 32b-it and 64-bit
      systems. The second medium contains proprietary add-on software.
     </para>
     <para>
      This installation option does not require any network access for
      installation, nor do you need to set up external repositories to
      install the full &productname;. You can, however, make the contents of
      the DVD available on an installation server and make them available
      all across your network.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>DVD-download</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      One DVD5, available via download for 32-bit or 64-bit systems.
     </para>
     <para>
      Choose this installation option if you want a fully-fledged
      &productname; system. Beyond the downloading of the DVD ISO, there is
      no network connection required to make use of this installation
      option. Once the medium has been fully downloaded and the physical
      medium created, you can go ahead with the installation. You can also
      make the contents of the DVDs available on an installation server and
      make them available all across your network.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry os="osuse">
    <term>KDE4/GNOME LiveCD</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The LiveCD versions, available via download, include the KDE4 or GNOME
      desktops together with the most popular applications for 32-bit or
      64-bit systems.
     </para>
     <para>
      Choose this medium option for a first look at &productname;. The
      LiveCD version runs on your computer using RAM without touching your
      hard drive and no installation is needed. However, you can also
      install &productname; from the running live system. There is no
      network connection required beyond the mere downloading of the medium.
     </para>
     <tip>
      <title>Booting the LiveCD from an USB Stick</title>
      <para>
       Live CD iso images can also be used as boot images for USB sticks.
       Create a bootable USB stick by using the command-line program
       <command>dd</command> with the following syntax:
      </para>
<screen>dd if=<replaceable>ISO_IMAGE</replaceable> of=<replaceable>USB_STICK_DEVICE</replaceable> bs=4M</screen>
      <para>
       <command>dd</command> is available on Linux and MacOS by default. A
       Microsoft Windows* version can be downloaded from
       <ulink url="http://www.chrysocome.net/dd"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
       Warning: Using this <command>dd</command> command will erase all data
       on the USB device!
      </para>
     </tip>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Mini CD</term>
<!-- fs 2008-09-12: name? -->
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The Mini CD contains the minimal Linux system needed to run the
      installation. The installation system itself and the installation data
      are loaded from a network source. To install from a network providing
      SLP, please start the installation as described in
      <xref
       linkend="sec.i.yast2.source.slp"/>. To install from a
      HTTP, FTP, NFS, or SMB server, follow the instructions in
      <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.source.network"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <important>
   <title>Add-On CDs&mdash;Installing Additional Software</title>
   <para>
    Although add-on CDs (extensions or third-party products) cannot be used
    as stand-alone installation media, they can be embedded as additional
    software sources during the installation.<phrase os="osuse"> Currently
    CDs with additional languages and non open source software are available
    as add-on CDs for &productname;.</phrase> Refer to
    <xref
     linkend="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.addon"/> for more information.
   </para>
  </important>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.method">
  <title>Choosing the Installation Method</title><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>method</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   After having selected the installation medium, determine the suitable
   installation method and boot option that best matches your needs:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry id="sec.i.yast2.source.cd">
    <term>Installing from the &productname; Media (DVD, CD, USB)</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Choose this option if you want to perform a stand-alone installation
      and do not want to rely on a network to provide the installation data
      or the boot infrastructure. The installation proceeds exactly as
      outlined in <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.steps"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry os="osuse">
    <term>Installing from the LiveCD</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      In order to install from a LiveCD, boot the live system from CD. In
      the running system, launch the installation routine by clicking on the
      <guimenu>Install</guimenu> icon on the desktop. Phase one of the
      installation will be carried out in a window on the desktop. It is not
      possible to update an existing system with a LiveCD, you can only
      perform a new installation (with automatic configuration).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Installing from a Network Server</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Choose this option if you have an installation server available in your
      network or want to use an external server as the source of your
      installation data. This setup can be configured to boot from physical
      media (USB storage, CD/DVD, or hard disk) or configured to boot via
      network using PXE/BOOTP. Refer to <xref
      linkend="sec.i.yast2.source.slp"/>, <xref
      linkend="sec.i.yast2.source.network"/>, or <xref
      linkend="cha.deployment.remoteinst"/> for details.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry os="osuse">
    <term>Installing with &productname; &productnumber; Installer from
     Windows</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Choose this installation option if you prefer a smooth transition from
      using Windows to using Linux. &productname; &productnumber; Installer
      allows you to boot into the &productname; installation right from a
      running Windows by modifying the Windows boot loader. This
      installation option is only available from the DVD media. Refer to
      <xref
       linkend="sec.i.yast2.source.instlux"/> for details.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   &productname; supports several different boot options from which you can
   choose, depending on the hardware available and on the installation
   scenario you prefer. <phrase os="osuse">Booting from the &productname;
   media or using &productname; &productnumber; Installer are the most
   straightforward options, but special requirements might call for special
   setups</phrase><phrase os="sles;sled">Booting from the &productname;
   media is the most straightforward option, but special requirements might
   call for special setups</phrase>:
  </para>

  <table id="tab.boot.opt">
   <title>Boot Options</title>
   <tgroup cols="2">
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Boot Option
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Description
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        DVD
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        This is the easiest boot option. This option can be used if the
        system has a local DVD-ROM drive that is supported by Linux.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        USB Mass Storage Device
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        In case your machine is not equipped with an optical drive, you can
        boot the installation image from a USB mass storage device such as a
        USB stick. To create a bootable USB storage device, you need to copy
        either the DVD or the Mini CD iso image to the device using the
        <command>dd</command> command (the USB device must not be mounted,
        all data on the device will be erased):
       </para>
<screen>dd if=<replaceable>PATH_TO_ISO_IMAGE</replaceable> of=<replaceable>USB_STORAGE_DEVICE</replaceable> bs=4M</screen>
       <para>
        <command>dd</command> is available on Linux and MacOS by default. A
        Microsoft Windows* version can be downloaded from
        <ulink url="http://www.chrysocome.net/dd"/>.
       </para>
       <important>
        <title>Compatibility</title>
        <para>
         Please note that booting from a USB Mass Storage Device is
         <emphasis>not</emphasis> supported on UEFI machines (this includes
         the complete ia64 architecture) and on the ppc64 architecture.
        </para>
       </important>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row os="osuse">
      <entry>
       <para>
        &productname; &productnumber; Installer
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        &productname; &productnumber; Installer is installed under Microsoft
        Windows and makes it possible to boot directly into the installation
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        PXE or BOOTP
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Booting over the network must be supported by the system's BIOS or
        firmware, and a boot server must be available in the network. This
        task can also be handled by another &productname; system.
        <phrase os="osuse">See
        <ulink
          url="http://en.opensuse.org/SDB:PXE_boot_installation"/>
        for more information.</phrase><phrase>Refer to
        <xref linkend="cha.deployment.remoteinst"/> for more
        information.</phrase>
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Hard Disk
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        &productname; installation can also be booted from the hard disk. To
        do this, copy the kernel (<systemitem>linux</systemitem>) and the
        installation system (<systemitem>initrd</systemitem>) from the
        directory
        <filename>/boot/<replaceable>architecture</replaceable>/</filename>
        on the installation media to the hard disk and add an appropriate
        entry to the existing boot loader of a previous &productname;
        installation.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>

  <tip arch="amd64;em64t">
   <title>Booting from DVD on UEFI machines</title>
   <para arch="amd64;em64t">
    DVD1 can be used as a boot medium for machines equipped with UEFI
    (Unified Extensible Firmware Interface). Refer to your vendor's
    documentation for specific information. If booting fails, try to enable
    CSM (Compatibility Support Module) in your firmware.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.source.slp">
   <title>Installing from a Network Server Using SLP</title><indexterm>
   <primary>installation</primary>
   <secondary>network</secondary>
   <tertiary>SLP</tertiary></indexterm>
   <para>
    If your network setup supports OpenSLP and your network installation
    source has been configured to announce itself via SLP (described in
    <xref
     linkend="sec.deployment.remoteinst.instserver"/>), boot the
    system, press <keycap>F4</keycap> in the boot screen and select
    <guimenu>SLP</guimenu> from the menu.
   </para>
   <para>
    The installation program configures the network connection with DHCP and
    retrieves the location of the network installation source from the
    OpenSLP server. If the automatic DHCP network configuration fails, you
    are prompted to enter the appropriate parameters manually. The
    installation then proceeds as described below with the exception of the
    network configuration step that is needed prior to adding additional
    repositories. This step is not needed as the network is already
    configured and active at this point.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2
   id="sec.i.yast2.source.network">
   <title>Installing from a Network Source without SLP</title><indexterm>
   <primary>installation</primary>
   <secondary>network</secondary>
   <tertiary>other</tertiary></indexterm>
   <para>
    If your network setup does not support OpenSLP for the retrieval of
    network installation sources, boot the system and press
    <keycap>F4</keycap> in the boot screen to select the desired network
    protocol (NFS, HTTP, FTP, or SMB/CIFS). Provide the server's address and
    the path to the installation media.
   </para>
   <para>
    The installation program automatically configures the network connection
    with DHCP. If this configuration fails, you are prompted to enter the
    appropriate parameters manually. The installation retrieves the
    installation data from the source specified. The installation then
    proceeds as described below with the exception of the network
    configuration step needed prior to adding additional repositories. This
    step is not needed as the network is already configured and active at
    this point.
   </para>
  </sect2>

<!-- fs 2009-08-13:
 what about openSUSE11_2_NET.exe ?
-->

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.source.instlux" os="osuse">
   <title>Installing with the &productname; &productnumber; Installer from Windows</title><indexterm>
   <primary>installation</primary>
   <secondary>windows</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    &productname; &productnumber; Installer is a Microsoft Windows
    application that prepares your computer to directly boot into the
    &productname; installation without having to adjust BIOS settings. It is
    only available on DVD media. To use the installer, insert the
    &productname; media under Windows. The &productname; &productnumber;
    <literal>Installer</literal> setup automatically starts (if not, run
    <filename>openSUSE11_2_LOCAL.exe</filename> from the DVD). Choose a
    language for the installation and follow the instructions on the screen.
    The language you choose here is also pre-configured to be used for the
    &productname; installation.
   </para>
   <para>
    On the next reboot, the Microsoft Windows boot loader launches. Choose
<!-- <guimenu>&productname; &productnumber; Installer</guimenu>-->
    <emphasis>&productname; &productnumber; Installer</emphasis> to start
    the &productname; installation. In order to proceed with the
    installation, you will be prompted to insert the installation media. The
    installation proceeds as described below. When Microsoft Windows is
    booted again, &productname; &productnumber; Installer is automatically
    uninstalled.
   </para>
   <tip>
    <title>Installing &productname; alongside Microsoft Windows</title>
    <para>
     &productname; can easily be installed alongside Microsoft Windows.
     Carry out the installation as described below&mdash;an existing Windows
     installation will automatically be detected and a dual boot option will
     be installed. If Windows covers the whole installation disk, the
     installation routine will make a proposal to shrink an existing Windows
     partition in order to make room for the &productname;. Please read
     <xref
      linkend="sec.i.yast2.proposal.partitioning.windows"/> prior
     to the installation for detailed information.
    </para>
   </tip>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.steps">
  <title>The Installation Workflow</title><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>workflow</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   The &productname; installation is split into three main parts:
   preparation, installation, and configuration. During the preparation
   phase you configure some basic parameters such as language, time,
   <phrase
    os="sled;osuse">desktop type, users, passwords, </phrase>hard
   disk setup and installation scope. In the non-interactive installation
   phase the software is installed and the system is prepared for the first
   boot. Upon finishing the installation the machine reboots into the newly
   installed system and starts the final system configuration.
   <phrase
    os="osuse;sled">You can choose whether to do a fully
   automatic or a manual configuration. </phrase>In this stage, network and
   Internet access, as well as hardware components such as printers, are set
   up.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1
  id="sec.i.yast2.start.ppc" arch="ipseries" os="sles">
  <title>IBM &ppc;: System Start-Up for Network Installation</title>

  <para>
   For IBM &ppc; platforms, the system is booted (IPL, Initial Program Load)
   as described in <xref linkend="cha.ppc.prep"/>. For a network
   installation, &sls; does not show a splash screen or a boot loader
   command line on these systems. During the installation load the kernel
   manually. &yast; starts with its installation screen as soon as a
   connection has been established to the installation system via VNC, X, or
   SSH. Because there is no splash screen or boot loader command line,
   kernel or boot parameters cannot be entered on the screen, but must be
   included in the kernel image using the
   <command>mkzimage_cmdline</command> utility.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>IBM &ppc;: The Next Steps</title>
   <para>
    To install, follow the description of the installation procedure with
    &yast; starting from <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.welcome"/>.
   </para>
  </tip>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.start.390" arch="zseries" os="sles">
  <title>IBM &zseries;: System Start-Up for Installation</title>

  <para>
   For IBM &zseries; platforms, the system is booted (IPL, Initial Program
   Load) as described in <xref linkend="sec.prep.ipling"/>. &productname;
   does not show a splash screen on these systems. During the installation,
   load the kernel, initrd, and parmfile manually. &yast; starts with its
   installation screen as soon as a connection has been established to the
   installation system via VNC, X, or SSH. Because there is no splash
   screen, kernel or boot parameters cannot be entered on screen, but must
   be specified in a parmfile (see
   <xref linkend="sec.appdendix.parm"
   />).
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>IBM &zseries;: The Next Steps</title>
   <para>
    To install, follow the description of the installation procedure with
    &yast; starting from <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.welcome"/>.
   </para>
  </tip>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.start">
  <title>System Start-Up for Installation</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&yast;</primary>

  <secondary>system start-up</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>&yast;</primary>

  <secondary>starting</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>system start-up</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   You can install &productname; from local installation sources, such as
   the &productname; CDs or DVD, or from network source of an FTP, HTTP,
   NFS, or SMB server. Any of these approaches requires physical access to
   the system to install as well as user interaction during the
   installation. The installation procedure is basically the same regardless
   of the installation source. Any exceptions are sufficiently highlighted
   in the following workflow description.<phrase
    os="sles;sled"> For a
   description on how to perform non-interactive, automated installations,
   refer to <xref linkend="part.autoinstall"/>.</phrase>
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.bootscreen">
  <title>The Boot Screen on Machines Equipped with Traditional BIOS</title><indexterm>

  <primary>boot screen</primary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>boot screen</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   The boot screen displays a number of options for the installation
   procedure. <guimenu>Boot from Hard Disk</guimenu> boots the installed
   system and is selected by default, because the CD is often left in the
   drive. Select one of the other options with the arrow keys and press
   <keycap
    function="enter"/> to boot it. The relevant options are:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Installation</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The normal installation mode. All modern hardware functions are
      enabled. In case the installation fails, see
      <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.bootscreen.kernel"/> for boot options that
      disable potentially problematic functions.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Repair Installed System</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Boots into the graphical repair system. More information on repairing
      an installed system is available in
      <xref linkend="sec.trouble.data.recover"/>. <phrase os="osuse"> This
      option is not available on LiveCDs.</phrase>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Rescue System</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem><indexterm>
     <primary>&yast;</primary>
     <secondary>rescue system</secondary></indexterm>
     <para>
      Starts a minimal Linux system without a graphical user interface. For
      more information, see
      <xref linkend="sec.trouble.data.recover.rescue"/>. <phrase os="osuse">
      This option is not available on LiveCDs.</phrase>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
<!-- fs 2010-01-20: May change again, see bnc #572218 -->
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Check Installation Media</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem><indexterm>
     <primary>&yast;</primary>
     <secondary>media check</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
     <primary>installation</primary>
     <secondary>media check</secondary></indexterm>
     <para>
      This option is only available when you install from media created from
      downloaded ISOs. In this case it is recommended to check the integrity
      of the installation medium. This option starts the installation system
      before automatically checking the media. In case the check was
      successful, the normal installation routine starts. If a corrupt media
      is detected, the installation routine aborts.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
<!-- fs 20011-02-23: 
	   This entry will be removed in 11.4+, see bnc #619520 
-->
    <term><guimenu>Firmware Test</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem><indexterm>
     <primary>firmware test</primary></indexterm>
     <para>
      Starts a BIOS checker that validates ACPI and other parts of your
      BIOS.<phrase os="osuse"> This option is not available on the
      LiveCDs.</phrase>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Memory Test</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem><indexterm>
     <primary>memory test</primary></indexterm>
     <para>
      Tests your system RAM using repeated read and write cycles. Terminate
      the test by rebooting. For more information, see
      <xref linkend="sec.trouble.install.noboot"/>.<phrase os="osuse"> This
      option is not available on the LiveCDs.</phrase>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <figure os="osuse">
   <title>The Boot Screen on Machines with a Traditional BIOS</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_boot.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_boot.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <figure>
   <title>The Boot Screen on Machines with a Traditional BIOS</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_boot.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_boot.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   Use the function keys indicated in the bar at the bottom of the screen to
   change the language, screen resolution, installation source or to add an
   additional driver from your hardware vendor:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><keycap>F1</keycap><guimenu>Help</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Get context-sensitive help for the active element of the boot screen.
      Use the arrow keys to navigate, <keycap function="enter"/> to follow a
      link, and <keycap function="escape"/> to leave the help screen.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><keycap>F2</keycap><guimenu>Language</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Select the display language and a corresponding keyboard layout for
      the installation. The default language is English (US).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><keycap>F3</keycap><guimenu>Video Mode</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Select various graphical display modes for the installation. Select
      <guimenu>Text Mode</guimenu> if the graphical installation causes
      problems.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><keycap>F4</keycap><guimenu>Source</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Normally, the installation is performed from the inserted installation
      medium. Here, select other sources, like FTP or NFS servers. If the
      installation is deployed on a network with an SLP server, select an
      installation source available on the server with this option. Find
      information about SLP in <xref linkend="cha.slp"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry id="sec.i.yast2.bootscreen.kernel">
    <term><keycap>F5</keycap><guimenu>Kernel</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you encounter problems with the regular installation, this menu
      offers to disable a few potentially problematic functions. If your
      hardware does not support ACPI (advanced configuration and power
      interface) select <guimenu>No ACPI</guimenu> to install without ACPI
      support. <guimenu>No local APIC</guimenu> disables support for APIC
      (Advanced Programmable Interrupt Controllers) which may cause problems
      with some hardware. <guimenu>Safe Settings</guimenu> boots the system
      with the DMA mode (for CD/DVD-ROM drives) and power management
      functions disabled.
     </para>
     <para>
      If you are not sure, try the following options first:
      <guimenu>Installation&mdash;ACPI Disabled</guimenu> or
      <guimenu>Installation&mdash;Safe Settings</guimenu>. Experts can also
      use the command line (<guimenu>Boot Options</guimenu>) to enter or
      change kernel parameters.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><keycap>F6</keycap><guimenu>Driver</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Press this key to notify the system that you have an optional driver
      update for &productname;. With <guimenu>File</guimenu> or
      <guimenu>URL</guimenu>, load drivers directly before the installation
      starts. If you select <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>, you are prompted to
      insert the update disk at the appropriate point in the installation
      process.
     </para>
     <tip os="sles;sled">
      <title>Getting Driver Update Disks</title>
      <para>
       Driver updates for &sle; are provided at
       <ulink
       url="http://drivers.suse.com/"/>. These drivers have
       been created via the Partner Linux Driver Program.
      </para>
     </tip>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry os="osuse">
    <term><keycap>F7</keycap><guimenu>Arch</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you install from an installation medium supporting 32-bit and
      64-bit architectures and have a processor with 64-bit support, select
      whether to install a 64-bit or 32-bit system. By default, a 64-bit
      system is installed on a computer with 64-bit support. To install a
      32-bit system, press <keycap>F7</keycap> then select
      <guimenu>32bit</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <tip>
   <title>Using IPv6 during the Installation</title>
   <para>
    By default you can only assign IPv4 network addresses to your machine.
    To enable IPv6 during installation, enter one of the following
    parameters at the bootprompt: <literal>ipv6=1</literal> (accept IPv4 and
    IPv6) or <literal>ipv6only=1</literal> (accept IPv6 only).
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
   After starting the installation, &productname; loads and configures a
   minimal Linux system to run the installation procedure. To view the boot
   messages and copyright notices during this process, press
   <keycap>Esc</keycap>. On completion of this process, the &yast;
   installation program starts and displays the graphical installer.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>Installation without a Mouse</title>
   <para>
    If the installer does not detect your mouse correctly, use
    <keycap>Tab</keycap> for navigation, arrow keys to scroll, and
    <keycap>Enter</keycap> to confirm a selection. Various buttons or
    selection fields contain a letter with an underscore. Use
    <keycombo action="press"
      ><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Letter</keycap></keycombo>
    to select a button or a selection directly instead of navigating there
    with the <keycap>Tab</keycap> button.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.fun.yep" os="sles;sled">
   <title>Providing Data to Access an &smt; Server</title>
   <para>
    By default, updates for &productname; are delivered by the &ncc;. If
    your network provides a so called &smt; server to provide a local update
    source, you need to equip the client with the server's URL. Client and
    server communicate solely via HTTPS protocol, therefore you also need to
    enter a path to the server's certificate if the certificate was not
    issued by a certificate authority. This information can either be
    entered at the boot prompt (as described here) or during the
    registration process as described in
    <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.cc.local"
    />.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>regurl</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       URL of the &smt; server. This URL has a fixed format
       <literal>https://<replaceable>FQN</replaceable>/center/regsvc/</literal>
       <replaceable>FQN</replaceable> has to be a fully qualified hostname
       of the &smt; server. Example:
      </para>
<screen>regurl=https://smt.&exampledomain;/center/regsvc/</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>regcert</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Location of the &smt; server's certificate. Specify one of the
       following locations:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>URL</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Remote location (http, https or ftp) from which the certificate
          can be downloaded. Example:
         </para>
<screen>regcert=http://smt.&exampledomain;/smt-ca.crt</screen>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>local path</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Absolute path to the certificate on the local machine. Example:
         </para>
<screen>regcert=/data/inst/smt/smt-ca.cert</screen>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>Interactive</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Use <literal>ask</literal> to open a pop-up menu during the
          installation where you can specify the path to the certificate. Do
          not use this option with &ay;. Example
         </para>
<screen>regcert=ask</screen>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>Deactivate certificate installation</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Use <literal>done</literal> if either the certificate will be
          installed by an add-on product, or if you are using a certificate
          issued by an official certificate authority. Example:
         </para>
<screen>regcert=done</screen>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <warning>
    <title>Beware of typing errors</title>
    <para>
     Make sure the values you enter are correct. If
     <literal>regurl</literal> has not been specified correctly, the
     registration of the update source will fail. If a wrong value for
     regcert has been entered, you will be prompted for a local path to the
     certificate.
    </para>
    <para>
     In case regcert is not specified, it will default to
     <literal>http://<replaceable>FQN</replaceable>/smt.crt</literal> with
     <literal>FQN</literal> being the name of the SMT server.
    </para>
   </warning>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.fun.supportconfigurl" os="sles;sled">
   <title>Configuring an Alternative Data Server for <systemitem>supportconfig</systemitem></title>
   <para>
    The data that supportconfig (see <xref linkend="cha.adm.support"/> for
    more information) gathers is sent to the &ncc; by default. It is also
    possible to set up a local server to collect this data. If such a server
    is available on your network, you need to set the server's URL on the
    client. This information has to be entered at the boot prompt.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>supporturl</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       URL of the server. The URL has the format
       <literal>http://<replaceable>FQN</replaceable>/<replaceable>Path</replaceable>/</literal>
       <replaceable>FQN</replaceable> has to be full qualified hostname of
       the server, <replaceable>Path</replaceable> has to be replaced with
       the location on the server. Example:
      </para>
<screen>supporturl=http://support.&exampledomain;/supportconfig/data/</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.bootscreen_uefi">
  <title>The Boot Screen on Machines Equipped with UEFI</title>

  <para>
   UEFI (Unified Extensible Firmware Interface) is a new industry standard
   which replaces and extends the traditional BIOS. The latest UEFI
   implementations contain the <quote>Secure Boot</quote> extension, that
   prevents booting malicious code by only allowing signed boot loaders to
   be executed. See <xref linkend="cha.uefi"/> for more information.
  </para>

<!--
UEFI also replaces the MBR (Master Boot record) based partition tables with
GPT (GUID Partitioning Table). GPT supports booting from hard disks larger
than 2 TB and partitions larger than 2 TB.
-->

  <para>
   The boot manager &grub;, used to boot machines with a traditional BIOS,
   does not support UEFI, therefore &grub; is replaced with &elilo;. If Secure
   Boot is enabled, a &grub; UEFI module is used via an &elilo; compatibility
   layer. From an administrative and user perspective, both boot manager
   implementations behave the same and are referred to as
   <literal>&elilo;</literal> in the following.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>UEFI and Secure Boot are Supported by Default</title>
   <para>
    The installation routine of &sle; automatically detects if the machine
    is equipped with UEFI. All installation sources also support Secure
    Boot. If an EFI system partition already exists on dual boot machines
    (from a Microsoft Windows 8 installation, for example), it will
    automatically be detected and used. Partition tables will be written as
    GPT on UEFI systems.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
   The boot screen displays a number of options for the installation
   procedure. Change the selected option with the arrow keys and press
   <keycap function="enter"/> to boot it. The relevant options are:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Installation</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The normal installation mode.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Rescue System</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem><indexterm>
     <primary>&yast;</primary>
     <secondary>rescue system</secondary></indexterm>
     <para>
      Starts a minimal Linux system without a graphical user interface. For
      more information, see
      <xref linkend="sec.trouble.data.recover.rescue"/>. <phrase os="osuse">
      This option is not available on LiveCDs.</phrase>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
<!-- fs 2010-01-20: May change again, see bnc #572218 -->
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Check Installation Media</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem><indexterm>
     <primary>&yast;</primary>
     <secondary>media check</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
     <primary>installation</primary>
     <secondary>media check</secondary></indexterm>
     <para>
      This option is only available when you install from media created from
      downloaded ISOs. In this case it is recommended to check the integrity
      of the installation medium. This option starts the installation system
      before automatically checking the media. In case the check was
      successful, the normal installation routine starts. If a corrupt media
      is detected, the installation routine aborts.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <figure>
   <title>The Boot Screen on Machines with UEFI</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_boot_uefi.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_boot_uefi.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   &elilo; on &productname; does not support a graphical boot screen or a boot
   prompt. In order to add additional boot parameters you need to edit the
   respective boot entry. Highlight it using the arrow keys and press
   <keycap>E</keycap>. See the on-screen help for editing hints (note that
   only an English keyboard is available at this time). The
   <guimenu>Installation</guimenu> entry will look similar to the following:
  </para>

<screen>setparams 'Installation'

  set gfxpayload=keep
  echo 'Loading kernel ...'
  linuxefi /boot/x86_64/loader/linux
  echo 'Loading initial ramdisk ...'
  initrdefi /boot/x86_64/loader/initrd</screen>

  <para>
   Add space separated parameters to the end of the line starting with
   <literal>linuxefi</literal>. A list of parameters is available at
   <ulink
   url="https://en.opensuse.org/Linuxrc"/>. In the following
   example the installation language is set to German:
  </para>

<screen>linuxefi /boot/x86_64/loader/linux Language=de_DE</screen>

  <para>
   To boot the edited entry, press <keycap>F10</keycap>. If you access the
   machine via serial console, press <keycombo><keycap function="escape"/>
   <keycap>0</keycap></keycombo>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.welcome">
  <title>Welcome</title><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>language</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>keyboard</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>&yast;</primary>

  <secondary>language</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>&yast;</primary>

  <secondary>keyboard</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>license agreement</primary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Start the installation of &productname; by choosing your language.
   Changing the language will automatically preselect a corresponding
   keyboard layout. Override this proposal by selecting a different keyboard
   layout from the drop-down menu. The language selected here is also used
   to assume a time zone for the system clock. This setting&mdash;along with
   the selection of secondary languages to install on your system&mdash;can
   be modified later in the <guimenu>Installation Summary</guimenu>,
   described in <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.proposal"/>. For information
   about language settings in the installed system, see
   <xref linkend="cha.y2.lang"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Read the license agreement that is displayed beneath the language and
   keyboard selection thoroughly. Use <guimenu>License
   Translations...</guimenu> to access translations. If you agree to the
   terms, <phrase os="sles;sled">check <guimenu>I Agree to the License
   Terms</guimenu> and</phrase> click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed
   with the installation. If you do not agree to the license
   agreement<phrase os="sles;sled">, you cannot install
   &productname;;</phrase> click <guimenu>Abort</guimenu> to terminate the
   installation.
  </para>

  <figure os="osuse">
   <title>Welcome</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_welcome.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_welcome.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <figure>
   <title>Welcome</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_welcome.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_welcome.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.s390.part" arch="zseries" os="sles">
  <title>IBM &zseries;: Hard Disk Configuration</title>

  <para>
   When installing on IBM &zseries; platforms, the language selection dialog
   is followed by a dialog to configure the attached hard disks. Select
   DASD, Fibre Channel Attached SCSI Disks (zFCP), or iSCSI for installation
   of &productname;. The DASD and zFCP configuration buttons are only
   available if the corresponding devices are attached. For instructions on
   how to configure iSCSI disks, refer to <xref linkend="bj4rqa5"/>.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>Adding DASD or zFCP Disks at a Later Stage</title>
   <para>
    Adding DASD or zFCP disks is not only possible during the installation
    workflow, but also when the installation proposal is shown. To add disks
    at that stage, click <guimenu>Expert</guimenu> and scroll down. The DASD
    and zFCP entries are shown at the very bottom.
   </para>
   <para>
    After adding the disks, reread the partition table. Return to the
    installation proposal screen and choose <guimenu>Partitioning</guimenu>
    then select <guimenu>Reread Partition Table</guimenu>. This updates the
    new partition table.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.s390.part.dasd">
   <title>Configuring DASD Disks</title>
   <para>
    After selecting <guimenu>Configure DASD Disks</guimenu>, an overview
    lists all available DASDs. To get a clearer picture of the available
    devices, use the entry field located above the list to specify a range
    of channels to display. To filter the list according to such a range,
    select <guimenu>Filter</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <figure id="fig.s390_yast2.i_y2_sel_dasd">
    <title>IBM &zseries;: Selecting a DASD</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata width="70%" fileref="s390_i_y2_sel_dasd.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata width="70%" fileref="s390_i_y2_sel_dasd.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    Specify the DASDs to use for the installation by selecting the
    corresponding entries in the list. Click <guimenu>Select or
    Deselect</guimenu>. Activate and make the DASDs available for the
    installation by selecting <menuchoice> <guimenu>Perform Action</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Activate</guimenu> </menuchoice>. To format the DASDs, select
    <menuchoice> <guimenu>Perform Action</guimenu> <guimenu>Format</guimenu>
    </menuchoice> right away or use the &yast; partitioner later as
    described in <xref linkend="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.s390.part.zfcp">
   <title>Configuring zFCP Disks</title>
   <para>
    To use zFCP disks for the &productname; installation, select
    <guimenu>Configure zFCP Disks</guimenu> in the selection dialog. This
    opens a dialog with a list of the zFCP disks available on the system. In
    this dialog, select <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to open another dialog in
    which to enter zFCP parameters.
   </para>
   <para>
    To make a zFCP disk available for the &productname; installation, choose
    an available <guimenu>Channel Number</guimenu> from the drop-down list.
    <guimenu>Get WWPNs</guimenu> (World Wide Port Number) and <guimenu>Get
    LUNs</guimenu> (Logical Unit Number) return lists with available WWPNs
    and FCP-LUNs, respectively, to choose from. When completed, exit the
    zFCP dialog with <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and the general hard disk
    configuration dialog with <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> to continue with the
    rest of the configuration.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
<!-- fs 2010-01-20: May disappear again, see bnc #572218 -->
 <sect1  id="sec.i.yast2.mediacheck" os="sles;sled">
  <title>Media Check</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&yast;</primary>

  <secondary>media check</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   The media check dialog only appears if you install from media created
   from downloaded ISOs. If you install from the original media kit, the
   dialog is skipped.
  </para>

  <para>
   The media check examines the integrity of a medium. To start it, select
   the drive that contains the installation medium and click <guimenu>Start
   Check</guimenu>. The check can take some time.
  </para>

  <para>
   To test multiple media, wait until a result message appears in the dialog
   before changing the medium. If the last medium checked is not the one you
   started the installation with, &yast; prompts for the appropriate medium
   before continuing with the installation.
  </para>

  <para>
   If using ISO images (for example, for installing add-on products), click
   <guimenu>Check ISO File</guimenu> and choose the image via the file
   dialog.
  </para>

  <warning>
   <title>Failure of Media Check</title>
   <para>
    If the media check fails, your medium is damaged. Do not continue the
    installation because installation may fail or you may loose your data.
    Replace the broken medium and restart the installation process.
   </para>
  </warning>

  <para>
   If the media check turns out positive, click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to
   continue the installation.
  </para>

<!--
  <figure id="fig.yast2.inst_checkmedia" os="osuse">
   <title>Media Check</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_checkmedia.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_checkmedia.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
-->
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode">
  <title>Installation Mode</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&yast;</primary>

  <secondary>installation mode</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>mode</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   After a system analysis (where &yast; probes for storage devices and
   tries to find other installed systems on your machine) the available
   installation modes are displayed.<phrase os="osuse"> This step is skipped
   when installing from a LiveCD, since this medium only supports a new
   installation with automatic configuration.</phrase>
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>New installation</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Select this option to start a new installation from scratch.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Update</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Select this option to update an existing installation to a newer
      version. For more information about system update, see
      <xref
      linkend="cha.update.sle"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Repair Installed System</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Choose this option to repair a damaged system that is already
      installed. More information is available in
      <xref linkend="sec.trouble.data.recover"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <figure os="osuse">
   <title>Installation Mode</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_mode.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_mode.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <figure os="sled">
   <title>Installation Mode</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_mode_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_mode_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <figure os="sles">
   <title>Installation Mode</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_mode_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_mode_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para os="osuse;sled">
   By default, the automatic configuration is used when performing a new
   installation. In this mode the system automatically configures your
   hardware and the network, so the installation is performed with minimal
   user interaction. If necessary, you can change every configuration that
   is set up later in the installed system using &yast;. In repair mode the
   automatic configuration attempts to fix errors automatically. Uncheck
   <guimenu>Use Automatic Configuration</guimenu> if you prefer a manual
   configuration during the installation or to start the system's
   repair-process in expert mode.
  </para>

  <para os="sled;sles;osuse">
   Check <guimenu>Include Add-On Products from Separate Media</guimenu> to
   include add-on products during the installation. An add-on product can
   include extensions, third-party products and drivers or additional
   software for your system<phrase os="osuse"> such as support for
   additional languages</phrase>.
  </para>

<!-- fs, 2011-08-10: Fate #312624 -->

  <tip os="sles;sled">
   <title>Installing Product Patches from an SMT Server on Installation</title>
   <para>
    In case your organization provides the update channel for &productname;
    via an SMT server, it is possible to specify this channel as an Add-On
    product by entering its HTTP address. As a consequence, the system will
    be installed with the most current packages without having to apply the
    updates at the end of the installation.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
   Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed. If you selected to include an
   add-on product, proceed with
   <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.addon"/>, otherwise skip the next
   section and advance to <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.timezone"/>.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.addon">
   <title>Add-On Products</title><indexterm>
   <primary>&yast;</primary>
   <secondary>add-on</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>installation</primary>
   <secondary>add-on</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Add-on products can be installed either from a local source (CD, DVD, or
    directory) or from a network source (HTTP, FTP, NFS, CIFS,...). When
    installing from a network source, you need to configure the network
    first (unless you are performing a network installation&mdash; in this
    case the existing network configuration is used). Choose <guimenu>Yes,
    Run the Network Setup</guimenu> and proceed as described in
    <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.network"/>. If the add-on product
    is available locally, select <guimenu>No, Skip the Network
    Setup</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and specify the product source. Source
    types available are <guimenu>CD</guimenu>, <guimenu>DVD</guimenu>,
    <guimenu>Hard Disk</guimenu>, <guimenu>USB Mass Storage</guimenu>, a
    <guimenu>Local Directory</guimenu> or a <guimenu>Local ISO
    Image</guimenu> (if no network was configured). If the add-on product is
    available on removable media, the system automatically mounts the media
    and reads its contents. If the add-on product is available on hard disk,
    choose <guimenu>Hard Disk</guimenu> to install from an unmounted hard
    drive, or <guimenu>Local Directory</guimenu>/<guimenu>Local ISO
    Image</guimenu> to install from the local file system. Add-on products
    may be delivered as a repository or as a set of RPM files. In the latter
    case, check <guimenu>Plain RPM Directory</guimenu>. Whenever a network
    is available, you can choose from additional remote sources such as
    HTTP, SLP, FTP, etc. It is also possible to specify a URL directly.
   </para>
   <para>
    Check <guimenu>Download Repository Description Files</guimenu> to
    download the files describing the repository now. If unchecked, they
    will be downloaded once the installation starts. Proceed with
    <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and insert a CD or DVD if required. Depending on
    the product's content it may be necessary to accept additional license
    agreements.
   </para>
   <para>
    It is also possible to configure add-on products later. Using add-on
    products on the installed system is described in
    <xref linkend="cha.add-ons"/>.
   </para>
   <tip os="sles;sled">
    <title>Driver Updates</title>
    <para>
     You can also add driver update repositories via the Add-On Products
     dialog. Driver updates for &sle; are provided at
     <ulink
     url="http://drivers.suse.com/"/>. These drivers have been
     created via the Partner Linux Driver Program.
    </para>
   </tip>
   <sect3
    id="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.network">
    <title>Network Setup</title><indexterm>
    <primary>installation</primary>
    <secondary>network</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     When invoking the network setup, &yast; scans for available network
     cards. If more than one network card is found, you must choose the card
     to configure from the list.
    </para>
    <para>
     If an ethernet network adapter is not already connected, a warning will
     open. Make sure the network cable is plugged in and choose
     <guimenu>Yes, Use It</guimenu>. If your network is equipped with a DHCP
     server, choose <guimenu>Automatic Address Setup (via DHCP)</guimenu>.
     To manually set up the network choose <guimenu>Static Address
     Setup</guimenu> and specify <guimenu>IP Address</guimenu>,
     <guimenu>Netmask</guimenu>, <guimenu>Default Gateway IP</guimenu>, and
     the <guimenu>DNS Server IP</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Some networks require the use of a proxy server to access the Internet.
     Tick the check box <guimenu>Use Proxy for Accessing the
     Internet</guimenu> and enter the appropriate specifications. Click
     <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to perform the network setup. The
     installation procedure will continue with the add-on products or
     repositories setup as described in
     <xref
      linkend="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.addon"/>.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1
  id="sec.i.yast2.timezone">
  <title>Clock and Time Zone</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&yast;</primary>

  <secondary>time zone</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>&yast;</primary>

  <secondary>clock</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>time zone</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>clock</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   In this dialog, select your region and time zone. Both are preselected
   according to the selected installation language. To change the
   preselected values, either use the map or the drop down lists for
   <guimenu>Region</guimenu> and <guimenu>Time Zone</guimenu>. When using
   the map, point the cursor at the rough direction of your region and
   left-click to zoom. Now choose your country or region by left-clicking.
   Right-click to return to the world map.
  </para>

  <figure
   os="osuse">
   <title>Clock and Time Zone</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_timezone.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_timezone.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <figure>
   <title>Clock and Time Zone</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_timezone.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_timezone.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   To set up the clock, choose whether the <guimenu>Hardware Clock is Set to
   UTC</guimenu>. If you run another operating system on your machine, such
   as Microsoft Windows, it is likely your system uses local time instead.
   If you only run Linux on your machine, set the hardware clock to UTC and
   have the switch from standard time to daylight saving time performed
   automatically.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Set the Hardware Clock to UTC</title>
   <para>
    The switch from standard time to daylight saving time (and vice versa)
    can only be performed automatically when the hardware clock (CMOS clock)
    is set to UTC. This also applies if you use automatic time
    synchronization with NTP, because automatic syncing will only be
    performed if the time difference between the hardware and system clock
    is less than 15 minutes.
   </para>
   <para>
    Since a wrong system time can cause severe problems (missed backups,
    dropped mail messages, mount failures on remote file systems, etc.) it
    is strongly recommended to <emphasis>always</emphasis> set the hardware
    clock to UTC.
   </para>
  </important>

  <para>
   If a network is already configured,<phrase os="osuse"> the time is
   automatically synced via Network Time Protocol (NTP) with a time
   server.</phrase><phrase os="sles;sled"> you can configure time
   synchronization with an NTP server.</phrase> Click
   <guimenu>Change</guimenu> to either alter the NTP settings or to
   <guimenu>Manually</guimenu> set the time. See
   <xref linkend="cha.netz.xntp"/> for more information on configuring the
   NTP service. When finished, click <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to continue
   the installation.
  </para>

  <note arch="zseries" os="sles">
   <title>Time Cannot be Changed on IBM &zseries;</title>
   <para>
    Since the operating system is not allowed to change time and date
    directly, the <guimenu>Change</guimenu> option is not available on IBM
    &zseries;.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.desktop" os="osuse">
  <title>Desktop Selection</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&yast;</primary>

  <secondary>desktop selection</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>&yast;</primary>

  <secondary>system type</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>desktop selection</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>system type</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   In &productname;, you can choose from various desktops. The major ones,
   <guimenu>KDE</guimenu> and <guimenu>GNOME</guimenu>, are powerful
   graphical desktop environments similar to Windows. Find information about
   these in the <xref linkend="book.kdeuser"/> and the
   <xref linkend="book.gnomeuser"/>.<phrase os="osuse"> This step is skipped
   when installing from a LiveCD, since this medium is already
   pre-configured to either use KDE or GNOME.</phrase>
  </para>

  <para>
   If you prefer a different desktop, choose <guimenu>Other</guimenu> for
   more options. The <guimenu>XFCE Desktop</guimenu> is a fast and
   lightweight desktop environment suitable for modest hardware. With
   <guimenu>Minimal X Window</guimenu>, install a graphical window manager
   that allows for running stand-alone X applications and console windows
   but does not provide the usual integrated desktop functionality. In
   <guimenu>Minimal Server Selection (Text Mode)</guimenu>, only console
   terminals are available.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.inst.sys_type">
   <title>Desktop Selection</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_sys_type.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_sys_type.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.server" os="sles">
  <title>Server Base Scenario</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&yast;</primary>

  <secondary>server scenario</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   In &productname;, you can choose from three base scenarios. The selected
   scenario affects the package selection.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Physical Machine</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Choose this scenario when installing on a <quote>real</quote> machine
      or a fully virtualized guest.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Virtual Machine</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Choose this scenario when installing a paravirtualized guest.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>XEN Virtualization Host</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Choose this scenario when installing on a machine that should serve as
      a XEN host.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <figure>
   <title>Server Base Scenario</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_server_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_server_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.partitioning" os="osuse">
  <title>Suggested Partitioning</title><indexterm>

  <primary>partitions</primary>

  <secondary>creating</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>&yast;</primary>

  <secondary>partitioning</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>partitioning</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Define a partition setup for &productname; in this step. In most cases a
   reasonable scheme that can be accepted without change is proposed. If a
   hard disk containing only Windows FAT or NTFS partitions is selected as
   the installation target, &yast; proposes to shrink one of these
   partitions. Accept the proposal with <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and proceed
   with the installation. Experienced users can also customize the proposal
   or apply their own partitioning scheme.
  </para>

  <para>
   The proposed partitioning is <guimenu>Partition Based</guimenu> by
   default. If you prefer an <guimenu>LVM Based</guimenu> setup, check the
   respective option to automatically convert the proposal. Refer to
   <xref linkend="sec.yast2.system.lvm"/> for more information about the
   Logical Volume Manager (LVM).
  </para>

  <para>
   To make small changes in the proposal (like changing the file system type
   or encrypt partitions), select <guimenu>Edit Partition Setup</guimenu>
   and adjust the settings. See <xref linkend="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert"/>
   for instructions.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.inst.partitioning" os="osuse">
   <title>Suggested Partitioning</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_partitioning.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_partitioning.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <note arch="ipseries">
   <title>Suggested Partitioning on IBM &ppc;</title>
   <para>
    An already existing boot partition is usually re-used by &yast; when
    making the partitioning proposal. This is not possible on IBM &ppc;.
   </para>
  </note>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.partitioning.disk">
   <title>Partitioning a Specific Disk</title>
   <para>
    If your machine contains more than one hard disk and you want to
    restrict the partitioning proposal to just one disk, choose
    <guimenu>Create Partition Setup</guimenu> and then select a specific
    disk from the list. If the chosen hard disk does not contain any
    partitions yet, the whole hard disk will be used for the proposal.
    Otherwise, you can choose which existing partition(s) to use. To add a
    separate partition for you personal data check <guimenu>Propose a
    Separate Home Partition</guimenu>. Instead of the default
    partition-based proposal, it is possible to <guimenu>Create an LVM Based
    Proposal</guimenu>. Choose two times <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed
    to the next step.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.partitioning.windows" os="sled;osuse">
    <title>Resizing a Windows Partition</title><indexterm>
    <primary>partitions</primary>
    <secondary>resizing Windows</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
    <primary>installation</primary>
    <secondary>partitioning</secondary>
    <tertiary>resizing Windows</tertiary></indexterm>
    <para>
     If the selected hard disk only contains a Windows FAT or NTFS
     partition, &yast; offers to delete or shrink this partition. If you
     select <guimenu>Delete Windows Completely</guimenu>, the Windows
     partition is marked for deletion and the space is used for the
     installation of &productname;.
    </para>
    <warning>
     <title>Deleting Windows</title>
     <para>
      If you delete Windows, all data will be lost beyond recovery as soon
      as the formatting starts.
     </para>
    </warning>
    <para>
     To <guimenu>Shrink the Windows Partition</guimenu>, you need to
     interrupt the installation and boot Windows to prepare the partition
     before shrinking it. For all Windows file systems, proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Deactivate a <literal>Virtual Memory</literal> file, if there is one.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Run <command>scandisk</command>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Run <command>defrag</command>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
     After these preparations, restart the &productname; installation. When
     you turn to the partitioning setup, proceed as before and select
     <guimenu>Shrink Windows Partition</guimenu>. After a quick check of the
     partition, the dialog for resizing the Windows partition opens.
    </para>
    <para>
     The bar graph shows how much disk space is currently occupied by
     Windows and how much space is still available. To change the proposed
     settings use the slider or the input fields to adjust the partition
     sizing.
    </para>
    <figure
     id="fig.yast2.inst_resize_ui-000">
     <title>Resizing the Windows Partition</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="i_y2_disk_resizer.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="i_y2_disk_resizer.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
     If you leave this dialog by selecting <guimenu>Next</guimenu>, the
     settings are stored and you are returned to the previous dialog. The
     actual resizing takes place later, before the hard disk is formatted.
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>Writing on NTFS Partitions</title>
     <para>
      <indexterm>
      <primary>file systems</primary>
      <secondary>NTFS</secondary>
      </indexterm> By default, the Windows uses the NTFS file system.
      &productname; includes read and write access to the NTFS file system,
      but this feature has a few limitations. This means that you cannot
      read or write encrypted or compressed files. Furthermore, the Windows
      file permissions are not honored at the moment.<phrase os="osuse"> See
      <ulink
	url="http://en.opensuse.org/SDB:NTFS"/> for more
      information.</phrase>
     </para>
    </important>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.partitioning.custom">
   <title>Custom Partitioning</title>
   <para>
    Set up your own partitioning scheme by selecting <guimenu>Create
    Partition Setup</guimenu> and then <guimenu>Custom
    Partitioning</guimenu>. The Expert Partitioner opens, displaying the
    current partition setup. Expand the <guimenu>Hard Disks</guimenu> in the
    System View pane by clicking on the <guimenu>+</guimenu>, then click on
    one of the listed hard disks. Now you can <guimenu>Add</guimenu>,
    <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>, <guimenu>Resize</guimenu>, or
    <guimenu>Delete</guimenu> partitions. For more information about custom
    partitioning and configuring advanced features, refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert"/>
   </para>
   <warning>
    <title>Custom Partitioning on UEFI machines</title>
    <para>
     A UEFI machine <emphasis>requires</emphasis> an EFI system partition
     that must be mounted to <filename>/boot/efi</filename>. This partition
     must be formatted with the <literal>FAT</literal> file system.
    </para>
    <para>
     If an EFI system partition is already present present on your system
     (for example from a previous Windows installation) use it by mounting
     it to <filename>/boot/efi</filename> without formatting it.
    </para>
   </warning>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.user" os="osuse;sled">
  <title>Create New User</title><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>user</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Create a local user in this step. Administrating local users is a
   suitable option for stand-alone workstations. If setting up a client on a
   network with centralized user authentication, click
   <guimenu>Change</guimenu> and proceed with the
   <xref
    linkend="sec.i.yast2.user.expert"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   After entering the first name and last name, either accept the proposal
   or specify a new <guimenu>Username</guimenu> that will be used to log in.
   Finally, enter a password for the user. Reenter it for confirmation (to
   ensure that you did not type something else by mistake). To provide
   effective security, a password should be between five and eight
   characters long. The maximum length for a password is 72 characters.
   However, if no special security modules are loaded, only the first eight
   characters are used to discern the password. Passwords are
   case-sensitive. Special characters (7-bit ASCII) and the digits 0 to 9
   are allowed. Other special characters like umlauts or accented characters
   are not allowed.
  </para>

  <para>
   Passwords you enter are checked for weakness. When entering a password
   that is easy to guess (such as a dictionary word or a name) you will see
   a warning. It is a good security practice to use strong passwords.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Username and Password</title>
   <para>
    Remember both your username and the password because they are needed
    each time you log in to the system.
   </para>
  </important>

  <figure os="osuse">
   <title>Create New User</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_user.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_user.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <figure os="sled">
   <title>Create New User</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_user_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_user_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   Three additional options are available:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Use this Password for the System Administrator</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If checked, the same password you have entered for the user will be
      used for the system administrator &rootuser;. This option is suitable
      for stand-alone workstations or machines in a home network that are
      administrated by a single user. When not checked, you are prompted for
      a system administrator password in the next step of the installation
      workflow (see <xref
       linkend="sec.i.yast2.user.root"/>).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Receive System Mail</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Checking this box sends messages created by the system services to the
      user. These are usually only sent to &rootuser;, the system
      administrator. This option is useful for the most frequently used
      account, because it is highly recommended to log in as &rootuser; only
      in special cases.
     </para>
     <para>
      The mails sent by system services are stored in the local mailbox
      <filename>/var/spool/mail/</filename><replaceable>username</replaceable>,
      where <replaceable>username</replaceable> is the login name of the
      selected user. To read e-mails after installation, you can use any
      e-mail client, for example KMail or Evolution.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Automatic Login</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option automatically logs the current user in to the system when
      it starts. This is mainly useful if the computer is operated by only
      one user. <phrase os="sles">For automatic login to work, the option
      must be explicitly enabled.</phrase>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <warning os="osuse;sled">
   <title>Automatic Login</title>
   <para>
    With the automatic login enabled, the system boots straight into your
    desktop with no authentication at all. If you store sensitive data on
    your system, you should not enable this option as long as the computer
    can also be accessed by others.
   </para>
  </warning>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.user.expert">
   <title>Expert Settings</title><indexterm>
   <primary>installation</primary>
   <secondary>user</secondary>
   <tertiary>expert settings</tertiary></indexterm>
   <para os="osuse;sled">
    Click <guimenu>Change</guimenu> in the Create User dialog to set up
    network authentication or, if present, import users from a previous
    installation. Also change the password encryption type in this dialog.
   </para>
   <para os="sles">
    If network access was configured successfully during the previous steps
    of the installation, you can now choose from several user management
    options. If a network connection has not been configured, create local
    user accounts. You may also, if present, import users from a previous
    installation. Also change the password encryption type in this dialog.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can also add additional user accounts or change the user
    authentication method in the installed system. For detailed information
    about user management, see <xref linkend="cha.y2.userman"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The default authentication method is <guimenu>Local
    (/etc/passwd)</guimenu>. If a former version of &productname; or another
    system using <filename>/etc/passwd</filename> is detected, you may
    import local users. To do so, check <guimenu>Read User Data from a
    Previous Installation</guimenu> and click <guimenu>Choose</guimenu>. In
    the next dialog, select the users to import and finish with
    <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Access to the following network authentication services can be
    configured:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>LDAP</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Users are administered centrally on an LDAP server for all systems in
       the network. More information is available in
       <xref linkend="sec.security.ldap.yast.client"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>NIS</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Users are administered centrally on a NIS server for all systems in
       the network. See <xref linkend="sec.nis.client"/> for more
       information.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Windows Domain</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SMB authentication is often used in mixed Linux and Windows networks.
       <phrase os="sles"
        >Detailed information is available in
       <xref linkend="sec.samba.adnet"/></phrase> and
       <phrase
        os="sled;osuse"><xref linkend="sec.security.ad.config"/></phrase>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry os="sled">
     <term>eDirectory LDAP</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       eDirectory authentication is used in Novell networks.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    Along with user administration via <guimenu>LDAP</guimenu> and
    <guimenu>NIS</guimenu>, you can use Kerberos authentication. To use it,
    select <guimenu>Set Up Kerberos Authentication</guimenu>. For more
    information on Kerberos, refer to
    <xref
     linkend="cha.security.kerberos"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.user.root">
   <title>Password for the System Administrator &rootuser;</title><indexterm>
   <primary>&yast;</primary>
   <secondary>root password</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>installation</primary>
   <secondary>root password</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    If you have not chosen <guimenu>Use this Password for the System
    Administrator</guimenu> in the previous step, you will be prompted to
    enter a Password for the System Administrator &rootuser;. Otherwise this
    configuration step is skipped.
   </para>
   <para>
    &rootuser; is the name of the superuser, or the administrator of the
    system. Unlike regular users (who may or may not have permission to
    access certain areas or execute certain commands on the system),
    &rootuser; has unlimited access to change the system configuration,
    install programs, and set up new hardware. If users forget their
    passwords or have other problems with the system, &rootuser; can help.
    The &rootuser; account should only be used for system administration,
    maintenance, and repair. Logging in as &rootuser; for daily work is
    rather risky: a single mistake could lead to irretrievable loss of
    system files.
   </para>
   <para>
    For verification purposes, the password for &rootuser; must be entered
    twice. Do not forget the &rootuser; password. Once entered, this
    password cannot be retrieved.
   </para>
   <para>
    The &rootuser; can be changed any time later in the installed system. To
    do so run &yast; and start <menuchoice> <guimenu>Security and
    Users</guimenu> <guimenu>User and Group Management</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>.
   </para>
   <warning>
    <title>The root User</title>
    <para>
     The user &rootuser; has all the permissions needed to make changes to
     the system. To carry out such tasks, the &rootuser; password is
     required. You cannot carry out any administrative tasks without this
     password.
    </para>
   </warning>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal">
  <title>Installation Settings</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&yast;</primary>

  <secondary>installation settings</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>&yast;</primary>

  <secondary>installation summary</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>settings</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>summary</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   On the last step before the real installation takes place, you can alter
   installation settings suggested by &yast; and also review the settings
   you made so far. <phrase os="sles;sled"
    >Basic settings can be
   changed in the <guimenu>Overview</guimenu> tab, advanced options are
   available on the <guimenu>Experts</guimenu> tab. </phrase>To modify the
   suggestions, either click <guimenu>Change</guimenu> and select the
   category to change or click on one of the headlines. After configuring
   any of the items presented in these dialogs, you are always returned to
   the Installation Settings window, which is updated accordingly.
  </para>

  <figure os="osuse">
   <title>Installation Settings</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_summary.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_summary.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <figure os="sled">
   <title>Installation Settings</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_summary_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_summary_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <figure os="sles">
   <title>Installation Settings</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_summary_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="i_y2_inst_summary_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <tip>
   <title>Restoring the Default Settings</title>
   <para>
    You can reset all changes to the defaults by clicking <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Change</guimenu> <guimenu>Reset to Defaults</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>. &yast; then shows the original proposal again.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.partitioning">
   <title><guimenu>Partitioning</guimenu><phrase os="sles;sled"> (Overview)</phrase></title>
   <para>
    Review and, if necessary, change the partition setup<phrase os="osuse">
    you configured earlier</phrase><phrase os="sled;sles"> proposed by the
    system</phrase>. <phrase os="sled;sles"
     >Changing the partition
    setup either lets you partition a specific disk or, when choosing
    <guimenu>Custom Partitioning</guimenu>, apply your own partitioning
    scheme.</phrase> Modifying the partition setup opens the Expert
    Partitioner described in
    <xref
     linkend="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert"/>.
   </para>
   <tip os="sles">
    <title>Btrfs as a default filesystem</title>
    <para>
     The default partitioning scheme is based on Ext3 file system. To use
     Btrfs as a default file system instead, click
     <guimenu>Partitioning</guimenu> in the <guimenu>Overview</guimenu> tab
     and check <guimenu>Use Btrfs as Default Filesystem</guimenu>
    </para>
   </tip>
   <note os="sles" arch="zseries">
<!-- Bug #270526 -->
    <title>Using Minidisks in z/VM</title>
    <para>
     If &productname; is installed on minidisks in z/VM, which reside on the
     same physical disk, the access path of the minidisks (/dev/disk/by-id/)
     is not unique but rather the ID of the physical disk. So if two or more
     minidisks are on the same physical disk, they all have the same ID.
    </para>
    <para>
     To avoid problems when mounting the minidisks, always mount them either
     "by path" or "by UUID".
    </para>
   </note>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.booting">
   <title><guimenu>Booting</guimenu><phrase os="sles;sled"> (Expert)</phrase></title>
   <para arch="zseries" os="sles">
    This module cannot be used to configure the boot loader (zipl) on the
    IBM &zseries; platforms.
   </para>
   <para>
    &yast; proposes a boot configuration for your system. Other operating
    systems found on your computer, such as Microsoft Windows or other Linux
    installations, will automatically be detected and added to the boot
    loader. However, &productname; will be booted by default. Normally, you
    can leave these settings unchanged. If you need a custom setup, modify
    the proposal for your system. For information, see
    <xref linkend="grub2.yast2.config"/>. <phrase
     os="osuse">The
    boot method should only be changed by experienced users. </phrase>
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.sofware">
   <title><guimenu>Software</guimenu><phrase os="sles;sled"> (Overview)</phrase></title>
   <para>
    &productname; contains a number of software patterns for various
    application purposes. Click <guimenu>Software</guimenu> to start the
    pattern selection and modify the installation scope according to your
    needs. Select your pattern from the list and see a pattern description
    in the right part of the window. Each pattern contains a number of
    software packages needed for specific functions (e.g.
    <phrase
     os="osuse;sled">Multimedia or Office
    software</phrase><phrase
     os="sles">Web and LAMP server or a print
    server</phrase>). For a more detailed selection based on software
    packages to install, select <guimenu>Details</guimenu> to switch to the
    &yast; Software Manager.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can also install additional software packages or remove software
    packages from your system at any later time with the &yast; Software
    Manager. For more information, refer to
    <xref
     linkend="cha.y2.sw"/>.
   </para>
   <figure os="osuse">
    <title>Software Selection and System Tasks</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="i_y2_software.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="i_y2_software.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <figure os="sled">
    <title>Software Selection and System Tasks</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="i_y2_software_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="i_y2_software_sled.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <figure os="sles">
    <title>Software Selection and System Tasks</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="i_y2_software_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="i_y2_software_sles.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <note os="sles">
    <title>Default Desktop</title>
    <para>
     The default desktop of &productname; is GNOME. A light-weight alternative
     is available with IceWM. To install it, select <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Software</guimenu> <guimenu>Details</guimenu> </menuchoice> and
     search for <literal>icewm</literal>.
    </para>
   </note>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.locale">
   <title><guimenu os="osuse">Locale Settings</guimenu><guimenu os="sles;sled"
     >Language</guimenu><phrase os="sles;sled"> (Overview)</phrase></title>
   <para>
    Here you can change the system
    <guimenu>Language</guimenu><phrase os="osuse"> and <guimenu>Keyboard
    Layout</guimenu></phrase> you defined in the first step of the
    installation. It is also possible to add additional languages. To adjust
    the system language settings, select <guimenu>Language</guimenu>. Select
    a language from the list. The primary language is used as the system
    language. You can also adapt keyboard layout and time zone to the
    primary language if the current settings differ.
    <guimenu>Details</guimenu> lets you modify language settings for the
    user &rootuser;, set <systemitem>UTF-8</systemitem> support, or further
    specify the language (e.g. select South African English).
   </para>
   <para>
    Choose secondary languages to be able to switch to one of these
    languages at any time without having to install additional packages. For
    more information, see <xref
     linkend="cha.y2.lang"/>.
   </para>
   <para os="osuse">
    To change the keyboard layout, select <guimenu>Keyboard
    Layout</guimenu>. By default, the layout corresponds to the language
    chosen for installation. Select the keyboard layout from the list. Use
    the <guimenu>Test</guimenu> field at the bottom of the dialog to check
    if you can enter special characters of that layout correctly. Options to
    fine-tune various settings are available under <guimenu>Expert
    Mode</guimenu>. When finished, click <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to return
    to the installation summary.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.add-on" os="sles;sled">
   <title><guimenu>Add-On Products</guimenu> (Expert)</title>
   <para>
    If you added a source for an add-on media earlier, it appears here. Add,
    remove, or modify add-on products here, if needed.This is the same
    configuration dialog as discussed earlier in
    <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.addon"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.keyboard" os="sles;sled">
   <title><guimenu>Keyboard Layout</guimenu> (Expert)</title>
   <para>
    To change the keyboard layout, select <guimenu>Keyboard
    Layout</guimenu>. By default, the layout corresponds to the language
    chosen for installation. Select the keyboard layout from the list. Use
    the <guimenu>Test</guimenu> field at the bottom of the dialog to check
    if you can enter special characters of that layout correctly. Options to
    fine-tune various settings are available under <guimenu>Expert
    Mode</guimenu>.
<!-- Find more information about changing the keyboard layout
    in <xref linkend="cha.y2.hw.keym"/>.-->
    When finished, click <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to return to the
    installation summary.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.timezone">
   <title><guimenu>Time Zone</guimenu><phrase os="sles;sled"> (Expert)</phrase></title>
   <para>
    Adjust time zone and clock settings here. Provided a network is
    configured, you can also set up a Network Time Protocol (NTP) client
    that automatically synchronizes your computer with a time server. This
    is the same configuration as shown earlier in
    <xref
     linkend="sec.i.yast2.timezone"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.user" os="osuse">
   <title><guimenu>User Settings</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    Change the current <guimenu>User</guimenu> settings and change or set
    the <guimenu>Root Password</guimenu> here. This is the same
    configuration as shown earlier in
    <xref
     linkend="sec.i.yast2.user"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.runlevel">
   <title><guimenu>Default Runlevel</guimenu><phrase os="sles;sled"> (Expert)</phrase></title>
   <para>
    &productname; can boot to different runlevels. Normally, there should be
    no need to change anything here, but if necessary set the default
    runlevel with this dialog.
<!-- fs 2001-11-07: SYSTEMD
    Refer to <xref linkend="sec.boot.runlevel.edit"/> for more information about
    runlevel configuration.
-->
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.system">
   <title><guimenu>System</guimenu><phrase os="sles;sled"> (Expert)</phrase></title>
   <para>
    This dialog presents all the hardware information &yast; could obtain
    about your computer. When called, the hardware detection routine is
    started. Depending on your system, this may take some time. Select any
    item in the list and click <guimenu>Details</guimenu> to see detailed
    information about the selected item. Use <guimenu>Save to File</guimenu>
    to save a detailed list to either the local file system or a removable
    device. Advanced users can also change the PCI ID setup and Kernel
    Settings by choosing <guimenu>Kernel Settings</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.kdump" os="sles">
   <title><guimenu>Kdump</guimenu> (Expert)</title>
   <para>
    Using kdump, you can save a dump of the kernel (in case of a crash) to
    analyze what went wrong. Use this dialog to enable and configure kdump.
    Find detailed information at <xref
     linkend="cha.tuning.kexec"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.images" os="osuse">
   <title><guimenu>Installation from Images</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    Installing from images considerably speeds up the installation. Images
    contain compressed snapshots of installed systems matching your
    selection of patterns. Packages not contained in the images deployed
    will be installed conventionally.
   </para>
   <para>
    Unless your custom software selection does not match any of the
    available images, this feature is <guimenu>Enabled</guimenu> by default.
    In case of problems, <guimenu>Disable</guimenu> it for debugging
    purposes.
   </para>
   <note>
<!-- fs 2012-04-16: bnc #732914 -->
    <title>Installation Time Stamps</title>
    <para>
     The RPM database keeps track of the date a package was last installed
     or updated (check with for example <command>rpm <option>-qa
     --last</option></command>). When installing from images, the time
     stamps of all packages originating from the images do not match the
     installation date but rather the date the image was created.
    </para>
   </note>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.proposal.firewall" os="osuse">
   <title><guimenu>Firewall</guimenu></title>
   <para>
    By default &susefirewall; is enabled on all configured network
    interfaces. To globally disable the firewall for this computer, click on
    <guimenu>Disable</guimenu>. If the firewall is enabled, you may
    <guimenu>Open</guimenu> the SSH port in order to allow remote
    connections via secure shell.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.perform">
  <title>Performing the Installation</title><indexterm>

  <primary>installation</primary>

  <secondary>performing</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   After configuring all installation settings, click
   <guimenu>Install</guimenu> in the Installation Settings window to start
   the installation. Some software may require a license confirmation. If
   your software selection includes such software, license confirmation
   dialogs are displayed. Click <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to install the
   software package. When not agreeing to the license, click <guimenu>I
   Disagree</guimenu> and the software package will not be installed. In the
   dialog that follows, confirm with <guimenu>Install</guimenu> again.
  </para>

  <para>
   The installation usually takes between 15 and 30 minutes, depending on
   the system performance and the selected software scope. After having
   prepared the hard disk<phrase os="sles;sled"> and having saved and
   restored the user settings,</phrase><phrase os="osuse">, having saved and
   restored the user settings, and having deployed the installation
   images,</phrase> the software installation starts.
   <phrase os="osuse;sled">During this procedure a slide show introduces the
   features of &productname;. Choose <guimenu>Details</guimenu> to switch to
   the installation log<phrase
     os="osuse"> or <guimenu>Release
   Notes</guimenu> to read important up-to-date information which was not
   available when the manuals were printed</phrase>.</phrase>
  </para>

  <note os="osuse">
   <title>Release Notes</title>
   <para>
    <indexterm>
    <primary>installation</primary>
    <secondary>release notes</secondary>
    </indexterm> The release notes that can be viewed during this step are
    the ones printed on the installation CD. A newer version may be
    available on the Internet. When manually configuring network and
    Internet access as described in
    <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.network"/>, the latest version of
    the release notes will be displayed at the end of the installation.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   After the software installation has completed, the basic system is set
   up. Among others, <quote>Finishing the Basic Installation</quote>
   includes installing the boot manager, initializing fonts and more. Next
   &yast; boots into the new Linux system to start the system configuration.
  </para>

  <tip>
<!-- fs 2008-09-12: Fate #300421 -->
   <title>Existing SSH Host Keys</title>
   <para>
    If you install &productname; on a machine with existing Linux
    installations, the installation routine automatically imports the SSH
    host key with the most recent access time from an existing installation.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <sect2 id="sec.s390.inst.reipl" arch="zseries" os="sles">
   <title>IBM &zseries;: IPLing the Installed System</title>
   <para>
    In most cases, &yast; automatically reboots into the installed system on
    the IBM &zseries; platform. Known exceptions to this are installations
    wherein the bootloader resides on an FCP device in environments with
    LPAR on a machine older than z9 or with z/VM older than release 5.3. The
    bootloader gets written to the device that holds the
    <filename>/boot</filename> directory. If <filename>/boot</filename> is
    not on a separate partition, it is on the same partition as the root
    file system <filename>/</filename>.
   </para>
   <para>
    In cases where an automatic reboot is not possible, &yast; will show a
    dialog box containing information about from which device to do an IPL.
    Accept the shutdown option and perform an IPL after the shutdown. The
    procedure varies according to the type of installation:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>LPAR Installation</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <indexterm>
       <primary>LPAR installation</primary>
       <secondary>IPL</secondary>
       </indexterm> In the IBM &zseries; HMC, select
       <guimenu>Load</guimenu>, select <guimenu>Clear</guimenu>, then enter
       the loading address (the device address of the device holding the
       <filename>/boot</filename> directory with the bootloader). If using a
       ZFCP disk as the boot device, choose <guimenu>Load from
       SCSI</guimenu> and specify the load address of your FCP adapter as
       well as WWPN and LUN of the boot device. Now start the loading
       process.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>z/VM Installation</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <indexterm>
       <primary>z/VM Installation</primary>
       <secondary>IPL</secondary>
       </indexterm> Log in to the VM guest (see
       <xref
        linkend="ex.prep.prep_ipl.vm.linux_guest.config"/> for
       the configuration) as
       <systemitem
        class="username">LINUX1</systemitem> and proceed
       to IPL the installed system:
      </para>
<screen>IPL 151 CLEAR</screen>
      <para>
       <literal>151</literal> is an example address of the DASD boot device,
       replace this value with the correct address.
      </para>
      <para>
       If using a ZFCP disk as the boot device, specify both the ZFCP WWPN
       and LUN of the boot device before initiating the IPL. The parameter
       length is limited to eight characters. Longer numbers must be
       separated by spaces:
      </para>
<screen>SET LOADDEV PORT 50050763 00C590A9 LUN 50010000 00000000 </screen>
      <para>
       Finally, initiate the IPL:
      </para>
<screen>IPL FC00</screen>
      <para>
       <literal>FC00</literal> is an example address of the ZFCP adapter,
       replace this value with the correct address.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.s390.inst.reipl.reconnect" arch="zseries" os="sles">
   <title>IBM &zseries;: Connecting to the Installed System</title>
   <para>
    After IPLing the installed system, establish a connection with it to
    complete the installation. The steps involved in this vary depending on
    the type of connection used at the outset.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.s390.inst.reipl.reconnect.vnc">
    <title>Using VNC to Connect</title>
    <para>
     A message in the 3270&nbsp;terminal asks you to connect to the Linux
     system using a VNC client. This message is easily missed, however,
     because it is mixed with kernel messages and the terminal process might
     quit before you become aware of the message. If nothing happens for
     five minutes, try to initiate a connection to the Linux system using a
     VNC viewer.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you connect using a Java-capable browser, enter the complete URL,
     consisting of the IP address of the installed system along with the
     port number, in the following fashion:
    </para>
<screen> http://&lt;IP of installed system&gt;:5801/ </screen>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.s390.inst.reipl.reconnect.x">
    <title>Using X to Connect</title>
    <para>
     When IPLing the installed system, make sure that the X server used for
     the first phase of the installation is up and still available before
     booting from the DASD. &yast; opens on this X server to finish the
     installation. Complications may arise if the system is booted up but
     unable to connect to the X server in a timely fashion.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.s390.inst.reipl.reconnect.ssh">
    <title>Using SSH to Connect</title>
    <important>
     <title>IBM &zseries;: Connecting from a Linux or UNIX System</title>
     <para>
      Start SSH in an xterm. Other terminal emulators lack complete support
      for the text-based interface of &yast;.
     </para>
    </important>
    <para>
     A message in the 3270&nbsp;terminal asks you to connect to the Linux
     system with an SSH client. This message is easily missed, however,
     because it is mixed with kernel messages and the terminal process might
     quit before you become aware of the message.
    </para>
    <para>
     Once the message appears, use SSH to log in to the Linux system as
     <systemitem
      class="username">root</systemitem>. If the connection
     is denied or times out, wait for the login timeout to expire, then try
     again (this time may vary depending on server settings).
    </para>
    <para>
     When the connection is established, execute the command
     <command>/usr/lib/YaST2/startup/YaST2.ssh</command>. Just executing the
     command <command>yast</command> does not suffice in this case.
    </para>
    <para>
     &yast; then begins completing the installation of the remaining
     packages and creating an initial system configuration.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.conf">
  <title>Configuration of the Installed System</title>

  <para>
   The system is now installed, but not yet configured for use. The
   hardware, the network and other services are not yet set
   up.<phrase os="osuse;sled"> If you follow the default installation path,
   the system will be automatically configured. If you have deselected the
   <guimenu>Automatic Configuration</guimenu>, the manual system
   configuration starts.</phrase>
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.auto" os="osuse;sled">
   <title>Automatic System Configuration</title><indexterm>
   <primary>installation</primary>
   <secondary>automatic configuration</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Having rebooted, the system starts the Automatic Configuration. This
    routine attempts to configure your network and Internet access and sets
    up your hardware. This process does not need any interaction. You can
    change the settings made by Automatic Configuration at any time on the
    installed system with &yast;. Continue with
    <phrase os="osuse"><xref
      linkend="sec.i.yast2.conf.dm"/></phrase><phrase os="sled"><xref
      linkend="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.cc"/></phrase>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual">
   <title><phrase os="osuse;sled;">Manual </phrase>System Configuration</title><indexterm>
   <primary>installation</primary>
   <secondary>manual configuration</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Having rebooted, the system starts the manual configuration. If the
    configuration fails at one of the steps of this stage, it restarts and
    continues from the last successful step.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.root">
    <title>Password for the System Administrator <quote>root</quote></title><indexterm>
    <primary>&yast;</primary>
    <secondary>root password</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     &rootuser; is the name of the superuser, the administrator of the
     system. Unlike regular users, who may or may not have permission to
     execute administrative commands on the system, &rootuser; has unlimited
     command capacity, for instance changing the system configuration,
     installing programs, and setting up new hardware. If users forget their
     passwords or have other problems with the system, &rootuser; can help.
     The &rootuser; account should only be used for system administration,
     maintenance, and repair. Logging in as &rootuser; for daily work is
     rather risky: a single mistake could lead to the irretrievable loss of
     system files.
    </para>
    <para>
     For verification purposes, the password for &rootuser; must be entered
     twice. Do not forget the &rootuser; password. Once entered, this
     password cannot be retrieved.
    </para>
    <para>
     When typing passwords, the characters are replaced by dots, so you do
     not see the string you are typing. If you are unsure whether you have
     typed the correct string, use the <guimenu>Test Keyboard
     Layout</guimenu> field for testing purposes.
    </para>
    <para>
     &productname; can use the DES, MD5, or Blowfish encryption algorithms
     for passwords. The default encryption type is Blowfish. To change the
     encryption type, click <menuchoice><guimenu>Expert
     Options</guimenu><guimenu>Encryption Type</guimenu></menuchoice> and
     select the new type.
    </para>
    <para>
     The &rootuser; can be changed any time later in the installed system.
     To do so run &yast; and start <menuchoice> <guimenu>Security and
     Users</guimenu> <guimenu>User and Group Management</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.hostname">
    <title>Hostname and Domain Name</title><indexterm>
    <primary>&yast;</primary>
    <secondary>hostname</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
    <primary>&yast;</primary>
    <secondary>domain name</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
    <primary>installation</primary>
    <secondary>hostname</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
    <primary>installation</primary>
    <secondary>domain name</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     The hostname is the computer's name in the network. The domain name is
     the name of the network. A hostname and domain are proposed by default.
     If your system is part of a network, the hostname has to be unique in
     this network, whereas the domain name has to be common to all hosts on
     the network.
    </para>
    <para>
     In many networks, the system receives its name over DHCP. In this case
     it is not necessary to modify the proposed hostname and domain name.
     Select <guimenu>Change Hostname via DHCP</guimenu> instead. To be able
     to access your system using this hostname, even when it is not
     connected to the network, select <guimenu>Assign Hostname to Loopback
     IP</guimenu>. Do not enable this option when your machine provides
     network services. If you often change networks without restarting the
     desktop environment (e.g. when switching between different WLANs), do
     not enable this option either, because the desktop system may get
     confused when the hostname in <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> changes.
    </para>
    <para>
     To change hostname settings at any time after installation, use &yast;
     <menuchoice><guimenu>Network Devices</guimenu><guimenu>Network
     Settings</guimenu></menuchoice>. For more information, see
     <xref linkend="sec.basicnet.yast.netcard"/>.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3
    id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.network">
    <title>Network Configuration</title><indexterm>
    <primary>&yast;</primary>
    <secondary>network configuration</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
    <primary>installation</primary>
    <secondary>network configuration</secondary></indexterm>
    <tip arch="zseries" os="sles">
     <title>IBM &zseries;: Network Configuration</title>
     <para>
      For the IBM &zseries; platforms, a working network connection is
      needed at installation time to connect to the target system, the
      installation source, and the &yast; terminal controlling the process.
      The steps to set up the network are discussed in
      <xref
       linkend="sec.prep.netcfg"/>. The IBM &zseries; platforms
      only support the types of network interfaces mentioned there (OSA
      Ethernet, OSA Gigabit Ethernet, OSA Express Fast Ethernet, Escon, and
      IUCV). The &yast; dialog simply displays the interface with its
      settings as already configured. Just confirm this dialog to continue.
     </para>
    </tip>
    <para os="osuse;sled">
     If you are installing &productname; on a laptop computer,
     <guimenu>Interfaces Controlled by &nm;</guimenu> is enabled. &nm; is a
     tool that enables automatic connection with minimal user intervention.
     It is ideal for WLAN and mobile computing. If you want to use the
     traditional method without &nm;, click <guimenu>Disable &nm;</guimenu>.
     Find detailed information about &nm; in <xref linkend="cha.nm"/>. If
     you are installing &productname; on any other type of machine, the
     traditional method without &nm; is selected by default. This
     configuration step also lets you configure the network devices of your
     system and make security settings, for example, for a firewall or
     proxy.
    </para>
    <para os="sles">
     By default, <guimenu>Traditional Method without &nm; Applet</guimenu>
     is enabled. If desired, you can also use &nm; to manage all your
     network devices. However, the traditional method is the preferred
     option for server solutions. Find detailed information about &nm; in
     <xref
      linkend="cha.nm"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The network can also be configured after the system installation has
     been completed. If you skip it now, your system is left offline unable
     to retrieve any available updates. To configure your network connection
     later, select <guimenu>Skip Configuration</guimenu> and click
     <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The following network settings can be configured in this step:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>General Network Settings</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Enable or disable the use of &nm; as described above. Also change
        the IPv6 support here. By default the IPv6 support is enabled. To
        disable it, click <guimenu>Disable IPv6</guimenu>. For more
        information about IPv6, see <xref linkend="sec.basicnet.ipv6"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Firewall</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        By default &susefirewall; is enabled on all configured network
        interfaces. To globally disable the firewall for this computer,
        click on <guimenu>Disable</guimenu>. If the firewall is enabled, you
        may <guimenu>Open</guimenu> the SSH port in order to allow remote
        connections via secure shell. To open the detailed firewall
        configuration dialog, click on <guimenu>Firewall</guimenu>. See
        <xref linkend="sec.security.firewall.SuSE.yast"/> for detailed
        information.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry os="sles;sled">
      <term><guimenu>Services</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The CIM (Common Information Model) Server is started by default.
        Click <guimenu>Disable</guimenu> to prevent the server from starting
        automatically at boot time. <phrase os="sles">For more information
        on CIM services refer to <xref linkend="cha.wbem"/>.</phrase>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Network Interfaces</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        All network cards detected by &yast; are listed here. If you have
        already set up a network connection during the installation (as
        described in
        <xref
         linkend="sec.i.yast2.inst_mode.network"/>) the card
        used for this connection is listed as <guimenu>Configured</guimenu>.
        A click on <guimenu>Network Interfaces</guimenu> opens the
        <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu> dialog, where you can change
        existing configurations, set up networks cards not configured yet,
        or add and configure additional cards.<phrase os="sled"> See
        <xref linkend="sec.internet.network"/> for checklists of
        configuration requirements for the various connection types and
        <xref linkend="sec.basicnet.yast.netcard"/> for configuration
        details.</phrase>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>DSL Connections</guimenu>, <guimenu>ISDN
        Adapters</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Modems</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If your computer is equipped with an internal DSL modem, an internal
        ADSL Fritz Card, an ISDN card or a modem, clicking on the respective
        headline opens the configuration dialog.
        <phrase os="sles;sled">Refer to <xref linkend="cha.internet"/> for
        further information.</phrase>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>VNC Remote Administration</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        To enable remote administration of your machine via VNC, click
        <guimenu>VNC Remote Administration</guimenu>. Choose <guimenu>Allow
        Remote Administration</guimenu> in the following dialog and adjust
        your firewall settings accordingly.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Proxy</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If you have a proxy server controlling the Internet access in your
        network, configure the proxy URLs and authentication details in this
        dialog.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <tip>
     <title>Resetting the Network Configuration to the Default Values</title>
     <para>
      Reset the network settings to the original proposed values by clicking
      <menuchoice> <guimenu>Change</guimenu> <guimenu>Reset to
      Defaults</guimenu> </menuchoice>. This discards any changes made.
     </para>
    </tip>
    <sect4 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.network.internet">
     <title>Test Internet Connection</title><indexterm>
     <primary>installation</primary>
     <secondary>internet connection</secondary></indexterm>
     <para>
      After having configured a network connection, you can test it. For
      this purpose, &yast; establishes a connection to the &productname;
      server and downloads the latest release notes. Read them at the end of
      the installation process. A successful test is also a prerequisite for
      the automatic addition of the default repositories and for updating
      online.
     </para>
     <para>
      If you have multiple network interfaces, verify that the desired card
      is used to connect to the Internet. If not, click <guimenu>Change
      Device</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <para>
      To start the test, select <guimenu>Yes, Test Connection to the
      Internet</guimenu> and click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. In the following
      dialog, view the progress of the test and the results. Detailed
      information about the test process is available via <guimenu>View
      Logs</guimenu>. If the test fails, click <guimenu>Back</guimenu> to
      return to the network configuration to correct your entries.
     </para>
     <para>
      Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. If the test was successful, the
      official software repositories for &productname; and the update
      repository will be configured. Downloading the repository data for the
      first time may take some time.
     </para>
     <para>
      If you do not want to test the connection at this point, select
      <guimenu>No, Skip This Test</guimenu> then <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
      This also skips downloading the release notes,
      <phrase os="sles;sled">configuring the customer center</phrase> and
      updating online. These steps can be performed any time after the
      system has been initially configured.
     </para>
    </sect4>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.cc" os="sles;sled">
    <title>&ncc; Configuration</title>
    <para>
     To get technical support and product updates, you need to register and
     activate your product with the &ncc;. The <guimenu>&ncc;
     Configuration</guimenu> provides assistance for doing so. Find detailed
     information about &ncc; at
     <ulink
      url="http://www.novell.com/documentation/ncc/"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you are offline or want to skip this step, select <guimenu>Configure
     Later</guimenu>. This also skips &productname;'s online update.
    </para>
    <para>
     In <guimenu>Include for Convenience</guimenu>, select whether to send
     unsolicited additional information, such as your <guimenu>Hardware
     Profile</guimenu> or <guimenu>Optional Information</guimenu> when
     registering. This simplifies the registration process. Click on
     <guimenu>Details</guimenu> to get in-depth information about how the
     data will be collected. In order to obtain information about which data
     will be sent for your specific product, the Novell server will be
     connected. Upon this initial connect no data other than the ID of your
     product will be sent to the Novell servers.
    </para>
    <para>
     In order to become entitled for support, make sure to check
     <guimenu>Registration Code</guimenu>. You will be prompted to enter the
     code when proceeding with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. Find more
     information about the technical support at
     <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/support/programs/"/>.
    </para>
    <note>
     <title>Data Privacy</title>
     <para>
      No information is passed to anyone outside Novell. The data is used
      for statistical purposes and to enhance your convenience regarding
      driver support and your Web account. Find a link to the detailed
      privacy policy by clicking on <guimenu>Details</guimenu>. View the
      information transmitted in the log file at
      <filename>/root/.suse_register.log</filename>.
     </para>
    </note>
    <para>
     Apart from activating and registering your product, this module also
     adds the official update repositories to your configuration. These
     repositories provide fixes for known bugs or security issues which can
     be installed via an online update.
    </para>
    <para>
     To keep your repositories valid, select <guimenu>Regularly Synchronize
     with Customer Center</guimenu>. This option checks your repositories
     and adds newly available catalogs or removes obsolete ones. It does not
     affect manually-added repositories.
    </para>
    <para os="sled">
     In addition to the update repositories, two more catalogs with official
     drivers for ATI and NVidia graphics cards are added. &productname;
     ships with open source drivers for these cards, but the official
     drivers, provided directly by the graphics cards manufacturers, offer
     additional functionality. In order to add these repositories, you need
     to import their public &gpg; keys&mdash;these keys are used to ensure
     the repositories is provided by the owner of the catalog. Click
     <guimenu>Trust Key</guimenu> and then <guimenu>Import</guimenu> to add
     the catalog. Click <guimenu>Skip package</guimenu> and then
     <guimenu>Abort</guimenu> to prevent this specific repository from being
     added to your configuration.
    </para>
    <para>
     Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. A connection with the Novell
     server is established. Follow the on-screen instructions to finish the
     registration.
    </para>
    <tip>
     <title>Re-registering an Installed System with a Different Registration Code</title>
     <para>
      When you register a system in &ncc;, registration data is stored
      locally and in the &ncc; database. Although it is normally not
      necessary, there are corner cases which may require you to re-register
      an already installed machine with a different registration code. To do
      so, proceed with the following steps on the installed system:
     </para>
     <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Enter the following command as user &rootuser; to delete the
        installation data on the local machine:
       </para>
<screen>suse_register.pl --erase-local-regdata</screen>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Next you need to remove the registered system from the &ncc;
        database. Go to <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/"/> in a browser and
        click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Support</guimenu> <guimenu>Customer
        Center</guimenu></menuchoice>. Log in and navigate to <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>My Systems</guimenu>
        <guimenu>System</guimenu></menuchoice>. Select the system and remove
        it by clicking on the dash sign in the bottom bar of the table.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Now you can re-register the machine with either
        <command>suse-register</command> or the &yast; module
        <guimenu>Online Update Configuration</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </orderedlist>
    </tip>
    <sect4 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.cc.local">
     <title>Local Registration Server</title>
     <para>
      If your organization provides a local registration server instead of
      using the &ncc;, you need to specify the server's URL. Client and
      server communicate solely via HTTPS protocol, therefore you also need
      to enter a path to the server's certificate if the certificate was not
      issued by a certificate authority. Open the dialog with <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> <guimenu>Local Registration
      Server</guimenu> </menuchoice>
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><guimenu>Registration Server</guimenu>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         URL of the registration server. The URL has a fixed format
         <literal>https://<replaceable>FQN</replaceable>/center/regsvc/</literal>
         <replaceable>FQN</replaceable> has to be full qualified hostname of
         the registration server. Example:
        </para>
<screen>https://smt.&exampledomain;/center/regsvc/</screen>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Server CA certificate location</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Location of the registration server's certificate. Specify one of
         the following locations:
        </para>
        <variablelist>
         <varlistentry>
          <term>URL</term>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            Remote location (http, https or ftp) from which the certificate
            can be downloaded. Example:
           </para>
<screen>http://smt.&exampledomain;/smt-ca.crt</screen>
          </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
          <term>local path</term>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            Absolute path to the certificate on the local machine. Example:
           </para>
<screen>/data/inst/smt/smt-ca.cert</screen>
          </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
          <term>Interactive</term>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            Use <literal>ask</literal> to open a pop-up menu where you can
            specify the path to the certificate. Do not use this option with
            &ay;. Example
           </para>
<screen>ask</screen>
          </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
          <term>Deactivate certificate installation</term>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            Use <literal>done</literal> if either the certificate will be
            installed by an add-on product, or if you are using a
            certificate issued by an official certificate authority.
            Example:
           </para>
<screen>done</screen>
          </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </sect4>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.update">
    <title>Online Update</title><indexterm>
    <primary>&yast;</primary>
    <secondary>software updates</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
    <primary>installation</primary>
    <secondary>online update</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
    <primary>&yast;</primary>
    <secondary>online update</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
    <primary>installation</primary>
    <secondary>software updates</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     If an Internet connection has been established, and updates are
     available, select whether to perform a &yast; online update. If there
     are any patched packages available on the servers, download and install
     them now to fix known bugs or security issues. For detailed
     instructions see <xref linkend="cha.onlineupdate.you"/>. Directives on
     how to perform an online update in the installed system are available
     at <xref linkend="sec.updater"/> or
     <xref
      linkend="cha.onlineupdate.you"/>. This step is skipped if
     no updates are available or no Internet connection has been
     established. Patches fixing security issues and recommended patches
     applying to your installation are automatically preselected. Click
     <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to install them and <guimenu>Next</guimenu>
     to proceed with the system configuration.
    </para>
    <important os="osuse">
     <title>Downloading Software Updates</title>
     <para>
      The download of updates might take quite some time, depending on the
      bandwidth of the Internet connection and the size of the update files.
      In case the patch system itself is updated, the online update will
      restart and download more patches after the restart. If the kernel was
      updated, the system will reboot before completing the configuration.
     </para>
    </important>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.servprop" os="sles">
    <title>Services Configuration</title>
    <para>
     After testing the Internet connection and downloading the first
     updates, a dialog opens in which to enable and configure three network
     services.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>CA Management</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The purpose of a CA (certificate authority) is to guarantee a trust
        relationship among all network services communicating with each
        other. Without a CA, you can secure server communications with SSL
        and TLS separately for each individual service. By default, a CA is
        created and enabled during the installation. Find details about the
        creation of a CA with &yast; in
        <xref linkend="cha.security.yast_ca"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>OpenLDAP Server</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        You can run an LDAP service on your host to have a central facility
        manage a range of configuration files. Typically, an LDAP server
        handles user account data, but with &productname; it can also be
        used for mail, DHCP, and DNS data. By default, an LDAP server is set
        up during the installation. If you decide against the use of an LDAP
        server, the &yast; mail server module does not work because it
        depends on LDAP functionality. However, you can still set up a mail
        server on your system with the help of the <guimenu>Mail Transfer
        Agent</guimenu> module. Find details about LDAP and its
        configuration with &yast; in <xref linkend="cha.security.ldap"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Services</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The CIM (Common Information Model) Server is started by default.
        Click <guimenu>Disable</guimenu> to prevent the server automatically
        stating at boot time. For more information on CIM services refer to
        <xref
	 linkend="cha.wbem"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
     If preferred, you can skip this configuration proposal for now. After
     the installation is finished, configure and start the same services
     with the help of &yast;.
    </para>
    <tip>
     <title>Resetting the Service Configuration to Defaults</title>
     <para>
      Restore the defaults by clicking <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Change</guimenu> <guimenu>Reset to Defaults</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>. This discards any changes made.
     </para>
    </tip>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.users" os="osuse;sled">
    <title>New Local User</title><indexterm>
    <primary>installation</primary>
    <secondary>user</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     If no local user was created in step one, you can create one in this
     dialog. To create more users, manage groups, modify defaults for new
     users and set up network authentication, launch <guimenu>User
     Management</guimenu>. Refer to <xref linkend="cha.y2.userman"/> for
     more information about user management. To skip this step, click
     <guimenu>Next</guimenu> without entering any data.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.user_auth" os="sles">
    <title>User Authentication Method</title><indexterm>
    <primary>installation</primary>
    <secondary>user</secondary>
    <tertiary>expert settings</tertiary></indexterm>
    <para>
     If network access was configured successfully during the previous steps
     of the installation, you can now choose from several user management
     options. If a network connection has not been configured, create local
     user accounts. You may also, if present, import users from a previous
     installation. Also change the password encryption type in this dialog.
    </para>
    <para>
     You can also add additional user accounts or change the user
     authentication method in the installed system. For detailed information
     about user management, see <xref
      linkend="cha.y2.userman"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The default authentication method is <guimenu>Local
     (/etc/passwd)</guimenu>. If a former version of &productname; or
     another system using <filename>/etc/passwd</filename> is detected, you
     may import local users. To do so, check <guimenu>Read User Data from a
     Previous Installation</guimenu> and click <guimenu>Choose</guimenu>. In
     the next dialog, select the users to import and finish with
     <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Manually enter local users by clicking <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. The New
     Local User dialog opens. After entering the first name and last name,
     either accept the proposal or specify a new <guimenu>Username</guimenu>
     that will be used to log in. Finally, enter a password for the user.
     Reenter it for confirmation (to ensure that you did not type something
     else by mistake). To provide effective security, a password should be
     between five and eight characters long. The maximum length for a
     password is 72 characters. However, if no special security modules are
     loaded, only the first eight characters are used to discern the
     password. Passwords are case-sensitive. Special characters (7-bit
     ASCII) and the digits 0 to 9 are allowed. Other special characters like
     umlauts or accented characters are not allowed.
    </para>
    <para>
     Passwords you enter are checked for weakness. When entering a password
     that is easy to guess, such as a dictionary word or a name, you will
     see a warning. It is a good security practice to use strong passwords.
    </para>
    <para>
     Two additional options are available:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Receive System Mail</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Checking this box sends messages created by the system services to
        the user. These are usually only sent to &rootuser;, the system
        administrator. This option is useful for the most frequently used
        account, because it is highly recommended to log in as &rootuser;
        only in special cases.
       </para>
       <para>
        The mails sent by system services are stored in the local mailbox
        <filename>/var/spool/mail/</filename><replaceable>username</replaceable>,
        where <replaceable>username</replaceable> is the login name of the
        selected user. To read e-mails after installation, you can use any
        e-mail client, for example KMail or Evolution.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Automatic Login</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        This option automatically logs the current user in to the system on
        start-up. This is mainly useful if the computer is operated by only
        one user. <phrase os="sles">For automatic login to work, the option
        must be explicitly enabled.</phrase>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <warning>
     <title>Automatic Login</title>
     <para>
      With automatic login enabled, the system boots straight to your
      desktop with no authentication at all. If you store sensitive data on
      your system, you should not enable this option if the computer can
      also be accessed by others.
     </para>
    </warning>
    <para>
     Enter more users by calling the <guimenu>User Management</guimenu>
     module described in <xref linkend="cha.y2.userman"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     When using a network server for user authentication, access to the
     following services can be configured:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>LDAP</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Users are administered centrally on an LDAP server for all systems
        in the network. More information is available in
        <xref linkend="sec.security.ldap.yast.client"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>NIS</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Users are administered centrally on a NIS server for all systems in
        the network. See <xref linkend="sec.nis.client"/> for more
        information.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Windows Domain</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        SMB authentication is often used in mixed Linux and Windows
        networks. Detailed information is available in
        <xref linkend="sec.samba.adnet"/> and
        <xref
         linkend="sec.security.ad.config"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
     Along with user administration via <guimenu>LDAP</guimenu> and
     <guimenu>NIS</guimenu>, you can use Kerberos authentication. To use it,
     select <guimenu>Set Up Kerberos Authentication</guimenu>. For more
     information on Kerberos, refer to
     <xref
      linkend="cha.security.kerberos"/>.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.relnotes"
     >
    <title>Release Notes</title><indexterm>
    <primary>installation</primary>
    <secondary>release notes</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     After completing the user authentication setup, &yast; displays the
     release notes. Reading them is recommended, because they contain
     important up-to-date information which was not available when the
     manuals were printed. If you successfully tested the Internet
     connection, read the most recent version of the release notes, as
     fetched from &productname;'s servers. Use <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Miscellaneous</guimenu> <guimenu>Release Notes</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> in &yast; or start the &suse; Help Center to view the
     release notes after installation.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.hardware">
    <title>Hardware Configuration</title><indexterm>
    <primary>installation</primary>
    <secondary>hardware configuration</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     At the end of the installation, &yast; opens a dialog for the
     configuration of <guimenu>Graphics Cards</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Printer</guimenu> <phrase os="sles">and
     <guimenu>Sound</guimenu></phrase><phrase
      os="sled"><guimenu>Sound</guimenu>
     and TV Card</phrase>. Click the individual components to start the
     hardware configuration. For the most part, &yast; detects and
     configures the devices automatically.
    </para>
    <tip arch="zseries" os="sles">
     <title>IBM &zseries;: Hardware Configuration</title>
     <para>
      On the IBM &zseries;, there is no display that would be supported by
      XFree. Accordingly, you do not find a <guimenu>Graphics
      Cards</guimenu> entry on these systems.
     </para>
    </tip>
    <para>
     You can skip any peripheral devices and configure them later, as
     described in <xref
      linkend="cha.y2.hw"/>. To skip the
     configuration, select <guimenu>Skip Configuration</guimenu> and click
     <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <tip>
     <title>Resetting Hardware Configuration to the Default Values</title>
     <para>
      You can cancel any changes to the hardware configuration by clicking
      <menuchoice> <guimenu>Change</guimenu> <guimenu>Reset to
      Defaults</guimenu> </menuchoice>. &yast; then shows the original
      proposal again.
     </para>
    </tip>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.complete">
    <title>Installation Completed</title><indexterm>
    <primary>&ay;</primary>
    <secondary>cloning system</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     After a successful installation, &yast; shows the Installation
     Completed dialog. In this dialog, select whether to clone your newly
     installed system for &ay;. To clone your system, select <guimenu>Clone
     This System for &ay;</guimenu>. The profile of the current system is
     stored in <filename>/root/autoyast.xml</filename>.
     <phrase os="sles">Cloning is selected by default.</phrase>
    </para>
    <para>
     &ay; is a system for installing one or more &productname; systems
     automatically without user intervention. &ay; installations are
     performed using a control file with installation and configuration
     data.<phrase os="sles">For detailed information, refer to
     <xref
       linkend="cha.deployment.autoinst"/>.</phrase> Finish the
     installation of &productname; with <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> in the
     final dialog.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.i.yast2.conf.dm">
  <title>Graphical Login</title>

  <tip arch="zseries" os="sles">
   <title>IBM &zseries;: No Graphical Login</title>
   <para>
    The graphical login is not available on IBM &zseries; platforms.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
   &productname; is now fully installed and configured. Unless you enabled
   the automatic login function or customized the default runlevel, you
   should see the graphical login on your screen in which to enter a
   username and password to log into the system. On single user systems with
   automatic login enabled, the desktop starts automatically.
  </para>

  <para os="sled;osuse">
   For a detailed information about the GNOME desktop environment, refer
   to the <xref linkend="book.gnomeuser"/>. This manual can be accessed via the
   <guimenu>Help</guimenu> in both GNOME.
  </para><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.Installation"/><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.Installation_YaST2"/><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.YaST2_Installation"/>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
