<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
 <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.internet">
 <title>Accessing the Internet</title><indexterm>
 <primary>internet</primary>
 <secondary>configuring</secondary></indexterm>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   If you have chosen not to configure Internet access during the
   installation, you can perform this task at any time using &yast;. How to
   configure your computer to access the Internet depends on your
   environment. If the computer you are installing is part of a network
   which already is connected to the Internet, the only thing to do is to
   link your machine to the network. If you are installing a machine that is
   directly connected to the Internet, the hardware and the access to the
   Internet Service Provider (ISP) needs to be set up.
  </para>

  <para>
   Please refer to the checklists below to make sure you have all the
   necessary data ready before starting to configure the Internet access.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <sect1 id="sec.internet.direct">
  <title>Direct Internet Connection</title><indexterm>

  <primary>internet</primary>

  <secondary>direct connection</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   When your computer is directly connected to the Internet, you first need
   to configure the hardware that is used for this task. This can either be
   an internal device (such as an ISDN card) or an external device (for
   example, a modem). In most cases it is detected automatically.
  </para>

  <para>
   Next, you need to enter the data provided by your ISP (such as login
   credentials, gateway, or name server, for example). You should have
   received a data sheet from your ISP where all the necessary data is
   listed.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you have successfully configured your hardware and ISP data, use the
   &nm; for managing the internet connection. See <xref linkend="cha.nm"/>
   for details.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.internet.direct.dsl">
   <title>Checklist DSL</title><indexterm>
   <primary>internet</primary>
   <secondary>dsl checklist</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>internet</primary>
   <secondary>dsl</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    There are different types of DSL devices available that use different
    point-to-point protocol (PPP) methods:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      a regular ethernet card connected to the external DSL modem uses PPP
      over Ethernet (PPPoE). In Austria the Point-to-Point Tunneling
      Protocol (PPTP) is used. With PPTP the external modem also has a
      static IP address.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      an internal DSL modem uses PPP over ATM (PPPoATM)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      an internal ADSL Fritz Card uses CAPI for ADSL
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    The DSL configuration module already contains the data for major ISPs in
    some countries. If your ISP is not listed, you will need to know how
    name resolving (DNS) and IP allocation is handled (in most cases this
    data is received automatically when connecting). Regardless whether you
    choose an ISP from the list or add a custom provider, you need to enter
    at least your login and password.
   </para>
   <!-- 2014-03-12, ke: this gone with sle 12
   <para>
    For configuration details, refer to
    <xref
     linkend="sec.basicnet.yast.xdsl"/>.
   </para>
   -->
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.internet.direct.isdn"
    >
   <title>Checklist ISDN</title><indexterm>
   <primary>internet</primary>
   <secondary>isdn checklist</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>internet</primary>
   <secondary>isdn</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    In case your internal ISDN card is not detected automatically you will
    need to know the vendor and the name of the device.
   </para>
   <para/>
   <note>
    <title>ISDN Modem or Terminal Adapter</title>
    <para>
     If you are using an external ISDN modem or terminal adapter, refer to
     <xref
      linkend="sec.internet.direct.modem"/> instead.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    In order to configure the ISDN device you will need the following data:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      ISDN Protocol (depends on your country)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Area code and phone number.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Interface type (SyncPPP or RawIP). If unsure, select SyncPPP, because
      RawIP is only used in connection with certain telephone systems.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Local and remote IP addresses for the dial-in server and the gateway,
      in the case that you were given a static IP address from your
      provider.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The ISDN configuration module already contains the data for major ISPs
      in some countries. If your ISP is not listed, you will need to know
      how name resolving (DNS) and IP allocation is handled (in most cases
      this data is received automatically when connecting). Regardless
      whether you chose an ISP from the list or added a custom provider, you
      need to enter at least your login and password.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <!-- 2014-03-12, ke: this gone with sle 12
   <para>
    For configuration details, refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.basicnet.yast.isdn"
    />.
   </para>
   -->
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.internet.direct.modem">
   <title>Checklist Modem</title><indexterm>
   <primary>internet</primary>
   <secondary>modem checklist</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>internet</primary>
   <secondary>modem</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    If your modem is not detected automatically, you will need to know
    whether it is connected to a serial port or to a USB port. Please note
    that not all USB modems and internal modems are supported by
    &productnamereg;.
   </para>
   <para>
    The modem configuration module already contains the data for major ISPs
    in some countries. If your ISP is not listed, you will need to know its
    dial-in number and how name resolving (DNS) and IP allocation is handled
    (in most cases this data is received automatically when connecting).
    Regardless whether you chose an ISP from the list or added a custom
    provider, you need to enter at least your login and password.
   </para>
   <!-- 2014-03-12, ke: this gone with sle 12
   <para>
    For configuration details, refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.basicnet.yast.modem"/>.
   </para>
   -->
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.internet.direct.cablemodem">
   <title>Checklist Cable Modem</title><indexterm>
   <primary>internet</primary>
   <secondary>cable modem checklist</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>internet</primary>
   <secondary>cable modem</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Accessing the Internet through the TV cable requires a cable modem. Such
    a modem is connected to the computer via ethernet cable. Therefore it is
    only necessary to configure your network card accordingly.
   <!-- 2014-03-12, ke: this gone with sle 12
    For details,
    refer to <xref linkend="sec.basicnet.yast.cablemodem"/>.
   -->
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.internet.network">
  <title>Internet Connection Via Network</title><indexterm>

  <primary>internet</primary>

  <secondary>network connection</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   If your machine is part of a network which is already connected to the
   Internet, it is very easy to gain Internet access (just configure your
   network card and connect your machine to the existing network and you are
   done). This not only applies to large company networks, but to small home
   networks as well. Even if the machine you are installing is only
   connected to a router (e.g. a DSL router) it is already part of a
   network. It is irrelevant whether you are using a wireless network
   adapter or a wired one.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>Routing and Name Services</title>
   <para>
    In the following it is assumed that the network is connected to the
    Internet and provides routing and name services. In case these services
    are provided by a router, make sure the router is configured correctly
    before setting up the client.
   </para>
  </note>

  <sect2>
   <title>Checklist Network</title><indexterm>
   <primary>internet</primary>
   <secondary>network checklist</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    If your network provides DHCP (Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol)
    check the appropriate check box when setting up the network card and you
    are done (all parameters needed will be provided by the DHCP server).
   </para>
   <para>
    If DHCP is not available, ask your network administrator for the
    following details:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Hostname
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Name server
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Gateway
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    For configuration details for wired network cards, refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.basicnet.yast.netcard"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
