<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!--taroth 090827: still watching out for GUI changes that
 are planned but not done so far according to http://techbase.kde.org/Schedules/KDE4/4.3_Feature_Plan#kdeutils-->
<chapter id="cha.kde.kwallet">
 <title>Managing Passwords with KWallet Manager</title><indexterm>
 <primary>KDE</primary>
 <secondary>KWallet</secondary></indexterm>
 <para>
  Remembering all the passwords for protected resources to which you need to
  log in can be problematic. KWallet remembers them for you. KWallet is a
  password management tool that can collect all passwords and stores them in
  an encrypted file. With a single master password, open your wallet to
  view, search, delete, or create entries.
 </para>
 <important>
  <title>Protect Your KWallet Password</title>
  <para>
   If you forget your KWallet password, it cannot be recovered. Furthermore,
   anyone who knows your password can obtain all information contained in
   the wallet.
  </para>
 </important>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.kwallet.start">
  <title>Starting KWallet</title>

  <para>
   When you enter a password in a KDE application for the first time (in
   KMail or Konqueror, for example), you are asked if you want to store the
   password in an encrypted wallet. If you click <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>, the
   KWallet wizard starts by default. KWallet is a password management tool
   that can collect all passwords and store them in an encrypted file.
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kwallet_welcome.png" width="50%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kwallet_welcome.png" width="65%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para>
   To activate KWallet, select <guimenu>Basic Setup</guimenu> and click
   <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. Select <guimenu>Yes, I wish to use the KDE
   wallet to store my personal information</guimenu> and enter a password.
   This is your master password to open KWallet. It cannot be recovered if
   you forget it. Click <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> to close the wizard. After
   this initial configuration, you can open your wallet at any time to view,
   search, delete, or create entries. Normally you do not need to insert an
   entry manually. KDE recognizes if a resource requires authentication and
   KWallet starts automatically, prompting you for the KWallet password. Of
   course, you can also use KWallet to store additional passwords by adding
   entries, as described in <xref linkend="pro.kde.kwallet.entries"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
<!--   You can alter the settings at any time by right-clicking the KWallet
   icon in the panel and selecting <guimenu>Configure Wallet</guimenu>. A
   dialog box opens where you can select several options.-->
   By default, all passwords are stored in one wallet,
   <guimenu>kdewallet</guimenu>, but you can also add new wallets. Once
   configured, KWallet appears in the panel. You can also start KWallet
   manually by pressing <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
   <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and entering
   <command>kwalletmanager</command>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.kwallet.manage">
  <title>Managing Your Passwords</title>

  <para>
   To store data in your wallet or view its contents, click the KWallet icon
   in the panel. A dialog box opens, showing the wallets that are accessible
   on your system. Click the wallet to open. A window prompts for your
   password.
  </para>

  <para>
   After a successful login, the KWallet Manager window opens. In the tree
   view on the left, navigate to the entry for which you want to view or
   change the password. For safety reasons, the password value is hidden by
   default when you click the entry. For passwords, click <guimenu>Show
   Contents</guimenu>. For maps, containing key and value pairs (like a WLAN
   ESSID and your password), activate <guimenu>Show Values</guimenu> to view
   the contents.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.kwalletmanager">
   <title>The KWallet Manager Window</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kde-kwallet-manager.png" width="75%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kde-kwallet-manager.png" width="65%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <procedure id="pro.kde.kwallet.entries">
   <title>Adding New Entries to Your Wallet</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     To manually add new passwords (or maps) to KWallet, select the
     subfolder to which to add an entry in the tree folder at the left.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To add a new password, right-click a <guimenu>Passwords</guimenu> entry
     and select <guimenu>New</guimenu> from the context menu.
    </para>
    <para>
     To add a new key pair (map), right-click a <guimenu>Map</guimenu> entry
     and select <guimenu>New</guimenu> from the context menu.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Specify a name for the new entry then click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. Your
     new entry is sorted under your folder entry.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the new entry to display it on the right side (the folder is
     initially empty).
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Show Contents</guimenu> or <guimenu>Show
     Values</guimenu> to open an input field where you can enter your new
     password or values.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To add a key pair, right-click the empty input field and select
     <guimenu>New Entry</guimenu> Type in your password (or you key and
     respective value for that key) and click <guimenu>Save</guimenu>.
     KWallet saves your entry to the subfolder selected.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure>
   <title>Changing the Password for a Wallet</title>
   <para>
    If needed, you can change your password for a wallet at any time.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open KWallet Manager and right-click the wallet for which to change the
     password.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Change Password</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter your new password twice.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.kwallet.configure">
  <title>Adjusting KWallet Settings</title><indexterm>

  <primary>KDE</primary>

  <secondary>configuring</secondary>

  <tertiary>settings, KWallet</tertiary></indexterm>

  <procedure>
   <para>
    By default, you define the settings for KWallet password manager with
    the help of a wizard when you use KWallet for the first time. You can
    adjust the initial settings at any time to increase security.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     If KWallet is already started, click the KWallet symbol in the panel
     and select <guimenu>Configure Wallet</guimenu>. Otherwise, in the main
     menu, select <guimenu>Configure Desktop</guimenu> and on the
     <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> tab, click <guimenu>KDE Wallet</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If KDE wallet subsystem is not yet enabled, activate the relevant check
     box at the top.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     By default, a wallet is closed when the last application stops using
     it. To increase security, you can set a more restrictive policy: to
     close a wallet automatically after a period of inactivity or after
     start-up of the screen saver, activate the relevant check boxes.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_kcontrol_kwallet.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_kcontrol_kwallet.png" width="55%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     By default, KWallet stores all passwords in one wallet named
     <literal>kdewallet</literal>. To store local and network-related
     passwords in different wallets, activate <guimenu>Different wallet for
     local passwords</guimenu>. Click <guimenu>New</guimenu> to create an
     additional wallet, if needed.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To remove the KWallet icon from the panel, deactivate <guimenu>Show
     manager in system tray</guimenu>. You can then only access KWallet from
     the main menu.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.kwallet.transfer">
  <title>Copying Your Wallet to Another Computer</title>

  <para>
   For the most part, KWallet resides silently in the panel and is
   automatically activated if needed. However, you can copy your wallet
   files to another computer (for example, your laptop). To simplify this
   task, wallets can be dragged from the manager window to a file browser
   window. This let you easily package a new wallet for transfer to another
   environment. For example, a new wallet could be created and copied onto a
   removable flash memory device. Important passwords could be transferred
   there, so you have them available in other locations.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
