<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!--taroth 2013-02-19: KGpg version and KDE version are still the same as listed
 below, therefore should still be valid for SLE 11 SP3-->
<!--taroth 081211: no idea if the certificate store (fate #302530) can also
 be accessed by KDE apps, please investigate for next revision-->
<chapter id="cha.crypto">
 <title>KGpg: Signing and Encrypting Data</title><indexterm class="startofrange" id="idx.encryption">
 <primary>encryption</primary></indexterm><indexterm class="startofrange" id="idx.kgpg">
 <primary>KGpg</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>KDE</primary>
 <secondary>KGpg</secondary></indexterm>
 <para>
  You can sign or encrypt data with KGpg, a graphical user interface for
  &gpg;. This program helps you to generate and manage all needed keys. Use
  its editor function for the quick creation and encryption of files or use
  the applet in your panel to encrypt or decrypt by dragging and dropping.
  Other programs, such as your mail program (Kontact or Evolution), access
  the key data to process signed or encrypted contents. In the following
  sections, learn how to execute the following steps necessary for signing
  and encrypting data with KGpg:
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <xref linkend="sec.crypto.kgpg.keygen" xrefstyle="select:title"/>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <xref linkend="sec.crypto.kgpg.mng.export" xrefstyle="select:title"/>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <xref linkend="sec.crypto.kgpg.mng.import" xrefstyle="select:title"/>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <xref linkend="sec.crypto.kgpg.applet" xrefstyle="select:title"/>
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <sect1 id="sec.crypto.kgpg.why">
  <title>Why Signing and Encrypting?</title>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Signing</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Signing means attaching electronic signatures to mails (or even
      software) to prove its origin. To avoid someone writing mails using
      your name and to protect both you and the recipients, you should sign
      your mails. Signatures help you to easily check the sender of the
      mails you receive and to distinguish authentic from malicious mails.
     </para>
     <para>
      Software developers sign their software so you are able to check its
      integrity. Even if you have the software from an unofficial server,
      you can verify the package with the signature.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Encrypting</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      You might have sensitive information you want to protect from other
      parties. Encrypting helps you to transform data and make it unreadable
      for others. This is especially important for companies who must
      protect internal information as well as the employees' privacy.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.crypto.kgpg.keygen">
  <title>Generating a New Key Pair</title><indexterm>

  <primary>KGpg</primary>

  <secondary>creating keys</secondary></indexterm>

<!--taroth 2011-08-05: documented is KGpg 2.2.2, KDE 4.3.5-->

  <para>
   To be able to exchange encrypted messages with other users, first
   generate your own key pair. One part of it&mdash;the <emphasis>public
   key</emphasis>&mdash;is distributed to your communication partners, who
   can use it to encrypt the files or e-mail messages they send. The other
   part of the key pair&mdash;the <emphasis>private key</emphasis>&mdash;is
   used to decrypt the encrypted contents.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Private Key versus Public Key</title>
   <para>
    Only you should have access to the private key. Do not grant other users
    access to this data.
   </para>
   <para>
    Your private key is protected with a passphrase. Choose the passphrase
    carefully: do not use words from a dictionary, and mix alphabetic with
    non-alphabetic characters.
   </para>
  </important>

  <para>
   To create a new pair, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     <indexterm>
     <primary>KGpg</primary>
     <secondary>starting</secondary>
     </indexterm> Start KGpg from the main menu or press <keycombo>
     <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter
     <command>kgpg</command>. When you start the program for the first time,
     a wizard appears, guiding you through the configuration. Follow the
     instructions up to the point where you are prompted to create a key.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice><guimenu>Keys</guimenu> <guimenu>Generate Key
     Pair</guimenu> </menuchoice>, if you want to create a new key pair.
    </para>
    <figure id="fig.kgpg_keygen">
     <title>KGpg: Creating a Key</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata width="40%" fileref="kgpg_keygen.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata width="35%" fileref="kgpg_keygen.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter a name, an e-mail address, and optionally, a comment. If you do
     not like the default settings provided, also set the expiration time
     for the key, the key size, and the encryption algorithm used.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To generate a standard key, confirm your settings with
     <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. After clicking <guimenu>OK</guimenu>, a dialog
     prompts you to enter a passphrase twice. The passphrase protects your
     private key. The relative strength of your chosen password is measured
     and displayed by the <guimenu>Password strength meter</guimenu>. The
     key pair will be generated. This can take some time.
    </para>
    <note>
     <title>Expert Mode</title>
     <para>
      If you are an experienced user, use the <guimenu>Expert Mode</guimenu>
      to define additional options. This takes you to a terminal window
      where you can set the type of key to be generated, the key size (in
      bits) and the date of expiration. After entering your name and e-mail
      address, you are prompted for a passphrase to protect your private
      key.
     </para>
    </note>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After the key generation is finished, a summary will be displayed. Save
     and print the revocation certificate and keep it in a save place. You
     will need the certificate to revoke your passphrase if you forgot it.
     After you have confirmed with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>, KGpg displays its
     main window and you are finished.
    </para>
    <figure id="fig.kgpg_manager">
     <title>KGpg Main Window: Key Management</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata width="90%" fileref="kgpg_manager.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata width="70%" fileref="kgpg_manager.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   The main window shows the keys that belong to your key ring: your own key
   and the keys from other persons that you have already imported. As &gpg;
   uses a more sophisticated implementation of key pairs, for each user
   name, several sub keys are displayed but these can be neglected for the
   purpose of this chapter. Apart from some other details (like expiration
   date or creation date of the key and the ID), the main windows also shows
   the level of trust for each key, indicated by colors. White means that
   the trust level is unknown, blue indicates a high level of trust. For
   more information, see <xref linkend="sec.crypto.kgpg.mng.trust"/>.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>KGpg Icon and Main Window</title>
   <para>
    When you start KGpg in later sessions, only a small icon with a padlock
    appears in the system tray. Click that icon to display the main KGpg
    window on your desktop.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
<?dbfo-need height="20em"?>
 <sect1 id="sec.crypto.kgpg.mng.export">
  <title>Exporting the Public Key</title><indexterm>

  <primary>KGpg</primary>

  <secondary>exporting public keys</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   After generating your key pair, make the public key available to other
   users. This enables them to use it to encrypt or sign the messages or
   files they send you. For example, if you want to encrypt a message for
   user &exampleuser;, you encrypt it using &exampleuser;' public key. To
   decrypt the message, &exampleuser; uses his private key. If &exampleuser;
   wants to send you a message, he encrypts it using your public key and you
   decrypt the message with your private key.
  </para>

  <para>
   To make the public key available for others, select <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Keys</guimenu> <guimenu>Export Public Keys</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>. The dialog that opens offers four options:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Email</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Your public key is sent to a recipient of your choice by e-mail. If
      you activate this option and confirm with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>, the
      dialog for creating a new e-mail message with your default mail
      program appears. Enter the recipient and click
      <guimenu>Send</guimenu>. The recipient receives your key and can then
      send you encrypted contents.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Clipboard</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      You can place your public key here before continuing to process it.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Default Key Server</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To make your public key available to a wide audience, export it to one
      of the key servers on the Internet. For more information, refer to
      <xref linkend="sec.crypto.kgpg.serv"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>File</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you prefer to distribute your key as a file on a data medium
      instead of sending it by e-mail, click this option, confirm or change
      the file path and name, and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.crypto.kgpg.mng.import">
  <title>Importing Public Keys from Others</title><indexterm>

  <primary>KGpg</primary>

  <secondary>importing keys</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   If you receive a key in a file (for example, as an e-mail attachment),
   integrate it in your key ring with <guimenu>Import Key</guimenu> and use
   it for encrypted communication with the sender. You can also import keys
   from a public server if the person you want to communicate with has
   stored his public key there. For more information, see
   <xref linkend="sec.crypto.kgpg.serv"
   />. The procedure is similar to
   the procedure for exporting keys already described.
  </para>

  <sect2
   id="sec.crypto.kgpg.mng.sign">
   <title>Signing Keys</title><indexterm>
   <primary>KGpg</primary>
   <secondary>signing keys</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Keys can be signed like every other file to guarantee their authenticity
    and integrity. If you are absolutely sure an imported key belongs to the
    individual specified as the owner, express your trust in the
    authenticity of the key with your signature.
   </para>
   <important>
    <title>Establishing a Web of Trust</title>
    <para>
     Encrypted communication is only secure to the extent that you can
     positively associate public keys in circulation with the specified
     user. By cross-checking and signing these keys, you contribute to the
     establishment of a Web of Trust. For these reasons, make really sure
     you only sign keys you have personally checked.
    </para>
   </important>
   <para>
    Before you can use your key, you need to sign it yourself.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Signing A Key</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the <guimenu>Key Management</guimenu> window, select the key to
      sign in the key list.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Keys</guimenu> <guimenu>Sign
      Keys</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the following dialog, select the private key to use for the
      signature. An alert reminds you to check the authenticity of this key
      before signing it. In the drop down list, select how you carefully you
      have checked that the key belongs to the person with whom you want to
      communicate.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Continue</guimenu> and enter your passphrase in the
      next step. With entering the passphrase, you sign the key with your
      own private key. The signed key now appears green in the trust column.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    Other users can now check the signature by means of your public key.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.crypto.kgpg.mng.trust">
   <title>Trusting Keys</title><indexterm>
   <primary>KGpg</primary>
   <secondary>trusting keys</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Normally, you are asked by the corresponding program whether you trust
    the key, or rather, whether you assume it is really used by its
    authorized owner. This happens each time a message needs to be decrypted
    or a signature has to be checked. To avoid this, edit the trust level of
    the newly imported key. To trust a key and set a certain trust level, do
    the following:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Right-click the key and select <guimenu>Key Properties</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the <guimenu>Owner Trust</guimenu> drop-down list, adjust the trust
      level. This value indicates how much you trust the owner of this key
      to correctly verify the identity of the keys he signs.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Close the property dialog. If you have set the trust level to
      <guimenu>Fully</guimenu> or <guimenu>Ultimately</guimenu>, the key now
      appears blue in the trust column.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    The lower the trust level is, the less you trust the signer of the key
    to have checked the true identity of the keys signed. You may be
    entirely sure about the signer's identity, but this user may not check
    other people's identities properly before signing their keys. Notice
    that the trust level does not trigger any automatic actions by KGpg.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.crypto.kgpg.serv">
  <title>The Key Server Dialog</title><indexterm>

  <primary>KGpg</primary>

  <secondary>key servers</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Several Internet-based key servers offer the public keys of many users.
   To engage in encrypted communication with a large number of users, use
   these servers to distribute your public key. For this purpose, export
   your public key to one of these servers. Similarly, KGpg enables you to
   search one of these servers for the keys of certain people and import
   their public keys from the server. Open the key server dialog with
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Key Server Dialog</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>.
  </para>

<?dbfo-need height="20em"?>

  <sect2 id="sec.crypto.kgpg.serv.import">
   <title>Importing a Key from a Key Server</title><indexterm>
   <primary>KGpg</primary>
   <secondary>key servers</secondary>
   <tertiary>importing keys</tertiary></indexterm>
   <para>
    By means of the <guimenu>Import</guimenu> tab in the key server dialog,
    import public keys from one of the Internet-based key servers. Select
    one of the pre-configured key servers and enter a search string (e-mail
    address of the communication partner) or the ID of the key to find. When
    you click <guimenu>Search</guimenu>, your system connects to the
    Internet and searches the specified key server for a key that matches
    your specifications.
   </para>
   <figure
    id="fig.kgpg_servimp">
    <title>Search Screen for Importing a Key</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata width="60%" fileref="kgpg_servimp.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata width="40%" fileref="kgpg_servimp.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    If your search on the key server is successful, a list of all retrieved
    server entries is displayed in a new window. Select the key to include
    in your key ring and click <guimenu>Import</guimenu>. Confirm the
    following message with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>, then exit the key server
    dialog with <guimenu>Close</guimenu>. The imported key then appears in
    the main overview of the key manager and is ready for use.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2
   id="sec.crypto.kgpg.serv.export">
   <title>Exporting Your Keys to a Key Server</title><indexterm>
   <primary>KGpg</primary>
   <secondary>key servers</secondary>
   <tertiary>exporting keys</tertiary></indexterm>
   <para>
    To export your key to one of the freely accessible key servers on the
    Internet, select the <guimenu>Export</guimenu> tab in the key server
    dialog. Designate the target server and the key to export by means of
    two drop-down menus. Then start the export with
    <guimenu>Export</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <figure id="fig.kgpg_servexp">
    <title>Exporting a Key to a Key Server</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata width="60%" fileref="kgpg_servexp.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata width="40%" fileref="kgpg_servexp.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.crypto.kgpg.applet">
  <title>Encrypting Your Data</title><indexterm>

  <primary>KGpg</primary>

  <secondary>text encryption</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>KGpg</primary>

  <secondary>file encryption</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>files</primary>

  <secondary>encrypting</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   After you have generated your key pair, exported your public key and
   imported public keys from others, you can also send or receive encrypted
   mails. Refer to <xref
    linkend="sec.kontact.mail.crypto"/> to learn
   how to make use of those options in KMail.
  </para>

  <para>
   KGpg also offers the possibility to encrypt text.
<!-- or clipboard contents.
   Right-click the padlock icon and find the options <guimenu>Encrypt
   clipboard</guimenu> and <guimenu>Decrypt clipboard</guimenu> as well as
   the option for opening the integrated editor.-->
   To open the integrated editor choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Open Editor</guimenu></menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <remark>outdated section</remark>

<!--
  <sect2
   id="sec.crypto.kgpg.klipper">
   <title>Encrypting and Decrypting the Clipboard</title>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>KGpg</primary>
    <secondary>clipboard encryption</secondary>
   </indexterm>
   <para>
    Files copied to the clipboard can easily be encrypted with a few clicks.
    Right-click the KGpg padlock icon and select <guimenu>Encrypt
    Clipboard</guimenu>. Select the key to use. A status message about the
    encryption procedure is displayed on the desktop. The encrypted contents
    can now be processed from the clipboard as needed. The decryption of
    clipboard contents is just as easy. Simply open the menu on the panel,
    select <guimenu>Decrypt Clipboard</guimenu>, and enter the passphrase
    associated with your private key. The decrypted version is now available
    for processing in the clipboard and in the KGpg editor. Note that you
    can only encrypt or decrypt the current clipboard object, not all
    entries that clipboard tools like Klipper store for you.
   </para>
  </sect2>
-->

  <sect2 id="sec.crypto.kgpg.dnd">
   <title>Encrypting and Decrypting from a File Manager</title>
   <para>
    KGpg is also integrated into file managers like Dolphin or Konqueror.
    Generally, PGP-encrypted files are designated with the suffix
    <filename>asc</filename>. There are several options how to encrypt or
    decrypt files inside a file manager:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Encrypt a File</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To encrypt a file inside a file manager, right-click the file and
       select <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenu>Encrypt
       File</guimenu></menuchoice>. Choose one of the trusted keys in the
       dialog. After clicking <guimenu>OK</guimenu> in the dialog, a new
       file with the <filename>asc</filename> suffix will be created in the
       same directory.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Decrypt a File on the fly</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To decrypt an encrypted file instantly, right-click the file and
       select <menuchoice><guimenu>Open with KGpg</guimenu></menuchoice>. If
       the original filename already exists, a dialog opens that asks how to
       name the file or if it should be overwritten. KGpg prompts for the
       password of your private key and saves the decrypted file in the same
       directory.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Decrypt with the editor</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To decrypt an encrypted file with the editor, right-click the file in
       the file manager and select <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu>
       <guimenu>View file decrypted</guimenu></menuchoice>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
<!--taroth 081211: unfortunately, the drag and drop
     functionality does not work currently, see bnc#458038-->
<!--To encrypt or decrypt files, click the icons on the desktop or in the
    file manager and select , drag them to the padlock in the panel, and drop them
    there. If the file is not encrypted, KGpg asks for the key to use. As
    soon as you select a key, the file is encrypted without any further
    messages.-->
<!--In the file manager, encrypted files are designated with
     the suffix <filename>.asc</filename>. These files can
    be decrypted by clicking the file icon, dragging it to the KGpg symbol
    in the panel, and dropping it there. If the original filename already
    exists, a dialog opens that asks how to name the file or if it should be
    overwritten.-->
<!-- 
    Then select whether the file should be decrypted and saved or displayed in
    the editor. If you select <guimenu>Decrypt and Save</guimenu>,
    KGpg prompts for the password of your private
    key and saves the decrypted file in the same directory as the encrypted
    file. 
    2005-12-30 - bg: there is no such menu anymore.
   -->
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.crypto.kgpg.edit">
   <title>The KGpg Editor</title><indexterm>
   <primary>KGpg</primary>
   <secondary>editor</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Instead of creating contents for encryption in an external editor then
    encrypting the file with one of the methods described above, you can use
    the integrated editor of KGpg. To open the editor, select <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenu>Open Editor</guimenu></menuchoice>. In
    the editor, enter the desired text (or copy it into the editor from the
    clipboard or any file), and click <guimenu>Encrypt</guimenu>. Then
    select the key to use and complete the encryption procedure. To decrypt
    files, use <guimenu>Decrypt</guimenu> and enter the password associated
    with the key.
   </para>
   <para>
    Generating and checking signatures is just as easy as encrypting
    directly from the editor. Go to <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Signature</guimenu> <guimenu>Generate Signature</guimenu>
    </menuchoice> and select the file to sign from the file dialog. Select
    the private key to use and enter the associated password. KGpg informs
    you of the successful generation of the signature. Files can also be
    signed from the editor by simply clicking
    <guimenu>Sign/Verify</guimenu>. To check a signed file, go to
    <menuchoice> <guimenu>Signature</guimenu> <guimenu>Verify
    Signature</guimenu></menuchoice> and select the file to check in the
    following dialog. After you confirm the selection, KGpg checks the
    signature and reports the result of the operation. Another possibility
    is to load the signed file into the editor and click
    <guimenu>Sign/Verify</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
<?dbfo-need height="15em"?>
 <sect1 id="sec.crypto.basics">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   For comprehensive background information about the encryption method,
   refer to the &gpg; project pages at
   <ulink url="http://www.gnupg.org/documentation/index.en.html"/>.
   <indexterm
    class="endofrange" startref="idx.encryption"/>
   <indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.kgpg"/>
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
