<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
  ]>
<!--taroth 2011-08-05: KDE 4.3.5 described here-->
<chapter id="cha.kde.start">
 <title>Getting Started with the KDE Desktop</title>
 <para>
  This chapter assists you in becoming familiar with the KDE desktop of your
  &productnamereg;. <phrase os="osuse">If you have not yet installed your
  system, refer to <xref linkend="cha.inst"
   />.</phrase>
  <phrase os="sled">If you have not yet installed your system, refer to
  <xref linkend="cha.inst"/> or to
  <xref linkend="art.sled.installquick"/>.</phrase>
 </para>
 <para>
  KDE stands for <emphasis>K Desktop Environment</emphasis> and is an
  easy-to-use graphical user interface that communicates with the underlying
  Linux system to access and manage files, folders, and programs. It has
  many applications designed to help you in your daily work. KDE also offers
  many choices to modify your desktop according to your needs and wishes.
  Read more about configuring your desktop in
  <xref linkend="cha.kde.cust"/>.
 </para>
 <para>
  The following description is based on the default configuration of the KDE
  4 desktop shipped with your product. If you or your system administrator
  has modified the defaults, some aspects may be different, such as
  appearance or keyboard shortcuts.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.start.login">
  <title>Logging In</title><indexterm>

  <primary>logging in</primary></indexterm>

  <para>
   If more than one user account is configured on your computer, usually all
   users must authenticate&mdash;unless <emphasis>Auto Login</emphasis> is
   configured for a certain user. Auto login logs the user in to the desktop
   environment automatically on boot. This feature can be enabled or
   disabled during installation or at any time using the &yast; user
   management module. For more information, see
   <xref linkend="cha.y2.userman"/>. If your computer is run in a network
   environment and you are not the only person using the machine, you are
   usually prompted to enter your username and password when you start your
   system. If you did not set up your system and your user account yourself,
   check with your system administrator for your username and password.
  </para>

  <para>
   The appearance of the login screen depends on the product you use and on
   the desktop environment installed on your system. The login process is
   managed by an application. For KDE, it is KDM. If the GNOME desktop is
   additionally installed on your system, it may be GDM.
  </para>

  <para>
   <indexterm>
   <primary>login</primary>
   <secondary>sessions</secondary>
   </indexterm> To start a normal login, enter your username and password.
   If desktops other than KDE are installed, you can select which desktop
   environment to start by clicking the <guimenu>Session Typing</guimenu>
   menu item at the bottom of the login screen. Press
   <keycap
    function="enter"/> to proceed. For information on how to log
   out or switch to another desktop, see
   <xref linkend="sec.kde.start.leave"/> and
   <xref linkend="sec.kde.start.switchdesk"/>.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>A KDM Login Screen</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kdm_screenshot.png" width="70%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kdm_screenshot.png" width="70%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   If your system administrator has created an encrypted home directory for
   you (which is useful as a protection against theft or unauthorized
   removal of the hard disk), your home directory is mounted on login. After
   login, you can directly access the data as usual&mdash;without entering
   another password.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>Connecting to an Active Directory Server</title>
   <para>
    To access shared network resources, you can also authenticate a KDE
    client machine against an Active Directory server. For further details,
    refer to <xref linkend="cha.network"/>. If your machine is configured
    for this kind of authentication, the login screen also provides an
    additional field. In this case, proceed as follows during login:
   </para>
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Select the domain from the list.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Enter your Windows* username.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Enter your Windows password and press
      <keycap function="enter">Enter</keycap>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
  </note>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.start.comp">
  <title>Exploring the Desktop Components</title>

  <para>
   After logging in to KDE for the first time, you see the KDE desktop. It
   consists of the following basic elements:
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Example KDE Desktop</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kde_desktop_menus.png" width="65%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kde_desktop_menus.png" width="60%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Desktop Icons and Desktop Folder:</title>
   <para>
    Desktop icons represent files, directories, applications, functions, and
    removable media, like CDs or DVDs. Click an icon on the desktop to
    access its associated program or application. By default, your desktop
    icons are shown in a <guimenu>Desktop Folder</guimenu>, a transparent
    region of the screen showing the contents of the
    <filename>Desktop</filename> folder of your home directory. If you drag
    an icon from the <guimenu>Desktop Folder</guimenu> and drop it on
    another part of the desktop, it appears as widget that you can tilt,
    enlarge or minimize. Widgets are small applications that can be
    integrated into your desktop. Right-click to open a context menu to
    access the icon properties, or to remove the icon. For more information,
    see <xref linkend="proc.kde.cust.conf.widgets"/>.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Desktop Context Menu:</title>
   <para>
    Right-click an empty area on the desktop to access the context menu for
    configuring the appearance of the desktop, adding panels or widgets to
    the desktop, locking the widgets in their current position, or for
    leaving the current session or locking the screen.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Desktop Toolbox:</title>
   <para>
    (Only visible if the desktop is not set to <guimenu>Plain Desktop
    View</guimenu>. For more information, see
    <xref
     linkend="pro.kde.cust.desk.activities"/>.) Move your mouse
    pointer to the icon in the upper right corner of the desktop to access a
    menu that lets you configure desktop widgets.
<!--taroth 2013-02-07: 
     no longer available from cashew icon: Use <guimenu>Show
    Dashboard</guimenu> to switch to a desktop view hiding all currently
    opened windows and panels. To show your windows and panels again, select
    <guimenu>Hide Dashboard</guimenu>.-->
    For the <guimenu>Add Widgets</guimenu> and <guimenu>Lock
    Widgets</guimenu> function, refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.kde.start.lock"/> for more information.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>KDE Panel:</title>
   <para>
    <indexterm>
    <primary>KDE</primary>
    <secondary>panels</secondary>
    </indexterm> The panel (in KDE also called <quote>Kicker</quote>) is a
    bar, typically located at the top or the bottom of the screen. By
    default, the panel of your KDE desktop consists of the following areas
    (from left to right): quick launcher with the main menu icon on the left
    and further program icons, pager (desktop previewer), taskbar, and
    system tray. You can add or remove icons in the panel and customize the
    appearance of the panel as well as its location on the desktop. If you
    hold your mouse pointer over an icon in the panel, a short description
    is displayed.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Quick Launcher:</title>
   <para>
    The quick launcher contains the main menu button and some larger icons
    that are shortcuts to frequently used programs, folders, and functions.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Main Menu Button:</title>
   <para>
    Use the icon at the far left of the panel to open a menu holding a
    search function at the top and several tabs at the bottom. The
    <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> tab shows all installed programs in a
    function-oriented menu structure which makes it easy to find the right
    application for your purpose, even if you do not know the application
    names yet. For more information, refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.kde.use.startprogr.menu"/> .
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Pager (Desktop Previewer):</title>
   <para>
    Between the quick launcher and the taskbar, find a miniature preview
    that shows your virtual desktops (if not configured otherwise, they are
    numbered). &productname; allows you to organize your programs and tasks
    on several desktops, which minimizes the number of windows to arrange on
    the screen. To switch between the virtual desktops, click one of the
    symbols in the pager. For more information, refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.kde.use.virtdesk"/>.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>Taskbar:</title>
   <para>
    By default, all started applications and open windows are displayed in
    the taskbar, which allows you to access any application regardless of
    the currently active desktop. Click to open the application. Right-click
    to see options for moving, restoring, or minimizing the window.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara>
   <title>System Tray:</title>
   <para>
    This rightmost part of the panel usually holds some smaller icons,
    including the system clock displaying time and date, the volume control,
    and several other helper applications.
   </para>
  </formalpara>

  <para>
   The integration and handling of desktop objects has changed from KDE 3.x
   to KDE 4, which now uses a new desktop and panel interface tool called
   Plasma. Plasma supports desktop widgets (also called
   <quote>plasmoids</quote>), similar to Apple’s dashboard widgets. Learn
   more about the key desktop objects in the following sections.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.kde.start.lock">
   <title>Locking and Unlocking Desktop Objects</title>
   <para>
    With KDE 4, desktop elements can be locked in their current position to
    prevent them from being moved around on the desktop. As long as the
    desktop elements are locked, you cannot add, move, or remove any objects
    to and from your desktop.
   </para>
   <para>
    To lock or unlock the desktop elements, right-click an empty space on
    the desktop and select <guimenu>Lock Widgets</guimenu> or
    <guimenu>Unlock Widgets</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <figure>
    <title>Unlocking Desktop Objects</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="kde_unlock_widgets.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="kde_unlock_widgets.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    Find how to add, remove and configure widgets and change numerous
    desktop elements in <xref linkend="cha.kde.cust"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kde.start.comp.desk">
   <title>Desktop Icons</title>
   <para>
    By default the <guimenu>Desktop Folder</guimenu>, showing the contents
    of the <filename>~/Desktop</filename> folder, displays the following
    icons:
   </para>
   <figure>
    <title>KDE Desktop Folder</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="kde_desktop_folder.png" width="70%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="kde_desktop_folder.png" width="50%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <remark>taroth 081121: Trash, Network Browsing and Printer icon are no longer to be seen
    here</remark>
   <variablelist>
<!--<varlistentry>
     <term> <indexterm>
      <primary>trash</primary>
     </indexterm>
      <guimenu>Trash</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para> Starts the file manager and shows the contents of your
       trash bin. The trash bin is a directory for files marked for
       deletion. Whenever you select <guimenu>Move to Trash</guimenu>
       for an object in the file manager or on your desktop, the file is
       moved to the trash bin. If you need to retrieve an item from the
       trash bin again, right-click the item and select
       <guimenu>Restore</guimenu>. As files in the trashcan also occupy
       disc space, it is advisable to delete the trash bin contents from
       time to time. To manually do so, right-click the trash bin icon
       and select <guimenu>Empty Trashcan</guimenu>. </para>
      <para> Contains files and folders that have been deleted. </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>-->
    <varlistentry>
     <term><indexterm>
      <primary>system information</primary></indexterm><guimenu>My Computer</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The <guimenu>My Computer</guimenu> icon is very useful for viewing
       the most important information about your hardware, network status,
       disks (hard disks, removable media, and external devices), operating
       system, and some common folders at one glance. For example, find
       processor type and speed listed there, information about your RAM and
       the current swap status, or your graphics card. <guimenu>OS
       Information</guimenu> lists the most important information about your
       operating system, such as the Kernel version included, the current
       user, version number and type of the operating system, as well as the
       KDE version number. &productname; ships with a number of further
       tools (either graphical or command line tools) that you can use to
       get more detailed information about your system. If you need detailed
       hardware information about your system, use the &yast; hardware
       probing, described in <xref
        linkend="sec.y2.hw.probe"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
<!-- <varlistentry>
     <term>
     <guimenu>Network Browsing</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>Displays network services you can access. Some of the
       services might require authentication. To learn more, refer to
       <xref linkend="cha.network"/>.</para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>-->
<!--<varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Printer</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para> Opens KJobViewer that displays print jobs you have sent to
       printers. See <xref linkend="sec.print.kjobviewer"/> for more information. </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>-->
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Firefox</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Opens the Firefox Web browser. For more information, refer to
       <xref
        linkend="cha.firefox"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Office</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Opens &ooo;. For an introduction to the office suite, refer to
       <xref linkend="cha.oo.oview"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry os="osuse">
     <term><guimenu>&opensuse;</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Opens the SUSEgreeter which holds introductory information and links
       to various information sources on &productname;.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry os="osuse">
     <term><guimenu>Online Help</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Starts the default Web browser and takes you to
       <ulink url="http://help.opensuse.org">the help page of the openSUSE
       community</ulink> from where you can access various documentation
       resources, mailing lists, Web forums or chats with members of the
       openSUSE community. Find more information about accessing and using
       help resources (integrated with your system or on the Web) in
       <xref linkend="cha.userhelp"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kde.start.comp.panel">
   <title>Panel Icons</title>
   <para>
    <indexterm>
    <primary>KDE</primary>
    <secondary>panels</secondary>
    </indexterm>The panel can be subdivided into three main areas holding
    icons: the quick launch area at the left, the taskbar in the middle and
    the system tray at the right. The taskbar has dynamic contents, showing
    the currently started applications and windows with their icons, whereas
    quick launcher and system tray are more static.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.kde.start.comp.panel.quicklaunch">
    <title>Quick Launch Area</title>
    <para>
     The quick launch area of your panel as shipped with &productname;,
     includes the following icons by default:
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Panel: Quick Launch Area</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_panel_quicklaunch.png" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_panel_quicklaunch.png" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Main Menu Icon</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Opens the main menu, similar to the Microsoft* Windows start menu.
        For more information, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.kde.use.startprogr.menu"/> .
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Show Dashboard Icon</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Hides all open windows and puts the widgets in front of them. Shows
        the cashew icon in the right upper corner of the desktop from which
        you can access a menu to configure your plasma workspace. For more
        information, refer to
        <xref linkend="pro.kde.cust.desk.activities"
        />.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Firefox Icon</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Starts the Firefox Web browser. For more information, refer to
        <xref linkend="cha.firefox"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Dolphin Icon</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Opens Dolphin, the default file manager. For more information, refer
        to <xref linkend="sec.kde.dolphin"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Device Notifier Icon</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Informs you about recently plugged or inserted devices such as USB
        sticks, external hard disks, cameras, CDs, and DVDs. For more
        information, refer to <xref
         linkend="sec.kde.use.media"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.kde.start.comp.panel.tray">
    <title>System Tray</title>
    <para>
     Apart from the larger icons in the quick launcher, the panel also holds
     a number of smaller icons in the system tray area on the right:
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Panel: System Tray</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_panel_systemtray.png" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_panel_systemtray.png" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Klipper</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        KDE's clipboard tool that <quote>remembers</quote> the last entries
        you have moved to the clipboard. To view the clipboard contents,
        click the Klipper icon or press <keycombo>
        <keycap function="control"/> <keycap function="alt"/>
        <keycap>V</keycap> </keycombo>. The most recent entry is listed on
        top and is marked as active with a black check mark. To insert the
        active clipboard entry again, move the mouse pointer to the target
        application, then middle-click. For more information on using
        Klipper, see <xref linkend="sec.kde.use.klipper"
       />.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Update Applet</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Helps you keep your system up-to-date. When you connect to the
        Internet, the update applet automatically checks whether software
        updates for your system are available. The applet icon changes color
        and appearance depending on the availability of updates for your
        system. For detailed information on how to install software updates
        with the updater applet and how to configure it, refer to
        <xref linkend="cha.onlineupdate.you"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>KMix</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Your desktop's default mixer (KMix) helps you to control sound on
        your desktop after your sound card has been detected and configured
        with &yast;. By default, clicking the KMix icon in the system tray
        shows the master controller with which to increase or decrease the
        overall volume. For more information, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.sound.mixers"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>&nm;</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If you manage your network connection with &nm; and have enabled the
        use of &nm; in &yast;, the &nm; icon also appears in your system
        tray be default. Use it to change and configure network connections.
        For detailed information, refer to <xref linkend="cha.nm"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
<!-- <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Kerry</guimenu>
      <remark>taroth 081119: find out if
      Kerry will stay</remark>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Kerry is a KDE front-end for the Beagle search tool, which indexes
       your personal information space to help you find whatever you need.
       You can use Kerry to find documents, e-mails, Web history, IM/ITC
       conversations, source code, images, music files, applications, and
       much more. For more information, refer to
       <xref
        linkend="cha.kerry"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>-->
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Job &amp; Notifications</guimenu></term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        This icons shows running jobs on your desktop (for example, if you
        are copying files) and notifies you about system events. Jobs are
        grouped to prevent the pop-up of too many dialogs and are
        automatically hidden after a few seconds. Animations signify that
        jobs are still running. Usually, the entries are automatically
        destroyed after some time, but in case you do not use your desktop
        during that time, they are retained, so you can safely stay away
        from your computer for a couple of hours, and when you come back,
        you will still be able to see which jobs have been finished during
        your absence. To configure which information to show or to disable
        auto-hiding, right-click the <guimenu>Job &amp;
        Notifications</guimenu> icon and select <guimenu>System-Tray
        Settings</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Clock</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        For information about the current date and time, click the clock in
        the system tray or move your mouse pointer over the clock. You can
        change the clock settings (such as appearance and additional data to
        be displayed) from the context menu available upon right-click. If
        you need to update the system time, start &yast; and select
        <menuchoice> <guimenu>System</guimenu> <guimenu>Date and
        Time</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.timezone"/> for more information.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Lock Screen</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Locks your screen and starts the screen saver. Access to the session
        can only be regained with a password.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Log Out</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Logs you out and ends your current KDE session. If not configured
        otherwise in the KDE 4 Personal Settings (see
        <xref linkend="pro.kde.cust.system.session"/>, the session manager
        will restore the currently open windows by default next time you log
        in to KDE.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Cashew Icon</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Give access to panel configuration options. For more information,
        see <xref
        linkend="proc.kde.cust.conf.panel"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
     You can change the way your KDE desktop looks and behaves to suit your
     own personal tastes and needs. To learn how to configure individual
     desktop elements or how change the overall appearance and behavior of
     your desktop, refer to <xref linkend="sec.kde.cust.kcontrol"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you would like to start working with your desktop now, continue
     reading at <xref
     linkend="cha.kde.use"/>. Otherwise you can leave
     your system with one of the possibilities described below.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.start.leave">
  <title>Leaving Your System</title>

  <para>
   <indexterm>
   <primary>KDE</primary>
   <secondary>logging out</secondary>
   </indexterm> When you have finished using the computer, there are several
   options for leaving your system. Some of them will leave the system
   running, others will shutdown the computer. If your system provides power
   management, you can also choose to <literal>suspend</literal> your
   computer. In this state, it will consume considerably less power than
   usual and will start much faster than after a complete shutdown and
   reboot. For more information, refer to
   <xref linkend="cha.kde.kpowersave"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can access all the options to leave your system from the main menu.
   Click the main menu icon on the left and switch to the
   <guimenu>Leave</guimenu> tab. Select one of the following options:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Logout</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Ends your current session and leaves your system running. If not
      configured otherwise in the KDE 4 Personal Settings, the session
      manager will restore the currently open windows by default the next
      time you log in to KDE 4. Find more information about the session
      manager and configuration options at
      <xref linkend="pro.kde.cust.system.session"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Lock</guimenu><indexterm>
     <primary>screen</primary>
     <secondary>locking</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
     <primary>KDE</primary>
     <secondary>locking</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Prevents unauthorized access by others by locking your screen and
      starting a screen saver. Access to the session can only be regained
      with a password. To unlock, enter your normal login password. For
      information about configuring your screen saver, see
      <xref linkend="pro.kde.cust.desk.ssaver"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Switch User</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Starts a second session with a graphical user interface on your
      machine. Your current session remains active while you are taken to
      the login screen where you can log in as a different user. You can
      access the first session again by pressing <keycombo>
      <keycap function="control"/> <keycap function="alt"/>
      <keycap>F7</keycap> </keycombo>. To access a new session, press
      <keycap>F8</keycap> instead of <keycap>F7</keycap>. Additional
      sessions can be accessed by pressing <keycombo>
      <keycap function="control"/> <keycap function="alt"/>
      <keycap>F9</keycap> </keycombo> to <keycap>F12</keycap>.
     </para>
     <para>
      If more than one desktop environment is installed on your system, you
      can also choose to switch to another desktop for the new session as
      described in <xref
       linkend="sec.kde.start.switchdesk"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Suspend to Disk</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This menu item is only available if your computer provides power
      management functionality. Pauses your computer without logging you
      out. All your data and the session data is saved to disk before the
      system is laid to rest. It is thus protected against data loss should
      you lose power in the meantime. Waking the system up again is much
      faster than with a fresh boot.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Suspend to RAM</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This menu item is only available if your computer provides power
      management functionality. Pauses your computer without logging you
      out. All your data and the session data is saved to RAM. Bringing the
      system up again is faster than restoring a session from disk.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Shutdown Computer</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Logs you out and turns your computer off.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Restart Computer</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Initiates the shutdown process and reboots your computer. Instead of
      selecting the desired boot option in the boot manager, you can also
      select the desired option directly&mdash;just click one of the options
      below <guimenu>Restart Computer</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   Alternatively, you can also use the desktop context menu or the icons in
   the system tray to leave your system.
  </para>

<!--<para>
   To access most of the options for leaving, you can also use the keyboard
   shortcut defined in the Personal Settings. Usually, this is <keycombo>
   <keycap function="control"/> <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>L</keycap>
   </keycombo>.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>Looking Up KDE Keyboard Shortcuts</title>
   <para>
    If you are interested in other KDE keyboard shortcuts, look them up in
    the KDE 4 Personal Settings, described in
    <xref linkend="cha.kde.cust"/>. For a description of how to change KDE
    keyboard shortcuts, refer to
    <xref linkend="pro.kde.cust.behav.shortcuts"/>.
   </para>
  </tip>-->

  <para>
   If you have already logged out, you can still access shutdown and restart
   option from the login screen by clicking <guimenu>Menu</guimenu> and
   selecting the relevant menu items.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.start.switchdesk">
  <title>Switching Desktops</title><indexterm>

  <primary>desktops</primary>

  <secondary>switching</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   If more than one desktop environment is installed on your system (for
   example, KDE and GNOME, or KDE 3.5.<replaceable>x</replaceable> and KDE
   4), you can choose to switch to another desktop when logging in again (or
   when logging in as a different user). To do so, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure id="pro.kde.start.switchdesk">
   <step>
    <para>
     On the login screen, click <guimenu>Session Type</guimenu> and select
     the desktop environment to start.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter a valid username and password. A new session on the selected
     desktop environment starts.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To switch back again, log out from the current desktop and select a
     different <guimenu>Session Type</guimenu> on the login screen. If you
     do not select a new session type, your next session will be of the same
     type as the session before.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
