<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
  ]>
<sect1 id="sec.kde.dolphin">
 <title>Using Dolphin File Manager</title>

 <para>
  With KDE 4, Dolphin has replaced Konqueror as the default file manager,
  while Konqueror still is still shipped and mainly functions as Web
  browser. For more information about Konqueror as Web browser, see
  <xref linkend="cha.konqueror"/>. To start Dolphin, click the card box icon
  in the panel or press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
  <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter <command>dolphin</command>.
 </para>

 <sect2 id="sec.kde.dolphin.oview">
  <title>Dolphin Main Window</title>
  <para>
   The Dolphin main window consists of the following elements:
  </para>
  <remark>taroth 090818: definitely new screenshot needed as skeleton for home
   directory has obviously changed (more subdirectories)!</remark>
  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="dolphin_main.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="dolphin_main.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <formalpara>
   <title>Menu Bar:</title>
   <para>
    The menu bar holds menu items for actions like copying, moving, and
    deleting files, changing views, starting additional tools, defining your
    settings, and getting help.
   </para>
  </formalpara>
  <formalpara>
   <title>Toolbar:</title>
   <para>
    The toolbar provides quick access to frequently used functions that can
    also be accessed via the menu. If you hover the mouse pointer over an
    icon, a short description is displayed.
   </para>
  </formalpara>
  <formalpara>
   <title>Location Bar:</title>
   <para>
    The location bar displays the path to the current directory. It is
    available in two versions. One shows the path to the current directory
    with icons for every parent folder in a <quote>bread crumb</quote> view.
    Click any icon in the bread crumb view to change to that directory. The
    second version of the location bar shows the path to the current
    directory as a string of text you can edit.
   </para>
  </formalpara>
  <formalpara>
   <title>Panels:</title>
   <para>
    By default, Dolphin shows only the <guimenu>Places</guimenu> panel on
    the left and the <guimenu>Information panel</guimenu> on the right.
    <guimenu>Places</guimenu> allows quick access to some often used places
    like your home directory, the <filename>/root</filename> directory of
    the file system, the trash bin, or removable media. There are several
    other panels you can add to the main window.
   </para>
  </formalpara>
  <formalpara>
   <title>Display Field (Working Space):</title>
   <para>
    The display field shows the contents of the selected directory or file.
    By default, Dolphin displays the contents of your home directory on
    start-up. Clicking a folder or file in Dolphin directly starts an
    action: Dolphin loads the file into an application for further
    processing, or opens the folder.
   </para>
  </formalpara>
  <formalpara>
   <title>Status Bar:</title>
   <para>
    Shows information about the currently selected object.
   </para>
  </formalpara>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.kde.dolphin.files.open">
  <title>Opening Files or Folders in Dolphin</title>
  <para>
   If not configured otherwise in the Personal Settings, clicking an object
   once in Dolphin usually starts an action directly: a program starts, a
   preview of the file is displayed, or the folder is opened. For each file
   type, you can define a default application with which to open the file in
   KDE, for example, when it is clicked in Dolphin. To view or change the
   default application assigned to the file type, proceed as described in
   <xref
    linkend="pro.kde.cust.system.fileass"/>. If KDE cannot find a
   default application for the file type (or if you want to open a file with
   a different application than usual), right-click the file in Dolphin and
   select <guimenu>Open With</guimenu>. If several applications are assigned
   to that file type, select the respective entry Otherwise click
   <guimenu>Other</guimenu> to select an application from the main menu with
   which to open the file.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.kde.dolphin.files.manage">
  <title>Managing Files and Folders</title>
  <para>
   To perform actions like copying, moving, creating or deleting files, you
   need appropriate permissions to the folders and files involved in your
   action.
  </para>
  <procedure id="pro.kde.dolphin.files">
   <title>Copying, Moving, or Delete Files or Folders</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     In order to select one or multiple files and folders in Dolphin, move
     your mouse pointer over the file or folder but do not click. A green
     cross appears on the upper-left edge. To select the file or folder now,
     click the green cross icon. Alternatively, press
     <keycap function="control"/> and click the file or files. To deselect
     again, click the red minus icon that appears if the object is currently
     selected.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step id="step.kde.dolphin.cut">
    <para>
     Right-click and select <guimenu>Copy</guimenu> or <guimenu>Cut
     </guimenu> from the context menu.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Navigate to the destination folder in which to insert the object.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To create a new folder at the current location, select <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Create New</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Folder</guimenu> </menuchoice> or press <keycap>F10</keycap>.
     Enter a folder name in the new window and press
     <keycap function="enter"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To insert the object you copied or cut in
     <xref linkend="step.kde.dolphin.cut"/>, right-click the destination
     folder in the main display field and select <guimenu>Paste</guimenu>.
     The object is copied or moved there.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To delete a file or folder, right-click the object in the main display
     field and select <guimenu>Move to Trash</guimenu> from the context
     menu. The object is moved to the trash bin. From there, you can restore
     it if necessary or delete the object irretrievably.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   To quickly filter for certain filenames in the current directory, press
   <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>I</keycap> </keycombo> or
   select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenu>Show Filter
   Bar</guimenu> </menuchoice> to add the <guimenu>Filter</guimenu> input
   field to the bottom of the Dolphin main window. Type any part of the
   filename you are searching for to see all files in the current directory
   containing the search string. For more detailed and advanced searches,
   press <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>F</keycap>
   </keycombo> to use KFind. For more information, refer to
   <xref linkend="sec.kde.use.find"/>.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.kde.dolphin.conf">
  <title>Configuring Dolphin</title>
  <para>
   Dolphin offers many options to adjust the view and the overall settings
   according to your needs.
  </para>
  <procedure id="pro.kde.dolphin.conf.view">
   <title>Changing the View</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     To toggle between the bread crumb view and the editable version of the
     location bar, press
     <remark>taroth 081121: CTRL+L works in
       both directions, F6 only in one: switch to editable bar</remark>
     <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>L</keycap> </keycombo>
     or click at the far right end of the location bar. Enter a path to a
     directory by typing it in. After typing an address, press
     <keycap function="enter"/>.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="dolphin_location_bar.png" width="72%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="dolphin_location_bar.png" width="60%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
     To delete the contents of the location bar click the black
     <literal>X</literal> symbol on the left. To switch back to the bread
     crumb view, press <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/>
     <keycap>L</keycap> </keycombo>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To change the view of the currently displayed folder, either click
     <guimenu>Icons</guimenu>, <guimenu>Details</guimenu>, or
     <guimenu>Columns</guimenu> in the toolbar. Dolphin remembers the
     selected view for each folder. Alternatively, press <keycombo>
     <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>1</keycap> </keycombo>, <keycombo>
     <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>2</keycap> </keycombo>, or
     <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>3</keycap> </keycombo>
     to switch between the view modes. Click <guimenu>Split</guimenu> or
     press <keycap>F3</keycap> to view the contents of the current folder in
     two separate columns. Now you can navigate to a different directory in
     each column and easily drag or drop objects or compare the contents of
     directories.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_dolphin_splitview.png" width="90%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_dolphin_splitview.png" width="90%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To make Dolphin also show hidden files, select <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>View</guimenu> <guimenu>Show Hidden Files</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> or press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
     <keycap>+</keycap> </keycombo>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To view more details about the files (like access permissions or
     ownership), select <menuchoice> <guimenu>View</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Additional Information</guimenu> </menuchoice> and enable the
     relevant options.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="dolphin_hiddenfiles.png" width="75%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="dolphin_hiddenfiles.png" width="50%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To add further directories to the <guimenu>Places</guimenu> panel, drag
     a folder from the working space to the <guimenu>Places</guimenu> panel
     and drop it there. Right-click and use the context menu to hide, edit
     or remove entries from <guimenu>Places</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If you want to add more panels to the main window, select <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>View</guimenu> <guimenu>Panels</guimenu> </menuchoice> and
     select additional panels such as <guimenu>Information</guimenu>,
     <guimenu>Folders</guimenu>, or <guimenu>Terminal</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The <guimenu>Information</guimenu> panel shows the properties and a
       preview of the currently selected file. It also lets you add comments
       to the file.
       <remark>taroth 081121: DEV -
         where to search for the comments I can add or what else to do
         with them?? - taroth 090818: see strigi/Nepomuk chapter and link there
         for next revision</remark>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The <guimenu>Folder</guimenu> panel shows a tree view of the whole
       file system and lets you navigate through all subdirectories of
       <filename>/root</filename>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The <guimenu>Terminal</guimenu> panel attaches a command line to the
       bottom of the main Dolphin window. Whenever you click a directory in
       the display field, the <guimenu>Terminal</guimenu> panel also changes
       to that directory, so you can easily switch to the command line for
       certain tasks you prefer to execute in a shell.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   You can even detach the panels from the main Dolphin window by clicking
   the left icon at the top of each panel. Click the panel's title bar and
   drag it to another place on the desktop. To reintegrate the panel into
   the Dolphin window again, click the left symbol at the top of the panel
   again.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <title>Changing Dolphin's Overall Behavior</title>
   <para>
    If you want to change Dolphin's overall behavior or view, select
    <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure
    Dolphin</guimenu> </menuchoice> and explore the options offered in the
    Dolphin configuration dialog.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     To use the same view mode for all folders, click the
     <guimenu>General</guimenu> category in the left sidebar. On the
     <guimenu>Behavior</guimenu> tab, activate <guimenu>Use Common View
     Properties for All Folders</guimenu>. If you want to adjust the options
     for the individual view modes, click <guimenu>View Modes</guimenu> in
     the left sidebar and set the options according to your wishes. Click
     <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> to save the changes.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If you want Dolphin to show a different default directory on start-up,
     or if you want to permanently use the editable location bar instead of
     the bread crumb view, change the relevant options in the
     <guimenu>Startup</guimenu> category.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to save the changes and to close the
     Dolphin configuration dialog.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
