<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
  ]>
<chapter id="cha.kde.use">
 <title>Working with Your Desktop</title>
 <para>
  The following sections give you a short introduction to the key
  functionalities and applications. Learn how to cope with basic and daily
  tasks and how small KDE utilities like a password manager or a clipboard
  tool can ease your life.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.startprogr">
  <title>Starting Programs</title>

  <para>
   You can start programs either from the main menu or from the command
   line, using the <guimenu>Run Command</guimenu> dialog or a shell.
   Additionally, you can start programs from the desktop or the panel by
   left-clicking the program icon once.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>Selecting and Starting Objects</title>
   <para>
    Clicking an object once in &productname; usually starts an action
    directly: a program starts, a preview of the file is displayed, or the
    folder is opened. To former users of Windows, this behavior may be
    rather unusual. If you just want to select one or several objects
    without any other action, press <keycap function="control"/> then click
    the object. Alternatively, alter your mouse settings in the KDE Personal
    Settings as described in <xref
     linkend="pro.kde.cust.hw.mouse"/>.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <sect2 id="sec.kde.use.startprogr.menu">
   <title>Using the Main Menu</title>
   <para>
    To open the main menu, click the main menu icon in the panel or press
    <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F1</keycap> </keycombo>. The
    main menu consists of the following elements: a search function at the
    top and several tabs at the bottom, providing quick access to the key
    functions of the menu.
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="kde_main_menu.png" width="50%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="kde_main_menu.png" width="40%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
   <para>
    The following tabs are available:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Favorites</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Shows a default selection of key programs for quick access.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Shows all applications installed on your system. The
       function-oriented menu structure makes it easy to find the right
       application for your purposes even if you do not know the application
       name yet. To navigate through the structure, click an entry and use
       the arrow icons at the right or the left to switch back and forth. To
       switch back to the top-level hierarchy from anywhere in the
       structure, just click the tab's name or icon.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Computer</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Gives quick access to some places often needed, such as important
       system folders (<filename>home</filename> directory, network folders)
       and media devices. Also allows you to quickly access system
       information, and to change your system configuration with &yast;, if
       necessary.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Recently Used</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Lists the most recently opened programs and files. To reopen a
       program or file, just click the entry. To remove all recently used
       programs or files from the list, right-click below the relevant
       heading and select <guimenu>Clear Recent Applications</guimenu> or
       <guimenu>Clear Recent Documents</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Leave</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Shows several options for leaving the session, such as logging out,
       locking the screen (access can only be regained with a password),
       shutting down or restarting the computer. For more information, see
       <xref linkend="sec.kde.start.leave"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    Additionally, the menu displays your login name and the hostname of your
    computer. This information is useful when you are logged in as a
    different user or to a remote computer&mdash;it always shows you which
    system you are currently working on.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kde.use.startprogr.krunner">
   <title>Using KRunner</title>
   <para>
    KRunner is a helper application which lets you quickly start programs.
    It also offers a search function for finding applications or locations.
    Refer to <xref
     linkend="sec.kde.use.startprogr.search"/> for more
    information.
   </para>
   <para>
    Press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap>
    </keycombo> to open the input field. Type a command, for example,
    <command>dolphin</command>, and press <keycap function="enter"/> to
    start the application. The command to start the application is often
    (but not always) the application name written in lowercase.
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="kde_krunner.png" width="70%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="kde_krunner.png" width="70%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
   <remark>taroth 090818: the following function is no longer available, therefore commenting for
    now</remark>
<!--<para> If you want to start an application as a different user (for example, as
    &rootuser;), click the wrench icon in the <guimenu>Run Command</guimenu>
    dialog. Activate <guimenu>Run as Different User</guimenu>, enter the
    user's password and press <keycap function="enter"/>.
    </para>-->
   <para>
    You can also use KRunner to show current processes running on your
    system. To do so, start KRunner and click the <guimenu>Show System
    Activity</guimenu> icon. The dialog that appears also allows you to kill
    processes (for example, to terminate a <quote>runaway</quote>
    application).
   </para>
   <para>
    KRunner's abilities can be extended by a huge number of plug-ins that
    provide additional functionality. For example, if the <guimenu>Web
    Shortcuts</guimenu> plug-in is activated, you can use the Web shortcuts
    defined in Konqueror also in KRunner: send search requests directly to a
    search engine like Google* without opening the browser and visiting the
    Web sites before. For more information, refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.konq.webshortcut"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Click the wrench symbol to explore the full range of KRunner's
    abilities: If the <guimenu>Contacts</guimenu> plug-in is activated, just
    enter the name of one of your contacts and then press
    <keycap function="enter"/> to open KMail and to start typing your mail.
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="kde_krunner_extensions.png" width="70%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="kde_krunner_extensions.png" width="70%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
   <para>
    If the relevant plug-in is activated, you can also use KRunner as a
    calculator or to convert units.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kde.use.startprogr.search">
   <title>Searching for Programs</title>
   <para>
    Both the main menu and KRunner offer a search function that lets you
    quickly start programs, even if you do not know the exact application
    name or command yet. To search for an application, start typing a
    command or part of the application name in the main menu
    <guimenu>Search</guimenu> field of the menu or the input field in the
    <guimenu>Run Command</guimenu> dialog. Each character you enter further
    narrows your search.
   </para>
   <para>
    From the list below the input field, choose the application or object
    matching your query.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="kde_use_dolphin_i.xml"/>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.klipper">
  <title>Moving Text between Applications</title>

  <para>
   To copy text to the clipboard and insert it again, former MS Windows
   users automatically try the keyboard shortcut <keycombo>
   <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>C</keycap> </keycombo> and
   <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>V</keycap> </keycombo>,
   which often works in Linux as well. Copying and inserting texts is even
   easier in Linux: to copy a text to the clipboard, just select the text
   with the mouse then move the mouse cursor to the position to which to
   insert the text. Click the middle (or wheel) button on the mouse to
   insert the text (on a two-button mouse, press both mouse buttons
   simultaneously).
  </para>

  <para>
   With some applications, if text is already selected in the application
   where you want to insert the text, this method does not work because the
   text in the clipboard is overwritten by the other selected text. For such
   cases, the KDE application Klipper is very useful. Klipper
   <quote>remembers</quote> the last entries you have moved to the
   clipboard. By default, Klipper is started when KDE is loaded and appears
   as a clipboard icon in the panel. To view the clipboard contents, click
   the Klipper icon or press <keycombo>
   <keycap function="control"/><keycap function="alt"/><keycap>V</keycap>
   </keycombo>. The most recent entry is listed on top and is marked as
   active with a black check mark. If extensive text was copied to Klipper,
   only the first line of the text is displayed.
  </para>

  <para>
   To copy an older text fragment from Klipper to the clipboard, click the
   respective entry in Klipper to select it. To insert the text fragment,
   move the mouse pointer to the target application, then middle-click. Some
   applications, such as &libo;, do not support middle-clicking for
   inserting texts from the clipboard. In this case, make sure the text you
   want to insert is selected in Klipper, then press <keycombo>
   <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>V</keycap> </keycombo>. For further
   information about Klipper, especially on how to configure selection
   behavior, see the Klipper online help.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.find">
  <title>Finding Data on your Computer or in the File System</title>

  <remark>taroth 2010-03-29: strigi/nepomuk does not work with SLED 11 SP1 RC1 as
   it needs the sesame backend (see bnc#548007) which is not available on the
   SLED media -- therefore still sticking to kerry which is available</remark>

  <para>
   KDE provides more than one application for finding data on your computer
   or in the file system. With Kerry, you can very easily search your
   personal information space (usually your home folder) to find documents,
   e-mails, Web history, IM/ITC conversations, source code, images, music
   files, applications, and much more. For more information, refer to
   <xref
    linkend="cha.kerry"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   With KFind, you can locate files on your computer or in the file system
   using a variety of search criteria, such as file content, dates, owner,
   or file size. Start it from the main menu with <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> <guimenu>Find Files/Folders</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>. Alternatively, press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
   <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter <command>kfind</command>.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.kde.use.kfind">
   <title>Finding Files with KFind</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kde_find.png" width="85%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kde_find.png" width="80%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect2 id="sec.kde.use.find.basic">
   <title>Finding Files</title>
   <procedure id="pro.kde.use.kfind.files">
    <para>
     To perform a search for certain filenames, proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start KFind from the main menu or command line.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>Name&sol;Location</guimenu> tab to perform a basic
      search.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Specify the name of the file to find in <guimenu>Named</guimenu>. You
      can use the following wild cards:
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Asterisk</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         The asterisk (&ast;) stands for any number of missing characters
         (even zero). For example, searching for
         <command>marc&ast;</command> can find the files
         <emphasis>marc</emphasis>,<emphasis> marc.png</emphasis>, and
         <emphasis>marc&lowbar;must&lowbar;not&lowbar;read&lowbar;this.kwd</emphasis>.
         Searching for <guimenu>mar&ast;.kwd</guimenu> can find
         <emphasis>marketplace.kwd</emphasis> and
         <emphasis>marc&lowbar;must&lowbar;not&lowbar;read&lowbar;this.kwd</emphasis>.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Question Mark</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         The question mark (?) stands for exactly one character. For
         example, searching for <command>mar?</command> can find
         <emphasis>marc</emphasis>, but <command>marc?</command> cannot find
         anything if your files are named <emphasis>marc</emphasis> and
         <emphasis>marc.png</emphasis>. You can put as many question marks
         in the search term as you want. It finds exactly that number of
         characters.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
     <para>
      You can combine those two wild card symbols in any search term.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Specify the folder to search in <guimenu>Look In</guimenu> or click
      <guimenu>Browse</guimenu> to find the folder you want. Select
      <guimenu>Include Subfolders</guimenu> to also search all subfolders
      starting from your specified folder.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Press <keycap function="enter"/> or click <guimenu>Find</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kde.use.find.adv">
   <title>Performing an Advanced File Search</title>
   <para>
    For a more detailed search, you can also specify further options, such
    as text that the file to find must contain:
   </para>
   <procedure id="pro.kde.use.kfind.adv">
    <step>
     <para>
      Start KFind from the main menu or the command line.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>Name&sol;Location</guimenu> tab.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Specify the name of the file to find in <guimenu>Named</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Specify the folder in which to search in <guimenu>Look In</guimenu> or
      click <guimenu>Browse</guimenu> to find the folder.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>Contents</guimenu> tab.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In <guimenu>File Type</guimenu>, specify the type of file to find.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In <guimenu>Containing Text</guimenu>, enter the word or phrase that
      the file you are searching for must contain.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      If you want to specify further options, click the
      <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> tab and choose the options you want.
<!--If
  you hold the mouse pointer over the options or fields, a short
  description is displayed.-->
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Find</guimenu> to perform the search.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    For detailed information about the search options available, refer to
    the KFind online help.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.media">
  <title>Accessing Removable Media and External Devices</title>

  <para>
   If you insert removable media (such as CDs or DVDs) into your computer's
   drive, or connect external devices such as USB sticks, external hard
   disks, media players or digital cameras, these are usually automatically
   detected. In KDE 4, a panel widget alerts you to any recently plugged or
   inserted devices.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Device Notifier</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata width="40%" fileref="kde_device_notifier.png"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata width="60%" fileref="kde_device_notifier.png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   Click on the entry to show the device's contents with Dolphin.
  </para>

  <para>
   If the device is not automatically displayed in the device notifier, try
   to access it manually with Dolphin.
  </para>

<!--Clicking
   <guimenu>My Computer</guimenu> on the desktops opens a view as shown in
   <xref linkend="fig.kdenld.removable.mycomp"/>.
  </para>
  <figure id="fig.kdenld.removable.mycomp">
   <title>My Computer</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kde_mycomputer.png" width="65%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kde_mycomputer.png" width="50%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>-->

  <para>
   Start the Dolphin file manager and switch to the editable version of the
   location bar as described in <xref linkend="pro.kde.dolphin.conf.view"/>.
   Enter <command>/media</command> to access any type of drive mounted
   there. If the medium has been detected, it is also listed in the
   <guimenu>Places</guimenu> panel. Click the relevant entry to show the
   contents. Digital cameras can also be accessed by entering the URL
   <literal>camera:/</literal> into Dolphin's location bar. In case your
   camera is not automatically detected, configure it first with the KDE 4
   Personal Settings or with digiKam as described in
   <xref linkend="sec.digikam.config"/>. Navigate through the camera's
   directory structure until the files are shown. Use the usual Dolphin file
   management features to copy the files as desired.
  </para>

  <para>
   Another way to access detected media devices is to click the <guimenu>My
   Computer</guimenu> icon on your desktop. The detected devices are listed
   in the <guimenu>Disk Information</guimenu> section.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>Removing Media Safely</title>
   <para>
    If you want to remove or disconnect a device from your computer, make
    sure that the data on it is currently not being accessed by any
    application or user. Otherwise, you risk a loss of data. To safely
    remove the device, proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Open a view that displays the removable device (for example, with
      Dolphin or <guimenu>My Computer</guimenu>).
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Right-click the device in the <guimenu>Places</guimenu> panel (or
      below <guimenu>Disk Information</guimenu>) and select <guimenu>Safely
      Remove</guimenu> or <guimenu>Eject</guimenu>. <guimenu>Safely Remove
      </guimenu> unmounts the device, after which you can disconnect it from
      your computer. <guimenu>Eject</guimenu> automatically opens the CD or
      DVD drive of your computer.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
  </note>
 </sect1>
<!--taroth 081123: commenting the old stuff but still leaving it
  here - hopefully handling of removable media can be configured with
  KDE 4 one day-->
<!-- <sect2>
  <title>Inserting or Connecting Removable Media</title>
  <indexterm>
  <primary>media</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
  <primary>USB</primary>
  <secondary>digital cameras</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
  <primary>USB</primary>
  <secondary>media</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
  If you insert or connect removable media to your computer (such as
  CD-ROMs, digital cameras, or USB sticks), these are usually
  automatically detected. In KDE, a dialog appears, showing the medium
  type detected and offering several options of what to do with the new
  medium. The list of options depends on the type of medium inserted.
  </para>
  <figure id="fig.kde_nld.removable.autodetect">
  <title>Automatic Detection of a USB Stick in KDE</title>
  <mediaobject>
  <imageobject role="fo">
  <imagedata fileref="kde_remov_detect.png" width="40%"/>
  </imageobject>
  <imageobject role="html">
  <imagedata fileref="kde_remov_detect.png" width="40%"/>
  </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
  To view the data with a file manager, select <guimenu>Open in New
  Window</guimenu> and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. The Konqueror file
  manager appears, showing the contents of the removable device.
  </para>
  <figure id="fig.kde_nld.removable.contents">
  <title>Viewing the Contents of a USB Stick</title>
  <mediaobject>
  <imageobject role="fo">
  <imagedata fileref="konqui_contents_usb.png" width="55%"/>
  </imageobject>
  <imageobject role="html">
  <imagedata fileref="konqui_contents_usb.png" width="60%"/>
  </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
  For the same action to be performed every time you insert a removable
  medium of that type, activate <guimenu>Always do this for this type of
  media</guimenu> in the detection dialog before clicking
  <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
  </para>
  <para>
  If you insert or connect a removable medium to the system that has been
  encrypted with LUKS (Linux Unified Key Setup), KDE recognizes this and
  prompts for the password as shown in
  <xref
  linkend="fig.kde_nld.removable.crypto.autodetect"/>. Enter
  the password to access the encrypted medium.
  </para>
  <figure id="fig.kde_nld.removable.crypto.autodetect">
  <title>Automatic Detection of an Encrypted USB Stick</title>
  <mediaobject>
  <imageobject role="fo">
  <imagedata fileref="kde_cryptoremov_detect.png" width="45%"/>
  </imageobject>
  <imageobject role="html">
  <imagedata fileref="kde_cryptoremov_detect.png" width="35%"/>
  </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
  For information about encrypting removable media, refer to
  <xref linkend="sec.cryptofs.y2.removables"/>.
  </para>
  <procedure>
  <title>Configuring Removable Media Handling</title>
  <para>
  In the autodetection dialog, you can also configure how KDE should
  handle several types of removable media. For example, if you know that
  a certain type of medium that you use often always contains photos, you
  can configure it to open an image viewer application automatically:
  </para>
  <step>
  <para>
  In the autodetection dialog, click <guimenu>Configure</guimenu>.
  </para>
  </step>
  <step>
  <para>
  A configuration dialog appears, showing a list of all available
  actions.
  </para>
  </step>
  <step>
  <para>
  Click the <guimenu>Medium types</guimenu> drop-down list and select
  the type of medium for which to configure a certain action. The list
  of available actions now only shows actions applicable to the medium
  type selected.
  </para>
  </step>
  <step>
  <para>
  Select the action to apply and click <guimenu>Toggle as Auto
  Action</guimenu>.
  </para>
  <figure id="fig.kde_nld.removable.conf">
  <title>KDE Configuration Dialog for Removable Media</title>
  <mediaobject>
  <imageobject role="fo">
  <imagedata fileref="kde_remov_conf.png" width="60%"/>
  </imageobject>
  <imageobject role="html">
  <imagedata fileref="kde_remov_conf.png" width="55%"/>
  </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  </step>
  <step>
  <para>
  Click the <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> tab and make sure
  <guimenu>Enable medium application autostart after mount</guimenu> is
  selected.
  </para>
  </step>
  <step>
  <para>
  Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to apply the changes and close the
  configuration dialog. Now every time you insert a medium of this type,
  the configured action is executed automatically and the autodetection
  dialog does not appear any more.
  </para>
  </step>
  </procedure>
  <procedure>
  <title>Restoring Default Media Handling Options</title>
  <para>
  To reset the action assigned to the type of medium and restore the
  default options, proceed as follows:
  </para>
  <step>
  <para>
  Start the KDE control center from the main menu by selecting
  <menuchoice> <guimenu>Favorites</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure Desktop
  (Personal Settings)</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
  </para>
  </step>
  <step>
  <para>
  In the left-hand navigation bar, click <menuchoice>
  <guimenu>Peripherals</guimenu> <guimenu>Storage Media</guimenu>
  </menuchoice>. The configuration dialog appears on the right.
  </para>
  </step>
  <step>
  <para>
  Click <guimenu>Default</guimenu> and <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>. The
  next time you insert a medium, the autodetection dialog appears again,
  leaving you the choice of what to do with the medium.
  </para>
  </step>
  </procedure>
  </sect2>
  
  <?dbfo-need height="20em"?>
  
  <sect2 id="sec.kdenld_basics.accessmedia">
  <title>Accessing Removable Media</title>
  <para>
  KDE offers several ways to access removable media at any time. Clicking
  <guimenu>My Computer</guimenu> on the desktops opens a view as shown in
  <xref linkend="fig.kdenld.removable.mycomp"/>.
  </para>
  <figure id="fig.kdenld.removable.mycomp">
  <title>My Computer</title>
  <mediaobject>
  <imageobject role="fo">
  <imagedata fileref="kde_mycomputer.png" width="65%"/>
  </imageobject>
  <imageobject role="html">
  <imagedata fileref="kde_mycomputer.png" width="50%"/>
  </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
  If you start Konqueror as a file manager (see
  <xref
  linkend="sec.kde.dolphin"/>) and click <guimenu>Storage
  Media</guimenu> on the start window or enter
  <filename>media:/</filename> in the location bar, Konqueror displays the
  storage devices as shown in
  <xref
  linkend="fig.kde_nld.removable.konqui"/>.
  </para>
  <figure id="fig.kde_nld.removable.konqui">
  <title>Displaying Media in Konqueror</title>
  <mediaobject>
  <imageobject role="fo">
  <imagedata fileref="konqui_media.png" width="45%"/>
  </imageobject>
  <imageobject role="html">
  <imagedata fileref="konqui_media.png" width="45%"/>
  </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
  You can also name removable devices, such as USB sticks, with Konqueror.
  Right-click the USB stick in Konqueror and select
  <guimenu>Properties</guimenu>. On the <guimenu>General</guimenu> tab,
  enter a name in the input field and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. When
  inserting the stick the next time, Konqueror displays the name of the
  stick.
  </para>
  <para>
  A small green arrow indicates that a medium has been
  <emphasis>mounted</emphasis> (integrated into your file system, which is
  necessary to access the data on the medium). In &productname;, you normally
  do not have to care about mounting removable devices because this is
  done automatically by default.
  </para>
  <note>
  <title>Removing Media Safely</title>
  <para>
  If you want to remove or disconnect a medium from your computer, make
  sure that the data on the medium is currently not accessed by any
  application or user. Otherwise, you risk a loss of data. To safely
  remove the medium, proceed as follows:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para>
  Open a view that displays all removable media.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para>
  Right-click the medium to remove and select <guimenu>Safely
  Remove</guimenu> or <guimenu>Eject</guimenu>. <guimenu>Safely Remove
  </guimenu> unmounts the medium after which you can disconnect the
  medium from your computer. <guimenu>Eject</guimenu> automatically
  opens the CD or DVD drive of your computer.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  </note>
  </sect2>
 -->
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.virtdesk">
  <title>Using Virtual Desktops</title>

  <para>
   The desktop environment allows you to organize your programs and tasks on
   several virtual desktops between which you can switch the pager in the
   panel (see <xref
    linkend="sec.kde.start.comp"/>). If you often run a
   lot of programs simultaneously, this minimizes the number of windows to
   arrange on your screen. You might, for example, use one desktop for
   e-mailing and keeping your calendar and another for word processing or
   graphics applications.
  </para>

  <procedure id="proc.kde.use.virtdesk.move">
   <title>Moving an Application to Another Virtual Desktop</title>
   <para>
    You can display a running application on one or all virtual desktops or
    move it to other desktops.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open the application.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Right-click the title bar of the application.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>To Desktop</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the desktop on which to place the application.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To switch between desktops, click the desired desktop in the pager in
     the panel.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   Some users might need more desktops than provided by default. Learn how
   to add additional desktops in <xref linkend="pro.kde.cust.desk.vdesk"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.connecitivity">
  <title>Managing Internet Connections</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Internet</primary>

  <secondary>connecting to</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   To surf the Internet or send and receive e-mail messages or use Instant
   Messengers, you must have configured an Internet connection with &yast;
   or &nm;. For more details, see <xref
    linkend="sec.basicnet.yast"/>
   and <xref linkend="cha.nm"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.internet">
  <title>Exploring the Internet</title>

  <para>
   Once an Internet connection is established, either use Firefox or
   Konqueror for browsing. Konqueror is KDE's Web browser but &productname;
   also includes Firefox. To start Konqueror or Firefox, press <keycombo>
   <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter
   <command>konqueror</command> or <command>firefox</command>.
  </para>

  <para>
   With features like tabbed browsing, pop-up window blocking, and download
   and image management, both browsers combine the latest Web technologies.
   Their easy access to different search engines helps you to find the
   information you need.
  </para>

  <para>
   For more information about Firefox, see <xref linkend="cha.firefox"/>.
   Learn more about Konqueror as a Web browser in
   <xref linkend="cha.konqueror"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.mailpim">
  <title>E-Mail and Scheduling</title>

  <para>
   For reading and managing your mails and appointments, you can use Kontact
   as your personal information management tool (PIM). Kontact combines KDE
   applications like KMail, KOrganizer, and KAddressBook into a single
   interface. This gives you easy access to your e-mail, calendar, address
   book, and other PIM functionality. KMail can also manage multiple e-mail
   accounts, such as your private and business e-mails. To start Kontact,
   press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt">Alt</keycap> <keycap>F2</keycap>
   </keycombo> and enter <command>kontact</command>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Before you can send or receive mails, you must configure an e-mail
   account. When starting KMail for the first time, a configuration wizard
   appears that assists you in setting up your account. For detailed
   information about configuring and using Kontact, see
   <xref
    linkend="cha.kontact"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Instant Messaging</title>

  <para>
   Kopete is an online messenger application that allows multiple partners
   connected to the Internet to chat with each other. Kopete currently
   supports a number of common messenger protocols. To be able to use
   instant messaging (IM), you must register with a provider offering IM
   services and configure a Kopete account.
  </para>

  <para>
   To start Kopete, press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
   <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter <command>kopete</command>.
   Learn more about Kopete in <xref
    linkend="cha.kopete"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.kwallet">
  <title>Managing Passwords</title>

  <para>
   When you enter a password in a KDE application for the first time (in
   KMail or Konqueror, for example), you are asked if you want to store the
   password in an encrypted wallet. If you click <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>,
   KWallet wizard starts by default. KWallet is a password management tool
   that can collect all passwords and store them in an encrypted file. For
   more information on how to configure and use KWallet, refer to
   <xref linkend="cha.kde.kwallet"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Whereas KWallet is designed to centrally manage passwords for several KDE
   applications, Firefox also offers the ability to store data when you
   enter a username and a password on a Web site. If you accept by clicking
   <guimenu>Remember</guimenu>, the password will be stored on your hard
   disk in an encrypted format. The next time you access this site, Firefox
   will automatically fill in the login data.
  </para>

  <para>
   To review or manage your passwords in Firefox, click <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Security</guimenu> <guimenu>Saved Passwords...</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.ooo">
  <title>Opening or Creating Documents with &ooo;</title>

  <para>
   The office suite &ooo; offers a complete set of office tools, including
   word processor, spreadsheet, presentation, vector drawing, and database
   components. Because &ooo; is available for a number of operating systems,
   you can use the same data across different computing platforms. You can
   also open and edit files in Microsoft Office formats then save them back
   to this format, if needed.
  </para>

  <para>
   Start &ooo; from the main menu or click the Office icon on the desktop.
   You can also start individual components, like the word processor, by
   pressing <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap>
   </keycombo> and entering <command>oowriter</command>.
  </para>

  <para>
   For an introduction to &ooo;, see <xref linkend="cha.oo.oview"/> or view
   the help in an &ooo; program.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.viewer">
  <title>Viewing PDF Files and Other Documents</title>

  <para>
   Documents that need to be shared or printed across platforms can be saved
   as PDF (Portable Document Format) files, for example, in the &ooo; suite.
   View them with Okular, the default KDE document viewer.
  </para>

  <para>
   Start Okular from the main menu or press <keycombo>
   <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter
   <command>okular</command>.
  </para>

  <para>
   To open a document, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Open</guimenu> </menuchoice> and choose the desired file from
   the file system. Navigate through the documents by using the navigation
   icons at the top or bottom of the window. If your PDF document provides
   bookmarks, you can access them in the left panel of the viewer.
  </para>

  <para>
   Okular also allows you to review a document by highlighting certain text
   parts or adding annotations. For more information about working with
   Okular, see <xref linkend="cha.okular"/>.
  </para>

  <para os="osuse">
   You can also view PDF files with Adobe Acrobat Reader. If Acrobat Reader
   is not installed by default, install the
   <systemitem>acroread</systemitem> package with &yast;. To start Acrobat
   reader, press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap>
   </keycombo> and enter <command>acroread</command> or start the program
   from the main menu. Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Open</guimenu> </menuchoice>, locate the desired PDF file and
   click <guimenu>Open</guimenu> to view the file.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.ksnapshot">
  <title>Taking Screen Shots</title><indexterm>

  <primary>screen shots</primary>

  <secondary>KSnapshot</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>KDE</primary>

  <secondary>KSnapshot</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   With KSnapshot, you can create snapshots of your screen or individual
   application windows. Start the program from the main menu or by pressing
   <keycombo> <keycap function="alt">Alt</keycap> <keycap>F2</keycap>
   </keycombo> and entering <command>ksnapshot</command>. On start-up,
   KSnapshot takes a snapshot of the screen and displays it as preview. You
   can choose to save the current snapshot, to open it with an graphics
   application or to copy it to the clipboard. Before creating a new
   snapshot, check if the options in the lower part of the window match your
   needs. For example, to automatically capture a dialog window or a certain
   region (instead of the full screen), adjust the <guimenu>Capture
   Mode</guimenu>. If you need to take some other actions first (like
   selecting a certain object in the window), adjust the <guimenu>Snapshot
   Delay</guimenu> and choose if to <guimenu>Include the window
   decorations</guimenu> or not. Then click <guimenu>New Snapshot</guimenu>
   to take a new snapshot which you then can save or edit further.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.ksnapshot">
   <title>KSnapshot</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata width="75%" fileref="ksnapshot.png" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata width="50%" fileref="ksnapshot.png" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.ark">
  <title>Displaying, Decompressing, and Creating Archives</title><indexterm>

  <primary>KDE</primary>

  <secondary>Ark</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>files</primary>

  <secondary>archiving</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   To save space on the hard disk, use a packer that compresses files and
   directories to a fraction of their original size. The application Ark can
   be used to manage such archives. It supports common formats, such as
   <literal>zip</literal>, <literal>tar.gz</literal>,
   <literal>tar.bz2</literal>, <literal>lha</literal>,
   <literal>rar</literal> and <literal>LZMA/XZ</literal>.
<!--taroth 090817: the latter according to
    http://www.kde.org/announcements/4.3/-->
  </para>

  <para>
   Start Ark from the main menu or from the command line with
   <command>ark</command>.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.kdeplus.ark">
   <title>Ark: File Archive Preview</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata width="80%" fileref="ark.png" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata width="70%" fileref="ark.png" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   Once you have opened an archive, perform various actions.
   <guimenu>Action</guimenu> offers options such as <guimenu>Add
   File</guimenu>, <guimenu>Add Folder</guimenu>, <guimenu>Delete</guimenu>,
   <guimenu>Extract</guimenu>, <guimenu>View</guimenu>, <guimenu>Edit
   With</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Open With</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Creating an Archive</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     To create a new archive, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu>
     <guimenu>New</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the name of the new archive in the dialog that opens, and specify
     the format using <guimenu>Filter</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     After confirming with <guimenu>Save</guimenu> or by pressing
     <keycap>Enter</keycap>, the Ark window shows an empty archive.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To fill the archive, drag and drop files and directories from the file
     manager into this window or click <guimenu>Add File</guimenu> or
     <guimenu>Add Folder</guimenu> to add the objects you want to add to the
     archive.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To remove a file from the archive, select the file and click
     <guimenu>Delete</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If all files to be archived are displayed in the window, just close
     Ark. Ark automatically compresses everything into the previously
     selected archive format and saves the archive.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure>
   <title>Viewing and Extracting Archives</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     To view the contents of an archive, start Ark and select <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenu>Open</guimenu></menuchoice> to open the
     file. Alternatively, just drag the archive from an open file manager
     window to the Ark window.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To see a preview of individual files, select a file and click
     <guimenu>Preview</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To extract all files from the archive, click
     <guimenu>Extract</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you want to extract individual files from the archive only, select
     one or more files (by keeping the <keycap function="control"/> key
     pressed) and click <guimenu>Extract</guimenu>. In the following dialog,
     you can still decide to save <guimenu>All Files</guimenu> or the
     <guimenu>Selected Files Only</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the path to the <guimenu>Destination Folder</guimenu>, select if
     to <guimenu>Open Destination Folder After Extraction</guimenu> and
     click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to extract the files.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Creating CDs or DVDs</title>

  <para>
   If you possess a CD or DVD writer, you can burn files to a CD or DVD with
   K3b. To start K3b, press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
   <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter <command>k3b</command>. Learn
   more about K3b in <xref linkend="cha.k3b"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.images">
  <title>Viewing and Managing Digital Images</title>

  <para>
   You can view digital images in the file manager
   <remark>taroth 080730: mention in Dolphin
    section and add link</remark>
   or with Gwenview. Start Gwenview by pressing <keycombo>
   <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and entering
   <command>gwenview</command>. Gwenview can load and save all image formats
   supported by KDE. It shows them either as thumbnails, in full screen
   view, or in slide show mode. When browsing JPEG images with EXIF
   information, Gwenview automatically rotates them according to the EXIF
   Orientation tag.
  </para>

  <para>
   For managing and editing your digital images, digiKam is the right
   choice. Download your images from the camera, edit and improve them,
   organize them in albums (or flag them with tags for easy retrieval,
   independent of folders or albums), and archive them on CD (or export them
   to a Web image gallery).
  </para>

  <para>
   To start digiKam, press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
   <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter <command>digikam</command>.
   Find an introduction to digiKam in <xref
    linkend="cha.digicam"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.amarok">
  <title>Managing Your Music Collection</title>

  <para>
   KDE's &amarok; music player allows you to play various audio formats,
   create playlists,
<!--taroth 090818: not sure if this function still exists: import music from an iPod* (or upload files to your
   iPod),-->
   and listen to streaming audio broadcasts of radio stations on the
   Internet. The file types supported depend on the engine used for
   &amarok;. To start &amarok;, press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
   <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter <command>amarok</command>. To
   define the folders where &amarok; should look for your music files, from
   the main menu select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Configure &amarok;</guimenu> <guimenu>Collection</guimenu>
   </menuchoice> and set the options according to your wishes. For more
   information about &amarok;, refer to <xref linkend="cha.sound"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.trouble">
  <title>Troubleshooting</title>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Plasma Crashes</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      In case your desktop (or plasma crashes), use the following commands
      to kill and restart plasma:
     </para>
<screen>kbuildsycoca4
kquitapp plasma-desktop
kstart plasma-desktop 
    </screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Plasma Configuration Files</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you ever need to manually modify the Plasma configuration files,
      find them in your system under <filename>
      ~/.kde4/share/config/plasmarc</filename> and
      <filename>~/.kde4/share/config/plasma-appletsrc</filename>. The first
      one stores global settings like the desktop theme, while the latter
      stores the settings for all the individual applets.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Restoring Panels</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you accidentally deleted a custom panel, there is no way to restore
      it with all the elements it held. In this case, add a new panel as
      described in <xref linkend="proc.kde.cust.conf.panel"/> and start
      customizing it from scratch.
     </para>
     <para>
      However, you can restore the <emphasis>default</emphasis> panel with
      the following steps:
     </para>
     <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Log out from the current KDE session.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Press <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/>
        <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and log in
        on the command line with the same username.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Execute the following command:
       </para>
<screen>rm ~/.kde4/share/config/plasma-appletsrc</screen>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Press <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/>
        <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F7</keycap> </keycombo> and log
        back into the graphical user interface.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </orderedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.use.more">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   As well as the applications described here for getting started, KDE can
   run many other applications. Find detailed information on many important
   applications in the other parts of this manual.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To learn more about KDE and KDE applications, also refer to
     <ulink url="http://www.kde.org/"/>,
     <ulink url="http://www.kde-apps.org/"/> and
     <ulink url="http://userbase.kde.org/"></ulink>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Communicate and discuss topics with other KDE users and get help at
     <ulink url="http://forum.kde.org/index.php"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To learn more about the helper applications included in the KDE, see
     also <ulink url="http://utils.kde.org/"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To report bugs or add feature requests, go to
     <ulink url="http://bugs.kde.org/"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
