<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
  ]>
<chapter id="cha.kde.cust">
 <title>Customizing Your Settings</title>
 <para>
  You can change the way your KDE desktop looks and behaves to suit your own
  personal tastes and needs. There are several ways to influence the look
  and feel of the KDE desktop depending on the scope of changes to make. For
  users, the following options are available:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To change the appearance or behavior of individual desktop objects only,
    you can usually access a configuration dialog by right-clicking the
    object.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To change the overall appearance and behavior of your KDE desktop, use
    the <guimenu>Personal Settings</guimenu> that in KDE 4 replaced the
    former KDE&nbsp;Control&nbsp;Center. Personal Settings offers access to
    numerous configuration modules and dialogs, some of which can also be
    accessed via the context menu of individual desktop objects.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.cust.kcontrol">
  <title>Personal Settings - Overview</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>KDE</primary>
   <secondary>personal settings</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
   The Personal Settings are the central place for users to change the
   overall appearance and behavior of many components of the KDE desktop.
   Start the Personal Settings from the main menu by selecting <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Favorites</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure Desktop</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>.
<!-- or press <keycombo>
     <keycap function="alt"/>
     <keycap>F2</keycap>
     </keycombo> and enter <command>systemsettings</command>-->
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.kde.cust.kcontrol">
   <title>Personal Settings</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kde_kcontrol_main.png" width="90%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kde_kcontrol_main.png" width="75%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect2 id="sec.kde.cust.kcontrol.use">
   <title>Use</title>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>General</guimenu> and <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> tabs
    provide different categories of settings. To get an impression of the
    numerous possibilities, just click a category icon and explore the
    possibilities provided there. Performing tasks in some areas of the
    personal settings requires system administrator (&rootuser;)
    permissions.
   </para>
   <para>
    Change the settings as desired. No changes take effect until you click
    <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>. To discard changes in the recent view that you
    have not yet applied, click <guimenu>Reset</guimenu>. To reset all items
    in the recent view to the default values, click
    <guimenu>Defaults</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    To get back to the start-up view (showing all categories) again, click
    <guimenu>Overview</guimenu>. You can also enter a search string at the
    top of the window (for example, <guimenu>Screen Saver</guimenu>) to find
    the category which holds options related to the search string. Each
    character you enter in the <guimenu>Search</guimenu> field further
    narrows the search.
   </para>
   <para>
    For easier overview of all categories, you can also switch to a tree
    view by clicking <guimenu>Configure</guimenu> and selecting another
    <guimenu>View Style</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kde.cust.kcontrol.categories">
   <title>Categories</title>
   <para>
    The following list introduces the major categories, and highlights the
    most important settings you can change there. If you hover the mouse
    pointer over the icons in each category, a tool tip shows you which
    settings can be found there. Detailed information is provided by the
    <guimenu>Help</guimenu> button on each page of the settings, or in the
    help center.
   </para>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>General</guimenu> tab holds the following categories:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Look &amp; Feel</guimenu>
      <indexterm>
       <primary>KDE</primary>
       <secondary>personal settings</secondary>
       <tertiary>Look &amp; Feel</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Holds settings for the appearance of your KDE 4 desktop (such as
       themes, window decorations, and styles of desktop elements). Allows
       you to configure 3D desktops effects, increase or decrease the number
       of virtual (multiple) desktops, or configure screen saver options.
       Cursor behavior, window behavior and the splash screen that appears
       on KDE start-up can also be modified here.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Personal</guimenu>
      <indexterm>
       <primary>KDE</primary>
       <secondary>personal settings</secondary>
       <tertiary>Personal</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Holds settings for changing the default paths to the subdirectories
       of your home directory. Allows you to change the default applications
       (like e-mail client, text editor, messenger, and Web browser) that
       are called whenever a KDE application needs to start applications of
       these types. Define country and language-specific options here, such
       as default spell checking options, currency, number and date format,
       and keyboard layouts for different languages. This category also
       offers accessibility options for handicapped users, such as sound and
       keyboard options and mouse gestures.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Network &amp; Connectivity</guimenu>
      <indexterm>
       <primary>KDE</primary>
       <secondary>personal settings</secondary>
       <tertiary>Network &amp; Connectivity</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Allows you to set options for network management, local network
       browsing and proxy servers.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Computer Administration</guimenu>
      <indexterm>
       <primary>KDE</primary>
       <secondary>personal settings</secondary>
       <tertiary>Computer Administration</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Allows you to configure date and time settings for your KDE desktop,
       to change size and orientation of your display, and to specify power
       management options for saving energy. Also holds settings for
       joysticks, keyboard and mouse. You can view and modify the predefined
       KDE shortcuts. You can also install personal or systemwide fonts here
       and configure your sound system.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> tab holds the following categories:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Advanced User Settings</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use this category to configure options like encoding or to which
       database to connect for track listings of audio CDs, to configure
       your digital camera, or to change the settings for KWallet (the KDE
       password management tool). If needed, change the default file
       associations in order to identify a file type and start an
       appropriate application. Define how KDE handles sessions on login or
       shutdown and define which applications should be started
       automatically.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>System</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Holds options for the login manager, &pk;, power management and
       Samba.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
<!-- <tip>
    <title>Starting Individual Modules</title>
    <para>
     You can also start individual modules of the Personal Settings from the
     shell or by adding a special applet to your panel.
    </para>
    <para>
     To start modules from a shell, enter <command>kcmshell4
     <option>&#45; &#45;list</option></command> to get a list of all available
     modules. Then enter <command>kcmshell4 <option> <replaceable>module
     name</replaceable> </option></command> to start the desired module.
    </para>
    <para>
     Alternatively, add the <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> applet to your panel
     according to the description in
     <xref linkend="sec.kde.cust.desk.panel"/>.
    </para>
   </tip>-->
   <para>
    In the following sections, find examples of how to configure some
    aspects of your KDE desktop that you might want to customize.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.cust.desk">
  <title>Configuring Desktop Objects and Appearance</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>KDE</primary>
   <secondary>configuring</secondary>
   <tertiary>desktop objects</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>KDE</primary>
   <secondary>configuring</secondary>
   <tertiary>desktop appearance</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
   Your KDE desktop comes with a predefined set of desktop icons. By adding
   various objects such as folders, files, or widgets, you can create
   additional icons on your desktop and arrange them as you like.
  </para>

  <procedure id="proc.kde.cust.desk.icons">
   <title>Adding Program Icons to the Desktop</title>
   <para>
    To create a link to an application and place it on the desktop or the
    panel, proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the main menu button and browse to the desired application.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Right-click and select <guimenu>Add to Desktop</guimenu> or
     <guimenu>Add to Panel</guimenu> from the context menu that appears. If
     these menu items are not available, your desktop elements are probably
     locked. Unlock them first as described in
     <xref
      linkend="sec.kde.start.lock"/>.
    </para>
<!--taroth 090819: this doesn't work currently:
     <para>
     If your desktop objects are not locked, you can also just drag items
     from the main menu onto the desktop and drop them there to create a
     link to this application or folder.
    </para>-->
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To change the icon position on the desktop, left-click the icon and
     drag it to the desired place.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

<!-- <para>
   To delete an icon from your desktop, right-click the icon and select
   <guimenu>Remove this Icon</guimenu>.
  </para>-->

  <sect2 id="sec.kde.cust.desk.widgets">
   <title>Widgets</title>
   <procedure id="proc.kde.cust.desk.add.widgets">
    <title>Adding Widgets to the Desktop</title>
    <para>
     Widgets are small applications that can be integrated into your desktop
     or your panel.
    </para>
    <step>
     <para>
      To add widgets to you desktop, right-click an empty patch on your
      desktop and select <guimenu>Add Widgets</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <para>
      If these menu items are not available, your desktop elements are
      probably locked. Unlock them first as described in
      <xref linkend="sec.kde.start.lock"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step id="step.proc.kde.cust.add.widgets">
     <para>
      In the dialog box that appears, you can limit the selection of widgets
      that is shown with the drop-down list at the top or by entering a
      search string into the input field.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_add_widget.png" width="65%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_add_widget.png" width="40%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select a widget and click <guimenu>Add Widget</guimenu>. The widget
      appears on your desktop.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To position the widget on your desktop, left-click the widget and drag
      it to the desired place.
<!--taroth 2010-03-26: this function does not
       show any effect at all-->
<!--To align all widgets to a grid, right-click
      an empty patch on the desktop and select <menuchoice><guimenu>Icons
     </guimenu><guimenu>Align to Grid</guimenu></menuchoice>.-->
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    To remove a widget from your desktop, right-click the widget and select
    the
    <remark>taroth
     080507: added dots on purpose because the menu item also contains the widgets name, e.g.
     "Remove this Analog Clock"</remark>
    <guimenu>Remove...</guimenu> entry. Conversely, hover your mouse pointer
    over the widget and click the <literal>X</literal> symbol in the frame.
   </para>
   <procedure id="proc.kde.cust.conf.widgets">
    <title>Configuring Widgets</title>
    <para>
     In order to configure widgets, the desktop elements need to be unlocked
     as described in <xref linkend="sec.kde.start.lock"/>.
    </para>
    <step>
     <para>
      To configure a widget, hover your mouse pointer over the widget until
      a translucent panel appears on the left or right side of the widget,
      showing a number of symbols.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_widget_frame.png" width="45%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_widget_frame.png" width="40%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
     <para>
      If the panel does not appear, your widgets are probably locked. Unlock
      them first as described in <xref linkend="sec.kde.start.lock"/>
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To change the widget size, left-click the resize symbol in the panel
      and keep the mouse button pressed while moving your cursor across the
      desktop to scale the widget size.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To rotate the widget in any direction, left-click the arrow symbol in
      the panel and keep the mouse button pressed while moving your cursor
      in a circle across the desktop. There is a sticky boundary in the
      horizontal and vertical positions where you can <quote>clamp</quote>
      the widget, if you like. You can also arrange it in any tilted
      position.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To change the contents, settings, or properties of a widget,
      left-click the wrench symbol in the panel. In the configuration dialog
      box that appears, set the options according to your wishes.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    Use the <literal>X</literal> symbol in the panel if you want to close
    the widget.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kde.cust.desk.misc">
   <title>Virtual Desktops, Background and Screen Saver</title>
   <procedure id="proc.kde.cust.desk.back">
    <title>Changing the Desktop Background</title>
    <para>
     You can change the background colors of your desktop or select a
     picture to use as the background.
    </para>
    <step>
     <para>
      Right-click an empty patch of the desktop and select either
      <guimenu>Desktop Settings</guimenu>, <guimenu>Folder View
      Settings</guimenu> or <guimenu>Plain Desktop Settings</guimenu>
      (depending on the currently active desktop view). A configuration
      dialog appears.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the <guimenu>Wallpaper</guimenu> section, choose an option from the
      <guimenu>Type</guimenu> drop-down list, for example
      <guimenu>Image</guimenu>, <guimenu>Slide Show</guimenu> or
      <guimenu>Color</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_conf_deskback.png" width="80%"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_conf_deskback.png" width="60%"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        For an image wallpaper, choose a wallpaper from the
        <guimenu>Picture</guimenu> list. Click <guimenu>Get New
        Wallpapers</guimenu> to download and install new wallpapers. To use
        a custom picture, click the folder button beneath the list and
        select an image file from the file system. Define the
        <guimenu>Positioning</guimenu> of the image.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        To have multiple images appear in <guimenu>Slide Show</guimenu>
        mode, define the directory from which to select the pictures and set
        the interval after which to change the images.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Set the other options in the configuration dialog according to your
      wishes, and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to save your changes and leave
      the configuration dialog.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure id="pro.kde.cust.desk.vdesk">
    <title>Adding Additional Virtual Desktops</title>
    <indexterm>
     <primary>KDE</primary>
     <secondary>configuring</secondary>
     <tertiary>virtual desktops</tertiary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
     Some users might need more desktops than provided by default.
    </para>
    <step>
     <para>
      Right-click the desktop previewer in the panel and select
      <guimenu>Configure Desktops</guimenu>. A configuration dialog appears
      where you can increase or decrease the number of virtual desktops. You
      can also change the default names of desktops.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_add_virtdesk.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_add_virtdesk.png" width="60%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to apply the changes and close the
      configuration dialog.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      For the names of the desktops to appear in the desktop previewer
      rather than the number, right-click the desktop previewer and select
      <menuchoice> <guimenu>Pager Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Desktop
      Name</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure id="pro.kde.cust.desk.activities">
    <title>Using Different Options for Each Virtual Desktop</title>
    <remark>taroth 090819: check this against upcoming milestones as it may change again</remark>
    <para>
     Though somewhat more complicated than with KDE 3.x, you can configure
     your virtual desktops in a way that allows you to use different
     wallpapers or widgets on each.
    </para>
    <note>
     <title>Combining Virtual Desktops with Plasma Activities</title>
     <para>
      Note that the implementation in this release of KDE is still in an
      experimental state. Some features may not work as expected.
     </para>
    </note>
    <para>
     To access the relevant configuration options, you need to show the
     cashew icon at the upper right corner first. If it is not visible, you
     need to switch to a different view first. To do so, right-click an
     empty patch on your desktop and select <guimenu>Plain Desktop
     Settings</guimenu>. In the dialog that appears, click
     <guimenu>Type</guimenu> below <guimenu>Desktop Activity</guimenu> and
     either select <guimenu>Folder View</guimenu> or
     <guimenu>Desktop</guimenu> from the list. Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>
     to confirm the settings and to close the dialog. Now the cashew icon is
     visible at the upper right corner of your desktop.
    </para>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the cashew icon at the upper right corner of your desktop and
      select <guimenu>Configure Plasma</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the Plasma configuration dialog, activate <guimenu>Different
      Activity for Each Desktop</guimenu> and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <para>
      From now on, each of your virtual desktops will have separate plasma
      activities. This will allow you to have a different wallpaper on each
      virtual desktop, as well as a completely separate set of widgets.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Now switch to the virtual desktop you want to configure and set a
      custom background as described in
      <xref linkend="proc.kde.cust.desk.back"/> or add new widgets for the
      virtual desktop as described in
      <xref linkend="proc.kde.cust.desk.add.widgets"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    To make all virtual desktops appear the same again and to remove the
    binding between virtual desktops and activities, zoom out of your
    current desktop again and deactivate <guimenu>Different Activity for
    Each Desktop</guimenu> in the Plasma configuration dialog.
   </para>
   <procedure id="pro.kde.cust.desk.ssaver">
    <title>Configuring the Screen Saver</title>
    <indexterm>
     <primary>KDE</primary>
     <secondary>configuring</secondary>
     <tertiary>screen saver</tertiary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
     &productnamereg; comes with predefined screen saver settings that you
     can adjust.
    </para>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the Personal Settings from the main menu by selecting
      <menuchoice> <guimenu>Favorites</guimenu> <guimenu>Configure
      Desktop</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      On the <guimenu>General</guimenu> tab, select
      <guimenu>Desktop</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the dialog that opens, click <guimenu>Screen Saver</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the list of screen savers, click a screen saver to see a preview in
      the right side of the dialog.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_kcontrol_screen.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_kcontrol_screen.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Setup</guimenu> to adjust options like speed or shapes.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      You can also choose to view a blank screen instead or to let KDE start
      a random screen saver. Find these options at the end of the screen
      saver list.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Under <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>, determine after how long a time of
      inactivity the screen saver should start and whether a password is
      required to unlock the screen after the screen saver has started.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to apply the changes and close the
      configuration dialog.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.kde.cust.desk.panel">
   <title>Panel</title>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>KDE</primary>
    <secondary>configuring</secondary>
    <tertiary>panel</tertiary>
   </indexterm>
   <para>
    You can customize the KDE panel according to your preferences.
    Applications and widgets can be added to the quick launch area or the
    system tray in the main panel or to additional panels. Panel elements
    and additional panels can be moved to different places or be completely
    removed at any time.
   </para>
   <procedure id="proc.kde.cust.conf.panel">
    <title>Customizing the Panel</title>
    <step id="step.kde.cust.panel.move">
     <para>
      Right-click an empty patch in the panel and select <guimenu>Panel
      Settings</guimenu> to access any panel options. Conversely, click the
      cashew icon at the end of the panel. The panel changes view and shows
      its configurations options.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_move_panel.png" width="85%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="kde_move_panel.png" width="50%" format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
     <para>
      If the menu item and the icon are not available, your desktop objects
      are probably locked. To unlock, right-click and select <guimenu>Unlock
      Widgets</guimenu> first.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To move panel objects to a different place within the panel, hover the
      mouse cursor over the respective panel object (for example, program
      icon, pager, task manager, system tray). The mouse cursor turns into a
      crosslines-like form. Move the cursor to the desired position in the
      panel, then click again to fix the object in the new position.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To change the panel width, click and drag the small arrow icons at the
      far left and right end of the settings panel.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To change the panel height, click the <guimenu>Height</guimenu> button
      and move the mouse cursor to the desired end location.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To place the panel at different sides of the screen use the
      <guimenu>Screen Edge</guimenu> button. Drag and drop the panel to the
      preferred location.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      If you need additional widgets on your panel, add them with the
      <guimenu>Add Widgets...</guimenu> button as described in
      <xref linkend="step.proc.kde.cust.add.widgets"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To remove program icons or widgets from the panel, right-click the
      unwanted object and select the menu item to remove the icon or widget.
     </para>
     <para>
      The icons in the system tray usually belong to applications running in
      the background. Therefore you can only remove those icons if you close
      those applications (right-click the icon and select
      <guimenu>Quit</guimenu>).
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To prevent the panel and widgets from being moved accidentally, use
      <guimenu>Lock Widgets</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      For additional configurations options like alignment and functions
      (like auto hide), click <guimenu>More Settings...</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      If all panel changes are according to your wishes, close the settings
      panel with the red close button on the right side.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
<!--taroth 081124: excluding for now - no time left to update-->
<!-- <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  href="kde_customizing_session_xgl.xml"/>-->
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="kde_custom_hw_i.xml"/>
 <sect1 id="sec.kde.cust.system">
  <title>Configuring Behavior and System Aspects</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>KDE</primary>
   <secondary>configuring</secondary>
   <tertiary>behavior</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>KDE</primary>
   <secondary>configuring</secondary>
   <tertiary>system</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

<!--<para>With the Personal Settings you can not only modify the appearance of
   objects, but also change the behavior of some components. In the following,
   find some examples.</para>
  <procedure id="pro.kde.cust.behav.cursor">
   <title>Changing the Cursor Behavior</title>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>KDE</primary>
    <secondary>configuring</secondary>
    <tertiary>cursor</tertiary>
   </indexterm>
   <para>If you want to deactivate the bouncing cursor that shows when
    starting an application from the graphical user interface, proceed as
    follows:</para>
   <step>
    <para>Open the Personal Settings and select <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Appearance &amp; Themes</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Launch Feedback</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>. </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>From the drop-down list, select another option for <guimenu>Busy
      Cursor</guimenu>.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to apply the changes and close the
     configuration dialog.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>You can set a number of mouse options in the Personal Settings, from
   cursor themes to acceleration and double-click intervals. You can also
   change the default Linux behavior (use single mouse-click to open files or
   folders) to a double-click option (like in Microsoft Windows). </para>-->

  <procedure id="pro.kde.cust.system.defaultapps">
   <title>Changing Default Applications</title>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>KDE</primary>
    <secondary>configuring</secondary>
    <tertiary>applications, default</tertiary>
   </indexterm>
   <para>
    There are certain default applications defined in KDE: For example, when
    you click an e-mail address, KMail starts.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     To change this behavior and set your preferred Web browser or e-mail
     client as default, open the Personal Settings and click
     <guimenu>Default Applications</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To change the Web browser:
    </para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       In the list of components, select <guimenu>Web Browser</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select <guimenu>Open http and https URLs in the following
       browser</guimenu> and click the browse button beneath.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       A dialog opens, showing the main menu structure. Select the Web
       browser to set as default and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. The
       component chooser now shows the selected application in the display
       field.
      </para>
      <informalfigure>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
         <imagedata fileref="kde_kcontrol_defaultapps.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
         <imagedata fileref="kde_kcontrol_defaultapps.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To change the e-mail client:
    </para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       In the list of components, select <guimenu>Email Client</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select <guimenu>Use a different email client</guimenu> and click the
       browse button.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       A dialog showing the main menu structure opens. Select the e-mail
       client to set as default and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. The
       component chooser now shows the selected application in the display
       field.
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If desired, change other default applications for KDE, like the
     application for the terminal window or the instant messenger client.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     When all options are set according to your wishes, click
     <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure id="pro.kde.cust.system.fileass">
   <title>Changing File Associations</title>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>KDE</primary>
    <secondary>configuring</secondary>
    <tertiary>file associations</tertiary>
   </indexterm>
   <para>
    Similar to setting the default Web browser or e-mail application, you
    can change file associations in KDE. File associations determine which
    application should be used to open a specific file type.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open the Personal Settings, click the <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> tab
     and select <guimenu>File Associations</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To search for an extension, enter the extension in <guimenu>Find File
     Type or File Name Pattern</guimenu>. Only file types with a matching
     file pattern appear in the list. For example, to modify the application
     for *.png files, enter <command>png</command> in <guimenu>Find File
     Type or File Name Pattern</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Known Types</guimenu> list, click the file type to open
     the setting dialog for this file type. You can change the icon,
     filename patterns, description, and the order of the applications.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_kcontrol_fileass.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_kcontrol_fileass.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
     If your tool is not listed, click <guimenu>Add</guimenu> in
     <guimenu>Application Preference Order</guimenu> then select the program
     for the file type.
    </para>
    <para>
     To change the order of the list entries, click the program to move.
     Give it a higher or lower priority by clicking <guimenu>Move
     Up</guimenu> or <guimenu>Move Down</guimenu>. The application listed at
     the top is used by default when you click a file of this type.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     When all options are set according to your wishes, click
     <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure id="pro.kde.cust.system.regional">
   <title>Adjusting Regional Settings</title>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>KDE</primary>
    <secondary>configuring</secondary>
    <tertiary>settings, regional</tertiary>
   </indexterm>
   <para>
    To adjust settings such as time and date format, number format, or
    currency, select the desired country as the default country in KDE. If
    more than one system language is installed on your computer, you can
    also select the different languages in which KDE should show the
    graphical user interface and application interfaces.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     To set your default country options, open the Personal Settings and
     select <guimenu>Regional &amp; Language</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_kcontrol_lang.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_kcontrol_lang.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Locale</guimenu> tab, click <guimenu>Change</guimenu>
     next to the <guimenu>Country or Region</guimenu> entry. In the dialog
     that opens, select the region and country you want to set as default in
     KDE and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Number, date and time formats are automatically adjusted to the new
     country's default values that are shown in the display field at the
     bottom of the <guimenu>Locale</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If you need to make further adjustments for those, click the relevant
     tabs and set the options according to your wishes.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If more than one language is installed on your system (as secondary
     languages with &yast;) and you want to change the graphical interface
     of KDE to a different language, click <guimenu>Add Language</guimenu>
     on the <guimenu>Locale</guimenu> tab. This opens a list of languages
     currently installed on your system.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the language for the graphical user interface. The new language
     is now shown at the top position in the <guimenu>Language</guimenu>
     list.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To confirm the changes, click <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>. All newly
     started applications or desktop objects now appear in the new language.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To switch to another language, re-sort the languages in the
     <guimenu>Languages</guimenu> list until the desired language is at the
     top position and apply your changes.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>KDE</primary>
    <secondary>session manager</secondary>
   </indexterm>
   KDE runs a session manager that starts after your username and password
   are authenticated by the login process. It lets you save the status of a
   certain session and return to that status the next time you log in. For
   example, it can automatically start the applications that you were
   running in the most recent session or when you manually saved a session.
   It can save and restore the following settings:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Appearance and behavior settings (such as fonts, colors, and mouse
     settings).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Applications that you were running (such as a file manager or &ooo;).
    </para>
    <note>
     <title>Saving and Restoring Applications</title>
     <para>
      You cannot save and restore applications that Session Manager does not
      manage. For example, if you start the vi editor from the command line
      in a terminal window, Session Manager cannot restore your editing
      session.
     </para>
    </note>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <procedure id="pro.kde.cust.system.session">
   <title>Adjusting the Session Handling</title>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>KDE</primary>
    <secondary>configuring</secondary>
    <tertiary>settings, session</tertiary>
   </indexterm>
   <step>
    <para>
     To change the session handling options, open the Personal Settings and
     on the <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> tab, click <guimenu>Session
     Manager</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     By default, Session Manager restores the applications that were running
     when you logged out from the previous session, enabling an automatic
     start of these applications.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To be able to save a certain session manually and restore this session
     each time you log in to KDE, select <guimenu>Restore manually saved
     sessions</guimenu>. This adds a new menu item, <guimenu>Save
     Session</guimenu>, to your main menu. After a session is saved, KDE
     automatically restores the saved session on each login.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To start with a <quote>fresh</quote> session each time you log in,
     select <guimenu>Start with an empty session</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To change the default options that appear when logging out, adjust the
     relevant options in the <guimenu>General</guimenu> and <guimenu>Default
     Leave Option</guimenu> groups.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> to confirm your changes.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure id="pro.kde.cust.system.autostart">
   <title>Starting Programs Automatically</title>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>KDE</primary>
    <secondary>configuring</secondary>
    <tertiary>autostart</tertiary>
   </indexterm>
   <para>
    Apart from the applications from the last session that are restored by
    the Session Manager, you can configure which applications should be
    always be started after login.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open the Personal Settings and on the <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> tab,
     click <guimenu>Autostart</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To add an application, click <guimenu>Add Program</guimenu> and from
     the menu structure, select the program you want to start automatically.
    </para>
    <para>
     To add a shell script, click <guimenu>Add Script</guimenu> and click
     the <guimenu>Open File Dialog</guimenu> icon in the next window to
     select the script from the file system. The program or script is added
     to the list and you can view and change the <guimenu>Status</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_kcontrol_autostart.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_kcontrol_autostart.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> to confirm your changes. When logging in
     the next time, the applications and scripts start automatically.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
