<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.network">
 <title>Accessing Network Resources</title>
 <indexterm id="idx.files.shared"
  class="startofrange">
  <primary>files</primary>
  <secondary>shared</secondary>
 </indexterm>
 <indexterm>
  <primary>networks</primary>
  <secondary>files</secondary>
 </indexterm>
 <para>
  From your desktop, you can access files and directories or certain
  services on remote hosts or make your own files and directories available
  to other users in your network. &productnamereg; offers various different
  ways of accessing and creating network shared resources:
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Network Browsing</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Your file managers, Dolphin or Konqueror, let you browse your network
     for shared resources and services. Learn more about this in
     <xref linkend="sec.network.accshare"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Sharing Folders in Mixed Environments</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Using Dolphin or Konqueror, configure your files and folders to share
     with other members in your network. Make your data readable or writable
     for users from any Windows or Linux workstation. Learn more about this
     in <xref linkend="sec.network.smbshare"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Managing Windows Files</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &productname; can be configured to integrate into an existing Windows
     network. Your Linux machine then behaves like a Windows client. It
     takes all account information from the Active Directory domain
     controller, just as Windows clients do. Learn more about this in
     <xref
      linkend="sec.network.ad.data"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
<!--<varlistentry>
   <term>Configuring and Accessing a Windows Network Printer</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <indexterm>
      <primary>networks</primary>
      <secondary>printers</secondary>
     </indexterm> You can configure a Windows network printer through
     the Personal Settings in KDE 4 . Learn how to configure this in
      <xref linkend="sec.network.ad.printer"/>.</para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>-->
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Configuring Shortcuts to Network Folders</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     By creating shortcuts to remote network folders (FTP, WebDAV, Windows
     Network Drives, and SSH), interacting with them can be greatly
     simplified. Learn how to configure this in
     <xref
      linkend="sec.network.netattach"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry os="osuse">
   <term>Configuring a Small Web Server</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If you need a simple way to share information with others, set up a
     lean Web server. Learn how to do this in
     <xref
      linkend="sec.network.kpf"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <note>
  <title>Network Share Support in Dolphin</title>
  <para>
   Dolphin is KDE 4's default file manager and most of the network functions
   described in this chapter are already integrated. However not all of them
   might work flawlessly&mdash;if in doubt, try using Konqueror instead.
  </para>
 </note>
 <sect1 id="sec.network.general">
  <title>General Notes on File Sharing and Network Browsing</title>

  <para>
   Whether and to what extent you can use file sharing and network browsing
   on your machine and in your network highly depends on the network
   structure and on the configuration of your machine. Before setting up
   either of them, contact your system administrator to make sure that your
   network structure supports this feature and to check whether your
   company's security policies permit it.
  </para>

  <para>
   Network browsing, be it SMB browsing for Windows shares or SLP browsing
   for remote services, relies heavily on the machine's ability to send
   broadcast messages to all clients in the network. These messages and the
   clients' replies to them enable your machine to detect any available
   shares or services. For broadcasts to work effectively, your machine must
   be part of the same subnet as all other machines it is querying. If
   network browsing does not work on your machine or the detected shares and
   services do not match with what you expected, contact your system
   administrator to make sure that you are connected to the appropriate
   subnet.
  </para>

  <para>
   To allow network browsing, your machine needs to keep several network
   ports open to send and receive network messages that provide details on
   the network and the availability of shares and services. The standard
   &productname; is configured for tight security and has a firewall up and
   running that protects your machine against the Internet. To adjust the
   firewall configuration, you would either need to ask your system
   administrator to open a certain set of ports to the network or to tear
   down the firewall entirely according to your company's security policy.
   If you try to browse a network with a restrictive firewall running on
   your machine, Dolphin warns you about security restrictions not allowing
   it to query the network.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.network.accshare">
  <title>Accessing Network Shares</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>networks</primary>
   <secondary>shares</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>networks</primary>
   <secondary>browsing</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
   Networking workstations can be set up to share folders. Typically, files
   and folders are marked to let remote users access them. These are called
   <emphasis>network shares</emphasis>. If your system is configured to
   access network shares, you can use your file manager to access and browse
   them just as easily as if they were located on your local machine. Having
   read or write access to the shared folders depends on the permissions
   granted to you by the owner of the shares.
  </para>

  <para>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>Dolphin</primary>
    <secondary>network shares</secondary>
   </indexterm>
   To access network shares, start Dolphin and click the
   <guimenu>Network</guimenu> icon in the <guimenu>Places</guimenu> panel or
   enter <command>remote:/</command> in the location bar. Dolphin then opens
   a virtual folder that displays the network share types that you can
   access. Click a network resource type then click the network share to
   access. You might be required to authenticate to the resource by
   providing a username and password.
  </para>

  <figure
   id="fig.network.browse">
   <title>Network Browsing</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="networkplaces.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="networkplaces.png" width="75%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.network.smbshare">
  <title>Sharing Folders in Mixed Environments</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>Samba</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
   Sharing and exchanging documents is a must-have in corporate
   environments. Dolphin offers you file sharing with Samba, which makes
   your files and folders available to both Linux and Windows users. For
   information on how to install and set up Samba, refer to
   <xref
    linkend="cha.samba"/>. After you have installed Samba and set
   up a server, you can configure the folders to share with Dolphin. Dolphin
   then writes its configuration to a paragraph in the main Samba
   configuration file at <filename>/etc/samba/smb.conf</filename>.
  </para>

<?dbfo-need height="20em"?>

  <procedure>
   <title>Configuring Samba File Shares with Dolphin</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open Dolphin.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Home</guimenu>, right-click the window background and
     then select <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> from the context menu.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> dialog, click the
     <guimenu>Share</guimenu> tab. If file sharing is not yet enabled, you
     are alerted to this on the tab. To enable file sharing or select the
     files to share, click <guimenu>Configure File Sharing</guimenu> and
     enter the &rootuser; password.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To enable or disable file sharing, select or deselect <guimenu>Enable
     Local Network File Sharing</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Enabling File Sharing</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="share_select_folder.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="share_select_folder.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the appropriate sharing option: <guimenu>Simple
     Sharing</guimenu> or <guimenu>Advanced Sharing</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To limit the number of users allowed to share folders to certain
     groups, click <guimenu>Allowed Users</guimenu>, select <guimenu>Only
     users of a certain group are allowed to share folders</guimenu>, click
     <guimenu>Choose Group</guimenu>, and select the appropriate group from
     the list in the window that opens. Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to close
     that window.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>File Sharing</guimenu> dialog, add the folder to share
     to the list of shared items by clicking <guimenu>Add</guimenu> at the
     bottom of the dialog and specifying the folder's exact path.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Detailed Sharing Options</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="share_select_specify.png" width="50%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="share_select_specify.png" width="35%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Activate <guimenu>Share with Samba</guimenu> to enable Samba file
     sharing. If needed, apply some fine-tuning to the Samba options:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Name</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Specify a name other than the preset default.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Public/Writable</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Determine which kind of access to grant others to your share. You
        can grant users full read and write access or limit their access to
        read-only.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Apply your settings and leave the file sharing dialog with
     <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The folder now appears in Dolphin with a globe icon.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Shared Folder: Music</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="share_success.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="share_success.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
     To revoke the share, enter the file sharing dialog again and remove the
     folder from the list of shared items. The folder then appears without a
     globe icon.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   Other members of your network can reach your share by entering
   <filename>smb:/</filename> in the location bar of Dolphin and clicking
   the appropriate workgroup icon and hostname.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Samba Domain Browsing</title>
   <para>
    Samba domain browsing only works if your system's firewall is configured
    accordingly. Either disable the firewall entirely or assign the browsing
    interface to the internal firewall zone. Ask your system administrator
    about how to proceed. This procedure is described in more detail in 
    <xref linkend="sec.security.ad.config"/>.
   </para>
  </important>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.network.ad.data">
  <title>Managing Windows Files</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>Active Directory</primary>
   <secondary>accessing data</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para> With your &productname; machine being an Active Directory client as
   described in <xref linkend="sec.security.ad.config"/>, you can browse, view, and
   manipulate data located on Windows servers. The following examples are just
   the most prominent ones: </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Browsing Windows Files with Dolphin</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use Dolphin's <filename>smb:/</filename> browsing option to browse
      your Windows data.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Viewing Windows Data with Dolphin</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use Dolphin to display the contents of your Windows user folder just
      as you would for displaying a Linux directory. Create new files and
      folders on the Windows server.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Manipulating Windows Data with KDE Applications</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      KDE applications, such as the Kate text editor, allow you to open
      files on the Windows server, manipulate them, and save them to the
      Windows server.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Single-Sign-On</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      KDE applications (including Dolphin) support Single-Sign-On, which
      means that to access other Windows resources, such as Web servers,
      proxy servers, or groupware servers like MS Exchange, you do not need
      to reauthenticate. Authentication against all these is handled
      silently in the background after you provide your username and
      password on login.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <procedure>
   <title>Accessing Windows Data with Dolphin</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap>
     </keycombo> and enter <filename>smb:/</filename> or start Dolphin and
     enter <filename>smb:/</filename> in the location bar.
    </para>
    <para>
     Dolphin displays all Samba workgroups and domains that could be found
     in your network.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the icon of the workgroup or domain of your AD server.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Browsing Data on the AD Server</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="ad_server_browse.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="ad_server_browse.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the <guimenu>Users</guimenu> folder and select your personal user
     folder icon. The contents of your <guimenu>My Documents</guimenu>
     folder are displayed.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   To create folders in your Windows user folder, proceed as you would when
   creating a Linux folder:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Right-click the background of the Dolphin folder view to open the menu.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Create New</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Folder</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the new folder's name when prompted to do so.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   To create a file on the AD server, proceed as described in the following
   example for the KWrite text editor.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap>
     </keycombo> and enter <command>kwrite</command>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter your text.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Editing a Text File with KWrite</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="ad_kwrite_remote.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="ad_kwrite_remote.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To save the newly created text, select <guimenu>Save as</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the <guimenu>Network</guimenu> icon in the
     <guimenu>Places</guimenu> view and select <guimenu>SMB
     Shares</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Saving a File to a Remote Windows Folder</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="ad_kwrite_save.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="ad_kwrite_save.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Navigate to your Windows folder.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the filename and click <guimenu>Save</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The file is saved on the Windows server.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   Make use of Dolphin's Single-Sign-On support, as in the following
   example&mdash;Web access to your MS Exchange mailbox:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Make sure that you have a valid MS Exchange account under your current
     Windows user identity.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Request the Exchange server's address from your system administrator.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap>
     </keycombo> and enter
     <command>dolphin&nbsp;<option>http://<replaceable>address_exchange_server</replaceable></option></command>.
    </para>
    <para>
     You are logged in to your Exchange account without having to
     reauthenticate.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Write or read your e-mails and log out as usual.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
<!--taroth 081212: couldn't find out how if and how this works for 11.1 -
  commenting for now-->
<!--<sect1 id="sec.network.ad.printer">
  <title>Configuring and Accessing a Windows Network Printer</title>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>networks</primary>
   <secondary>printers</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>printing</primary>
   <secondary>network printer</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>Being part of a corporate network and authenticating against a
   Windows Active Directory server, you can access corporate resources,
   such as printers. KDE allows you to configure printing from your
   Linux client to a Windows network printer.</para>

  <para>To configure a Windows network printer for use through your
   Linux workstation, proceed as follows:</para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>Start the KDE Control Center from the main menu.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Select <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Peripherals</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Printers</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>. </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Adding a Printer</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="winprinter_pseudo.png" width="75%"
        format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="winprinter_pseudo.png" width="75%"
        format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Select <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Add</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Add Special (pseudo) Printer</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>. </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Adding Printer Details</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="winprinter_details.png" width="60%"
        format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="winprinter_details.png" width="50%"
        format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Enter the printer's name, a short description, and its
     location.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Enter a command line similar to the following example in
      <guimenu>Command Settings</guimenu>:</para>
    <screen>
smbclient //<replaceable>domain</replaceable>/<replaceable>printer</replaceable> -k -d 0 -c 'put %in' &gt; /dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1
</screen>
    <para>Replace <replaceable>domain</replaceable> and
      <replaceable>printer</replaceable> with the exact values matching
     your setup.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Check <guimenu>Enable output file</guimenu> and select
      <guimenu>application/postscript</guimenu> to pipe all your print
     jobs to a PostScript file.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> Leave the printer configuration with
    <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Leave the KDE Control Center with <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Quit</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>. </para>
    <para>The printer is ready for use.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>To print to the Windows network printer configured above, just
   select it from the list of available printers in KPrinter.</para>
 </sect1>-->
 <sect1 id="sec.network.netattach">
  <title>Configuring Shortcuts to Network Folders</title>

  <para>
   With KNetAttach, you can also add new network folders to this view by
   clicking <guimenu>Add a Network Folder</guimenu> in a Dolphin
   <filename>remote:/</filename> view. A wizard opens where you can select
   the type of network folder to access and enter the details, such as a
   name for the network folder, the address of the server (either the IP
   address or domain name), the login name, the port, and the path to folder
   to access.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.network.knetattach">
   <title>Adding a Network Folder</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="knetattach.png" width="50%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="knetattach.png" width="50%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   After finishing, you can access the network share in Dolphin by clicking
   <guimenu>Network</guimenu> in the <guimenu>Places</guimenu> panel.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you add a network folder in this way, you can also access this folder
   easily when opening or saving a file from a KDE application. If you click
   <guimenu>Network</guimenu> in the left-hand bar of an <guimenu>Open
   File</guimenu> or a <guimenu>Save File</guimenu> dialog, the network
   folder you added appears.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>Linking to Network Shares on the Desktop</title>
   <para>
    For quick access to network shares, you can also create links to these
    resources on your desktop. To do so, select the desired resource in
    Dolphin and drag it onto your desktop while keeping the left mouse
    button pressed. From the context menu, select <guimenu>Icon</guimenu> or
    <guimenu>Folder View</guimenu> to either display the folder as icon or
    in the folder view, directly displaying the contents of the directory.
   </para>
  </tip>

<!--taroth 2010-03-25: need this indexterm twice and profiled (the same is 
   included in the next section that is profiled for osuse), otherwise PDF
   refuses to build --><indexterm os="sled;sles" startref="idx.files.shared" class="endofrange"/>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.network.kpf" os="osuse">
  <title>Configuring and Using a Small Web Server</title><indexterm>

   <primary>Web servers</primary>

  <secondary>Kepas</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Kepas is a file transfer utility that lets you transfer files (or other
   contents such as Klipper or KNotes entries) to your friends. You can also
   use it to set up and monitor a small public file server. To use Kepas,
   install the <systemitem class="resource">kepas</systemitem> package with
   &yast; or zypper. You can then either add Kepas as widget to your KDE 4
   desktop or run Kepas from the system tray, both provide the same
   functions.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Security Considerations</title>
   <para>
    When setting up a public file server with Kepas, there are no access
    restrictions to shared files. Whatever you select for sharing is
    available to anyone.
   </para>
   <para>
    Before doing so, check with your system administrator whether your
    company's security policies allow to set up a public file server. Also
    in a private environment, you should only set up a public file server if
    your network is protected by an outer firewall. Otherwise you risk
    accidentally leaking sensitive information to the Web.
   </para>
   <para>
    In addition to that, any Web server is a potential target for hackers.
   </para>
  </important>

  <para>
   Kepas is designed to be used for sharing files with friends, not to act
   as a fully-fledged Web server like Apache. Kepas is the successor of kpf
   that was primarily conceived as an easy way to share files with others
   while chatting on IRC (Internet Relay Chat, or chat rooms).
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Setting Up a Public File Server with Kepas</title>
   <para>
    To add Kepas to your system tray, press <keycombo>
    <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter
    <command>kepas</command>. If you want to add a Kepas widget to your
    desktop instead, proceed as outlined in
    <xref linkend="proc.kde.cust.desk.add.widgets"/>.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     To set up a file server, left-click the Kepas widget (or right-click
     the Kepas icon in the system tray) and select <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Public Server</guimenu> <guimenu>New Server</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Specify the directory containing the files you want to share then click
     <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. Typically the <filename>public_html</filename>
     folder in your home directory is designed for that purpose.
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>Public Availability of Sensitive Information</title>
     <para>
      When sharing a directory, <emphasis>all</emphasis> files in the
      directory and its subdirectories are made publicly available,
      including hidden files (files that start with a dot) and symbolic
      links.
     </para>
     <para>
      Be careful not to share sensitive information, such as passwords,
      cryptographic keys, your address book, or documents private to your
      organization. Make sure that any symbolic links included do not point
      outside your published folder, because that would give others access
      to areas of your system that are not intended for public viewing.
     </para>
    </important>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="kepas_seldir.png" width="60%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="kepas_seldir.png" width="50%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     You can keep the default values for the <guimenu>Listening
     Port</guimenu>, the <guimenu>Bandwidth Limit</guimenu> and the
     <guimenu>Server Name</guimenu> in the next steps (they can also be
     altered later, if needed).
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> to publish the availability of the
     newly created file server in the network.
    </para>
   </step>
<!--taroth 090901: the public_html directory shows the worl icon by default, 
        other directories only show the world icon when shared-->
<!--<step>
    <para>If you open the parent directory in Dolphin's icon view, the shared
     directory is now marked with a world icon.</para>
   </step>-->
  </procedure>

  <para>
   To make a file available to people with whom you are chatting online,
   just copy the file into your <filename>public_html</filename> folder and
   announce to those listening that your file is now available at
   <filename>http://<replaceable>servername</replaceable>:8001/<replaceable>filename</replaceable></filename>
   (rather than sending them each an e-mail with the file attached).
  </para>

  <para>
   To display an overview of all contents published on your public file
   server, the others only need to enter the following URL into their
   browsers:
   <filename>http://<replaceable>servername</replaceable>:8001</filename>.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Published Contents</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kepas_connect.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kepas_connect.png" width="60%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   To revoke the public file server, right-click the system tray icon (or
   left-click the Kepas widget) and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File
   Server</guimenu> <guimenu>Configured Server</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Remove</guimenu> </menuchoice>. If you want to change the file
   server settings (like port, bandwidth limit, server name or if to follow
   symbolic links or not), instead select <menuchoice> <guimenu>File
   Server</guimenu> <guimenu>Configured Server</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> </menuchoice> from the context menu to access
   the configuration dialog.
  </para>

  <indexterm
   startref="idx.files.shared" class="endofrange"/>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
