<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.kerry">
 <title>Searching with Kerry</title>
 <remark>taroth 2010-03-29: strigi/nepomuk does not work with SLED 11 SP1 RC1 as
  it needs the sesame back-end (see bnc#548007) which is not available on the
  SLED media, therefore still sticking to kerry which is still available
 </remark>
 <para>
  Kerry is a KDE front-end for the Beagle search tool, which indexes your
  personal information space to help you find whatever you need. You can use
  Kerry to find documents, e-mails, Web history, IM/ITC conversations,
  source code, images, music files, applications, and much more.
 </para>
 <para>
  Because Kerry is a front-end to Beagle, it needs the beagle daemon to be
  functional. Kerry and Beagle can now index many KDE-specific sources of
  information, such as Kopete conversations, Konqueror history, or KMail
  messages. The result is a smooth integration into the KDE environment
  through the Kerry interface. Find more about Beagle in
  <xref linkend="cha.gnome.beagle"/>.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="cha.kerry.search">
  <title>Searching Using Kerry</title>

  <procedure>
   <para>
    To find data using the Kerry tool, follow these steps:
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Press <keycombo><keycap function="alt"/><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>
     and enter <command>kerry</command> to start Kerry and to open the Kerry
     Beagle Search window. Alternatively, open the search window by
     left-clicking on the Kerry applet icon (a dog's head) in the system
     tray.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the term to find in <guimenu>Search</guimenu>. To quickly clear
     the previously entered text, press the black arrow on the left.
    </para>
    <para>
     The search is not case-sensitive. To search for optional terms, use the
     <emphasis>OR</emphasis> keyword (in uppercase). For example,
     <emphasis>Mars OR Venus</emphasis> finds all data containing any
     occurrence of Mars, Venus, or both. To exclude search terms, use a
     minus symbol (&ndash;) in front of them. For example, <replaceable>Mars
     -Venus</replaceable> finds all data containing any occurrence of Mars
     but without any occurrence of Venus. To search for an exact phrase,
     enclose the phrase in quotes. If you want to include only certain file
     type in results, specify the filename extension with
     <emphasis>ext:</emphasis>. For example, <replaceable>Mars
     ext:xml</replaceable> finds xml files containing Mars.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the scope of the search in the <guimenu>Show</guimenu> section
     of the right panel. To search all the indexed content, choose
     <guimenu>Everything</guimenu>. However, you can limit the search only
     to indexed <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>,
     <guimenu>Contacts</guimenu>, <guimenu>Office Documents</guimenu>,
     instant messenger <guimenu>Conversations</guimenu>,
     <guimenu>Images</guimenu>, <guimenu>Media</guimenu> files, <guimenu>Web
     Pages</guimenu>, or <guimenu>File/Path Names</guimenu> by clicking the
     appropriate item in the panel. You can change the scope before or after
     the search is performed.
    </para>
    <para>
     Change the sort order of results in the <guimenu>Sort By</guimenu>
     section of the right panel. To sort results by type, click
     <guimenu>Type</guimenu>. Sorting by <guimenu>Date</guimenu>,
     <guimenu>Name</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Relevance</guimenu> is also
     possible. You can change the sort order before or after the search is
     completed.
    </para>
    <para>
     You can limit the results by date of last modification. To show all
     results regardless of the date of the last modification, click
     <guimenu>Any Date</guimenu> in the right panel. You can show items
     modified today, since yesterday, this week, month, or year by clicking
     the appropriate item in the right panel. You can change this before or
     after the search is performed.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Press <keycap>Enter</keycap> or click the icon to the right of the
     search field to start the search. Results are displayed in the main
     area of the window.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   Results are displayed in a window, sorted according to your settings.
   Click any item to activate it. To open a folder containing a found file
   instead of the file itself, click the name of the folder to the right of
   the filename. To display more information about an item, click the icon
   with the <guimenu>i</guimenu> on the left.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can change the scope of the search, sort order, or limitation by date
   at any time by clicking appropriate item in the panel on the right.
  </para>

  <para>
   Use <guimenu>Previous results</guimenu> and <guimenu>Next
   results</guimenu> to move between pages of the result list. The number of
   items found is shown in the bottom part of the window.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="cha.kerry.conf">
  <title>Configuring Kerry</title>

  <para>
   You can configure Kerry by right-clicking its icon in the tray and
   choosing <guimenu>Configure Kerry</guimenu> or by clicking
   <guimenu>Configure</guimenu> in Kerry's main window. The configuration
   dialog has four tabs.
  </para>

  <para>
   On the <guimenu>Search</guimenu> tab, you can change the <guimenu>Default
   result sort order</guimenu>, <guimenu>Maximum number of results
   displayed</guimenu> on one page, or shortcuts for activating Kerry Beagle
   Search.
  </para>

  <para>
   On the <guimenu>Indexing</guimenu> tab, set whether the Beagle indexing
   service should be started automatically and if data should be indexed
   while the computer is operating on battery power. You can also determine
   which folders should be indexed by Kerry Beagle Search and which folders
   should not be indexed at all. See <xref linkend="cha.kerry.conf.index"/>
   and <xref
    linkend="cha.kerry.conf.noindex"/> for detailed
   instructions.
  </para>

  <para>
   On the <guimenu>Backends</guimenu> tab, choose which of the available
   Beagle back-ends should be enabled. To disable a back-end, uncheck it.
   For example, if you do not want your Kopete conversations be indexed by
   Kerry Beagle, uncheck the <guimenu>Kopete</guimenu> back-end.
  </para>

  <para>
   On the <guimenu>Daemon Status</guimenu> tab, check the status of Beagle
   daemon. You can stop or start the daemon manually here. To use Kerry
   Beagle Search functionality, the daemon must be running.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="cha.kerry.conf.index">
   <title>Indexing More Directories</title>
   <para>
    By default, Kerry indexes your home folder only. If you do not want your
    home folder to be indexed, uncheck the <guimenu>Index my home
    folder</guimenu> option on the <guimenu>Indexing</guimenu> tab of the
    Kerry configuration. To index more folders, follow these steps:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Right-click the Kerry icon in the tray and choose <guimenu>Configure
      Kerry</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>Indexing</guimenu> tab.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>Add</guimenu> button in the middle part
      (<guimenu>Index</guimenu>) of the tab.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the dialog that opens, choose the folder to index and click
      <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
<!--rwalter: removed step covered in next sect-->
    <step>
     <para>
      Press <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="cha.kerry.conf.noindex">
   <title>Preventing Files and Directories from Being Indexed</title>
   <para>
    To exclude some folders or files from being indexed by Kerry, follow
    these steps:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Right-click the Kerry icon in the tray and choose <guimenu>Configure
      Kerry</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>Indexing</guimenu> tab.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Add</guimenu> in the bottom part
      (<guimenu>Privacy</guimenu>) of the tab.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the dialog that opens, choose a folder not to index by selecting
      the <guimenu>Folder</guimenu> option. Specify the path to the folder
      in the text field or press the folder button and choose the folder in
      a file dialog.
     </para>
     <para>
      You can also specify files not to index by selecting <guimenu>File
      name pattern</guimenu> and specifying the file pattern.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Press <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
