<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.kde.kpowersave">
 <title>Controlling Your Desktop's Power Management</title>
 <indexterm>
  <primary>Power Management</primary>
 </indexterm>
 <para>
  In KDE 4, you can control power management functions supported by your
  system with just a few clicks on the desktop. You can choose between
  various power management profiles to match the tasks your system is
  facing. The <guimenu>Personal Settings</guimenu> hold a <guimenu>Power
  Management</guimenu> category, allowing you to configure detailed settings
  as described in <xref
   linkend="sec.kpowersave.configure"/>.
 </para>
 <para>
  Apart from power profiles that can be applied while you are interacting
  with your computer, there are also power saving functions (suspend modes)
  you can use instead of shutting down the computer completely during
  breaks.
 </para>
 <sect1
  id="sec.kpowersave.widget">
  <title>Using the Battery Monitor Widget</title>

  <para>
   If you are using mobile computers like a laptop, a widget in your panel
   displays the battery status and gives you access to power management
   functions. If the <guimenu>Battery Monitor</guimenu> widget is not
   displayed in your panel by default, add it manually. For more
   information, refer to <xref linkend="proc.kde.cust.desk.add.widgets"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   The widget allows you control the screen brightness when your system is
   running on battery power, to switch to a different power profile, or to
   trigger your system to enter a suspend mode. Click the panel icon to open
   the widget.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Battery Monitor Widget</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kde_battery_monitor.png" width="45%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kde_battery_monitor.png" width="55%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   Which suspend modes and power profiles are available depends on the power
   management abilities of your system and the profiles defined in the
   <guimenu>Personal Settings</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   The following suspend modes are widely available:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Sleep (Suspend to RAM)</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Pauses your computer without logging you out. All your data and the
      session data is saved to RAM. Bringing the system up again is faster
      than restoring a session from disk.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Hibernate (Suspend to Disk)</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Pauses your computer without logging you out. All your data and the
      session data is saved to disk before the system is laid to rest. It is
      thus protected against data loss should you lose power in the
      meantime. Waking the system up again is much faster than with a fresh
      boot.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   To manually suspend your computer, use the buttons in the widget or the
   suspend options on logging out (see
   <xref linkend="sec.kde.start.leave"/>). If supported by the system and
   configured accordingly, pressing sleep buttons on your machine or
   keyboard will also suspend your machine.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can configure your system to automatically switch to suspend mode
   after certain events like closing the lid (if you are using a laptop) or
   after a period of that time that the system has been idle. Refer to
   <xref linkend="sec.kpowersave.configure"/> for more information.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kpowersave.profiles">
  <title>Saving Power by Using Profiles</title>

  <para>
   Power management profiles let you adjust various power management
   parameters to the requirements of certain typical situations you are
   facing when using your machine. &productnamereg; ships with a set of four
   pre-configured profiles which you can adjust to your needs. To switch
   profiles, click the battery monitor panel icon and select a different
   <guimenu>Power Profile</guimenu>. The following profiles are available by
   default:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Performance</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Keep your machine running with full power and full speed to achieve
      maximum performance.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Presentation</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Disable any display power management and screen savers to make sure
      that your presentation is not interrupted by a blanked display or
      something similar.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Powersave</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Apply power management methods to make sure that your machine runs as
      long as possible when put on battery power instead of AC power.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Aggressive Powersave</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Apply stricter power management methods when the battery is at a low
      level. These include shorter idle intervals before triggering suspend
      events, reducing screen brightness, disabling 3D effects and using CPU
      scaling policies that preserve resources.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Xtreme Powersave</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Apply extreme power saving by reducing screen brightness even more and
      using stricter idle time and CPU scaling policies when the battery is
      already at warning level.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kpowersave.configure">
  <title>Configuring Power Management</title>

  <para>
   KDE 4 lets you adjust a number of power management settings: for example,
   when to trigger notifications or warnings, which power profile to use
   when running on battery, what to do when closing the laptop lid or
   pressing the power or sleep button.
  </para>

  <para>
   Access the configuration options from the main menu by selecting
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>Configure
   Desktop</guimenu><guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> <guimenu>Power
   Management</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Alternatively, click the battery
   monitor icon in the panel and click select <guimenu>More</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Power Management Settings</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="kde_power_management_main.png" width="90%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="kde_power_management_main.png" width="55%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   To get an overview of your system's power management abilities like
   supported suspend methods or CPU policies, click the
   <guimenu>Capabilities</guimenu> category on the left.
  </para>

  <para>
   In the following, find some examples of which aspects can be changed in
   the <guimenu>General Settings</guimenu> category and how to configure
   power management profiles.
  </para>

<?dbfo-need height="20em"?>

  <procedure id="pro.kpowersave.configure.settings">
   <title>Configuring General Settings</title>
   <para>
    To access the following options, click the <guimenu>General
    Settings</guimenu> entry on the left side of the power management
    configuration dialog.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Settings and Profiles</guimenu> group, decide if the
     screen should be locked after a suspend action, so that the user needs
     to type in his password when the machine resumes after a suspend.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Configure which notifications or warnings you want to receive for
     certain events (like low battery status), or if you want suspend
     actions to be executed immediately or only after a certain time
     interval.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In <guimenu>Profile Assignment</guimenu>, decide which power profiles
     should be applied by default when the system is running on AC power, on
     battery, or when the battery is low or at warning level.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Advanced Battery Settings</guimenu> if you want to
     fine-tune the battery levels that are regarded as low or critical or to
     define which action should be taken at a critical battery level.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     For detailed information about the available options, click
     <guimenu>Help</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If all options are set according to your wishes, click
     <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure id="pro.kpowersave.configure.profiles">
   <title>Configuring Power Management Profiles</title>
   <para>
    Apart from the general settings, you can adjust the default power
    management profiles or add new profiles in the <guimenu>Edit
    Profiles</guimenu> category. The list at the left show the available
    profiles.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select one of the profiles in the list to view or change the specific
     settings for that profile:
    </para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       In the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> group, decide which actions are
       taken when the lid of the laptop is closed or the
       <keycap>Power</keycap> or <keycap>Sleep</keycap> button is pressed.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       In the <guimenu>Screen</guimenu> group, configure how much the screen
       is dimmed and after how many minutes the display is turned off
       automatically.
      </para>
      <informalfigure>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
         <imagedata fileref="kde_power_management_profiles.png" width="90%" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
         <imagedata fileref="kde_power_management_profiles.png" width="55%" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>CPU and System</guimenu> to view or change which CPU
       to turn off (if supported by your machine) or to set the CPU
       frequency scaling policy for that profile.
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Use the icons at the bottom of the list of profiles if you want to add,
     delete, import or export power management profiles.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If all options are set according to your wishes, click
     <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.kpowersave.more" os="sled">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   For detailed and more technical information about power saving functions,
   see <xref
    linkend="cha.pmanage"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
