<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.kgraft" xml:lang="en">
<?suse-quickstart color="suse"?>
 <title>Live Patching the Linux Kernel Using &kg;</title>
 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
   </dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
      </dm:docmanager>
      <abstract>
        <para>
    This document describes the basic principles of the &kg; live
    patching technology and provides usage guidelines for the SLE Live
    Patching service.
   </para>
        <para>
    &kg; is a live patching technology for runtime patching of the Linux
    kernel, without stopping the kernel. This maximizes system uptime, and
    thus system availability, which is important for mission-critical
    systems. By allowing dynamic patching of the kernel, the technology also
    encourages users to install critical security updates without deferring
    them to a scheduled downtime.
   </para>
        <para>
    A &kg; patch is a kernel module, intended for replacing whole
    functions in the kernel. &kg; primarily offers in-kernel
    infrastructure for integration of the patched code with base kernel code
    at runtime.
   </para>
        <para>
    SLE Live Patching is a service provided on top of regular SUSE Linux
    Enterprise Server maintenance. &kg; patches distributed through SLE
    Live Patching supplement regular SLES maintenance updates. Common update
    stack and procedures can be used for SLE Live Patching deployment.
   </para>
      </abstract>
    </info>
    <sect1>
  <title>Advantages of &kg;</title>

  <para>
   Live kernel patching using &kg; is especially useful for quick
   response in emergencies (when serious vulnerabilities are known and
   should be fixed as soon as possible or there are serious system stability
   issues with a known fix). It is not used for scheduled updates where time
   is not critical.
  </para>

  <para>
   Typical use cases for &kg; include systems like memory databases with
   huge amounts of RAM, where boot-up times of 15 minutes or more are no
   exception, large simulations that need weeks or months without a restart,
   or infrastructure building blocks providing continuous service to a many
   consumers.
  </para>

  <para>
   The main advantage of &kg; is that it never requires stopping the
   kernel, not even for a short time period.
  </para>

  <para>
   A &kg; patch is a <filename>.ko</filename> kernel module in a KMP RPM
   package. It is inserted into the kernel using the
   <command>insmod</command> command when the RPM package is installed or
   updated. &kg; replaces whole functions in the kernel, even if they are
   being executed. An updated &kg; module can replace an existing patch
   if necessary.
  </para>

  <para>
   &kg; is also lean&mdash;it contains only a small amount of code,
   because it leverages other standard Linux technologies.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Low-level Function of &kg;</title>

  <para>
   &kg; uses the ftrace infrastructure to perform patching. The following
   describes the implementation on the x86-64 architecture.
  </para>

  <para>
   To patch a kernel function, &kg; needs some space at the start of the
   function to insert a jump to a new function. This space is allocated
   during kernel compilation by GCC with function profiling turned on. In
   particular, a 5-byte call instruction is injected to the start of kernel
   functions. When such instrumented kernel is booting, profiling calls are
   replaced by 5-byte NOP (no operation) instructions.
  </para>

  <para>
   After patching starts, the first byte is replaced by the INT3
   (breakpoint) instruction. This ensures atomicity of the 5-byte
   instruction replacement. The other four bytes are replaced by the address
   to the new function. Finally, the first byte is replaced by the JMP (long
   jump) opcode.
  </para>

  <para>
   Inter-processor non-maskable interrupts (IPI NMI) are used throughout the
   process to flush speculative decoding queues of other CPUs in the system.
   This allows switching to the new function without ever stopping the
   kernel, not even for a very short moment. The interruptions by IPI NMIs
   can be measured in microseconds and are not considered service
   interruptions as they happen while the kernel is running in any case.
  </para>

  <para>
   Callers are never patched. Instead, the callee's NOPs are replaced by a JMP
   to the new function. JMP instructions remain forever. This takes care of
   function pointers, including in structures, and does not require saving
   any old data for the possibility of un-patching.
  </para>

  <para>
   However, these steps alone would not be good enough: since the functions
   would be replaced non-atomically, a new fixed function in one part of the
   kernel could still be calling an old function elsewhere or vice versa. If
   the semantics of the function interfaces changed in the patch, chaos
   would ensue.
  </para>

  <para>
   Thus, until all functions are replaced, &kg; uses an approach based on
   trampolines and similar to RCU (read-copy-update), to ensure a consistent
   view of the world to each userspace thread, kernel thread and kernel
   interrupt. A per-thread flag is set on each kernel entry and exit. This
   way, an old function would always call another old function and a new
   function always a new one. Once all processes have the "new universe"
   flag set, patching is complete, trampolines can be removed and the code
   can operate at full speed without performance impact other than an
   extra-long jump for each patched function.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Installing &kg; Patches</title>

  <para>
   This section describes the activation of the SUSE Linux Enterprise Live
   Patching extension and the installation of &kg; patches.
  </para>

  <sect2>
   <title>Activation of SLE Live Patching</title>
   <para>
    To activate SLE Live Patching on your system, follow these steps:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      If your SLES system is not yet registered, register it. Registration
      can be done during the system installation or later using the
      &yast; <guimenu>Product Registration</guimenu> module
      (<command>yast2 registration</command>). After registration, click
      <guimenu>Yes</guimenu> to see the list of available online updates.
     </para>
     <para>
      If your SLES system is already registered, but SLE Live Patching is
      not yet activated, open the &yast; <guimenu>Product Registration</guimenu>
      module (<command>yast2 registration</command>) and
      click <guimenu>Select Extensions</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select <guimenu>SUSE Linux Enterprise Live Patching 12</guimenu> in
      the list of available extensions and click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Confirm the license terms and click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Enter the SLE Live Patching registration code and click
      <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Check the <guimenu>Installation Summary</guimenu> and selected
      <guimenu>Patterns</guimenu>. The pattern <systemitem>Live
      Patching</systemitem> should be selected for installation.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to complete the installation. This
      will install the base &kg; components on your system together with
      the initial live patch.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Updating System</title>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      SLE Live Patching updates are distributed in a form that allows using
      standard SLE update stack for patch application. The initial live
      patch can be updated using <command>zypper patch</command>, &yast;
      Online Update or equivalent method.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      The kernel is patched automatically during the package installation.
      However, invocations of the old kernel functions are not completely
      eliminated until all sleeping processes wake up and get out of the
      way. This can take a considerable amount of time. Despite this,
      sleeping processes that use the old kernel functions are not
      considered a security issue. Nevertheless, in the current version of
      &kg;, it is not possible to apply another &kg; patch until all
      processes cross the kernel-userspace boundary to use patched functions
      from the previous patch.
     </para>
     <para>
      To see the global status of patching, check the flag in
      <filename>/sys/kernel/kgraft/in_progress</filename>. The value
      <literal>1</literal> signifies the existence of sleeping processes
      that still need to be woken (the patching is still in progress). The
      value <literal>0</literal> signifies that all processes are using
      solely the patched functions and patching has finished already.
      Alternatively, use the <command>kgr status</command> command to obtain
      the same information.
     </para>
     <para>
      The flag can be checked on a per-process basis too. Check the number
      in
      <filename>/proc/<replaceable>process_number</replaceable>/kgr_in_progress</filename>
      for each process individually. Again, the value <literal>1</literal>
      signifies sleeping process that still needs to be woken.
      Alternatively, use the <command>kgr blocking</command> command to
      output the list of sleeping processes.
     </para>
    </step>
    <!-- 2015-09-09, tbazant: kernel sends the signals automatically now.
    <step>
     <para>
      It is up to the system administrator to decide how to deal with the
      sleeping processes. One possibility is to wait, another possibility is
      to send a SIGSTOP signal followed by a SIGCONT signal to all the
      sleeping processes. It can be achieved easily using the <command>kgr
       poke</command> command. Running processes are not interrupted.
     </para>
    </step>
     -->
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Removing a &kg; Patch</title>

  <para>
   To remove a &kg; patch, use the following procedure:
  </para>

<!--
  <para>
   Due to the way zypper operates, it is not sufficient to simply remove a
   &kg; patch with zypper. Rebuilding initrd and rebooting is required:
  </para>
 -->

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     First remove the patch itself using Zypper:
    </para>
<screen>zypper rm kgraft-patch-<replaceable>3_12_32-25-default</replaceable></screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Then reboot the machine.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Stuck Kernel Execution Threads</title>

  <para>
   Kernel threads need to be prepared to handle &kg;. Third-party
   software may not be completely ready for &kg; adoption and its kernel
   modules may spawn kernel execution threads. These threads will block the
   patching process indefinitely. As an emergency measure &kg; offers the
   possibility to force finishing of the patching process without waiting
   for all execution threads to cross the safety checkpoint. This can be
   achieved by writing <literal>0</literal> into
   <filename>/sys/kernel/kgraft/in_progress</filename>. Consult SUSE
   Support before performing this procedure.
  </para>

<!--</sect2>
   <sect2>
   <title>Live Patch Removal</title>
   <para>
    As an experimental feature &kg; supports patch removal. The low-level
    procedure is similar to patch installation. After writing
    <literal>1</literal> to
    <filename>/sys/kernel/kgraft/<replaceable>patch_name</replaceable>/revert</filename>
    the patch removal process starts. Again, processes need to leave kernel and
    kernel execution threads need to pass their checkpoints. After patching is
    finished the corresponding module can be removed from kernel. Please note
    that after performing this procedure support for the system cannot be
    claimed on SUSE.
   </para>
  </sect2>-->
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>The <command>kgr</command> Tool</title>

  <para>
   Several &kg; management tasks can be simplified with the
   <command>kgr</command> tool. The available commands are:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>kgr status</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Displays the overall status of &kg; patching
      (<literal>ready</literal> or <literal>in_progress</literal>).
<!--It takes the information from
      <filename>/sys/kernel/kgraft/in_progress</filename>.-->
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>kgr patches</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Displays the list of loaded &kg; patches.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>kgr blocking</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Lists processes that are preventing &kg; patching from finishing.
      By default only the PIDs are listed. Specifying <option>-v</option>
      prints command lines if available. Another <option>-v</option>
      displays also stack traces.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <!-- 2015-09-09, tbazant: kgr poke is obsolete
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>kgr poke</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Sends SIGSTOP and SIGCONT to all processess that are blocking &kg;
      patching from finishing.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   -->
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   For detailed information, see <command>man kgr</command>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Scope of &kg; Technology</title>

  <para>
   &kg; is based on replacing functions. Data structure alteration can be
   accomplished only indirectly with &kg;. As a result, changes to kernel
   data structure require special care and, if the change is too large,
   rebooting might be required. &kg; also might not be able to handle
   situations where one compiler is used to compile the old kernel and
   another compiler is used for compiling the patch.
  </para>

  <para>
   Because of the way &kg; works, support for third-party modules that
   are spawning kernel threads is limited.
<!--Sending SIGSTOP and SIGCONT signals to processes in D process state
  (uninterruptible sleep) does not make them to cross the kernel/user space
  boundary and does not have the intended effect.-->
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="scope_patching">
  <title>Scope of SLE Live Patching</title>

  <para>
   Fixes for CVSS (Common Vulnerability Scoring System) level 6+
   vulnerabilities and bug fixes related to system stability or data
   corruption will be shipped in the scope of SLE Live Patching. It might
   not be possible to produce a live patch for all kinds of fixes fulfilling
   the above criteria. SUSE reserves the right to skip fixes where
   production of a kernel live patch is unviable because of technical reasons.
   For more information on CVSS, see
   <link xlink:href="http://nvd.nist.gov/cvss.cfm/"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Interaction with the Support Processes</title>

  <para>
   While resolving a technical difficulty with SUSE Support, you may receive a
   so-called Program Temporary Fix (PTF). PTFs may be issued for various
   packages including those forming the base of SLE Live Patching.
  </para>

  <para>
   &kg; PTFs complying with the conditions described in the previous
   section can be installed as usual and SUSE will ensure that the system in
   question does not need to be rebooted and that future live updates are
   applied cleanly.
  </para>

  <para>
   PTFs issued for the base kernel disrupt the live patching process. First,
   installing the PTF kernel means a reboot as the kernel cannot be replaced
   as a whole at runtime. Second, another reboot is needed to replace the
   PTF with any regular maintenance updates for which the live patches are
   issued.
  </para>

  <para>
   PTFs for other packages in SLE Live Patching can be treated like regular
   PTFs with the usual guarantees.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
