<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.kvm.inst">
 <title>Guest Installation</title>
 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
          </dm:bugtracker>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <para>
  A &vmguest; is comprised of an image containing an operating system and
  data files and a configuration file describing the &vmguest;'s virtual
  hardware resources. &vmguest;s are hosted on and controlled by the
  &vmhost;. This section provides generalized instructions for installing
  a &vmguest;.
 </para>
 <para>
  Virtual machines have few if any requirements above those required to run
  the operating system. If the operating system has not been optimized for
  the virtual machine host environment, the unmodified OS can run only on
  <xref linkend="gloss.vt.hwassisted"/> virtualization computer hardware, in
  full virtualization mode, and requires specific device drivers to be
  loaded. The hardware that is presented to the &vmguest; depends on the
  configuration of the host.
 </para>
 <note>
  <title>Virtual Machine Architectures</title>
  <para>
   The virtual machine host runs only on &amd64; and &intel64;.
   Additionally, &kvm; for &zseries; is included on &sls; as a
   technology preview. It does not run on other system architectures such as
   &ppc;. A 64-bit virtual machine host can, however, run both 32-bit and
   64-bit &vmguest;s.
  </para>
 </note>
 <para>
  You should be aware of any licensing issues related to running a single
  licensed copy of an operating system on multiple virtual machines. Consult
  the operating system license agreement for more information.
 </para>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.libvirt.inst.vmm">
  <title>GUI-Based Guest Installation</title>

  <para>
   The <guimenu>New VM</guimenu> wizard helps you through the steps required
   to create a virtual machine and install its operating system. There are
   two ways to start it: Within &vmm; either click the <guimenu>Create
   New Virtual Machine</guimenu> icon or choose <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>New Virtual Machine</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>. Alternatively, start &yast; and choose
   <menuchoice><guimenu>Virtualization</guimenu> <guimenu>Create Virtual
   Machines for Xen and KVM</guimenu></menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the <guimenu>New VM</guimenu> wizard either from &yast; or
     &vmm;.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Choose an installation source - either a locally available media or a
     network installation source. If you would like to set up your
     &vmguest; from an existing image, choose <guimenu>import existing
     disk image</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     On a &vmhost; running the &xen; hypervisor, you can choose
     whether to install a paravirtualized or a fully virtualized guest. The
     respective option is available under <guimenu>Architecture
     Options</guimenu>. Depending on this choice, not all installation
     options may be available.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Depending on your choice in the previous step, you need to provide the
     following data:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Local Installation Media</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Specify the path on the &vmhost; to an iso image containing the
        installation data. If it is available as a volume in a libvirt
        storage pool, you can also select it via the
        <guimenu>Browse</guimenu> button (see
        <xref linkend="cha.libvirt.storage"/> for more information).
        Alternatively, choose a physical CDROM or DVD inserted in the
        optical drive of the &vmhost;.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Network Installation</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Provide the <guimenu>URL</guimenu> pointing to the installation
        source. Valid URL prefixes are, for example,
        <literal>ftp://</literal>, <literal>http://</literal>,
        <literal>https://</literal>, and <literal>nfs://</literal>. Under
        <guimenu>URL Options</guimenu> you may provide a path to an
        auto-installation file (&ay; or Kickstart, for example) and
        Kernel parameters. Having provided a URL, the operating system
        should be automatically be detected correctly. If this is not the
        case, deselect <guimenu>Automatically Detect Operating System Based
        on Install-Media</guimenu> and manually select the <guimenu>OS
        Type</guimenu> and <guimenu>Version</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Network Boot (PXE)</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        When booting via PXE, you only need to provide the <guimenu>OS
        Type</guimenu> and the <guimenu>Version</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Import an Existing Image</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        To set up the &vmguest; from an existing image, you need to
        specify the path on the &vmhost; to the image. If it is available
        as a volume in a libvirt storage pool, you can also select it via
        the <guimenu>Browse</guimenu> button (see
        <xref linkend="cha.libvirt.storage"/> for more information).
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Choose the memory size and number of CPUs for the new virtual machine.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     This step is omitted if having chosen <guimenu>Import an Existing
     Image</guimenu> in the first step.
    </para>
    <para>
     Set up a virtual hard disk for the &vmguest;. Either create a new
     disk image or choose an existing one from a storage pool (see
     <xref linkend="cha.libvirt.storage"/> for more information). If you
     choose to create a disk, a <literal>qcow2</literal> image will be
     created under <filename>/var/lib/libvirt/(images</filename>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Setting up a disk is optional. In case you are running a live system
     directly from CD or DVD, for example, you can omit this step by
     deselecting <guimenu>Enable Storage for this Virtual Machine</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The last screen of the wizard lets you specify the name for the virtual
     machine. Options to specify the network device and the MAC address can
     be found under <guimenu>Advanced Options</guimenu>. If you need to
     customize the configuration in detail before the installation, activate
     the relevant check box. Exit the wizard with <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>.
     Depending on your choice, this will either start the installation or
     open the &vmguest; configuration screen.
<!-- in the latter case, refer to FIXME for instructions -->
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <tip xml:id="tip.libvirt.inst.vmm.sticky">
   <title>Passing Key Combinations to Virtual Machines</title>
   <para>
    The installation starts in a &vmm; console window. Some key
    combinations, such as <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/>
    <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F1</keycap> </keycombo>, are recognized
    by the &vmhost; but are not passed to the virtual machine. To bypass
    the &vmhost;, &vmm; provides the <quote>sticky key</quote>
    functionality. Pressing <keycap function="control"/>,
    <keycap function="alt"/>, or <keycap function="shift"/> three times
    makes the key sticky, then you can press the remaining keys to pass the
    combination to the virtual machine.
   </para>
   <para>
    For example, to pass <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/>
    <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> to a Linux
    virtual machine, press <keycap function="control"/> three times, then
    press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/> <keycap>F2</keycap>
    </keycombo>. You can also press <keycap function="alt"/> three times,
    then press <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/> <keycap>F2</keycap>
    </keycombo>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The sticky key functionality is available in the &vmm; during and
    after installing a &vmguest;.
   </para>
  </tip>

<!-- fs 2014-09-09:
     VM guest hardware configuration with the new wizard is done via a screen
     almost identical to the VM hardware configuration after the machine has
     been installed. Once the respective chapter is finished, we can link to
     it. Commenting the VM install stuff, since we may be able to reuse some
     of its content for the Hardware chapter


  <sect2 id="cha.kvm.inst.virtman.custom">
   <title>Customizing the Default Settings</title>
   <para>
    If you activated <guimenu>Customize configuration before
    install</guimenu> on the last screen of the <guimenu>Create a new
    virtual machine</guimenu> wizard, a &vmguest; configuration dialog
    window opens. You can fine tune features of the newly created &vmguest;
    here.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="cha.kvm.inst.vmm.custom.name">
    <title><guimenu>Name of Virtual Machine</guimenu></title>
    <para>
     Specify a <guimenu>Name</guimenu> and an optional
     <guimenu>Description</guimenu> for the guest. The
     <guimenu>Name</guimenu> must contain only alphanumeric and
     <literal>_-.:+</literal> characters. It must be unique among all
     &vmguest;s on the &vmhost;. It is used to create and name the guest’s
     configuration file and you will be able to access the guest with this
     name from <command>virsh</command>.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="cha.kvm.inst.vmm.custom.hardware">
    <title><guimenu>Hardware</guimenu></title>
    <para>
     Change memory and CPU assignments in this screen. It is recommended not
     to specify values larger than the resources the &vmhost; can provide
     (overcommit), since it may result in errors or performance penalties.
    </para>
    <para>
     This dialog also allows you to assign PCI devices (for example a
     network card) that can be directly used by the &vmguest; (PCI
     pass-through). Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Host Devices</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Manage VM Devices</guimenu> </menuchoice> to get a list of
     available devices. Choose a device from the list and click
     <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to add it to the devices list for the &vmguest;.
     It is recommended to activate the <guimenu>Managed</guimenu> option for
     each device&mdash;it assures that &libvirt; automatically takes care of
     binding and unbinding drivers&mdash;see
     <xref linkend="tip.libvirt.config.pci.virsh.managed"/> for more
     information.
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>PCI devices cannot be shared</title>
     <para>
      PCI devices cannot be shared between host and &vmguest; or between
      &vmguest;s&mdash;each device can only be used by a single instance.
      Make sure to only add PCI devices not used elsewhere.
     </para>
    </important>
    <para>
     The <guimenu>Advanced Settings</guimenu> lets you activate or
     deactivate <xref linkend="gloss.vt.acpi"/>, 
     <xref linkend="gloss.vt.apic"/>, and <xref linkend="gloss.vt.acronym.pae"/>. It is recommended not to change the
     default settings. You can also enable or disable paravirtualized I/O
     with <systemitem>virtio</systemitem> or choose to execute the kernel on
     boot (linux only) here.
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>Paravirtualized I/O</title>
     <para>
      If you enable paravirtualized I/O by activating
      <guimenu>virtio</guimenu>, all hard disks you create will be
      configured as <systemitem>virtio</systemitem> disks. If your operating
      system does not have appropriate drivers, the installation will fail.
      A Windows operating system installation even fails if providing a
      driver. By default, this feature is only activated for operating
      systems known to ship with <systemitem>virtio</systemitem> drivers.
     </para>
    </important>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="cha.kvm.inst.vmm.custom.gfx">
    <title><guimenu>Peripheral Devices</guimenu></title>
    <para>
     Configure the type of virtualized graphics hardware, the keymap and
     sound device in this dialog. If you disable the graphics card support,
     the machine is only accessible via network services (ssh) or serial
     port. Sound in &vmguest;s is currently not supported by &suse;,
     therefore <guimenu>Sound</guimenu> should be set to
     <literal>None</literal>.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="cha.kvm.inst.vmm.custom.disk">
    <title><guimenu>Disks</guimenu></title>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Disks</guimenu>: Manage virtual hard disks and CD/DVD drives
     in this dialog. A &vmguest; must have at least one virtual
     disk&mdash;either an existing one or a newly created disk. Virtual
     disks can be:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       a single file with a fixed size
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
          a single file that grows on demand (<xref
          linkend="gloss.vt.storage.sparse"/>)
      </para>
      <important>
       <title>Sufficient Space for Sparse Image Files</title>
       <para>
        When creating <xref linkend="gloss.vt.storage.sparse"/>s, the
        partition on which you create them always needs sufficient free
        space. The &vmguest; has no means to check the &vmhost; disk
        space. Having no space left on the host partition causes write errors
        and loss of data on the guest system.
       </para>
      </important>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       a block device, such as an entire disk, partition, or a network
       volume.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     For best performance, create each virtual disk from an entire disk or a
     partition. For the next best performance, create an image file but do not
     create it as a <xref linkend="gloss.vt.storage.sparse"/>. A virtual disk
     based on a <xref linkend="gloss.vt.storage.sparse"/> delivers the most
     disk space flexibility but slows installation and disk access speeds.
    </para>
    <tip id="kvm.inst.vmm.tip.live.migration">
     <title>Live Migration</title>
     <para>
      If you need to be able to migrate your &vmguest; to another host
      without shutting it down (live migration), all disks must reside on a
      network resource (network file system or iSCSI volume) that is
      accessible from both hosts.
     </para>
    </tip>
    <para>
     By default, a single sparse raw disk image file is created in
     <filename>/var/lib/kvm/images/<replaceable>VM_NAME</replaceable>/</filename>
     where <replaceable>VM_NAME</replaceable> is the name of the virtual
     machine.
    </para>
    <note>
     <title>Supported Disk Formats And Protocols</title>
     <para>
      Please refer to <ulink
      url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/x86_64/SUSE-SLES/12/">&sls; 12
      releases notes</ulink> for more information about supported formats and
      protocols.
     </para>
     <para>
      In order to be able to create snapshots of the &vmguest;, choosing
      <literal>qcow2</literal> is required.
     </para>
    </note>
    <procedure>
     <title>Creating a Virtual Disk</title>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>Harddisk</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Enter a <guimenu>Source</guimenu>. If creating a file-backed disk,
       either enter the path directly or click <guimenu>New</guimenu>. When
       creating a disk from a device, enter the device node, for example
       <filename>/dev/disk/by-path/<replaceable>path</replaceable></filename>.
       It is strongly recommended not to use the simple device paths such as
       <filename>/dev/sdb</filename> or <filename>/dev/sda5</filename>,
       since they may change (by adding a disk or by changing the disk order
       in the BIOS).
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Specify the <guimenu>Protocol</guimenu>. For creating
       <literal>raw</literal> disks, choose either <guimenu>file</guimenu>
       for file-backed virtual disks or <guimenu>phy</guimenu> for
       device-backed disks. <literal>qcow2</literal> or
       <literal>qed</literal> disks can be created by choosing the
       corresponding value.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Enter a <guimenu>Size</guimenu> in GB. This option is only available
       for file-backed disks.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Choose whether to create a <guimenu>Sparse Image File</guimenu>. This
       option is only available for file-backed disks. If you want to
       disable write-access to the disk, choose <guimenu>Read-Only
       Access</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <para>
     If you want to install from DVD or CD-ROM, add the drive to the list of
     available hard disks. To learn about device nodes of the available
     optical drives, run:
    </para>
<screen>hwinfo \-\-cdrom | egrep "(Device File:|Model:)"</screen>
    <para>
     Instead of the real DVD or CD-ROM drive, you can also add the ISO image
     of an installation medium. Note that each CD-Rom drive or ISO image can
     only be used by one guest at the same time.
    </para>
    <para>
     To add a CD/DVD-ROM device or an ISO image, proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <procedure>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>CD-ROM</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Enter a <guimenu>Source</guimenu>. If adding a device, enter its
       node. If adding an ISO image, either enter the path directly or click
       <guimenu>Browse</guimenu> to open a file browser.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Specify the <guimenu>Protocol</guimenu>. Choose
       <guimenu>file</guimenu> for an ISO image and <guimenu>phy</guimenu>
       for a device.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <para>
     The disks are listed in the order in which they have been created. This
     order also represents the boot order. Use the <guimenu>Up</guimenu> and
     <guimenu>Down</guimenu> arrows to change the disk order.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="cha.kvm.inst.vmm.custom.nic">
    <title><guimenu>Network Adapters</guimenu></title>
    <para>
     By default, a single virtual network card is created for the virtual
     machine. It has a randomly generated MAC address that you can change to
     fit your desired configuration. If a bridge exists on the &vmhost;, the
     virtual network card will be attached to it, otherwise it will be
     attached to the <systemitem class="library">libvirt's</systemitem>
     default virtual bridge
     (<systemitem class="resource">virbr1</systemitem>).
 fs 2011-11-04: 
     For more information about
     <systemitem class="library">libvirt</systemitem> and networks, refer to
     FIXME

    </para>
    <para>
     To add a new network adapter or edit an existing one, proceed as
     follows:
    </para>
    <procedure>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>New</guimenu> to add a card or <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
       to change the configuration of the selected card.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Choose a <guimenu>Type</guimenu> from the drop-down list.
      </para>
      <note>
       <title>Supported Virtual Network Adapter Types</title>
       <para>
        Currently, only <guimenu>Fully Virtualized Realtek 8139</guimenu>,
        <guimenu>Fully Virtualized Intel e1000</guimenu> or the
        paravirtualized <guimenu>QEMU Virtualized NIC Card</guimenu>
        (<systemitem>virtio</systemitem>) are supported by &suse;.
       </para>
      </note>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Choose a <guimenu>Source</guimenu> from the drop-down list.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Choose whether to assign a randomly generated MAC address or manually
       specify an address.
      </para>
      <note>
       <title>MAC addresses need to be unique</title>
       <para>
        When choosing to manually specify a MAC address, make sure it is not
        already used in your network. If so, it may result in network
        problems, especially when using DHCP. Therefore avoid specifying
        obvious MAC addresses such as 52:54:00:12:34:56 or
        52:54:00:11:22:33, because they may already be in use. It is
        strongly recommended to always use a randomly generated MAC address
        for each adapter.
       </para>
      </note>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="cha.kvm.inst.vmm.custom.install">
    <title><guimenu>Operating System Installation</guimenu></title>
    <para>
     This dialog is only available when having chosen to install an
     operating system. The installation can be booted from a virtual disk,
     from a CD/DVD device, from an ISO image, a network resource or via PXE
     boot&mdash;use this dialog to configure the boot device.
    </para>

    <note>
     <title>Automated Installation</title>
     <para>
      If you are doing an automated installation (for example via &suse; Linux
      &ay;, or NetWare Response File), make sure the installation profile,
      response file, or script is accessible from the &vmguest;.
     </para>
     <para>
      Refer to your operating system manual for instructions on how to perform
      an automated installation.
     </para>
    </note>

    <para>
     Also use this dialog to configure the behavior of the &vmguest; when
     the operating system is powered off, rebooted or if it crashes. The
     following options are available
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>destroy</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        normal cleanup
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>restart</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        a new &vmguest; is started in place of the old one
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>preserve</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        no cleanup, do not delete temporary, configuration and image files
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>rename-restart</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        the &vmguest; is not cleaned up but is renamed and a new domain
        started in its place
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>coredump-destroy</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        a crashed machine's core is dumped before a normal cleanup is
        performed
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>coredump-restart</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        a crashed machine's core is dumped before a normal restart is
        performed
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
-->
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.libvirt.inst.virt-install">
  <title>Installing from the Command Line with <command>virt-install</command></title>

  <para>
   <command>virt-install</command> is a command line tool that helps you
   create new virtual machines using the &libvirt; library. It is useful
   if you cannot use the graphical user interface, or need to automatize the
   process of creating virtual machines.
  </para>

  <para>
   <command>virt-install</command> is a complex script with a lot of command
   line switches. The following are required. For more information, see the
   man page of <command>virt-install</command> (1).
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>General Options</term>
    <listitem>
     <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <option>--name <replaceable>vm_guest_name</replaceable></option>:
        Specify the name of the new virtual machine. The name must be unique
        across all guests known to the hypervisor on the same connection. It
        is used to create and name the guest’s configuration file and you
        will be able to access the guest with this name from
        <command>virsh</command>. Alphanumeric and <literal>_-.:+</literal>
        characters are allowed.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <option>--memory
        <replaceable>required_memory</replaceable></option>: Specify the
        amount of memory to allocate for the new virtual machine in
        megabytes.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <option>--vcpus <replaceable>number_of_cpus</replaceable></option>:
        Specify the number of virtual CPUs. For best performance, the number
        of virtual processors should be less than or equal to the number of
        physical processors.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Virtualization Type</term>
    <listitem>
     <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <option>--paravirt</option>: Set up a paravirtualized guest. This is
        the default if the &vmhost; supports paravirtualization and full
        virtualization.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <option>--hvm</option>: Set up a fully virtualized guest.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <option>--virt-type <replaceable>hypervisor</replaceable></option>:
        Specify the hypervisor. Supported values are <literal>kvm</literal>,
        <literal>xen</literal>, or <literal>lxc</literal>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Guest Storage</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Specify one of <option>--disk</option>, <option>--filesystem</option>
      or <option>--nodisks</option> the type of the storage for the new
      virtual machine. For example, <option>--disk size=10</option> creates
      10 GB disk in the default image location for the hypervisor and uses
      it for the &vmguest;. <option>--filesystem
      <replaceable>/export/path/on/vmhost</replaceable></option> specifies
      the directory on the &vmhost; to be exported to the guest. And
      <option>--nodisks</option> sets up a &vmguest; without a local
      storage (good for Live CDs).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Installation Method</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Specify the installation method using one of
      <option>--location</option>, <option>--cdrom</option>,
      <option>--pxe</option>, <option>--import</option>, or <option>--boot
      </option>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Accessing the Installation</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use the <option>--graphics <replaceable>value</replaceable></option>
      option to specify how to access the installation. &productname;
      supports the values <literal>vnc</literal> or <literal>none</literal>.
     </para>
     <para>
      If using vnc <command>virt-install</command> tries to launch
      <command>virt-viewer</command>. If it is not installed or cannot be
      run, connect to the &vmguest; manually with you preferred viewer.
      To explicitly prevent <command>virt-install</command> from launching
      the viewer use <option>--noautoconsole</option>. To define a password
      for accessing the VNC session, use the following syntax:
      <option>--graphics
      vnc,password=<replaceable>PASSWORD</replaceable></option>.
     </para>
     <para>
      In case you are using <option>--graphics none</option>, you can access
      the &vmguest; through operating system supported services, such as
      SSH or VNC. Refer to the operating system installation manual on how
      to set up these services in the installation system.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <example xml:id="ex.libvirt.inst.virt-install.example">
   <title>Example of a <command>virt-install</command> command line</title>
   <para>
    The following command line example creates a new &sled; 12 virtual
    machine with a virtio accelerated disk and network card. It creates a
    new 10 GB qcow2 disk image as a storage, the source installation media
    being the host CD-ROM drive. It will use VNC graphics, and it will
    auto-launch the graphical client.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>KVM</term>
     <listitem>
<screen>virt-install --connect qemu:///system --virt-type kvm  --name sled12 \
--memory 1024 --disk size=10 --cdrom /dev/cdrom --graphics vnc \
--os-variant sled12</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>&xen;</term>
     <listitem>
<screen>virt-install --connect xen:// --virt-type xen  --name sled12 \
--memory 1024 --disk size=10 --cdrom /dev/cdrom --graphics vnc \
--os-variant sled12</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </example>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.libvirt.inst.advanced">
  <title>Advanced Guest Installation Scenarios</title>

  <para>
   This section provides instructions for operations exceeding the scope of
   a normal installation, such as including modules and extensions packages.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="libvirt.advanced.balloon">
   <title>Memory Ballooning with Windows Guests</title>
   <para>
    Memory ballooning is a method to change the amount of memory used by
    &vmguest; at runtime. Both the &kvm; and &xen; hypervisors
    provide this method, but it has to be supported by the guest as well.
   </para>
   <para>
<!-- 2014-06-12 tbazant: FIXME add URL to VMDP once it exists -->
    While openSUSE and SLE-based guests support memory ballooning, Windows
    guests need the
    <link xlink:href="http://www.suse.com/products/vmdriverpack/">Virtual
    Machine Driver Pack (VMDP)</link> to provide ballooning. To set the
    maximum memory greater than the initial memory configured for Windows
    guests, follow these steps:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Install the Windows guest with the maximum memory equal or less than
      the initial value.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Install the Virtual Machine Driver Pack in the Windows guest to
      provide required drivers.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Shut down the Windows guest.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Reset the maximum memory of the Windows guest to the required value.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the Windows guest again.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="cha.kvm.inst.virtman_advanced.addons">
   <title>Including Add-On Products in the Installation</title>
   <para>
    Some operating systems such as &sls; offer to include add-on products
    in the installation process. In case the add-on product installation
    source is provided via network, no special &vmguest; configuration is
    needed. If it is provided via CD/DVD or ISO image, it is necessary to
    provide the &vmguest; installation system with both, the standard
    installation medium and an image for the add-on product.
   </para>
   <para>
    In case you are using the GUI-based installation, select
    <guimenu>Customize Configuration Before Install</guimenu> in the last
    step of the wizard and add the add-on product iso image via
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Add Hardware</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Storage</guimenu></menuchoice>. Specify the path to the image
    and set the <guimenu>Device Type</guimenu> to <guimenu>CD-ROM</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    If installing from the command line, you need to set up the virtual
    CD/DVD drives with the <option>--disk</option> parameter rather than
    with <option>--cdrom</option>. The device that is specified first is
    used for booting. The following example will install &sls; 12 plus
    SDK:
   </para>
<screen>virt-install --name sles12+sdk --memory 1024 --disk size=10 \
--disk /virt/iso/SLES12.iso,device=cdrom \
--disk /virt/iso/SLES12_SDK.iso,device=cdrom \
--graphics vnc --os-variant sles12</screen>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
