<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.libvirt.state">
 <title>Save and Restore of Virtual Machines</title>
 <para></para>
 <sect1 id="sec.libvirt.save.suspend">
  <title>Saving Virtual Machines</title>
  <para>
   The save operation preserves the exact state of the virtual machine’s
   memory. The operation is slightly similar to
   <emphasis>hibernating</emphasis> a computer. The virtual machine is off,
   but it can be quickly restored to its previously saved running condition.
   The operation does not make a copy of any portion of the virtual
   machine’s virtual disk.
  </para>

  <para>
   When saved, the virtual machine is paused, its current memory state saved
   to a location you specify, and then the virtual machine is stopped. The
   amount of time to save the virtual machine depends on the amount of
   memory allocated. When saved, a virtual machine’s memory is returned to
   the pool of memory available on the host.
  </para>

  <para>
   The restore operation is used to return a saved virtual machine to its
   original running state.
  </para>

  <important>
   <para>
    After using the save operation, do not boot, start, or run a virtual
    machine that you intend to restore. If the virtual machine is at any
    time restarted before it is restored, the saved memory state file
    becomes invalid and should not be used to restore.
   </para>
  </important>

  <procedure>
   <title>Save a Virtual Machine’s Current State (Virtual Machine Manager)</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Make sure the virtual machine to be saved is running.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the virtual machine.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Open</guimenu> to view the virtual machine console, then
     <guimenu>Details</guimenu> to view virtual machine information.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Virtual Machine</guimenu><guimenu>Shut
     Down</guimenu> <guimenu>Save</guimenu> </menuchoice> from the menu.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Name and save the file.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.libvirt.restore">
  <title>Restoring Virtual Machines</title>
  <para>
   The restore operation loads a virtual machine’s previously saved memory
   state file and starts the virtual machine. The virtual machine does not
   boot the operating system but resumes at the point that it was previously
   saved. The operation is slightly similar to coming out of hibernation.
  </para>

  <important>
   <para>
    After using the save operation, do not boot, start, or run the virtual
    machine you intend to restore. If the virtual machine is at any time
    restarted before it is restored, the saved memory state file becomes
    invalid and should not be used to restore.
   </para>
  </important>

  <procedure>
   <title>Restore a Virtual Machine’s Current State (Virtual Machine Manager)</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Make sure the virtual machine to be restored has not been started since
     you ran the save operation.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run the Virtual Machine Manager.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the hypervisor and connection used to restore the virtual
     machine. On the local machine, this is
     <systemitem>localhost</systemitem>. Right-click it and choose
     <guimenu>Details</guimenu> from the context menu.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Connection Details</guimenu> window, choose
     <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Restore Saved
     Machine</guimenu> </menuchoice> from the drop-down box.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Specify the previously saved file.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Open</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The virtual machine and the guest operating system are restored to the
     previously saved state.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
