<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.mobile">
 <title>Mobile Computing with Linux</title><indexterm id="idx.mobility"
  class="startofrange">
 <primary>mobility</primary></indexterm>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   Mobile computing is mostly associated with laptops, PDAs and cellular
   phones (and the data exchange between them). Mobile hardware components,
   such as external hard disks, flash drives, or digital cameras, can be
   connected to laptops or desktop systems. A number of software components
   are involved in mobile computing scenarios and some applications are
   tailor-made for mobile use.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <sect1 id="sec.mobile.nbook">
  <title>Laptops</title><indexterm class="startofrange"
   id="idx.notebook">

  <primary>laptops</primary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>laptops</primary>

  <secondary>hardware</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>laptops</primary>

  <secondary>PCMCIA</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>PCMCIA</primary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>mobility</primary>

  <secondary>laptops</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   The hardware of laptops differs from that of a normal desktop system.
   This is because criteria like exchangeability, space requirements and
   power consumption must be taken into account. The manufacturers of mobile
   hardware have developed standard interfaces like PCMCIA (Personal
   Computer Memory Card International Association), Mini PCI and Mini PCIe
   that can be used to extend the hardware of laptops. The standards cover
   memory cards, network interface cards, and
   external hard disks.
  </para>

  <!--<tip>
   <title>&productname; and Tablet PCs</title>
   <para>
    &productname; also supports Tablet PCs. Tablet PCs come with a
    touchpad/digitizer that allows you to use a digital pen or even
    fingertips to edit data right on the screen instead of using mouse and
    keyboard. They are installed and configured much like any other system.
    For a detailed introduction to the installation and configuration of
    Tablet PCs, refer to <xref
     linkend="cha.tablet"/>.
   </para>
  </tip>-->

<?dbfo-need height="20em"?>

  <sect2 id="sec.mobile.powerm">
   <title>Power Conservation</title><indexterm>
   <primary>laptops</primary>
   <secondary>power management</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>power management</primary></indexterm>
   <para>
    The inclusion of energy-optimized system components during laptop
    manufacturing contributes to their suitability for use without access to
    the electrical power grid. Their contribution towards conservation of
    power is at least as important as that of the operating system.
    &productnamereg; supports various methods that influence the power
    consumption of a laptop and have varying effects on the operating time
    under battery power. The following list is in descending order of
    contribution towards power conservation:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Throttling the CPU speed.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Switching off the display illumination during pauses.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Manually adjusting the display illumination.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Disconnecting unused, hotplug-enabled accessories (USB CD-ROM,
      external mouse, unused PCMCIA cards, Wi-Fi, etc.).
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Spinning down the hard disk when idling.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    Detailed background information about power management in &productname; is
    provided in <xref linkend="cha.pmanage"/>. <phrase os="sled">For desktop
    specific power management, see <xref
    linkend="sec.gnomeuser.start.power_mgmt"/> on how to use the GNOME Power
    Manager.</phrase>
   </para>
  </sect2>

<?dbfo-need height="20em"?>

  <sect2 id="sec.mobile.nbook.change">
   <title>Integration in Changing Operating Environments</title><indexterm>
   <primary>laptops</primary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Your system needs to adapt to changing operating environments when used
    for mobile computing. Many services depend on the environment and the
    underlying clients must be reconfigured. &productname; handles this task
    for you.
   </para>
   <figure id="fig.mobile.scpm">
    <title>Integrating a Mobile Computer in an Existing Environment</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata width="90%" fileref="mobile_scpm.svg" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata width="75%" fileref="mobile_scpm.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    The services affected in the case of a laptop commuting back and forth
    between a small home network and an office network are:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Network</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This includes IP address assignment, name resolution, Internet
       connectivity and connectivity to other networks.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Printing</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A current database of available printers and an available print
       server must be present, depending on the network.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>E-Mail and Proxies</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       As with printing, the list of the corresponding servers must be
       current.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>X (Graphical Environment)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If your laptop is temporarily connected to a projector or an external
       monitor, different display configurations must be available.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    &productname; offers several ways of integrating laptops into existing
    operating environments:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>&nm;</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <indexterm>
       <primary>&nm;</primary>
       </indexterm> <indexterm>
       <primary>laptops</primary>
       <secondary>&nm;</secondary>
       </indexterm> &nm; is especially tailored for mobile networking on
       laptops. It provides a means to easily and automatically switch
       between network environments or different types of networks such as
       mobile broadband (such as GPRS, EDGE, or 3G), wireless LAN, and
       Ethernet. &nm; supports WEP and WPA-PSK encryption in wireless LANs.
       It also supports dial-up connections (with smpppd). The GNOME desktop
       includes a front-end for &nm;. For more
       information, see <xref linkend="sec.nm.gnome"/>.
      </para>
<?dbfo-need height="20em"?>
      <table>
       <title>Use Cases for &nm;</title>
       <tgroup cols="2">
        <thead>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            My computer&hellip;
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            Use &nm;
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            is a laptop
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            Yes
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            is sometimes attached to different networks
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            Yes
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            provides network services (such as DNS or DHCP)
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            No
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            only uses a static IP address
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            No
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
        </tbody>
       </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>
       Use the &yast; tools to configure networking whenever &nm; should not
       handle network configuration.
      </para>
      <tip>
       <title>DNS configuration and various types of network connections</title>
       <para>
        If you travel frequently with your laptop and change different types
        of network connections, &nm; works fine when all DNS addresses are
        assigned correctly assigned with DHCP. If some of your connections
        use static DNS address(es), add it to the
        <literal>NETCONFIG_DNS_STATIC_SERVERS</literal> option in
        <filename>/etc/sysconfig/network/config</filename>.
       </para>
      </tip>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
     <term>SLP</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <indexterm>
       <primary>laptops</primary>
       <secondary>SLP</secondary>
       </indexterm> <indexterm>
       <primary>SLP</primary> </indexterm> The service location protocol (SLP)
       simplifies the connection of a laptop to an existing network. Without
       SLP, the administrator of a laptop usually requires detailed knowledge
       of the services available in a network. SLP broadcasts the availability
       of a certain type of service to all clients in a local network.
       Applications that support SLP can process the information dispatched by
       SLP and be configured automatically. SLP can also be used to install a
       system, minimizing the effort of searching for a suitable installation
       source.<phrase os="sles"> Find detailed information about SLP in <xref
       linkend="cha.slp"/>.</phrase>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

<?dbfo-need height="20em"?>

  <sect2 id="sec.mobile.nbook.soft">
   <title>Software Options</title>
   <para>
    There are various special task areas in mobile use that are covered by
    dedicated software: system monitoring (especially the battery charge),
    data synchronization, and wireless communication with peripherals and
    the Internet. The following sections cover the most important
    applications that &productname; provides for each task.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.mobile.nbook.soft.mon">
    <title>System Monitoring</title><indexterm>
    <primary>system monitoring</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
     Two System monitoring tools are provided by &productname;:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Power Management</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <indexterm>
        <primary>system monitoring</primary>
        <secondary>Power Management</secondary>
        </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>Power Management</primary>
        </indexterm> <guimenu>Power Management</guimenu> is an application
        which lets you adjust energy saving related behavior of the GNOME
        desktop. You can typically access it via
	<menuchoice><guimenu>Computer</guimenu> <guimenu>Control
	Center</guimenu> <guimenu>System</guimenu> <guimenu>Power
	Management</guimenu></menuchoice>. <phrase os="sled">See <xref
	linkend="sec.gnome.settings.system.power"/> for details.</phrase>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>System Monitor</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <indexterm>
        <primary>system monitoring</primary>
        <secondary>System Monitor</secondary>
        </indexterm>
	The <guimenu>System Monitor</guimenu> gathers measurable system
	parameters into one monitoring environment. It presents the output
	information in three tabs by default. <guimenu>Processes</guimenu>
	gives detailed information about currently running processes, such as
	CPU load, memory usage, or process ID number and priority. The
	presentation and filtering of the collected data can be customized
	&mdash; to add a new type of process information, left-click the
	process table header and choose which column to hide or add to the
	view. It is also possible to monitor different system parameters in
	various data pages or collect the data of various machines in parallel
	over the network. The <guimenu>Resources</guimenu> tab shows graphs of
	CPU, memory and network history and the <guimenu>File System</guimenu>
	tab lists all partitions and their usage.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.mobile.nbook.soft.sync">
    <title>Synchronizing Data</title>
    <para>
     When switching between working on a mobile machine disconnected from
     the network and working at a networked workstation in an office, it is
     necessary to keep processed data synchronized across all instances.
     This could include e-mail folders, directories and individual files
     that need to be present for work on the road as well as at the office.
     The solution in both cases is as follows:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Synchronizing E-Mail</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <indexterm>
        <primary>synchronizing data</primary>
        <secondary>e-mail</secondary>
        </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>e-mail</primary>
        <secondary>synchronizing</secondary> </indexterm> Use an IMAP account
        for storing your e-mails in the office network. Then access the
        e-mails from the workstation using any disconnected IMAP&ndash;enabled
        e-mail client, like Mozilla Thunderbird Mail, or Evolution <phrase
        os="sled"> as described in <xref
        linkend="book.gnomeuser"/></phrase>. The e-mail client must be
        configured so that the same folder is always accessed for
        <literal>Sent messages</literal>. This ensures that all messages are
        available along with their status information after the
        synchronization process has completed. Use an SMTP server implemented
        in the mail client for sending messages instead of the system-wide MTA
        postfix or sendmail to receive reliable feedback about unsent mail.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Synchronizing Files and Directories</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <indexterm>
        <primary>synchronizing data</primary>
        </indexterm> There are several utilities suitable for synchronizing
        data between a laptop and a workstation. One of the most widely used
        is a command-line tool called <command>rsync</command>. For more
        information, see its manual page (<command>man 1 rsync</command>).
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.mobile.nbook.soft.wifi">
    <title>Wireless Communication: Wi-Fi</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>networks</primary>
      <secondary>Wi-Fi</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <!-- **** -->
    <para>With the largest range of these wireless technologies,
        Wi-Fi is the only one suitable for the operation of large and
        sometimes even spatially separate networks. Single machines can
        connect with each other to form an independent wireless network or
        access the Internet. Devices called <emphasis>access
        points</emphasis> act as base stations for Wi-Fi-enabled devices and
        act as intermediaries for access to the Internet. A mobile user can
        switch among access points depending on location and which access
        point is offering the best connection. Like in cellular telephony, a
        large network is available to Wi-Fi users without binding them to a
        specific location for accessing it. </para>
    <para>Wi-Fi cards communicate using the 802.11 standard, prepared by the IEEE organization.
      Originally, this standard provided for a maximum transmission rate of 2&nbsp;Mbit/s.
      Meanwhile, several supplements have been added to increase the data rate. These supplements
      define details such as the modulation, transmission output, and transmission rates (see 
      <xref linkend="tab.mobile.wifistd"/>).
      Additionally, many companies implement hardware with proprietary or draft features. </para> 
    <table id="tab.mobile.wifistd">
      <title>Overview of Various Wi-Fi Standards</title>
      <tgroup cols="4">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para> Name (802.11) </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> Frequency (GHz) </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> Maximum Transmission Rate (Mbit/s) </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> Note </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para> a </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> 5 </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> 54 </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> Less interference-prone </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para> b </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> 2.4 </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> 11 </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> Less common </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para> g </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> 2.4 </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> 54 </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> Widespread, backwards-compatible with 11b </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para> n </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> 2.4 and/or 5 </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> 300 <remark>Kofler: 540</remark>
                <remark>Others: 600, depending on the channel</remark>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> Common </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>ac</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>5</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>up to ~865</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Expected to be common in 2015</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para> ad </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> 60 </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> up to appr. 7000 </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> Released 2012, currently less common; not supported in &sls; </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para> 802.11 Legacy cards are not supported by &productnamereg;. Most cards using 
      802.11 a/b/g/n are supported. New cards usually comply with the 802.11n
      standard, but cards using 802.11g are still available. </para>
  
        <sect4 id="sec.mobile.wlan.modes">
          <title>Operating Modes</title>
          <para> In wireless networking, various techniques and configurations are used to ensure
            fast, high-quality, and secure connections. In most cases, your Wi-Fi card operates in
              <emphasis>managed mode</emphasis>. However, different operating types need different
            setups. Wireless networks can be classified into four network modes: </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Managed Mode (Infrastructure Mode), via Access Point (default mode)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para> Managed networks have a managing element: the access point. In this mode
                  (also referred to as infrastructure or default mode), all connections of the Wi-Fi
                  stations in the network run through the access point, which may also serve as a
                  connection to an ethernet. To make sure only authorized stations can connect,
                  various authentication mechanisms (WPA, etc) are used. This is also the main mode
                  which consumes the least amount of energy</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Ad-hoc Mode (Peer-to-Peer Network)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para> Ad-hoc networks do not have an access point. The stations communicate
                  directly with each other, therefore an ad-hoc network is usually slower than a
                  managed network. However, the transmission range and number of participating
                  stations are greatly limited in ad-hoc networks. They also do not support WPA
                  authentication. If you intend to use WPA security, you should not use Ad-Hoc_Mode.
                  Be aware, not all cards support ad-hoc mode reliably. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Master Mode</term>
              <listitem>
                <para> In master mode, your Wi-Fi card is used as the access point, assuming your
                  card supports this mode. Find out the details of your Wi-Fi card on <ulink
                    url="http://linux-wless.passys.nl"/>. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Mesh Mode</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Wireless mesh networks are organized in a <emphasis>mesh topology</emphasis>.
                  A wireless mesh network's connection is spread among all wireless mesh
                    <emphasis>nodes</emphasis>. Each node belonging to this network is conntected to
                  other nodes to share the connection, possibly through a large area. <phrase
                    os="sles">(Not supported in &slea;12).</phrase></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="sec.mobile.wlan.func.auth">
          <title>Authentication</title>
          <para>Because a wireless network is much easier to intercept and compromise than a wired
            network, the various standards include authentication and encryption methods. </para>
          <para>Old Wi-Fi cards support only WEP (Wired Equivalent Privacy). However, because WEP
            has proven to be insecure, the Wi-Fi industry has defined an extension called WPA, which
            is supposed to eliminate the weaknesses of WEP. WPA, sometimes synonymous with WPA2,
            should be the default authentication method. </para>
          <para>Usually, in most cases the user cannot choose the authentication method at all. For
            example, when a card operates in managed mode the authentication is set by the access
            point. &nm; shows the authentication method. </para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="sec.mobile.wlan.func.encr">
          <title>Encryption</title>
          <para> There are various encryption methods to ensure that no unauthorized person can read
            the data packets that are exchanged in a wireless network or gain access to the network: </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>WEP (defined in IEEE 802.11)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para> This standard makes use of the RC4 encryption algorithm, originally with a
                  key length of 40&nbsp;bits, later also with 104&nbsp;bits. Often, the length is
                  declared as 64&nbsp;bits or 128&nbsp;bits, depending on whether the 24&nbsp;bits
                  of the initialization vector are included. However, this standard has some
                  weaknesses. Attacks against the keys generated by this system may be successful.
                  Nevertheless, it is better to use WEP than to not encrypt the network at all. </para>
                <para> Some vendors have implemented the non-standard <quote>Dynamic WEP</quote>. It
                  works exactly as WEP and shares the same weaknesses, except that the key is
                  periodically changed by a key management service. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>TKIP (defined in WPA/IEEE 802.11i)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para> This key management protocol defined in the WPA standard uses the same
                  encryption algorithm as WEP, but eliminates its weakness. Because a new key is
                  generated for every data packet, attacks against these keys are fruitless. TKIP is
                  used together with WPA-PSK. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>CCMP (defined in IEEE 802.11i)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para> CCMP describes the key management. Usually, it is used in connection with
                  WPA-EAP, but it can also be used with WPA-PSK. The encryption takes place
                  according to AES and is stronger than the RC4 encryption of the WEP standard.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </sect4>

   </sect3>
   
   <sect3 id="sec.mobile.nbook.soft.bluetooth">
     <title>Wireless Communication: Bluetooth</title>
     <para><indexterm>
        <primary>networks</primary>
        <secondary>Bluetooth</secondary>
        </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>Bluetooth</primary>
        </indexterm> Bluetooth has the broadest application spectrum of all
        wireless technologies. It can be used for communication between
        computers (laptops) and PDAs or cellular phones, as can IrDA. It can
        also be used to connect various computers within range. Bluetooth is
        also used to connect wireless system components, like a keyboard or
        a mouse. The range of this technology is, however, not sufficient to
        connect remote systems to a network. Wi-Fi is the technology of
        choice for communicating through physical obstacles like walls.
<!--taroth 081020: MOBILE - commenting as chapter has
         been excluded for now-->
<!--Find more information about Bluetooth, its applications, and
	configuration in <xref linkend="sec.pcmcia.btooth"/>.--></para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.mobile.nbook.soft.irda">
      <title>Wireless Communication: IrDA</title>
      <para>
        <indexterm>
        <primary>networks</primary>
        <secondary>IrDA</secondary>
        </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>IrDA</primary>
        </indexterm> IrDA is the wireless technology with the shortest
        range. Both communication parties must be within viewing distance of
        each other. Obstacles like walls cannot be overcome. One possible
        application of IrDA is the transmission of a file from a laptop to a
        cellular phone. The short path from the laptop to the cellular phone
        is then covered using IrDA. The long range transport of the file to
        the recipient of the file is handled by the mobile network. Another
        application of IrDA is the wireless transmission of printing jobs in
        the office.
<!--taroth 081020: MOBILE - commenting as chapter has been excluded for now-->
<!--Find more information about IrDA in
	<xref linkend="sec.pcmcia.irda"/>.--></para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.mobile.nbook.sec">
   <title>Data Security</title><indexterm>
   <primary>mobility</primary>
   <secondary>data security</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>security</primary>
   <secondary>encrypted file system</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>data security</primary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Ideally, you protect data on your laptop against unauthorized access in
    multiple ways. Possible security measures can be taken in the following
    areas:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Protection against Theft</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Always physically secure your system against theft whenever possible.
       Various securing tools (like chains) are available in retail stores.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Strong Authentication</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use biometric authentication in addition to standard authentication
       via login and password. &productname; supports fingerprint
       authentication. <!--taroth 2014-02-06: file no longer included because of
        fate#313128. According to #2, this should work out of the box via a GNOME
        UI now:  For more information, refer to
        <xref linkend="cha.security.fp"/>.-->
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Securing Data on the System</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Important data should not only be encrypted during transmission, but
       also on the hard disk. This ensures its safety in case of theft. The
       creation of an encrypted partition with &productname; is described in
       <xref linkend="cha.security.cryptofs"/>. Another possibility is to
       create encrypted home directories when adding the user with &yast;.
      </para>
      <important>
       <title>Data Security and Suspend to Disk</title>
       <para>
        Encrypted partitions are not unmounted during a suspend to disk
        event. Thus, all data on these partitions is available to any party
        who manages to steal the hardware and issue a resume of the hard
        disk.
       </para>
      </important>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Network Security</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Any transfer of data should be secured, no matter how the transfer is
       done. Find general security issues regarding Linux and networks in
       <xref linkend="cha.security"/>. 
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.notebook"/>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.mobile.hw">
  <title>Mobile Hardware</title><indexterm>

  <primary>mobility</primary>

  <secondary>USB</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>mobility</primary>

  <secondary>FireWire (IEEE1394)</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>FireWire (IEEE1394)</primary>

  <secondary>hard disks</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>USB</primary>

  <secondary>hard disks</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>USB</primary>

  <secondary>flash drives</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>flash drives</primary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>mobility</primary>

  <secondary>external hard disks</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>mobility</primary>

  <secondary>digital cameras</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>digital cameras</primary></indexterm>

  <para>
   &productname; supports the automatic detection of mobile storage devices
   over FireWire (IEEE 1394) or USB. The term <emphasis>mobile storage
   device</emphasis> applies to any kind of FireWire or USB hard disk, USB
   flash drive, or digital camera. These devices are automatically detected
   and configured as soon as they are connected with the system over the
   corresponding interface. The file manager of GNOME offers flexible handling
   of mobile hardware items. To unmount any of these media safely, use the
   <guimenu>Unmount Volume</guimenu> (GNOME) feature of the file manager.
   <phrase os="sled">For more details refer to <xref
   linkend="book.gnomeuser"/>.</phrase>
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>External Hard Disks (USB and FireWire)</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      As soon as an external hard disk is correctly recognized by the
      system, its icon appears in the file manager. Clicking the icon
      displays the contents of the drive. It is possible to create folders
      and files here and edit or delete them. To rename a hard disk from the
      name it had been given by the system, select the corresponding menu
      item from the menu that opens when the icon is right-clicked. This
      name change is limited to display in the file manager. The descriptor
      by which the device is mounted in <filename>/media</filename> remains
      unaffected by this.
     </para>
     <remark> 2008-04-25 - bg: maybe we should add a remark about
       filesystems on external hard drives in future. Using the same
       disk with different users strongly depends on the selected
       filesystem.
      </remark>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>USB Flash Drives</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      These devices are handled by the system just like external hard disks.
      It is similarly possible to rename the entries in the file manager.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry os="sled">
    <term>Digital Cameras (USB and FireWire)</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Digital cameras recognized by the system also appear as external drives
      in the overview of the file manager.  <phrase os="sled">The images
      can then be processed using &fspot;. For advanced photo processing use
      The GIMP. For a short introduction to f-spot and The GIMP, see <xref
      linkend="cha.gnome.fspot"/> and <xref linkend="cha.gimp"/>.</phrase>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.mobile.comm">
  <title>Cellular Phones and PDAs</title><indexterm>

  <primary>mobility</primary>

  <secondary>cellular phones</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>mobility</primary>

  <secondary>PDAs</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>cellular phones</primary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>PDAs</primary></indexterm>

  <para>
   A desktop system or a laptop can communicate with a cellular phone via
   Bluetooth or IrDA. Some models support both protocols and some only one
   of the two. The usage areas for the two protocols and the corresponding
   extended documentation has already been mentioned in
   <xref linkend="sec.mobile.nbook.soft.wifi"/>. The configuration of these
   protocols on the cellular phones themselves is described in their
   manuals.
<!--taroth 081020: MOBILE - commenting as chapter as been excluded for
    now-->
<!--The configuration of the
   Linux side is described in <xref linkend="sec.pcmcia.btooth"/> and
   <xref linkend="sec.pcmcia.irda"/>.-->
  </para>

  <para>
   <indexterm>
   <primary>synchronizing data</primary>
   <secondary>Evolution</secondary>
   </indexterm> <indexterm>
   <primary>synchronizing data</primary>
   <secondary>Kontact</secondary>
   </indexterm> <indexterm>
   <primary>Evolution</primary>
   </indexterm> <indexterm>
   <primary>Kontact</primary>
   </indexterm> The support for synchronizing with handheld devices
   manufactured by Palm, Inc., is already built into Evolution and Kontact.
   Initial connection with the device is easily performed with the
   assistance of a wizard. Once the support for Palm Pilots is configured,
   it is necessary to determine which type of data should be synchronized
   (addresses, appointments, etc.). <phrase os="sled"> For more
   information, see <xref linkend="book.gnomeuser"/>.</phrase>
  </para>

  <para os="sled">
   A more sophisticated synchronization solution is available with the
   program <literal>opensync</literal> (see the package libopensync and the
   respective plug-ins for the various devices).
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.mobile.info">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   The central point of reference for all questions regarding mobile devices
   and Linux is <ulink url="http://tuxmobil.org/"/>. Various sections of
   that Web site deal with the hardware and software aspects of laptops,
   PDAs, cellular phones and other mobile hardware.
  </para>

  <para>
   A similar approach to that of <ulink url="http://tuxmobil.org/"/> is made
   by <ulink url="http://www.linux-on-laptops.com/"/>. Information about
   laptops and handhelds can be found here.
  </para>

  <para>
   &suse; maintains a mailing list in German dedicated to the subject of
   laptops. See
   <ulink url="http://lists.opensuse.org/opensuse-mobile-de/"/>. On this
   list, users and developers discuss all aspects of mobile computing with
   &productname;. Postings in English are answered, but the majority of the
   archived information is only available in German. Use
   <ulink url="http://lists.opensuse.org/opensuse-mobile/"/> for English
   postings.
  </para>

  <para>
   Information about <literal>OpenSync</literal> is available on
   <ulink url="http://opensync.org/"/>.
  </para><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.mobility"/>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
