<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!-- fs: 2010-02-01: 
     Documentation for the YaST Squid module needs to be added -->
<chapter id="cha.squid">
 <title>The Proxy Server Squid</title><indexterm>
 <primary>Squid</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>proxies</primary>
 <see>Squid</see></indexterm>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   Squid is a widely-used proxy cache for Linux and Unix platforms. This
   means that it stores requested Internet objects, such as data on a Web or
   FTP server, on a machine that is closer to the requesting workstation
   than the server. It may be set up in multiple hierarchies to assure
   optimal response times and low bandwidth usage, even in modes that are
   transparent for the end user. Additional software like squidGuard may be
   used to filter Web contents.
  </para>
 </abstract><indexterm>
 <primary>Squid</primary>
 <secondary>caches</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>proxies</primary>
 <secondary>caches</secondary></indexterm>
 <para>
  Squid acts as a proxy cache. It redirects object requests from clients (in
  this case, from Web browsers) to the server. When the requested objects
  arrive from the server, it delivers the objects to the client and keeps a
  copy of them in the hard disk cache. One of the advantages of caching is
  that several clients requesting the same object can be served from the
  hard disk cache. This enables clients to receive the data much faster than
  from the Internet. This procedure also reduces the network traffic.
  <indexterm>
  <primary>proxies</primary>
  <secondary>advantages</secondary>
  </indexterm>
 </para>
 <para>
  <indexterm>
  <primary>Squid</primary>
  <secondary>features</secondary>
  </indexterm> Along with the actual caching, Squid offers a wide range of
  features such as distributing the load over intercommunicating hierarchies
  of proxy servers, defining strict access control lists for all clients
  accessing the proxy, allowing or denying access to specific Web pages with
  the help of other applications, and generating statistics about
  frequently-visited Web pages for the assessment of the users' surfing
  habits. Squid is not a generic proxy. It normally proxies only HTTP
  connections. It supports the protocols FTP, Gopher, SSL, and WAIS, but it
  does not support other Internet protocols, such as Real Audio, news, or
  video conferencing. Because Squid only supports the UDP protocol to
  provide communication between different caches, many other multimedia
  programs are not supported.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.squid.cacheinfos">
  <title>Some Facts about Proxy Caches</title>

  <para>
   As a proxy cache, Squid can be used in several ways. When combined with a
   firewall, it can help with security. Multiple proxies can be used
   together. It can also determine what types of objects should be cached
   and for how long.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.squid.security">
   <title>Squid and Security</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>security</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>security</primary>
   <secondary>Squid</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    It is possible to use Squid together with a firewall to secure internal
    networks from the outside using a proxy cache. The firewall denies all
    clients access to external services except Squid. All Web connections
    must be established by the proxy. With this configuration, Squid
    completely controls Web access.
   </para>
   <para>
    <indexterm>
    <primary>Squid</primary>
    <secondary>security</secondary>
    </indexterm> If the firewall configuration includes a DMZ, the proxy
    should operate within this zone.
    <xref linkend="sec.squid.proxyconfigtrans"/> describes how to implement
    a <emphasis>transparent</emphasis> proxy. This simplifies the
    configuration of the clients, because in this case they do not need any
    information about the proxy.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.squid.morecaches">
   <title>Multiple Caches</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>caches</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Several instances of Squid can be configured to exchange objects between
    them. This reduces the total system load and increases the chances of
    finding an object already existing in the local network. It is also
    possible to configure cache hierarchies, so a cache is able to forward
    object requests to sibling caches or to a parent cache&mdash;causing it
    to get objects from another cache in the local network or directly from
    the source.
   </para>
   <para>
    Choosing the appropriate topology for the cache hierarchy is very
    important, because it is not desirable to increase the overall traffic
    on the network. For a very large network, it would make sense to
    configure a proxy server for every subnet and connect them to a
    parent proxy, which in turn is connected to the proxy cache of the ISP.
   </para>
   <para>
    All this communication is handled by ICP (Internet cache protocol)
    running on top of the UDP protocol. Data transfers between caches are
    handled using HTTP (hypertext transmission protocol) based on TCP.
   </para>
   <para>
    To find the most appropriate server from which to get the objects, one
    cache sends an ICP request to all sibling proxies. These answer the
    requests via ICP responses with a HIT code if the object was detected or
    a MISS if it was not. If multiple HIT responses were found, the proxy
    server decides from which server to download, depending on factors such
    as which cache sent the fastest answer or which one is closer. If no
    satisfactory responses are received, the request is sent to the parent
    cache.
   </para>
   <tip>
    <para>
     To avoid duplication of objects in different caches in the network,
     other ICP protocols are used, such as CARP (cache array routing
     protocol) or HTCP (hypertext cache protocol). The more objects
     maintained in the network, the greater the possibility of finding the
     desired one.
    </para>
   </tip>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.squid.latching">
   <title>Caching Internet Objects</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>object status</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Not all objects available in the network are static. There are a lot of
    dynamically generated CGI pages, visitor counters, and encrypted SSL
    content documents. Objects like this are not cached because they change
    each time they are accessed.
   </para>
   <para>
    The question remains as to how long all the other objects stored in the
    cache should stay there. To determine this, all objects in the cache are
    assigned one of various possible states. Web and proxy servers find out
    the status of an object by adding headers to these objects, such as
    <quote>Last modified</quote> or <quote>Expires</quote> and the
    corresponding date. Other headers specifying that objects must not be
    cached are used as well.
   </para>
   <para>
    Objects in the cache are normally replaced, because of a lack of free hard
    disk space, using algorithms such as LRU (last recently used).
    This means that the proxy expunges the objects that have not been
    requested for the longest time.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.squid.sysneeds">
  <title>System Requirements</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Squid</primary>

  <secondary>system requirements</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   The most important thing is to determine the maximum network load the
   system must bear. Therefore, it is important to pay more attention to the
   load peaks, because these might be more than four times the day's
   average. When in doubt, it would be better to overestimate the system's
   requirements, because having Squid working close to the limit of its
   capabilities could lead to a severe loss in the quality of the service.
   The following sections point to the system factors in order of
   significance.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.squid.sysneeds.disk">
   <title>Hard Disks</title>
   <para>
    Speed plays an important role in the caching process, so this factor
    deserves special attention. For hard disks, this parameter is described
    as <emphasis>random seek time</emphasis>, measured in milliseconds.
    Because the data blocks that Squid reads from or writes to the hard disk
    tend to be rather small, the seek time of the hard disk is more
    important than its data throughput. For the purposes of a proxy, hard
    disks with high rotation speeds are probably the better choice, because
    they allow the read-write head to be positioned in the required spot
    more quickly. One possibility to speed up the system is to use a number
    of disks concurrently or to employ striping RAID arrays.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.squid.sysneeds.cache_size">
   <title>Size of the Disk Cache</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>caches</secondary>
   <tertiary>size</tertiary></indexterm>
   <para>
    In a small cache, the probability of a HIT (finding the requested object
    already located there) is small, because the cache is easily filled and
    the less requested objects are replaced by newer ones. If, for example,
    one GB is available for the cache and the users only surf ten MB per
    day, it would take more than one hundred days to fill the cache.
   </para>
   <para>
    The easiest way to determine the needed cache size is to consider the
    maximum transfer rate of the connection. With a 1 Mbit/s connection, the
    maximum transfer rate is 125 KB/s. If all this traffic ends up in the
    cache, in one hour it would add up to 450 MB and, assuming that all this
    traffic is generated in only eight working hours, it would reach
    3.6&nbsp;GB in one day. Because the connection is normally not used to
    its upper volume limit, it can be assumed that the total data volume
    handled by the cache is approximately 2&nbsp;GB. This is why 2&nbsp;GB
    of disk space is required in the example for Squid to keep one day's
    worth of browsed data cached.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.squid.ram">
   <title>RAM</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>RAM and</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    The amount of memory (RAM) required by Squid directly correlates to the
    number of objects in the cache. Squid also stores cache object
    references and frequently requested objects in the main memory to speed
    up retrieval of this data. Random access memory is much faster than a
    hard disk.
   </para>
   <para>
    In addition to that, there is other data that Squid needs to keep in
    memory, such as a table with all the IP addresses handled, an exact
    domain name cache, the most frequently requested objects, access control
    lists, buffers, and more.
   </para>
   <para>
    It is very important to have sufficient memory for the Squid process,
    because system performance is dramatically reduced if it must be swapped
    to disk. The cachemgr.cgi tool can be used for the cache memory
    management. This tool is introduced in
    <xref linkend="sec.squid.cachemgr"/>.
<!-- ke: This recommendation probably does not make sense anymore:
    Sites with huge network traffic
    should consider using an &amd64; or &intel64; system with more than
    4&nbsp;GB of memory.
    -->
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.squid.cpu">
   <title>CPU</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>CPU and</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Squid is not a program that requires intensive CPU usage. The load of
    the processor is only increased while the contents of the cache are
    loaded or checked. Using a multiprocessor machine does not increase the
    performance of the system. To increase efficiency, it is better to buy
    faster disks or add more memory.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.squid.start">
  <title>Starting Squid</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Squid</primary>

  <secondary>starting</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   If not already installed, install the <systemitem>squid</systemitem>
   package. <systemitem>squid</systemitem> does not belong to the default
   &productnamereg; installation scope.
  </para>

  <para>
   Squid is already preconfigured in &slsreg;, you can start it right after
   the installation. To ensure a smooth start-up, the network should be
   configured in a way that at least one name server and the Internet can be
   reached. Problems can arise if a dial-up connection is used with a
   dynamic DNS configuration. In this case, at least the name server should
   be entered, because Squid does not start if it does not detect a DNS
   server in <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename>.
  </para><indexterm>

  <primary>configuration files</primary>

  <secondary>resolv.conf</secondary></indexterm>

  <sect2 id="sec.squid.start.commands">
   <title>Commands for Starting and Stopping Squid</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>directories</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>scripts</primary>
   <secondary>init.d</secondary>
   <tertiary>squid</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>permissions</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>configuration files</primary>
   <secondary>squid.conf</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    To start Squid, enter
    <command>systemctl start squid.service</command> at the command
    line as <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>. In the initial
    start-up, the directory structure of the cache must first be defined in
    <filename>/var/cache/squid</filename>. This is done automatically by the
    start script <!--<filename>/etc/init.d/squid</filename> -->and can take a few
    seconds or even minutes. If <literal>done</literal> appears to the right
    in green, Squid has been successfully loaded. To test the functionality
    of Squid on the local system, enter <option>localhost</option> as the
    proxy and <option>3128</option> as the port in the browser.
   </para>
   <para>
    To allow users from the local system and other systems to access Squid
    and the Internet, change the entry in the configuration files
    <filename>/etc/squid/squid.conf</filename> from <option>http_access deny
    all</option> to <option>http_access allow all</option>. However, in
    doing so, consider that Squid is made completely accessible to anyone by
    this action. Therefore, define ACLs that control access to the proxy.
    More information about this is available in
    <xref linkend="sec.squid.acl"/>.
   </para><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>stopping</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    After modifying the configuration file
    <filename>/etc/squid/squid.conf</filename>, Squid must reload the
    configuration file. Do this with
    <command>systemctl reload squid.service</command>. Alternatively,
    completely restart Squid with
    <command>systemctl restart squid.service</command>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The command <command>systemctl status squid.service</command> can
    be used to check if the proxy is running. The command
    <command>systemctl stop squid.service</command> causes Squid to
    shut down. This can take a while, because Squid waits up to half a
    minute (<option>shutdown_lifetime</option> option in
    <filename>/etc/squid/squid.conf</filename>) before dropping the
    connections to the clients and writing its data to the disk.
   </para>
   <warning>
    <title>Terminating Squid</title>
    <para>
     <indexterm>
     <primary>Squid</primary>
     <secondary>caches</secondary>
     <tertiary>damaged</tertiary>
     </indexterm> Terminating Squid with <command>kill</command> or
     <command>killall</command> can damage the cache. To be able to restart
     Squid, a damaged cache must be deleted.
    </para>
   </warning><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>log files</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>log files</primary>
   <secondary>Squid</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>troubleshooting</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    If Squid dies after a short period of time even though it was started
    successfully, check whether there is a faulty name server entry or
    whether the <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename> file is missing. Squid
    logs the cause of a start-up failure in the file
    <filename>/var/log/squid/cache.log</filename>. If Squid should be loaded
    automatically when the system boots, enable the service with
    <command>systemctl enable squid.service</command>.
   </para><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>uninstalling</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    An uninstall of Squid does not remove the cache hierarchy or the log
    files. To remove these, delete the <filename>/var/cache/squid</filename>
    directory manually.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.squid.start.local_dns">
   <title>Local DNS Server</title><indexterm>
   <primary>DNS</primary>
   <secondary>Squid and</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>DNS</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>configuration files</primary>
   <secondary>named.conf</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Setting up a local DNS server makes sense even if it does not manage its
    own domain. It then simply acts as a caching-only name server and is
    also able to resolve DNS requests via the root name servers without
    requiring any special configuration (see
    <xref linkend="sec.dns.bind"/>). How this can be done depends on whether
    you chose dynamic DNS during the configuration of the Internet
    connection.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Dynamic DNS</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Normally, with dynamic DNS, the DNS server is set by the provider
       during the establishment of the Internet connection and the local
       <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename> file is adjusted automatically.
       This behavior is controlled in the
       <filename>/etc/sysconfig/network/config</filename> file with the
       <systemitem
	class="constant">NETCONFIG_DNS_POLICY</systemitem>
       sysconfig variable. Set
       <systemitem
	class="constant">NETCONFIG_DNS_POLICY</systemitem> to
       <systemitem class="constant">""</systemitem> with the &yast;
       sysconfig editor.
<!-- fs 2013-10-25: systemd (see <xref
       linkend="sec.boot.sysconfig.edit"/>) -->
        Then enter the local DNS server in the
       <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename> file with the IP address
       <systemitem
	class="ipaddress">127.0.0.1</systemitem> for
       <systemitem
	class="domainname">localhost</systemitem>. This way
       Squid can always find the local name server when it starts.
      </para>
      <remark>FIXME ke: check it.  Do you have to set more variables?</remark>
      <para>
       To make the provider's name server accessible, enter it in the
       configuration file <filename>/etc/named.conf</filename> under
       <systemitem>forwarders</systemitem> along with its IP address. With
       dynamic DNS, this can be achieved automatically during connection
       establishment by setting the sysconfig variable
       <systemitem
	class="constant">NETCONFIG_DNS_POLICY</systemitem> to
       <systemitem class="constant">auto</systemitem>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Static DNS</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       With static DNS, no automatic DNS adjustments take place while
       establishing a connection, so there is no need to change any
       sysconfig variables. You must, however, enter the local DNS server in
       the file <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename> as described above.
       Additionally, the providers static name server must be entered
       manually in the <filename>/etc/named.conf</filename> file under
       <systemitem>forwarders</systemitem> along with its IP address.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <tip>
    <title>DNS and Firewall</title>
    <para>
     If you have a firewall running, make sure DNS requests can pass it.
    </para>
   </tip>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.squid.configfile">
  <title>The /etc/squid/squid.conf Configuration File</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Squid</primary>

  <secondary>configuring</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>configuring</primary>

  <secondary>Squid</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>configuration files</primary>

  <secondary>squid.conf</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   All Squid proxy server settings are made in the
   <filename>/etc/squid/squid.conf</filename> file. To start Squid for the
   first time, no changes are necessary in this file, but external clients
   are initially denied access. The proxy is available for
   <systemitem class="domainname">localhost</systemitem>. The default port
   is <option>3128</option>. The pre-installed configuration file
   <filename>/etc/squid/squid.conf</filename> provides detailed information
   about the options and many examples. Nearly all entries begin with
   <literal>#</literal> (the lines are commented) and the relevant
   specifications can be found at the end of the line. The given values
   almost always correlate with the default values, so removing the comment
   signs without changing any of the parameters actually has little effect
   in most cases. If possible, leave the sample as it is and insert the
   options along with the modified parameters in the line below. This way,
   the default values may easily be recovered and compared with the changes.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>Adapting the Configuration File after an Update</title>
   <para>
    If you have updated from an earlier Squid version, it is recommended to
    edit the new <filename>/etc/squid/squid.conf</filename> and only apply
    the changes made in the previous file. If you try to use the old
    <filename>squid.conf</filename>, you risk that the configuration no
    longer works, because options are sometimes modified and new changes
    added.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <sect2 id="sec.squid.configfile.general">
   <title>General Configuration Options (Selection)</title>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>http_port 3128</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This is the port on which Squid listens for client requests. The
       default port is <option>3128</option>, but <option>8080</option> is
       also common. If desired, specify several port numbers separated by
       blank spaces.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      cache_peer <replaceable>hostname</replaceable><replaceable>type</replaceable><replaceable>proxy-port</replaceable><replaceable>icp-port</replaceable>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Here, enter a parent proxy, for example, if you want to use the proxy
       of your ISP. As <replaceable>hostname</replaceable>, enter the name
       or IP address of the proxy to use and, as
       <replaceable>type</replaceable>, enter <option>parent</option>. For
       <replaceable>proxy-port</replaceable>, enter the port number that is
       also given by the operator of the parent for use in the browser
       (usually <option>8080</option>). Set the
       <replaceable>icp-port</replaceable> to <option>7</option> or
       <option>0</option> if the ICP port of the parent is not known and its
       use is irrelevant to the provider. In addition,
       <option>default</option> and <option>no-query</option> may be
       specified after the port numbers to prohibit the use of the ICP
       protocol. Squid then behaves like a normal browser as far as the
       provider's proxy is concerned.
       <remark>This para is horrible, and I don't have a good
       explanation yet. The description tries to configure squid in a
       way, that the parent proxy only sees a browser and no child.
       This really needs an update - bg</remark>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>cache_mem 8 MB</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This entry defines the amount of memory Squid can use for very
       popular replies. The default is <option>8 MB</option>. This does not
       specify the memory usage of Squid and may be exceeded.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>cache_dir ufs /var/cache/squid/ 100 16 256</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The entry <emphasis>cache_dir</emphasis> defines the directory where
       all the objects are stored on disk. The numbers at the end indicate
       the maximum disk space in MB to use and the number of directories in
       the first and second level. The <option>ufs</option> parameter should
       be left alone. The default is 100 MB occupied disk space in the
       <filename>/var/cache/squid</filename> directory and creation of 16
       subdirectories inside it, each containing 256 more subdirectories.
       When specifying the disk space to use, leave sufficient reserve disk
       space. Values from a minimum of 50% to a maximum of 80% of the
       available disk space make the most sense here. The last two numbers
       for the directories should only be increased with caution, because
       too many directories can also lead to performance problems. If you
       have several disks that share the cache, enter several
       <emphasis>cache_dir</emphasis> lines.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>cache_access_log /var/log/squid/access.log</term>
     <term>cache_log  /var/log/squid/cache.log</term>
     <term>cache_store_log  /var/log/squid/store.log</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <indexterm>
       <primary>Squid</primary>
       <secondary>log files</secondary>
       </indexterm> <indexterm>
       <primary>log files</primary>
       <secondary>Squid</secondary>
       </indexterm> These three entries specify the paths where Squid log files
       all its actions. Normally, nothing is changed here. If Squid is
       experiencing a heavy usage burden, it might make sense to distribute
       the cache and the log files over several disks.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>emulate_httpd_log off</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If the entry is set to <emphasis>on</emphasis>, obtain readable log
       files. Some evaluation programs cannot interpret this, however.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>client_netmask 255.255.255.255</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       With this entry, mask IP addresses of clients in the log files. The
       last digit of the IP address is set to zero if you enter
       <systemitem class="netmask">255.255.255.0</systemitem> here. You may
       protect the privacy of your clients this way.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>ftp_user Squid@</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       With this, set the password Squid should use for the anonymous FTP
       login. It can make sense to specify a valid e-mail address here,
       because some FTP servers check these for validity.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>cache_mgr webmaster</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       An e-mail address to which Squid sends a message if it unexpectedly
       crashes. The default is <emphasis>webmaster</emphasis>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>logfile_rotate 0</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If you run <command>squid</command>&nbsp;<option>-k rotate</option>,
       <command>Squid</command> can rotate secured log files. The files are
       numbered in this process and, after reaching the specified value, the
       oldest file is overwritten. The default value is <option>0</option>
       because archiving and deleting log files in &productname; is carried
       out by a cron job set in the configuration file
       <filename>/etc/logrotate/squid</filename>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>append_domain &lt;domain&gt;</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       With <emphasis>append_domain</emphasis>, specify which domain to
       append automatically when none is given. Usually, your own domain is
       entered here, so entering <emphasis>www</emphasis> in the browser
       accesses your own Web server.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>forwarded_for on</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If you set the entry to <emphasis>off</emphasis>, Squid removes the
       IP address and the system name of the client from HTTP requests.
       Otherwise it adds a line to the header like
      </para>
<screen>X-Forwarded-For: &exampleclientip;</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>negative_ttl 5 minutes; negative_dns_ttl 5 minutes</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Normally, you do not need to change these values. If you have a
       dial-up connection, however, the Internet may, at times, not be
       accessible. Squid makes a note of the failed requests then refuses to
       issue new ones, although the Internet connection has been
       reestablished. In a case such as this, change the
       <emphasis>minutes</emphasis> to <emphasis>seconds</emphasis>. Then,
       after clicking <emphasis>Reload</emphasis> in the browser, the
       dial-up process should be reengaged after a few seconds.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>never_direct allow <replaceable>acl_name</replaceable>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To prevent Squid from taking requests directly from the Internet, use
       the above command to force connection to another proxy. This must
       have previously been entered in <emphasis>cache_peer</emphasis>. If
       <option>all</option> is specified as the
       <replaceable>acl_name</replaceable>, force all requests to be
       forwarded directly to the <emphasis>parent</emphasis>. This might be
       necessary, for example, if you are using a provider that strictly
       stipulates the use of its proxies or denies its firewall direct
       Internet access.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.squid.acl">
   <title>Options for Access Controls</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>ACLs</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>permissions</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Squid provides a detailed system for controlling the access to the
    proxy. By implementing ACLs, it can be configured easily and
    comprehensively. This involves lists with rules that are processed
    sequentially. ACLs must be defined before they can be used. Some default
    ACLs, such as <emphasis>all</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>localhost</emphasis>, already exist. However, the mere
    definition of an ACL does not mean that it is actually applied. This
    only happens in conjunction with <emphasis>http_access</emphasis> rules.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>acl &lt;acl_name&gt; &lt;type&gt; &lt;data&gt;</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <indexterm>
       <primary>configuration files</primary>
       <secondary>squid.conf</secondary>
       </indexterm> An ACL requires at least three specifications to define
       it. The name <emphasis>&lt;acl_name&gt;</emphasis> can be chosen
       arbitrarily. For <emphasis>&lt;type&gt;</emphasis>, select from a
       variety of different options, which can be found in the
       <emphasis>ACCESS CONTROLS</emphasis> section in the
       <filename>/etc/squid/squid.conf</filename> file. The specification
       for <emphasis>&lt;data&gt;</emphasis> depends on the individual ACL
       type and can also be read from a file, for example, via host names, IP
       addresses, or URLs. The following are some simple examples:
      </para>
<screen>
acl mysurfers srcdomain .my-domain.com
acl teachers src 192.168.1.0/255.255.255.0
acl students src 192.168.7.0-192.168.9.0/255.255.255.0
acl lunch time MTWHF 12:00-15:00
</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>http_access allow &lt;acl_name&gt;</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis>http_access</emphasis> defines who is allowed to use the
       proxy and who can access what on the Internet. For this, ACLs must be
       given. <emphasis>localhost</emphasis> and <emphasis>all</emphasis>
       have already been defined above, which can deny or allow access via
       <emphasis>deny</emphasis> or <emphasis>allow</emphasis>. A list
       containing any number of <emphasis>http_access</emphasis> entries can
       be created, processed from top to bottom, and, depending on which
       occurs first, access is allowed or denied to the respective URL. The
       last entry should always be <emphasis>http_access deny
       all</emphasis>. In the following example, the
       <emphasis>localhost</emphasis> has free access to everything while
       all other hosts are denied access completely.
      </para>
<screen>
http_access allow localhost
http_access deny all
</screen>
      <para>
       In another example using these rules, the group
       <systemitem class="groupname">teachers</systemitem> always has access
       to the Internet. The group
       <systemitem class="groupname">students</systemitem> only gets access
       Monday to Friday during lunch time.
      </para>
<screen>
http_access deny localhost
http_access allow teachers
http_access allow students lunch time
http_access deny all
</screen>
      <para>
       The list with the <emphasis>http_access</emphasis> entries should
       only be entered, for the sake of readability, at the designated
       position in the <filename>/etc/squid/squid.conf</filename> file. That
       is, between the text
      </para>
<screen>
# INSERT YOUR OWN RULE(S) HERE TO ALLOW ACCESS FROM YOUR
# CLIENTS
</screen>
      <para>
       and the last
      </para>
<screen>http_access deny all</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>redirect_program /usr/bin/squidGuard</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       With this option, specify a redirector such as squidGuard, which
       allows the blocking of unwanted URLs. Internet access can be
       individually controlled for various user groups with the help of
       proxy authentication and the appropriate ACLs. squidGuard is a
       separate package that can be installed and configured.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>auth_param basic program /usr/sbin/pam_auth</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If users must be authenticated on the proxy, set a corresponding
       program, such as pam_auth. When accessing pam_auth for the first
       time, the user sees a login window in which to enter the user name and
       password. In addition, an ACL is still required, so only clients with
       a valid login can use the Internet:
      </para>
<screen>
acl password proxy_auth REQUIRED

http_access allow password
http_access deny all
</screen>
      <para>
       The <emphasis>REQUIRED</emphasis> after
       <emphasis>proxy_auth</emphasis> can be replaced with a list of
       permitted user names or with the path to such a list.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>ident_lookup_access allow &lt;acl_name&gt;</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       With this, have an ident request run for all ACL-defined clients to
       find each user's identity. If you apply <emphasis>all</emphasis> to
       the <emphasis>&lt;acl_name&gt;</emphasis>, this is valid for all
       clients. Also, an ident daemon must be running on all clients. For
       Linux, install the pidentd package for this purpose. For Microsoft
       Windows, free software is available for download from the Internet.
       To ensure that only clients with a successful ident lookup are
       permitted, define a corresponding ACL here:
      </para>
<screen>
acl identhosts ident REQUIRED

http_access allow identhosts
http_access deny all
</screen>
      <para>
       Here, too, replace <emphasis>REQUIRED</emphasis> with a list of
       permitted user names. Using <emphasis>ident</emphasis> can slow down
       the access time quite a bit, because ident lookups are repeated for
       each request.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.squid.proxyconfigtrans">
  <title>Configuring a Transparent Proxy</title><indexterm>

  <primary>proxies</primary>

  <secondary>transparent</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>Squid</primary>

  <secondary>transparent proxies</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   The usual way of working with proxy servers is the following: the Web
   browser sends requests to a certain port in the proxy server and the
   proxy provides these required objects, whether they are in its cache or
   not. When working in a network, several situations may arise:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For security reasons, it is recommended that all clients use a proxy to
     surf the Internet.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     All clients must use a proxy, regardless of whether they are aware of
     it.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The proxy in a network is moved, but the existing clients need to
     retain their old configuration.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   In all these cases, a transparent proxy may be used. The principle is
   very easy: the proxy intercepts and answers the requests of the Web
   browser, so the Web browser receives the requested pages without knowing
   from where they are coming. As the name indicates, the entire process is
   done transparently.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.squid.proxyconfigtrans.squid_conf">
   <title>Configuration Options in /etc/squid/squid.conf</title><indexterm>
   <primary>configuration files</primary>
   <secondary>squid.conf</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    To inform squid that it should act as a transparent proxy, use the option
    <systemitem>transparent</systemitem> at the tag
    <systemitem>http_port</systemitem> in the main configuration file
    <filename>/etc/squid/squid.conf</filename>. After restarting squid, the
    only other thing that must be done is to reconfigure the firewall to
    redirect the HTTP port to the port given in
    <systemitem>http_port</systemitem>. In the following squid configuration
    line, this would be the port 3128.
   </para>
<screen>http_port 3128 transparent</screen>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.squid.proxyconfigtrans.firewall">
   <title>Firewall Configuration with &susefirewall;</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>firewalls and</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>firewalls</primary>
   <secondary>Squid and</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Now redirect all incoming requests via the firewall with help of a port
    forwarding rule to the Squid port. To do this, use the enclosed tool
    &susefirewall;, described in
    <xref
    linkend="sec.security.firewall.SuSE.yast"/>. Its configuration
    file can be found in <filename>/etc/sysconfig/&susefirewallfiles;</filename>.
    The configuration file consists of well-documented entries. To set a
    transparent proxy, you must configure several firewall options:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Device pointing to the Internet:
      <systemitem>FW_DEV_EXT</systemitem>="eth1"
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Device pointing to the network:
      <systemitem>FW_DEV_INT</systemitem>="eth0"
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    <indexterm>
    <primary>configuration files</primary>
    <secondary>services</secondary>
    </indexterm> Define ports and services (see
    <filename>/etc/services</filename>) on the firewall that are accessed
    from untrusted (external) networks such as the Internet. In this
    example, only Web services are offered to the outside:
   </para>
<screen>
FW_SERVICES_EXT_TCP="www"
</screen>
   <para>
    Define ports or services (see <filename>/etc/services</filename>) on the
    firewall that are accessed from the secure (internal) network, both via
    TCP and UDP:
   </para>
<screen>
FW_SERVICES_INT_TCP="domain www 3128"
FW_SERVICES_INT_UDP="domain"
</screen>
   <para>
    This allows accessing Web services and Squid (whose default port is
    <option>3128</option>).
<!--rwalter merging-->
    The service <quote>domain</quote> stands for DNS (domain name service).
    This service is commonly used. Otherwise, simply take it out of the
    above entries and set the following option to <literal>no</literal>:
   </para>
<screen>
FW_SERVICE_DNS="yes"
</screen>
   <para>
    The most important option is option number <option>15</option>:
   </para>
   <example id="dat.fw.opt15">
    <title>Firewall Configuration: Option 15</title>
<screen># 15.)
# Which accesses to services should be redirected to a local port on
# the firewall machine?
#
# This option can be used to force all internal users to surf via
# your squid proxy, or transparently redirect incoming webtraffic to
# a secure webserver.
#
# Format: 
# list of &lt;source network>[,&lt;destination network>,&lt;protocol>[,dport[:lport]]
# Where protocol is either tcp or udp. dport is the original
# destination port and lport the port on the local machine to
# redirect the traffic to
#
# An exclamation mark in front of source or destination network
# means everything EXCEPT the specified network
#
# Example: "10.0.0.0/8,0/0,tcp,80,3128 0/0,172.20.1.1,tcp,80,8080"
</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    The comments above show the syntax to follow. First, enter the IP
    address and the netmask of the internal networks accessing the proxy
    firewall. Second, enter the IP address and the netmask to which these
    clients send their requests. In the case of Web browsers, specify the
    networks <systemitem>0/0</systemitem>, a wild card that means <quote>to
    everywhere.</quote> After that, enter the original port to which these
    requests are sent and, finally, the port to which all these requests are
    redirected. Because Squid supports protocols other than HTTP, redirect
    requests from other ports to the proxy, such as FTP (port 21), HTTPS, or
    SSL (port 443). In this example, Web services (port <option>80</option>)
    are redirected to the proxy port (port <option>3128</option>). If there
    are more networks or services to add, they must be separated by a blank
    space in the respective entry.
   </para>
<screen>
FW_REDIRECT="192.168.0.0/16,0/0,tcp,80,3128"
</screen>
   <para>
    To start the firewall and the new configuration with it, change an entry
    in the <filename>/etc/sysconfig/&susefirewallfiles;</filename> file. The entry
    <systemitem>START_FW</systemitem> must be set to
    <literal>"yes"</literal>.
   </para>
   <para>
    <indexterm>
    <primary>log files</primary>
    <secondary>Squid</secondary>
    </indexterm> <indexterm>
    <primary>Squid</primary>
    <secondary>log files</secondary>
    </indexterm> Start Squid as shown in <xref linkend="sec.squid.start"/>.
    To verify that everything is working properly, check the Squid log files in
    <filename>/var/log/squid/access.log</filename>. <indexterm>
    <primary>ports</primary>
    <secondary>scanning</secondary>
    </indexterm> <indexterm>
    <primary>Squid</primary>
    <secondary>transparent proxies</secondary>
    </indexterm> To verify that all ports are correctly configured, perform
    a port scan on the machine from any computer outside your network. Only
    the Web services (port 80) should be open. To scan the ports with nmap,
    the command syntax is <command>nmap</command>&nbsp;<option>-O
    IP_address</option>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.squid.cachemgr">
  <title>cachemgr.cgi</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Squid</primary>

  <secondary>statistics</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>Squid</primary>

  <secondary>cachemgr.cgi</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   The cache manager (cachemgr.cgi) is a CGI utility for displaying
   statistics about the memory usage of a running Squid process. It is also
   a more convenient way to manage the cache and view statistics without
   logging the server.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.squid.cachemgr.setup">
   <title>Setup</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>Apache</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Apache</primary>
   <secondary>Squid</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    First, a running Web server on your system is required. Configure Apache
    as described in <xref linkend="cha.apache2"/>. To check if Apache is
    already running, as <systemitem
    class="username">root</systemitem>
    enter the command
    <command>systemctl status apache2.service</command>. <!--If a message
    like this appears:
   </para>
<screen>
Checking for service httpd: OK 
Server uptime: 1 day 18 hours 29 minutes 39 seconds   
</screen>
   <para>
    Apache is running on the machine.--> Otherwise, enter
    <command>systemctl start apache2.service</command> to start Apache
    with the &productname; default settings. The last step to set it up is
    to copy the file <filename>cachemgr.cgi</filename> to the Apache
    directory <filename>cgi-bin</filename>. For 32-bit, this works as
    follows:
   </para>
<screen>cp /usr/lib/squid/cachemgr.cgi /srv/www/cgi-bin/</screen>
   <para>
    In a 64-bit environment, the file <filename>cachemgr.cgi</filename> is
    located below <filename>/usr/lib64/squid/</filename> and the command to
    copy it to the Apache directory is the following:
   </para>
<screen>cp /usr/lib64/squid/cachemgr.cgi /srv/www/cgi-bin/</screen>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.squid.cachemgr.acls">
   <title>Cache Manager ACLs in /etc/squid/squid.conf</title><indexterm>
   <primary>Squid</primary>
   <secondary>access controls</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>configuration files</primary>
   <secondary>squid.conf</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    There are some default settings in the original file required for the
    cache manager. First, two ACLs are defined, then http_access options use
    these ACLs to grant access from the CGI script to Squid. The first ACL
    is the most important, because the cache manager tries to communicate
    with Squid over the cache_object protocol.
   </para>
<screen>
acl manager proto cache_object
acl localhost src 127.0.0.1/255.255.255.255
</screen>
   <para>
    The following rules give Apache the access rights to Squid:
   </para>
<screen>
http_access allow manager localhost
http_access deny manager
</screen>
   <para>
    These rules assume that the Web server and Squid are running on the same
    machine. If the communication between the cache manager and Squid
    originates at the Web server on another computer, include an extra ACL
    as in <xref linkend="dat.acl"/>.
   </para>
   <example id="dat.acl">
    <title>Access Rules</title>
<screen>
acl manager proto cache_object
acl localhost src 127.0.0.1/255.255.255.255
acl webserver src 192.168.1.7/255.255.255.255 # webserver IP
</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    Then add the rules in <xref linkend="dat.access"/> to permit access from
    the Web server.
   </para>
   <example id="dat.access">
    <title>Access Rules</title>
<screen>
http_access allow manager localhost
http_access allow manager webserver
http_access deny manager
</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    Configure a password for the manager for access to more options, like
    closing the cache remotely or viewing more information about the cache.
    For this, configure the entry <systemitem>cachemgr_passwd</systemitem>
    with a password for the manager and the list of options to view. This
    list appears as a part of the entry comments in
    <filename>/etc/squid/squid.conf</filename>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Restart Squid every time the configuration file is changed. Do this
    easily with <command>systemctl reload squid.service</command>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.squid.cachemgr.statistics">
   <title>Viewing the Statistics</title>
   <para>
    Go to the corresponding Web
    site&mdash;<ulink url="http://webserver.example.org/cgi-bin/cachemgr.cgi"/>.
    Press <guimenu>continue</guimenu> and browse through the different
    statistics.
<!-- toms 2011-08-25: Link does not work (404)
    More details for each entry shown by the cache manager is in
    the Squid FAQ at
    <ulink url="http://www.squid-cache.org/Doc/FAQ/FAQ-9.html"/>. -->
    <indexterm>
    <primary>Squid</primary>
    <secondary>statistics</secondary>
    </indexterm> <indexterm>
    <primary>Squid</primary>
    <secondary>cachemgr.cgi</secondary>
    </indexterm>
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.squid.squidguard">
  <title>squidGuard</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Squid</primary>

  <secondary>squidGuard</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   This section is not intended to explain an extensive configuration of
   squidGuard, only to introduce it and give some advice for using it. For
   more in-depth configuration issues, refer to the squidGuard Web site at
   <ulink url="http://www.squidguard.org"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   squidGuard is a free (GPL), flexible, and fast filter, redirector, and
   access controller plug-in for Squid. It lets you define multiple access
   rules with different restrictions for different user groups on a Squid
   cache. squidGuard uses Squid's standard redirector interface. squidGuard
   can do the following:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Limit Web access for some users to a list of accepted or well-known Web
     servers or URLs.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Block access to some listed or blacklisted Web servers or URLs for some
     users.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Block access to URLs matching a list of regular expressions or words
     for some users.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Redirect blocked URLs to an <quote>intelligent</quote> CGI-based
     information page.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Redirect unregistered users to a registration form.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Redirect banners to an empty GIF.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Use different access rules based on time of day, day of the week, date,
     etc.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Use different rules for different user groups.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   squidGuard and Squid cannot be used to:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Edit, filter, or censor text inside documents.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Edit, filter, or censor HTML-embedded script languages, such as
     JavaScript or VBscript.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist><indexterm>

  <primary>configuration files</primary>

  <secondary>squidguard.conf</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>configuration files</primary>

  <secondary>squid.conf</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Before it can be used, install
   <systemitem
    class="resource">squidGuard</systemitem>. Provide a
   minimal configuration file as <filename>/etc/squidguard.conf</filename>.
   Find configuration examples in
   <ulink url="http://www.squidguard.org/Doc/examples.html"/>. Experiment
   later with more complicated configuration settings.
  </para>

  <para>
   Next, create a dummy <quote>access denied</quote> page or a more or less
   complex CGI page to redirect Squid if the client requests a blacklisted
   Web site. Using Apache is strongly recommended.
  </para>

  <para>
   Now, configure Squid to use squidGuard. Use the following entry in the
   <filename>/etc/squid/squid.conf</filename> file:
  </para>

<screen>
redirect_program /usr/bin/squidGuard
</screen>

  <para>
   Another option called <systemitem>redirect_children</systemitem>
   configures the number of <quote>redirect</quote> (in this case
   squidGuard) processes running on the machine. The more processes you set,
   the more RAM is required. Try low numbers first, for example <literal>4</literal>.
  </para>

<screen>
redirect_children 4
</screen>

  <para>
   Last, have Squid load the new configuration by running
   <command>systemctl reload squid.service</command>. Now, test your
   settings with a browser.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.squid.calamaris">
  <title>Cache Report Generation with Calamaris</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Squid</primary>

  <secondary>Calamaris</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>Squid</primary>

  <secondary>reports</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Calamaris is a Perl script used to generate reports of cache activity in
   ASCII or HTML format. It works with native Squid access log files. The
   Calamaris home page is located at
   <ulink
   url="http://Calamaris.Cord.de/"/>. This tool does not belong to
   the &productname; default installation scope&mdash;to use it, install the
   <systemitem>calamaris</systemitem> package.
  </para>

  <para>
   Log in as <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> then enter
   <command>cat access.log | calamaris <replaceable>options</replaceable>
   &gt; reportfile</command>. It is important when piping more than one log
   file that the log files are chronologically ordered with older files
   first. These are some options of the program:
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>Shell and File Sequences</title>
   <para>
    If you have multiple similar files like
    <filename>access.log.1</filename>, <filename>access.log.2</filename> and
    so on, the default shell Bash would sort those files not in the number
    sequence when listing <filename>access.log.*</filename>. To solve this
    issue, you may use the syntax <filename>access.log.{1..42}</filename>
    which generates a list of files extended with numbers from 1 to 42.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>-a</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      output all available reports
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>-w</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      output as HTML report
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>-l</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      include a message or logo in report header
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   More information about the various options can be found in the program's
   manual page with <command>man</command>&nbsp;<option>calamaris</option>.
  </para>

  <para>
   A typical example is:
  </para>

<screen>
cat access.log.{10..1} access.log | calamaris -a -w \ 
&gt; /usr/local/httpd/htdocs/Squid/squidreport.html
</screen>

  <para>
   This puts the report in the directory of the Web server. Apache is
   required to view the reports.
  </para>

 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.squid.moreinfo">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   Visit the home page of Squid at
   <ulink url="http://www.squid-cache.org/"/>. Here, find the <quote>Squid
   User Guide</quote> and a very extensive collection of FAQs on Squid.
  </para>

  <para>
   Following the installation, a small HOWTO about transparent proxies is
   available in <systemitem class="resource">howtoenh</systemitem> as
   <filename>/usr/share/doc/howto/en/txt/TransparentProxy.gz</filename>. In
   addition, mailing lists are available for Squid at
   <ulink
    url="squid-users@squid-cache.org"/>. The archive for this is
   located at
   <ulink url="http://www.squid-cache.org/mail-archive/squid-users/"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
