<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.ntp">
<!-- =============================================================== -->
<!-- ==                                                           == -->
<!-- =============================================================== -->
 <title>Time Synchronization with NTP</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    The NTP (network time protocol) mechanism is a protocol for synchronizing
    the system time over the network. First, a machine can obtain the time from
    a server that is a reliable time source. Second, a machine can itself act
    as a time source for other computers in the network. The goal is
    twofold&mdash;maintaining the absolute time and synchronizing the system
    time of all machines within a network.
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  Maintaining an exact system time is important in many situations. The
  built-in hardware clock does often not meet the requirements of applications
  such as databases or clusters. Manual correction of the system time would
  lead to severe problems because, for example, a backward leap can cause
  malfunction of critical applications. Within a network, it is usually
  necessary to synchronize the system time of all machines, but manual time
  adjustment is a bad approach. NTP provides a mechanism to solve these
  problems. The NTP service continuously adjusts the system time with reliable
  time servers in the network. It further enables the management of local
  reference clocks, such as radio-controlled clocks.
 </para>
 <note os="sled;osuse">
  <para>
   To enable time synchronization by means of active directory, follow the
   instructions found at <xref linkend="proc.ad.join"/>.
  </para>
 </note>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.ntp.yast">
  <title>Configuring an NTP Client with &yast;</title>

  <para>
   The NTP daemon (<systemitem class="daemon">ntpd</systemitem>) coming with
   the <systemitem>ntp</systemitem> package is preset to use the local computer
   clock as a time reference. Using the hardware clock, however, only serves as
   a fallback for cases where no time source of better precision is available.
   &yast; simplifies the configuration of an NTP client.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.ntp.yast.basic">
   <title>Basic Configuration</title>
   <para>
    The &yast; NTP client configuration (<menuchoice><guimenu>Network
    Services</guimenu> <guimenu>NTP Configuration</guimenu></menuchoice>)
    consists of tabs. Set the start mode of
    <systemitem class="daemon">ntpd</systemitem> and the server to query on the
    <guimenu>General Settings</guimenu> tab.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Only Manually</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Select <guimenu>Only Manually</guimenu>, if you want to manually start
       the <systemitem class="daemon">ntpd</systemitem> daemon.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Synchronize without Daemon</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Select <guimenu>Synchronize without Daemon</guimenu> to set the system
       time periodically without a permanently running
       <systemitem class="daemon">ntpd</systemitem>. You can set the
       <guimenu>Interval of the Synchronization in Minutes</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Now and On Boot</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Select <guimenu>Now and On Boot</guimenu> to start
       <systemitem class="daemon">ntpd</systemitem> automatically when the
       system is booted. This setting is recommended.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

<!-- ==================================================================== -->

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.ntp.yast.new_sync">
   <title>Changing Basic Configuration</title>
   <para>
    The servers and other time sources for the client to query are listed in
    the lower part of the <guimenu>General Settings</guimenu> tab. Modify this
    list as needed with <guimenu>Add</guimenu>, <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>, and
    <guimenu>Delete</guimenu>. <guimenu>Display Log</guimenu> provides the
    possibility to view the log files of your client.
   </para>
   <para>
    Click <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to add a new source of time information. In
    the following dialog, select the type of source with which the time
    synchronization should be made. The following options are available:
   </para>
   <figure xml:id="fig.yast.ntp.selserv">
    <title>&yast;: NTP Server</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast_ntp_selserv.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast_ntp_selserv.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Server</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In the drop-down <guimenu>Select</guimenu> list (see
       <xref linkend="fig.yast.ntp.selserv"/>), determine whether to set up
       time synchronization using a time server from your local network
       (<guimenu>Local NTP Server</guimenu>) or an Internet-based time server
       that takes care of your time zone (<guimenu>Public NTP
       Server</guimenu>). For a local time server, click
       <guimenu>Lookup</guimenu> to start an SLP query for available time
       servers in your network. Select the most suitable time server from the
       list of search results and exit the dialog with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
       For a public time server, select your country (time zone) and a suitable
       server from the list under <guimenu>Public NTP Server</guimenu> then
       exit the dialog with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. In the main dialog, test the
       availability of the selected server with <guimenu>Test</guimenu>.
       <guimenu>Options</guimenu> allows you to specify additional options for
       <systemitem class="daemon">ntpd</systemitem>.
      </para>
      <para>
       Using <guimenu>Access Control Options</guimenu>, you can restrict the
       actions that the remote computer can perform with the daemon running on
       your computer. This field is enabled only after checking
       <guimenu>Restrict NTP Service to Configured Servers Only</guimenu> on
       the <guimenu>Security Settings</guimenu> tab (see
       <xref linkend="fig.yast.ntp.adv.sec"/>). The options correspond to the
       <literal>restrict</literal> clauses in
       <filename>/etc/ntp.conf</filename>. For example, <literal>nomodify
       notrap noquery</literal> disallows the server to modify NTP settings of
       your computer and to use the trap facility (a remote event logging
       feature) of your NTP daemon. Using these restrictions is recommended for
       servers out of your control (for example, on the Internet).
      </para>
      <para>
       Refer to <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/ntp-doc</filename> (part of
       the <systemitem>ntp-doc</systemitem> package) for detailed information.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Peer</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A peer is a machine to which a symmetric relationship is established: it
       acts both as a time server and as a client. To use a peer in the same
       network instead of a server, enter the address of the system. The rest
       of the dialog is identical to the <guimenu>Server</guimenu> dialog.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Radio Clock</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To use a radio clock in your system for the time synchronization, enter
       the clock type, unit number, device name, and other options in this
       dialog. Click <guimenu>Driver Calibration</guimenu> to fine-tune the
       driver. Detailed information about the operation of a local radio clock
       is available in
       <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/ntp-doc/refclock.html</filename>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Outgoing Broadcast</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Time information and queries can also be transmitted by broadcast in the
       network. In this dialog, enter the address to which such broadcasts
       should be sent. Do not activate broadcasting unless you have a reliable
       time source like a radio controlled clock.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Incoming Broadcast</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If you want your client to receive its information via broadcast, enter
       the address from which the respective packets should be accepted in this
       fields.
<!--
       Further options are described in
       <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/ntp-doc</filename>.
       -->
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
<!-- =============================================================== -->
<!-- ==                                                           == -->
<!-- =============================================================== -->
   <figure xml:id="fig.yast.ntp.adv.sec">
    <title>Advanced NTP Configuration: Security Settings</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_xntp_adv_sec.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_xntp_adv_sec.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    In the <guimenu>Security Settings</guimenu> tab (see
    <xref
    linkend="fig.yast.ntp.adv.sec"/>), determine whether
    <systemitem
    class="daemon">ntpd</systemitem> should be started in a
    chroot jail. By default, <guimenu>Run NTP Daemon in Chroot Jail</guimenu>
    is not activated. The chroot jail option increases the security in the
    event of an attack over <systemitem
    class="daemon">ntpd</systemitem>,
    as it prevents the attacker from compromising the entire system.
   </para>
   <para>
    <guimenu>Restrict NTP Service to Configured Servers Only</guimenu>
    increases the security of your system by disallowing remote computers to
    view and modify NTP settings of your computer and to use the trap facility
    for remote event logging. After being enabled, these restrictions apply to
    all remote computers, unless you override the access control options for
    individual computers in the list of time sources in the <guimenu>General
    Settings</guimenu> tab. For all other remote computers, only querying for
    local time is allowed.
   </para>
   <para>
    Enable <guimenu>Open Port in Firewall</guimenu> if &susefirewall; is active
    (which it is by default). If you leave the port closed, it is not possible
    to establish a connection to the time server.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
<!-- =============================================================== -->
<!-- ==                                                           == -->
<!-- =============================================================== -->
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.ntp.netconf">
  <title>Manually Configuring NTP in the Network</title>

  <para>
<!-- adjust to standard network example -->
   The easiest way to use a time server in the network is to set server
   parameters. For example, if a time server called
   <systemitem>&ntpname;</systemitem> is reachable from the network, add its
   name to the file <filename>/etc/ntp.conf</filename> by adding the following
   line:
  </para>

<screen>server &ntpname;</screen>

  <para>
   To add more time servers, insert additional lines with the keyword
   <literal>server</literal>. After initializing
   <systemitem class="daemon">ntpd</systemitem> with the command
   <command>systemctl start ntp</command>, it takes about one hour until the
   time is stabilized and the drift file for correcting the local computer
   clock is created. With the drift file, the systematic error of the hardware
   clock can be computed when the computer is powered on. The correction is
   used immediately, resulting in a higher stability of the system time.
  </para>

  <para>
   There are two possible ways to use the NTP mechanism as a client: First, the
   client can query the time from a known server in regular intervals. With
   many clients, this approach can cause a high load on the server. Second, the
   client can wait for NTP broadcasts sent out by broadcast time servers in the
   network. This approach has the disadvantage that the quality of the server
   is unknown and a server sending out wrong information can cause severe
   problems.
  </para>

  <para>
   If the time is obtained via broadcast, you do not need the server name. In
   this case, enter the line <literal>broadcastclient</literal> in the
   configuration file <filename>/etc/ntp.conf</filename>. To use one or more
   known time servers exclusively, enter their names in the line starting with
   <literal>servers</literal>.
  </para>

<!--
  <para>
   Normally, every ntpd in the network can also be addressed as a time server.
   To run  ntpd with broadcasts,
   configure the <option>broadcast</option> option:
  </para>
  <screen>broadcast 192.168.0.255</screen>
  <para>
   Adjust the broadcast address to your circumstances.
   Make sure the time server uses the correct time.
    This can be done with reference clocks.
  </para>
  -->
 </sect1>
<!-- =============================================================== -->
<!-- ==                                                           == -->
<!-- =============================================================== -->
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.ntp.dynamic">
  <title>Dynamic Time Synchronization at Runtime</title>

<!-- For reference see fate#306288 -->

  <para>
   If the system boots without network connection,
   <systemitem class="daemon">ntpd</systemitem> starts up, but it cannot
   resolve DNS names of the time servers set in the configuration file. This
   can happen if you use &nm; with an encrypted Wi-Fi.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you want <systemitem class="daemon">ntpd</systemitem> to resolve DNS
   names at runtime, you must set the <systemitem>dynamic</systemitem> option.
   When a network connection is established after booting,
   <systemitem class="daemon">ntpd</systemitem> looks up the names again and
   can reach the time servers to get the time.
  </para>

  <para>
   Manually edit <filename>/etc/ntp.conf</filename> and add
   <systemitem>dynamic</systemitem> to one or more
   <systemitem>server</systemitem> entries:
  </para>

<screen>server &ntpname; dynamic</screen>

  <para>
   Or use &yast; and proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     In &yast; click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Network Services</guimenu>
     <guimenu>NTP Configuration</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the server you want to configure. Then click
     <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Activate the <guimenu>Options</guimenu> field and add
     <literal>dynamic</literal>. Separate it with a space, if there are already
     other options entered.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Ok</guimenu> to close the edit dialog. Repeat the previous
     step to change all servers as wanted.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Finally click <guimenu>Ok</guimenu> to save the settings.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
<!-- =============================================================== -->
<!-- ==                                                           == -->
<!-- =============================================================== -->
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.ntp.reference-clock">
  <title>Setting Up a Local Reference Clock</title>

  <para>
   The software package <systemitem class="daemon">ntpd</systemitem> contains
   drivers for connecting local reference clocks. A list of supported clocks is
   available in the <systemitem class="resource">ntp-doc</systemitem> package
   in the file
   <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/ntp-doc/refclock.html</filename>. Every
   driver is associated with a number. In NTP, the actual configuration takes
   place by means of pseudo IP addresses. The clocks are entered in the file
   <filename>/etc/ntp.conf</filename> as though they existed in the network.
   For this purpose, they are assigned special IP addresses in the form
   <literal>127.127.<replaceable>T</replaceable>.<replaceable>U</replaceable></literal>.
   Here, <replaceable>T</replaceable> stands for the type of the clock and
   determines which driver is used and <replaceable>U</replaceable> for the
   unit, which determines the interface used.
<!--
   Refer to the above-mentioned file containing the list of reference clocks to
   get the value for <option>t</option>.
   <option>u</option> is the device number that is
   only higher than <option>0</option> if you use several clocks of the same
   type on the computer. For example, a <quote>Type 8 Generic Reference Driver
    (PARSE)</quote> has the pseudo IP address <option>127.127.8.0</option>.
   -->
  </para>

  <para>
   Normally, the individual drivers have special parameters that describe
   configuration details. The file
   <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/ntp-doc/drivers/driver<replaceable>NN</replaceable>.html</filename>
   (where <replaceable>NN</replaceable> is the number of the driver) provides
   information about the particular type of clock. For example, the
   <quote>type&nbsp;8</quote> clock (radio clock over serial interface)
   requires an additional mode that specifies the clock more precisely. The
   Conrad DCF77 receiver module, for example, has mode&nbsp;5. To use this
   clock as a preferred reference, specify the keyword
   <literal>prefer</literal>. The complete <literal>server</literal> line for a
   Conrad DCF77 receiver module would be:
  </para>

<screen>server 127.127.8.0 mode 5 prefer</screen>

  <para>
   Other clocks follow the same pattern. Following the installation of the
   <systemitem class="resource">ntp-doc</systemitem> package, the documentation
   for NTP is available in the directory
   <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/ntp-doc</filename>. The file
   <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/ntp-doc/refclock.html</filename> provides
   links to the driver pages describing the driver parameters.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.ntp.etr" arch="zseries">
  <title>Clock Synchronization to an External Time Reference (ETR)</title>

<!-- taken from bnc#341392; also see fate#301693 -->

  <para>
   Support for clock synchronization to an external time reference (ETR) is
   available. The external time reference sends an oscillator signal and a
   synchronization signal every 2**20 (2 to the power of 20) microseconds to
   keep TOD clocks of all connected servers synchronized.
  </para>

  <para>
   For availability two ETR units can be connected to a machine. If the clock
   deviates for more than the sync-check tolerance all CPUs get a machine check
   that indicates that the clock is out of sync. If this happens, all DASD I/O
   to XRC enabled devices is stopped until the clock is synchronized again.
  </para>

  <para>
   The ETR support is activated via two <literal>sysfs</literal> attributes;
   run the following commands as &rootuser;:
  </para>

<screen>echo 1 &gt; /sys/devices/system/etr/etr0/online
echo 1 &gt; /sys/devices/system/etr/etr1/online
</screen>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
