<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="sec.basicnet.manconf">
 <title>Configuring a Network Connection Manually</title>

 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
          </dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <para>
  Manual configuration of the network software should be the last
  alternative. Using &yast; is recommended. However, this background
  information about the network configuration can also assist your work with
  &yast;.
 </para>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.basicnet.manconf.wicked">
<!--
      initially and heavily based on
      /usr/share/doc/packages/wicked/README
      The version of that README used here, I stored at
      background_information/wicked-readme
  -->
  <title>The <command>wicked</command> Network Configuration</title>
  <para>
   The tool and library called <command>wicked</command> provides a new
   framework for network configuration.
  </para>
  <para>
   One of the challenges with traditional network interface management is
   that different layers of network management get jumbled together into one
   single script, or at most two different scripts, that interact with each
   other in a not-really-well-defined way, with side effects that are
   difficult to be aware of, obscure constraints and conventions, etc.
   Several layers of special hacks for a variety of different scenarios
   increase the maintenance burden. Address configuration protocols are
   being used that are implemented via daemons like dhcpcd, which interact
   rather poorly with the rest of the infrastructure. Funky interface naming
   schemes that require heavy udev support are introduced to achieve
   persistent identification of interfaces.
  </para>
  <para>
   The idea of wicked is to decompose the problem in several ways. None of
   them is entirely novel, but trying to put ideas from different projects
   together is hopefully going to create a better solution overall.
  </para>
  <para>
   One approach is to use a client/server model. This allows wicked to
   define standardized facilities for things like address configuration that
   are well integrated with the overall framework. For example, with address
   configuration, the administrator may request that an interface should be
   configured via DHCP or IPv4 zeroconf, and all the address configuration
   service does is obtain the lease from its server, and pass it on to the
   wicked server process, which installs the requested addresses and routes.
  </para>
  <para>
   The other approach to decomposing the problem is to enforce the layering
   aspect. For any type of network interface, it is possible to define a
   dbus service that configures the network interface's device
   layer&mdash;a VLAN, a bridge, a bonding, or a paravirtualized device.
   Common functionality, such as address configuration, is implemented by
   joint services that are layered on top of these device specific services,
   without having to implement them specifically.
  </para>
  <para>
   The wicked framework implements these two aspects by using a variety of
   dbus services, which get attached to a network interface depending on its
   type. Here is a rough overview of the current object hierarchy in wicked.
  </para>
  <para>
   Each network interface is represented via a child object of
   <systemitem>/org/opensuse/Network/Interfaces</systemitem>. The name of
   the child object is given by its ifindex. For example, the loopback
   interface, which usually gets ifindex 1, is
   <systemitem>/org/opensuse/Network/Interfaces/1</systemitem>, the first
   Ethernet interface registered is
   <systemitem>/org/opensuse/Network/Interfaces/2</systemitem>.
  </para>
  <para>
   Each network interface has a <quote>class</quote> associated with it,
   which is used to select the dbus interfaces it supports. By default, each
   network interface is of class <literal>netif</literal>, and <systemitem
    class="daemon">wickedd</systemitem> will
   automatically attach all interfaces compatible with this class. In the
   current implementation, this includes the following interfaces:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>org.opensuse.Network.Interface</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Generic network interface functions, such as taking the link up or
      down, assigning an MTU, etc.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>org.opensuse.Network.Addrconf.ipv4.dhcp</term>
    <term>org.opensuse.Network.Addrconf.ipv6.dhcp</term>
    <term>org.opensuse.Network.Addrconf.ipv4.auto</term>
<!-- not jet implemented
    <term>org.opensuse.Network.Addrconf.ipv6.auto</term>
    -->
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Address configuration services for DHCP,
<!-- IPv6 autoconf, -->
      IPv4 zeroconf, etc.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
   Beyond this, network interfaces may require or offer special
   configuration mechanisms. For example, for an Ethernet device, you may
   want to be able to control the link speed, offloading of checksumming,
   etc. To achieve this, Ethernet devices have a class of their own, called
   <literal>netif-ethernet</literal>, which is a subclass of
   <literal>netif</literal>. As a consequence, the dbus interfaces assigned
   to an Ethernet interface include all the services listed above, plus
   <systemitem>org.opensuse.Network.Ethernet</systemitem>, which is a
   service available only to objects belonging to the
   <literal>netif-ethernet</literal> class.
  </para>
  <para>
   Similarly, there exist classes for interface types like bridges, VLANs,
   bonds, or infinibands.
  </para>
  <para>
   How do you interact with an interface that needs to be created
   first&mdash;such as a VLAN, which is really a virtual network
   interface that sits on top of an Ethernet device. For these, wicked
   defines factory interfaces, such as
   <systemitem>org.opensuse.Network.VLAN.Factory</systemitem>. Such a
   factory interface offers a single function that lets you create an
   interface of the requested type. These factory interfaces are attached to
   the <systemitem>/org/opensuse/Network/Interfaces</systemitem> list node.
  </para>
  <sect3 xml:id="sec.basicnet.manconf.supported">
   <title>Supported Features</title>
   <para>
    <command>wicked</command> currently supports:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Configuration file back-ends to parse SUSE style
      <filename>/etc/sysconfig/network</filename> files.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      An internal configuration back-end to represent network interface
      configuration in XML.
<!--
      according to mt, that's nowerdays misleading:
      -->
<!-- The syntax evolved out of what netcf uses. -->
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Bring up and shutdown of <quote>normal</quote> network interfaces such
      as Ethernet or InfiniBand, VLAN, bridge, bonds, tun, tap,
      dummy, macvlan, macvtap, hsi, qeth, iucv, and wireless (currently
      limited to one wpa-psk/eap network) devices.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A built-in DHCPv4 client and a built-in DHCPv6 client.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The nanny daemon (enabled by default) helps to automatically bring up
      configured interfaces as soon as the device is available (interface
      hotplugging) and set up the IP configuration when a link (carrier) is
      detected.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
  <sect3 xml:id="sec.basicnet.manconf.using_wicked">
   <title>Using <command>wicked</command></title>
   <para>
    On &sle;, <command>wicked</command> is running by default. In case
    you want to check what is currently enabled and whether it is running,
    call:
   </para>
<screen>systemctl status network</screen>
   <para>
    If <command>wicked</command> is enabled, you will see something along
    these lines:
   </para>
<!-- 2nd line of the output is intentionally indented! -->
<screen>wicked.service - wicked managed network interfaces
    Loaded: loaded (/usr/lib/systemd/system/wicked.service; enabled)
    ...</screen>
   <para>
    In case something different is running (for example, &nm;) and you
    want to switch to <command>wicked</command>, first stop what is running
    and then enable <command>wicked</command>:
   </para>
<screen>systemctl is-active network &amp;&amp; \
systemctl stop      network
systemctl enable --force wicked</screen>
   <para>
    This enables the wicked services, creates the
    <filename>network.service</filename> to
    <filename>wicked.service</filename> alias link, and starts the network
    at the next boot.
   </para>
   <para>
    Starting the server process:
   </para>
<screen>systemctl start wickedd</screen>
   <para>
    This starts <command>wickedd</command> (the main server) and associated
    supplicants:
   </para>
<screen>/usr/lib/wicked/bin/wickedd-auto4 --systemd --foreground
/usr/lib/wicked/bin/wickedd-dhcp4 --systemd --foreground
/usr/lib/wicked/bin/wickedd-dhcp6 --systemd --foreground
/usr/sbin/wickedd --systemd --foreground
/usr/sbin/wickedd-nanny --systemd --foreground</screen>
   <para>
    Then bringing up the network:
   </para>
<screen>systemctl start wicked</screen>
   <para>
    Alternatively use the <filename>network.service</filename> alias:
   </para>
<screen>systemctl start network</screen>
   <para>
    These commands are using the default or system configuration sources as
    defined in <filename>/etc/wicked/client.xml</filename>.
   </para>
   <para>
    To enable debugging, set <literal>WICKED_DEBUG</literal> in
    <filename>/etc/sysconfig/network/config</filename>, for example:
   </para>
<screen>WICKED_DEBUG="all"</screen>
   <para>
    Or, to omit some:
   </para>
<screen>WICKED_DEBUG="all,-dbus,-objectmodel,-xpath,-xml"</screen>
   <para>
    Use the client utility to display interface information for all
    interfaces or the interface specified with
    <replaceable>ifname</replaceable>:
   </para>
<screen>wicked show all
wicked show <replaceable>ifname</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    In XML output:
   </para>
<screen>wicked show-xml all
wicked show-xml <replaceable>ifname</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    Bringing up one interface:
   </para>
<screen>wicked ifup eth0
wicked ifup wlan0
...</screen>
   <para>
    Because there is no configuration source specified, the wicked client
    checks its default sources of configuration defined in
    <filename>/etc/wicked/client.xml</filename>:
   </para>
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
<!-- yes, the colon (:) is part of the attribution value in
          client.xml -->
     <para>
      <literal>firmware:</literal> iSCSI Boot Firmware Table (iBFT)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>compat:</literal> <literal>ifcfg</literal>
      files&mdash;implemented for compatibility
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
   <para>
    Whatever <command>wicked</command> gets from those sources for a given
    interface is applied. The intended order of importance is
    <literal>firmware</literal>, then
    <literal>compat</literal>&mdash;this may be changed in the future.
   </para>
<!--
   <para>
    Now let's bring up something interesting, for example a sample VLAN
    interface:
   </para>
<screen>wicked ifup -\-ifconfig ./samples/wicked/vlan-static.xml eth0.42</screen>
   <para>
    This should bring up a VLAN interface named <quote>eth0.42</quote>, with
    a VLAN tag of 42, and a few statically assigned IP addresses. To see
    whether it worked, try:
   </para>
<screen>ip addr show
ip route show</screen>
   <para>
    The above command retrieves the description of all interfaces from the
    specified file, and brings up the one named <quote>eth0.42</quote>.
    Because the file contains only one interface, you could have used
    <literal>all</literal> instead of the interface name. As the name
    implies, this brings up all interfaces listed in the file.
   </para>
   <para>
    To bring up a single interface the client executes several server
    methods and arguments from XML elements, telling the server to
    transition the desired interface state to <quote>up</quote>. This
    operation will create the VLAN interface on the fly if it is not yet
    there.
   </para>
   <para>
    Use the analogous approach to bring down the interface:
   </para>
<screen>wicked ifdown eth0.42</screen>
   <para>
    To bring down and delete the interface, use:
   </para>
<screen>wicked ifdown -\-delete -\-ifconfig ./samples/wicked/vlan-static.xml eth0.42</screen>
-->
   <para>
    For more information, see the <command>wicked</command> man page.
   </para>
  </sect3>
  <sect3 xml:id="sec.basicnet.manconf.using_nanny">
   <title>Nanny</title>
   <para>
    Nanny is an event and policy driven daemon that is responsible for
    asynchronous or unsolicited scenarios such as hotplugging devices. Thus
    the nanny daemon helps with starting or restarting delayed or temporarily
    gone devices. Nanny monitors device and link changes, and integrates new
    devices defined by the current policy set. Nanny continues to set up even
    if <command>ifup</command> already exited because of specified timeout
    constraints.
   </para>
   <para>
    By default, the nanny daemon is active on the system.
    It is enabled in the
    <filename>/etc/wicked/common.xml</filename> configuration file:
   </para>
<screen>&lt;config&gt;
  ...
  &lt;use-nanny&gt;true&lt;/use-nanny&gt;
&lt;/config&gt;</screen>
   <para>
    This setting causes ifup and ifreload to apply a policy with the effective
    configuration to the nanny daemon; then, nanny configures <systemitem
    class="daemon">wickedd</systemitem> and thus ensures hotplug support. It
    waits in the background for events or changes (such as new devices or
    carrier on).
   </para>
  </sect3>
<!-- ============================================================== -->
  <sect3 xml:id="sec.basicnet.manconf.multiple">
   <title>Bringing Up Multiple Interfaces</title>
   <para>
    For bonds and bridges, it may make sense to define the entire device
    topology in one file (ifcfg-bondX), and bring it up in one go. wicked
    then can bring up the whole configuration if you specify the top level
    interface names (of the bridge or bond):
   </para>
<screen>wicked ifup br0</screen>
   <para>
    This command automatically sets up the bridge and its dependencies in
    the appropriate order without the need to list the dependencies (ports,
    etc.) separately.
   </para>
   <para>
    To bring up multiple interfaces in one command:
   </para>
<screen>wicked ifup bond0 br0 br1 br2</screen>
   <para>
    Or also all interfaces:
   </para>
<screen>wicked ifup all</screen>
  </sect3>
<!-- ============================================================== -->
  <sect3 xml:id="sec.basicnet.manconf.incremental">
   <title>Handling Incremental Changes</title>
   <para>
    With <command>wicked</command>, there is no need to actually take down
    an interface to reconfigure it (unless it is required by the Kernel).
    For example, to add another IP address or route to a statically
    configured network interface, add the IP address to the interface
    definition, and do another <quote>ifup</quote> operation. The server
    will try hard to update only those settings that have changed. This
    applies to link-level options such as the device MTU or the MAC address,
    and network-level settings, such as addresses, routes, or even
    the address configuration mode (for example, when moving from a static
    configuration to DHCP).
   </para>
   <para>
    Things get tricky of course with virtual interfaces combining several
    real devices such as bridges or bonds. For bonded devices, it is not
    possible to change certain parameters while the device is up. Doing that
    will result in an error.
   </para>
   <para>
    However, what should still work, is the act of adding or removing the
    child devices of a bond or bridge, or choosing a bond's primary
    interface.
   </para>
  </sect3>
<!-- ============================================================== -->
  <sect3 xml:id="sec.basicnet.manconf.address_config">
   <title>Wicked Extensions: Address Configuration</title>
   <para>
    <command>wicked</command> is designed to be extensible with shell
    scripts. These extensions can be defined in the
    <filename>config.xml</filename> file.
   </para>
   <para>
    Currently, several different classes of extensions are supported:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      link configuration: these are scripts responsible for setting up a
      device's link layer according to the configuration provided by the
      client, and for tearing it down again.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      address configuration: these are scripts responsible for managing a
      device's address configuration. Usually address configuration and DHCP
      are managed by <command>wicked</command> itself, but can be
      implemented by means of extensions.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      firewall extension: these scripts can apply firewall rules.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    Typically, extensions have a start and a stop command, an optional
    <quote>pid file</quote>, and a set of environment variables that get
    passed to the script.
   </para>
   <para>
    To illustrate how this is supposed to work, look at a firewall extension
    defined in <filename>etc/server.xml</filename>:
   </para>
<screen>&lt;dbus-service interface="org.opensuse.Network.Firewall"&gt;
 &lt;action name="firewallUp"   command="/etc/wicked/extensions/firewall up"/&gt;
 &lt;action name="firewallDown" command="/etc/wicked/extensions/firewall down"/&gt;

 &lt;!-- default environment for all calls to this extension script --&gt;
 &lt;putenv name="WICKED_OBJECT_PATH" value="$object-path"/&gt;
 &lt;putenv name="WICKED_INTERFACE_NAME" value="$property:name"/&gt;
 &lt;putenv name="WICKED_INTERFACE_INDEX" value="$property:index"/&gt;
&lt;/dbus-service&gt;</screen>
   <para> The extension is attached to the <tag class="starttag">dbus-service</tag> tag
    and defines commands to execute for the actions of this interface. Further,
    the declaration can define and initialize environment variables passed to
    the actions. </para>
  </sect3>
<!-- ============================================================== -->
  <sect3 xml:id="sec.basicnet.manconf.configuration_files">
   <title>Wicked Extensions: Configuration Files</title>
   <para>
    You can extend the handling of configuration files with scripts as well.
    For example, DNS updates from leases are ultimately handled by the
    <filename>extensions/resolver</filename> script, with behavior
    configured in <filename>server.xml</filename>:
   </para>
<screen>&lt;system-updater name="resolver"&gt;
 &lt;action name="backup" command="/etc/wicked/extensions/resolver backup"/&gt;
 &lt;action name="restore" command="/etc/wicked/extensions/resolver restore"/&gt;
 &lt;action name="install" command="/etc/wicked/extensions/resolver install"/&gt;
 &lt;action name="remove" command="/etc/wicked/extensions/resolver remove"/&gt;
&lt;/system-updater&gt;</screen>
   <para>
    When an update arrives in <systemitem>wickedd</systemitem>, the system
    updater routines parse the lease and call the appropriate commands
    (<literal>backup</literal>, <literal>install</literal>, etc.) in the
    resolver script. This in turn configures the DNS settings using
    <command>/sbin/netconfig</command>, or by manually writing
    <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename> as a fallback.
   </para>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>

 <xi:include href="net_config_files.xml"/>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.basicnet.manconf.testing">
  <title>Testing the Configuration</title>
  <para>
   Before you write your configuration to the configuration files, you can
   test it. To set up a test configuration, use the <command>ip</command>
   command. To test the connection, use the <command>ping</command> command.
  </para>
  <para>
   The command <command>ip</command> changes the network configuration
   directly without saving it in the configuration file. Unless you enter
   your configuration in the correct configuration files, the changed
   network configuration is lost on reboot.
  </para>
  <note>
   <title><command>ifconfig</command> and <command>route</command> Are Obsolete</title>
   <para>
    The <command>ifconfig</command> and <command>route</command> tools are
    obsolete. Use <command>ip</command> instead.
    <command>ifconfig</command>, for example, limits interface names to
    9 characters.
   </para>
  </note>
  <sect3 xml:id="sec.basicnet.manconf.ip">
   <title>Configuring a Network Interface with <command>ip</command></title><indexterm>
   <primary>commands</primary>
   <secondary>ip</secondary></indexterm>
   <remark>
From: Marius Tomaschewski mt@suse.de&gt;
Subject: Re: Manual Network Config
To: Karl Eichwalder ke@suse.de&gt;
Date: Mon, 24 Aug 2009 14:21:44 +0200

Das ifconfig utility ist obsolete und unterstützt nur Interface-
Namen bis 9 Zeichen, z.B. "foo012345". Die restlichen Zeichen
werden abgeschnitten und nicht angezeigt.
Das "ip" utility unterstützt hingegen die derzeit volle Länge von
15 Zeichen, z.B. "foo012345678901".

Statt "ifconfig" sollte "ip addr" und "ip link" verwendet werden,
um routing zu konfigurieren, sollte nicht "route", sondern "ip route"
verwendendet werden.

...

IMO besser wäre es die Beispiel-Ausgaben von route und ifconfig zu
entfernen und stattdessen Beispiel-Ausgaben von:

"ip link show", "ip addr show",
"ip -4 route show", "ip -6 route show"
(und ggf. auch "ip rule show")

im "Configuring a Network Interface with ip" zu bringen. Eventuell
mit ein Paar Beispielen als eine Art Kurzanleitung, in etwa:

ip link set up dev eth0

ip addr add 192.168.0.100/24 dev eth0
ip addr add 2001:DB8:cafe::dead/64 dev eth0

ip route add 192.168.1.0/24 via 192.168.0.200 dev eth0
ip route add 2001:DB8:cafe:1::/64 via 2001:DB8:cafe::feed dev eth0

ip route add default via 192.168.0.254 dev eth0
ip route add default via 2001:DB8:cafe::beef dev eth0

ip addr show dev eth0
ip -4 route show # dev eth0
ip -6 route show # dev eth0

ip route del 192.168.1.0/24 via 192.168.0.200 dev eth0
ip route del 2001:DB8:cafe:1::/64 via 2001:DB8:cafe::feed dev eth0

ip route del default via 192.168.0.254 dev eth0
ip route del default via 2001:DB8:cafe::beef dev eth0

ip addr del 192.168.0.100/24 dev eth0
ip addr del 2001:DB8:cafe::dead/64 dev eth0

ip link set down dev eth0
</remark>
   <remark>
 ke 2014-05-15: ifconfig and route is removed sind quite some time.
 Maybe, we should add more ip examples as Marius proposes...
</remark>
   <para>
    <command>ip</command> is a tool to show and configure network devices,
    routing, policy routing, and tunnels.
   </para>
   <para>
    <command>ip</command> is a very complex tool. Its common syntax is
    <command>ip</command>&nbsp;<option><replaceable>options</replaceable>
    <replaceable>object</replaceable>
    <replaceable>command</replaceable></option>. You can work with the
    following objects:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>link</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This object represents a network device.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>address</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This object represents the IP address of device.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>neighbor</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This object represents an ARP or NDISC cache entry.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>route</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This object represents the routing table entry.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>rule</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This object represents a rule in the routing policy database.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>maddress</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This object represents a multicast address.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>mroute</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This object represents a multicast routing cache entry.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>tunnel</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This object represents a tunnel over IP.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    If no command is given, the default command is used (usually
    <command>list</command>).
   </para>
   <para>
    Change the state of a device with the command <command>ip link
    set</command>&nbsp;<option><replaceable>device_name</replaceable></option>&nbsp;<command/>
    . For example, to deactivate device eth0, enter <command>ip link
    set</command> <option>eth0 down</option>. To activate it again, use
    <command>ip link set</command> <option>eth0 up</option>.
   </para>
   <para>
    After activating a device, you can configure it. To set the IP address,
    use <command>ip addr
    add</command>&nbsp;<option><replaceable>ip_address</replaceable> +
    dev <replaceable>device_name</replaceable></option>. For example, to set
    the address of the interface eth0 to 192.168.12.154/30 with standard
    broadcast (option <option>brd</option>), enter <command>ip
    addr</command>&nbsp;<option>add 192.168.12.154/30 brd + dev
    eth0</option>.
   </para>
   <para>
    To have a working connection, you must also configure the default
    gateway. To set a gateway for your system, enter <command>ip route
    add</command>&nbsp;<option>gateway_ip_address</option>. To translate
    one IP address to another, use <command>nat</command>: <command>ip route
    add
    nat</command>&nbsp;<option>ip_address</option>&nbsp;<command>via</command>&nbsp;<option>other_ip_address</option>.
   </para>
   <para>
    To display all devices, use <command>ip link ls</command>. To display
    the running interfaces only, use <command>ip link ls up</command>. To
    print interface statistics for a device, enter <command>ip -s link
    ls</command>&nbsp;<option>device_name</option>. To view addresses of
    your devices, enter <command>ip addr</command>. In the output of the
    <command>ip addr</command>, also find information about MAC addresses of
    your devices. To show all routes, use <command>ip route show</command>.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more information about using <command>ip</command>, enter
    <command>ip</command>&nbsp;<option>help</option> or see the
    <systemitem>ip(8)</systemitem> man page. The <option>help</option>
    option is also available for all <command>ip</command> subcommands. If,
    for example, you need help for
    <command>ip</command>&nbsp;<option>addr</option>, enter
    <command>ip</command>&nbsp;<option>addr help</option>. Find the
    <command>ip</command> manual in
    <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/iproute2/ip-cref.pdf</filename>.
   </para>
  </sect3>
  <sect3 xml:id="sec.basicnet.manconf.testingping">
   <title>Testing a Connection with ping</title><indexterm>
   <primary>commands</primary>
   <secondary>ping</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>ping</primary></indexterm>
   <para>
    The <command>ping</command> command is the standard tool for testing
    whether a TCP/IP connection works. It uses the ICMP protocol to send a
    small data packet, ECHO_REQUEST datagram, to the destination host,
    requesting an immediate reply. If this works, <command>ping</command>
    displays a message to that effect. This indicates that the network link
    is functioning.
   </para>
   <para>
    <command>ping</command> does more than only test the function of the
    connection between two computers: it also provides some basic
    information about the quality of the connection. In
    <xref linkend="ex.basicnet.manconf.ping"/>, you can see an example of
    the <command>ping</command> output. The second-to-last line contains
    information about the number of transmitted packets, packet loss, and
    total time of <command>ping</command> running.
   </para>
   <para>
    As the destination, you can use a host name or IP address, for example,
    <command>ping</command>&nbsp;<option>&exampledomain;</option> or
    <command>ping</command>&nbsp;<option>&wwwip;</option>. The program
    sends packets until you press
    <keycombo><keycap function="control"/><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you only need to check the functionality of the connection, you can
    limit the number of the packets with the <option>-c</option> option. For
    example to limit ping to three packets, enter
    <command>ping</command>&nbsp;<option>-c 3
    &exampledomain;</option>.
   </para>
   <example xml:id="ex.basicnet.manconf.ping">
    <title>Output of the Command ping</title>
<screen>ping -c 3 &exampledomain;
PING &exampledomain; (&wwwip;) 56(84) bytes of data.
64 bytes from &exampledomain; (&wwwip;): icmp_seq=1 ttl=49 time=188 ms
64 bytes from &exampledomain; (&wwwip;): icmp_seq=2 ttl=49 time=184 ms
64 bytes from &exampledomain; (&wwwip;): icmp_seq=3 ttl=49 time=183 ms
--- &exampledomain; ping statistics ---
3 packets transmitted, 3 received, 0% packet loss, time 2007ms
rtt min/avg/max/mdev = 183.417/185.447/188.259/2.052 ms</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    The default interval between two packets is one second. To change the
    interval, ping provides the option <option>-i</option>. For example, to
    increase the ping interval to ten seconds, enter
    <command>ping</command>&nbsp;<option>-i 10
    &exampledomain;</option>.
   </para>
   <para>
    In a system with multiple network devices, it is sometimes useful to
    send the ping through a specific interface address. To do so, use the
    <option>-I</option> option with the name of the selected device, for
    example, <command>ping</command>&nbsp;<option>-I wlan1
    &exampledomain;</option>.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more options and information about using ping, enter
    <command>ping</command>&nbsp;<option>-h</option> or see the
    <systemitem>ping (8)</systemitem> man page.
   </para>
   <tip>
    <title>Pinging IPv6 Addresses</title>
    <para>
     For IPv6 addresses use the <command>ping6</command> command. Note, to
     ping link-local addresses, you must specify the interface with
     <option>-I</option>. The following command works, if the address is
     reachable via <literal>eth1</literal>:
    </para>
<screen>ping6 -I eth1 fe80::117:21ff:feda:a425</screen>
   </tip>
  </sect3>
<!--
  <sect3 id="sec.basicnet.manconf.testingifconfig">
   <title>Configuring the Network with ifconfig</title><indexterm>
   <primary>commands</primary>
   <secondary>ifconfig</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    <command>ifconfig</command> is a network configuration tool.
   </para>
   <note>
    <title><command>ifconfig</command> and <command>ip</command></title>
    <para>
     The <command>ifconfig</command> tool is obsolete. Use
     <command>ip</command> instead. In contrast to <command>ip</command>,
     you can use <command>ifconfig</command> only for interface
     configuration. It limits interface names to 9 characters.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    Without arguments, <command>ifconfig</command> displays the status of
    the currently active interfaces. As you can see in
    <xref
     linkend="ex.basicnet.manconf.ifconfig"/>,
    <command>ifconfig</command> has very well-arranged and detailed output.
    The output also contains information about the MAC address of your
    device (the value of <option>HWaddr</option>) in the first line.
   </para>
   <example id="ex.basicnet.manconf.ifconfig">
    <title>Output of the <command>ifconfig</command> Command</title>
<screen>eth0      Link encap:Ethernet  HWaddr 00:08:74:98:ED:51
          inet6 addr: fe80::208:74ff:fe98:ed51/64 Scope:Link
          UP BROADCAST MULTICAST  MTU:1500  Metric:1
          RX packets:634735 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:4 frame:0
          TX packets:154779 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 carrier:1
          collisions:0 txqueuelen:1000
          RX bytes:162531992 (155.0 Mb)  TX bytes:49575995 (47.2 Mb)
          Interrupt:11 Base address:0xec80

lo        Link encap:Local Loopback
          inet addr:127.0.0.1  Mask:255.0.0.0
          inet6 addr: ::1/128 Scope:Host
          UP LOOPBACK RUNNING  MTU:16436  Metric:1
          RX packets:8559 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 frame:0
          TX packets:8559 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 carrier:0
          collisions:0 txqueuelen:0
          RX bytes:533234 (520.7 Kb)  TX bytes:533234 (520.7 Kb)    

wlan1     Link encap:Ethernet  HWaddr 00:0E:2E:52:3B:1D
          inet addr:192.168.2.4  Bcast:192.168.2.255  Mask:255.255.255.0
          inet6 addr: fe80::20e:2eff:fe52:3b1d/64 Scope:Link
          UP BROADCAST NOTRAILERS RUNNING MULTICAST  MTU:1500  Metric:1
          RX packets:50828 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 frame:0
          TX packets:43770 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 carrier:0
          collisions:0 txqueuelen:1000
          RX bytes:45978185 (43.8 Mb)  TX bytes:7526693 (7.1 MB)</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    For more options and information about using
    <command>ifconfig</command>, enter
    <command>ifconfig</command>&nbsp;<option>-h</option> or see the
    <systemitem>ifconfig (8)</systemitem> man page.
   </para>
  </sect3>
  <sect3>
   <title>Configuring Routing with <command>route</command></title><indexterm>
   <primary>commands</primary>
   <secondary>route</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    <command>route</command> is a program for manipulating the IP routing
    table. You can use it to view your routing configuration and to add or
    remove routes.
   </para>
   <note>
    <title><command>route</command> and <command>ip</command></title>
    <para>
     The program <command>route</command> is obsolete. Use
     <command>ip</command> instead.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    <command>route</command> is especially useful if you need quick and
    comprehensible information about your routing configuration to determine
    problems with routing. To view your current routing configuration, enter
    <command>route</command> <option>-n</option> as &rootuser;.
   </para>
   <example id="ex.basicnet.manconf.route">
    <title>Output of the <command>route <option>-n</option></command> Command</title>
<screen><?dbsuse-fo font-size="7pt"?>route -n
Kernel IP routing table
Destination     Gateway         Genmask         Flags   MSS Window  irtt Iface
10.20.0.0       *               255.255.248.0   U         0 0          0 eth0
link-local      *               255.255.0.0     U         0 0          0 eth0
loopback        *               255.0.0.0       U         0 0          0 lo
default         styx.exam.com   0.0.0.0         UG        0 0          0 eth0</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    For more options and information about using route, enter
    <command>route</command>&nbsp;<option>-h</option> or see the
    <systemitem>route (8)</systemitem> man page.
   </para>
  </sect3>
-->
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.basicnet.manconf.scripts">
  <title>Unit Files and Start-Up Scripts</title><indexterm>
  <primary>scripts</primary>
  <secondary>init.d</secondary></indexterm>
  <para>
   Apart from the configuration files described above, there are also
   systemd unit files and various scripts that load the network services
   while the machine is booting. These are started as soon as the system is
   switched to the <systemitem>multi-user.target</systemitem> target. Some
   of these unit files and scripts are described in
   <xref linkend="var.net.start.scripts"/>. For more information about
   <systemitem>systemd</systemitem>, see <xref linkend="cha.systemd"/> and
   for more information about the <systemitem>systemd</systemitem> targets,
   see the man page of <systemitem>systemd.special</systemitem>
   (<command>man systemd.special</command>).
   <remark>taroth 2014-02-13: FIXME: SYSTEMD, WICKED</remark>
  </para>
  <variablelist xml:id="var.net.start.scripts">
   <title>Some Unit Files and Start-Up Scripts for Network Programs</title>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><systemitem>network.target</systemitem>
<!--ix--><indexterm>
     <primary>unit file</primary>
     <secondary>network.target</secondary></indexterm>
<!--ix-->
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <systemitem>network.target</systemitem> is the systemd target for
      networking, but its mean depends on the settings provided by the
      system administrator.
     </para>
     <para>
      For more information, see
      <link xlink:href="http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/systemd/NetworkTarget/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><systemitem>multi-user.target</systemitem>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
<!--ix-->
      <indexterm>
      <primary>unit file</primary>
      <secondary>multi-user.target</secondary>
      </indexterm>
<!--ix-->
      <systemitem>multi-user.target</systemitem> is the systemd target for a
      multiuser system with all required network services.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><systemitem>xinetd</systemitem>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Starts xinetd. xinetd can be used to make server services available on
      the system. For example, it can start vsftpd whenever an FTP
      connection is initiated.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><systemitem>rpcbind</systemitem>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Starts the rpcbind utility that converts RPC program numbers to
      universal addresses. It is needed for RPC services, such as an NFS
      server.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><systemitem>ypserv</systemitem>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Starts the NIS server.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><systemitem>ypbind</systemitem>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Starts the NIS client.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename>/etc/init.d/nfsserver</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Starts the NFS server.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename>/etc/init.d/postfix</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Controls the postfix process.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
<!-- FIXME: consider to add wicked related files. -->
 </sect2>
</sect1>
