<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<sect1 id="sec.smpppd">
 <title>smpppd as Dial-up Assistant</title><indexterm id="idx.Internet_smpppd">

 <primary>Internet</primary>

 <secondary>smpppd</secondary></indexterm><indexterm id="idx.Internet_dial-up">

 <primary>Internet</primary>

 <secondary>dial-up</secondary></indexterm>

 <para>
  Some home users do not have a dedicated line connecting them to the
  Internet. Instead, they use dial-up connections. If you use DSL as dial-up
  method, the connection is controlled by pppd.
  To start these programs correctly, you now need to go online.
 </para>

 <para>
  If you have a flat-rate connection that does not generate any additional
  costs for the dial-up connection, simply start the respective daemon.
  Control the dial-up connection with a desktop applet or a command-line
  interface. If the Internet gateway is not the host you are using, you
  might want to control the dial-up connection by way of a network host.
 </para>

 <para>
  This is where smpppd (SUSE Meta PPP Daemon) is involved. It provides a
  uniform interface for auxiliary programs and acts in two directions.
  First, it programs the required pppd and controls its dial-up
  properties. Second, it makes various providers available to the user
  programs and transmits information about the current status of the
  connection. As smpppd can also be controlled by way of the network, it is
  suitable for controlling dial-up connections to the Internet from a
  workstation in a private subnetwork.
 </para>

 <sect2>
  <title>Configuring smpppd</title>
  <para>
   The connections provided by smpppd are automatically configured by
   &yast;. The actual dial-up programs cinternet are also
   pre-configured. Manual settings are only required to configure additional
   features of smpppd such as remote control.
  </para>
  <para>
   The configuration file of smpppd is
   <filename>/etc/smpppd.conf</filename>. By default, it does not enable
   remote control. The most important options of this configuration file
   are:
  </para><indexterm>
  <primary>configuration files</primary>
  <secondary>smppd.conf</secondary></indexterm>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>open-inet-socket = <replaceable>yes|no</replaceable>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To control smpppd via the network, set this option to
      <literal>yes</literal>. smpppd listens on port
      <literal>3185</literal>. If this parameter is set to
      <literal>yes</literal>, the parameters
      <literal>bind-address</literal>, <literal>host-range</literal> and
      <literal>password</literal> must be set accordingly.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>bind-address = <replaceable>ip address</replaceable>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If a host has several IP addresses, use this parameter to determine at
      which IP address smpppd should accept connections. The default is to
      listen at all addresses.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>host-range = <replaceable>min ip</replaceable><replaceable>max ip</replaceable>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The parameter <literal>host-range</literal> defines a network range.
      Hosts whose IP addresses are within this range are granted access to
      smpppd. All hosts not within this range are denied access.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>password = <replaceable>password</replaceable>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      By assigning a password, limit the clients to authorized hosts. As
      this is a plain-text password, you should not overrate the security it
      provides. If no password is assigned, all clients are permitted to
      access smpppd.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>slp-register = <replaceable>yes|no</replaceable>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      With this parameter, the smpppd service can be announced in the
      network via SLP.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
   More information about smpppd is available in the
   <systemitem>smpppd(8)</systemitem> and
   <systemitem>smpppd.conf(5)</systemitem> man pages.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2>
  <title>Configuring <command>cinternet</command> for Remote Use</title><indexterm>
  <primary>Internet</primary>
  <secondary>cinternet</secondary></indexterm>
  <para>
   cinternet can be used to control a local or remote smpppd. cinternet is
   the command-line counterpart to the graphical KInternet. To prepare these
   utilities for use with a remote smpppd, edit the configuration file
   <filename>/etc/smpppd-c.conf</filename> manually or using cinternet. This
   file only uses four options:
  </para><indexterm>
  <primary>configuration files</primary>
  <secondary>smpppd-c.conf</secondary></indexterm>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>sites = <replaceable>list of sites</replaceable>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <replaceable>list of sites</replaceable> where the front-ends search
      for smpppd. The front-ends test the options in the order specified
      here. <literal>local</literal> orders the establishment of a
      connection to the local smpppd. <literal>gateway</literal> points to
      an smpppd on the gateway. <literal>config-file</literal> indicates
      that the connection should be established to the smpppd specified in
      the <systemitem>server</systemitem> and <systemitem>port</systemitem>
      options in <filename>/etc/smpppd-c.conf</filename>.
      <literal>slp</literal> orders the front-ends to connect to an smpppd
      found via SLP.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>server = <replaceable>server</replaceable>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The host on which smpppd runs.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>port = <replaceable>port</replaceable>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The port on which smpppd runs.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>password = <replaceable>password</replaceable>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The password selected for smpppd.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
   If smpppd is active, try to access it. For example, with
   <command>cinternet</command> <option>--verbose --interface-list</option>.
   In case of difficulties at this point, refer to the
   <systemitem>smpppd-c.conf(5)</systemitem> and
   <systemitem>cinternet(8)</systemitem> man pages.
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
