<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.dhcp">
<!--ix-->
 <title>DHCP</title>
 <info>
      <abstract>
        <para>
    The purpose of the <emphasis>Dynamic Host Configuration
    Protocol</emphasis> (DHCP) is to assign network settings centrally (from a
    server) rather than configuring them locally on every workstation. A host
    configured to use DHCP does not have control over its own static
    address. It is enabled to configure itself completely and automatically
    according to directions from the server. If you use the &nm; on the client
    side, you do not need to configure the client at all. This is useful if
    you have changing environments and only one interface active at a
    time. Never use &nm; on a machine that runs a DHCP server.
   </para>
      </abstract>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
          </dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <!--ix--><indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="idx.DHCP">
 <primary>DHCP</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>networks</primary>
 <secondary>DHCP</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>IP addresses</primary>
 <secondary>dynamic assignment</secondary></indexterm>
 <tip arch="zseries" os="sles">
  <title>IBM &zseries;: DHCP Support</title>
  <para>
   On IBM &zseries; platforms, DHCP only works on interfaces using the
   OSA and OSA Express network cards. These cards are the only ones with a
   MAC, which is required for the DHCP autoconfiguration features.
  </para>
 </tip>
 <para>
  One way to configure a DHCP server is to identify each client using the
  hardware address of its network card (which should be fixed in most
  cases), then supply that client with identical settings each time it
  connects to the server. DHCP can also be configured to assign addresses to
  each relevant client dynamically from an address pool set up for this
  purpose. In the latter case, the DHCP server tries to assign the same
  address to the client each time it receives a request, even over extended
  periods. This works only if the network does not have more clients than
  addresses.
 </para>
 <para>
  DHCP makes life easier for system administrators. Any changes, even bigger
  ones, related to addresses and the network configuration in general can be
  implemented centrally by editing the server's configuration file. This is
  much more convenient than reconfiguring numerous workstations. It is also
  much easier to integrate machines, particularly new machines, into the
  network, because they can be given an IP address from the pool. Retrieving
  the appropriate network settings from a DHCP server is especially useful
  in case of laptops regularly used in different networks.
 </para>
 <para>
  In this chapter, the DHCP server will run in the same subnet as the
  workstations, <systemitem class="ipaddress">&subnetIImask;</systemitem>
  with <systemitem class="ipaddress">&routerintipII;</systemitem> as
  gateway. It has the fixed IP address
  <systemitem class="ipaddress">&dhcpip;</systemitem> and serves two
  address ranges,
  <systemitem class="ipaddress">&subnetII;.10</systemitem> to
  <systemitem class="ipaddress">&subnetII;.20</systemitem> and
  <systemitem class="ipaddress">&subnetII;.100</systemitem> to
  <systemitem class="ipaddress">&subnetII;.200</systemitem>.
 </para>
 <para>
  A DHCP server supplies not only the IP address and the netmask, but also
  the host name, domain name, gateway, and name server addresses for the
  client to use. In addition to that, DHCP allows several other
  parameters to be configured in a centralized way, for example, a time
  server from which clients may poll the current time or even a print
  server.
 </para>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.dhcp.yast">
  <title>Configuring a DHCP Server with &yast;</title>

<!--ix--><indexterm>

  <primary>&yast;</primary>

  <secondary>DHCP</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>DHCP</primary>

  <secondary>configuring with &yast;</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   To install a DHCP server, start &yast; and select
   <menuchoice><guimenu>Software</guimenu> <guimenu>Software
   Management</guimenu></menuchoice>. Choose
   <menuchoice><guimenu>Filter</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Patterns</guimenu></menuchoice> and select <guimenu>DHCP and DNS
   Server</guimenu>. Confirm the installation of the dependent packages to
   finish the installation process.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>LDAP Support</title>
   <para>
    The &yast; DHCP module can be set up to store the server
    configuration locally (on the host that runs the DHCP server) or to have
    its configuration data managed by an LDAP server. If you want to use
    LDAP, set up your LDAP environment before configuring the DHCP server.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more information about LDAP, see
    <xref linkend="cha.security.ldap"/>.
   </para>
  </important>

  <para>
   The &yast; DHCP module (<systemitem>yast2-dhcp-server</systemitem>)
   allows you to set up your own DHCP server for the local network. The
   module can run in wizard mode or expert configuration mode.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.dhcp.yast.init">
   <title>Initial Configuration (Wizard)</title>
   <para>
    When the module is started for the first time, a wizard starts,
    prompting you to make a few basic decisions concerning server
    administration. Completing this initial setup produces a very basic
    server configuration that should function in its essential aspects. The
    expert mode can be used to deal with more advanced configuration tasks.
    Proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <remark>
   It has changed in the meantime.  DHCP Server Configuration ("expert mode")
   now allows more detailed configuration.  2010-06-22, ke.
  </remark>
   <procedure xml:id="pro.dhcp.yast.init">
    <step>
     <para>
      Select the interface from the list to which the DHCP server should
      listen and click <guimenu>Select</guimenu>. After this, select
      <guimenu>Open Firewall for Selected Interfaces</guimenu> to open the
      firewall for this interface, and click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. See
      <xref linkend="fig.yast2.dhcp.wiz1"/>.
     </para>
     <figure xml:id="fig.yast2.dhcp.wiz1">
      <title>DHCP Server: Card Selection</title>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_wiz1.png" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_wiz1.png" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </figure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use the check box to determine whether your DHCP settings should be
      automatically stored by an LDAP server. In the text boxes, provide the
      network specifics for all clients the DHCP server should manage. These
      specifics are the domain name, address of a time server, addresses of
      the primary and secondary name server, addresses of a print and a WINS
      server (for a mixed network with both Windows and Linux clients),
      gateway address, and lease time. See
      <xref linkend="fig.yast2.dhcp.wiz2"/>.
     </para>
     <figure xml:id="fig.yast2.dhcp.wiz2">
      <title>DHCP Server: Global Settings</title>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_wiz2.png" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_wiz2.png" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </figure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Configure how dynamic IP addresses should be assigned to clients. To
      do so, specify an IP range from which the server can assign addresses
      to DHCP clients. All these addresses must be covered by the same
      netmask. Also specify the lease time during which a client may keep
      its IP address without needing to request an extension of the lease.
      Optionally, specify the maximum lease time&mdash;the period during
      which the server reserves an IP address for a particular client. See
      <xref linkend="fig.yast2.dhcp.wiz3"/>.
     </para>
     <figure xml:id="fig.yast2.dhcp.wiz3">
      <title>DHCP Server: Dynamic DHCP</title>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_wiz3.png" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_wiz3.png" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </figure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Define how the DHCP server should be started. Specify whether to start
      the DHCP server automatically when the system is booted or manually
      when needed (for example, for testing purposes). Click
      <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> to complete the configuration of the server.
      See <xref linkend="fig.yast2.dhcp.start"/>.
<!-- Alternatively, you can select
       <guimenu>Host Management</guimenu> from the tree structure to the
       left to configure special host management features in addition to the
       basic configuration (see <xref linkend="fig.yast2.dhcp.statdhcp"/>). -->
     </para>
     <figure xml:id="fig.yast2.dhcp.start">
      <title>DHCP Server: Start-Up</title>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_start.png" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_start.png" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </figure>
    </step>
    <step os="sles;osuse">
     <para>
      Instead of using dynamic DHCP in the way described in the preceding
      steps, you can also configure the server to assign addresses in
      quasi-static fashion. Use the text boxes provided in the lower part to
      specify a list of the clients to manage in this way. Specifically,
      provide the <guimenu>Name</guimenu> and the <guimenu>IP
      Address</guimenu> to give to such a client, the <guimenu>Hardware
      Address</guimenu>, and the <guimenu>Network Type</guimenu> (token ring
      or Ethernet). Modify the list of clients, which is shown in the upper
      part with <guimenu>Add</guimenu>, <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>, and
      <guimenu>Delete from List</guimenu>. See
      <xref linkend="fig.yast2.dhcp.statdhcp"/>.
     </para>
     <figure xml:id="fig.yast2.dhcp.statdhcp">
      <title>DHCP Server: Host Management</title>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_statdhcp.png" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_statdhcp.png" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </figure>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.dhcp.yast.expert" os="sles;osuse">
   <title>DHCP Server Configuration (Expert)</title>
   <para>
    In addition to the configuration method discussed earlier, there is also
    an expert configuration mode that allows you to change the DHCP server
    setup in every detail. Start the expert configuration by clicking
    <guimenu>DHCP Server Expert Configuration</guimenu> in the
    <guimenu>Start-Up</guimenu> dialog (see
    <xref linkend="fig.yast2.dhcp.start"/>).
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Chroot Environment and Declarations</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In this first dialog, make the existing configuration editable by
       selecting <guimenu>Start DHCP Server</guimenu>. An important feature
       of the behavior of the DHCP server is its ability to run in a chroot
       environment or chroot jail, to secure the server host. If the DHCP
       server should ever be compromised by an outside attack, the attacker
       will still be behind bars in the chroot jail, which prevents him from
       touching the rest of the system. The lower part of the dialog
       displays a tree view with the declarations that have already been
       defined. Modify these with <guimenu>Add</guimenu>,
       <guimenu>Delete</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>. Selecting
       <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> takes you to additional expert dialogs.
       See <xref linkend="fig.yast2.dhcp.chroot"/>. After selecting
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu>, define the type of declaration to add. With
       <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu>, view the log file of the server,
       configure TSIG key management, and adjust the configuration of the
       firewall according to the setup of the DHCP server.
      </para>
      <figure xml:id="fig.yast2.dhcp.chroot">
       <title>DHCP Server: Chroot Jail and Declarations</title>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
         <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_chroot.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
         <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_chroot.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </figure>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Selecting the Declaration Type</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The <guimenu>Global Options</guimenu> of the DHCP server are made up
       of several declarations. This dialog lets you set the declaration
       types <guimenu>Subnet</guimenu>, <guimenu>Host</guimenu>,
       <guimenu>Shared Network</guimenu>, <guimenu>Group</guimenu>,
       <guimenu>Pool of Addresses</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Class</guimenu>.
       This example shows the selection of a new subnet (see
       <xref linkend="fig.yast2.dhcp.newdec"/>).
      </para>
      <figure xml:id="fig.yast2.dhcp.newdec">
       <title>DHCP Server: Selecting a Declaration Type</title>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
         <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_newdec.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
         <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_newdec.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </figure>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Subnet Configuration</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This dialog allows you specify a new subnet with its IP address and
       netmask. In the middle part of the dialog, modify the DHCP server
       start options for the selected subnet using <guimenu>Add</guimenu>,
       <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Delete</guimenu>. To set up
       dynamic DNS for the subnet, select <guimenu>Dynamic DNS</guimenu>.
      </para>
      <figure xml:id="fig.yast2.dhcp.sub">
       <title>DHCP Server: Configuring Subnets</title>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
         <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_sub.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
         <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_sub.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </figure>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>TSIG Key Management</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If you chose to configure dynamic DNS in the previous dialog, you can
       now configure the key management for a secure zone transfer.
       Selecting <guimenu>OK</guimenu> takes you to another dialog in which
       to configure the interface for dynamic DNS (see
       <xref linkend="fig.yast2.dhcp.dyndns"/>).
      </para>
      <figure xml:id="fig.yast2.dhcp.tsig">
       <title>DHCP Server: TSIG Configuration</title>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
         <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_tsig.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
         <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_tsig.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </figure>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Dynamic DNS: Interface Configuration</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       You can now activate dynamic DNS for the subnet by selecting
       <guimenu>Enable Dynamic DNS for This Subnet</guimenu>. After doing
       so, use the drop-down box to activate the TSIG keys for forward and
       reverse zones, making sure that the keys are the same for the DNS and
       the DHCP server. With <guimenu>Update Global Dynamic DNS
       Settings</guimenu>, enable the automatic update and adjustment of the
       global DHCP server settings according to the dynamic DNS environment.
       Finally, define which forward and reverse zones should be updated per
       dynamic DNS, specifying the name of the primary name server for each
       of the two zones. Selecting <guimenu>OK</guimenu> returns to the
       subnet configuration dialog (see
       <xref linkend="fig.yast2.dhcp.sub"/>). Selecting
       <guimenu>OK</guimenu> again returns to the original expert
       configuration dialog.
      </para>
      <figure xml:id="fig.yast2.dhcp.dyndns">
       <title>DHCP Server: Interface Configuration for Dynamic DNS</title>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
         <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_dyndns.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
         <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_dyndns.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </figure>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Network Interface Configuration</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To define the interfaces the DHCP server should listen to and to
       adjust the firewall configuration, select <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> <guimenu>Interface
       Configuration</guimenu> </menuchoice> from the expert configuration
       dialog. From the list of interfaces displayed, select one or more
       that should be attended by the DHCP server. If clients in all subnets
       need to be able to communicate with the server and the server host
       also runs a firewall, adjust the firewall accordingly. To do so,
       select <guimenu>Adapt Firewall Settings</guimenu>. &yast; then
       adjusts the rules of &susefirewall; to the new conditions (see
       <xref linkend="fig.yast2.dhcp.fire"/>), after which you can return to
       the original dialog by selecting <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
      </para>
      <figure xml:id="fig.yast2.dhcp.fire">
       <title>DHCP Server: Network Interface and Firewall</title>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
         <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_fire.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
         <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_dhcp_fire.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </figure>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    After completing all configuration steps, close the dialog with
    <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. The server is now started with its new
    configuration.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.dhcp.soft">
  <title>DHCP Software Packages</title><indexterm>

  <primary>DHCP</primary>

  <secondary>packages</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Both the DHCP server and the DHCP clients are available for &sls;. The
   DHCP server available is <systemitem class="daemon">dhcpd</systemitem>
   (published by the Internet Systems Consortium).
<!-- the client software is available on SLED as well. -->
   On the client side, there is <systemitem>dhcp-client</systemitem> (also
   from ISC) and tools coming with the <systemitem>wicked</systemitem>
   package.
  </para>

  <para>
   By default, the <systemitem>wicked</systemitem> tools are installed with
   the services <systemitem>wickedd-dhcp4</systemitem> and
   <systemitem>wickedd-dhcp6</systemitem>. Both are
   launched automatically on each system boot to watch for a DHCP server.
   They do not need a configuration file to do their job and work out of the
   box in most standard setups. For more complex situations, use the ISC
   <systemitem>dhcp-client</systemitem>, which is controlled by means of the
   configuration files <filename>/etc/dhclient.conf</filename> and
   <filename>/etc/dhclient6.conf</filename>.
<!--ix-->
   <indexterm>
   <primary>configuration files</primary>
   <secondary>dhclient.conf</secondary>
   </indexterm>
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.dhcp.server">
  <title>The DHCP Server dhcpd</title>

<!--ix--><indexterm>

  <primary>configuration files</primary>

  <secondary>dhcpd.conf</secondary></indexterm><indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="idx.dhcp_server">

  <primary>DHCP</primary>

  <secondary>server</secondary></indexterm><indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="idx.dhcp_dhcpd">

  <primary>DHCP</primary>

  <secondary>dhcpd</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   The core of any DHCP system is the dynamic host configuration protocol
   daemon. This server <emphasis>leases</emphasis> addresses and watches how
   they are used, according to the settings defined in the configuration
   file <filename>/etc/dhcpd.conf</filename>. By changing the parameters and
   values in this file, a system administrator can influence the program's
   behavior in numerous ways. Look at the basic sample
   <filename>/etc/dhcpd.conf</filename> file in
   <xref linkend="dat.dhcp.conf"/>.
  </para>

  <example xml:id="dat.dhcp.conf">
   <title>The Configuration File /etc/dhcpd.conf</title>
<screen><!--adjust to standard network example-->
default-lease-time 600;         # 10 minutes
max-lease-time 7200;            # 2  hours

option domain-name "&exampledomain;";
option domain-name-servers &dnsip;;
option broadcast-address &subnetIIbc;;
option routers &routerintipII;;
option subnet-mask &subnetmask;;

subnet &subnetII;.0 netmask &subnetmask;
 {
  range &subnetII;.10 &subnetII;.20;
  range &subnetII;.100 &subnetII;.200;
 }
</screen>
  </example>

  <para>
   This simple configuration file should be sufficient to get the DHCP
   server to assign IP addresses in the network. Make sure that a semicolon
   is inserted at the end of each line, because otherwise dhcpd is not
   started.
  </para>

  <para>
   The sample file can be divided into three sections. The first one defines
   how many seconds an IP address is leased to a requesting client by
   default (<literal>default-lease-time</literal>) before it should apply
   for renewal. This section also includes a statement of the maximum period
   for which a machine may keep an IP address assigned by the DHCP server
   without applying for renewal (<literal>max-lease-time</literal>).
  </para>

  <para>
   In the second part, some basic network parameters are defined on a global
   level:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The line <literal>option domain-name</literal> defines the default
     domain of your network.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     With the entry <literal>option domain-name-servers</literal>, specify
     up to three values for the DNS servers used to resolve IP addresses
     into host names and vice versa. Ideally, configure a name server on
     your machine or somewhere else in your network before setting up DHCP.
     That name server should also define a host name for each dynamic
     address and vice versa. To learn how to configure your own name server,
     read <xref linkend="cha.dns"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The line <literal>option broadcast-address</literal> defines the
     broadcast address the requesting client should use.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     With <literal>option routers</literal>, set where the server should
     send data packets that cannot be delivered to a host on the local
     network (according to the source and target host address and the subnet
     mask provided). Usually, especially in smaller networks, this
     router is identical to the Internet gateway.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     With <literal>option subnet-mask</literal>, specify the netmask
     assigned to clients.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   The last section of the file defines a network, including a subnet mask.
   To finish, specify the address range that the DHCP daemon should use to
   assign IP addresses to interested clients. In
   <xref linkend="dat.dhcp.conf"/>, clients may be given any address between
   <literal>&subnetII;.10</literal> and
   <literal>&subnetII;.20</literal> or
   <literal>&subnetII;.100</literal> and
   <literal>&subnetII;.200</literal>.
  </para>

  <para>
   After editing these few lines, you should be able to activate the DHCP
   daemon with the command <command>systemctl start dhcpd</command>.
   It will be ready for use immediately. Use the command
   <command>rcdhcpd</command>&nbsp;<option>check-syntax</option>
<!--taroth 2014-02-13: systemd - this command is going to stay according to a
    discussion with Marius (mt): "Could you open a bug for me, that rcdhcpd /
    rcdhcp6 currently does not support the "check-syntax" action (referring to
    bnc#861124)? I'd submit the required scripts ASAP then and you can keep
    the text" - see also
    http://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=868713-->
<!--ke 2014-05-14: mt implemented it as promised.-->
   to perform a brief syntax check. If you encounter any unexpected problems
   with your configuration (the server aborts with an error or does not
   return <literal>done</literal> on start), you should be able to find out
   what has gone wrong by looking for information either in the main system
   log that can be queried with the command <command>journalctl</command>
   (see <xref linkend="cha.journalctl"/> for more information).
  </para>

  <para>
   On a default &productname; system, the DHCP daemon is started in a
   chroot environment for security reasons. The configuration files must be
   copied to the chroot environment so the daemon can find them. Normally,
   there is no need to worry about this because the command
   <command>systemctl start dhcpd </command> automatically copies
   the files.
  </para><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.dhcp_server"/><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.dhcp_dhcpd"/>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.dhcp.statip">
   <title>Clients with Fixed IP Addresses</title><indexterm>
   <primary>DHCP</primary>
   <secondary>static address assignment</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    DHCP can also be used to assign a predefined, static address to a
    specific client. Addresses assigned explicitly always take priority over
    dynamic addresses from the pool. A static address never expires in the
    way a dynamic address would, for example, if there were not enough
    addresses available and the server needed to redistribute them among
    clients.
   </para>
   <para>
    To identify a client configured with a static address, dhcpd uses the
    hardware address (which is a globally unique, fixed numerical code
    consisting of six octet pairs) for the identification of all network
    devices (for example, <literal>&wsImac;</literal>). If the respective
    lines, like the ones in <xref linkend="dat.dhcp.conf.add"/>, are added
    to the configuration file of <xref linkend="dat.dhcp.conf"/>, the DHCP
    daemon always assigns the same set of data to the corresponding client.
   </para>
   <example xml:id="dat.dhcp.conf.add">
    <title>Additions to the Configuration File</title>
<screen>host &wsI; {
hardware ethernet &wsImac;;
fixed-address &wsIip;;
}</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    The name of the respective client (<literal>host</literal>
    <replaceable>host name</replaceable>, here
    <systemitem>&wsI;</systemitem>) is entered in the first line and the
    MAC address in the second line. On Linux hosts, find the MAC address
    with the command <command>ip</command> <option>link show</option>
    followed by the network device (for example, <literal>eth0</literal>).
    The output should contain something like
   </para>
<screen>link/ether &wsImac;</screen>
   <para>
    In the preceding example, a client with a network card having the MAC
    address <literal>&wsImac;</literal> is assigned the IP address
    <systemitem class="ipaddress">&wsIip;</systemitem> and the host name
    <literal>&wsI;</literal> automatically. The type of hardware to enter
    is <literal>ethernet</literal> in nearly all cases, although
    <literal>token-ring</literal>, which is often found on IBM systems, is
    also supported.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.dhcp.sle">
   <title>The &productname; Version</title>
   <para>
    To improve security, the &productname; version of the ISC's DHCP
    server comes with the non-root/chroot patch by Ari Edelkind applied.
    This enables dhcpd to run with the user ID
    <systemitem class="username">nobody</systemitem> and run in a chroot
    environment (<filename>/var/lib/dhcp</filename>). To make this possible,
    the configuration file <filename>dhcpd.conf</filename> must be located
    in <filename>/var/lib/dhcp/etc</filename>. The init script automatically
    copies the file to this directory when starting.
   </para>
   <para>
    Control the server's behavior regarding this feature by means of entries
    in the file <filename>/etc/sysconfig/dhcpd</filename>. To run dhcpd
    without the chroot environment, set the variable
    <systemitem>DHCPD_RUN_CHROOTED</systemitem> in
    <filename>/etc/sysconfig/dhcpd</filename> to <quote>no</quote>.
   </para>
   <para>
    To enable dhcpd to resolve host names even from within the chroot
    environment, some other configuration files must be copied as well:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <filename>/etc/localtime</filename>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <filename>/etc/host.conf</filename>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <filename>/etc/hosts</filename>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    These files are copied to <filename>/var/lib/dhcp/etc/</filename> when
    starting the init script. Take these copies into account for any changes
    that they require if they are dynamically modified by scripts like
    <filename>/etc/ppp/ip-up</filename>. However, there should be no need to
    worry about this if the configuration file only specifies IP addresses
    (instead of host names).
   </para>
   <para>
    If your configuration includes additional files that should be copied
    into the chroot environment, set these under the variable
    <systemitem>DHCPD_CONF_INCLUDE_FILES</systemitem> in the file
    <filename>/etc/sysconfig/dhcpd</filename>. To ensure that the DHCP
    logging facility keeps working even after a restart of the syslog
    daemon, there is an additional entry
    <systemitem>SYSLOGD_ADDITIONAL_SOCKET_DHCP</systemitem> in the file
    <filename>/etc/sysconfig/syslog</filename>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.dhcp.addinfo">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   More information about DHCP is available at the Web site of the
   <emphasis>Internet Systems Consortium</emphasis>
   (<link xlink:href="http://www.isc.org/products/DHCP/"/>). Information is
   also available in the <option>dhcpd</option>,
   <option>dhcpd.conf</option>, <option>dhcpd.leases</option>, and
   <option>dhcp-options</option> man pages.
  </para><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.DHCP"/>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
