<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- [DOCU] Create a network bridge section in
                 administration guide doc
     -->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" version="5.1" xml:id="sec-network-iface-bridge">
 <title>Configuring a network bridge device</title>

 <info>
  <meta name="description" its:translate="yes">Configure network bridge device </meta>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>

 <para>
        A network bridge is a virtual Link Layer (Layer 2) device used to connect multiple network segments into a single logical network. The bridge behaves like a virtual network switch, inspecting traffic and forwarding data frames dynamically based on hardware MAC addresses. A common use case for network bridges is virtualization environments (such as KVM or Xen), where physical network interfaces are shared with multiple guest virtual machines.
    </para>
    <para>
        Network bridges can be configured either graphically using <keycap>YaST</keycap> or manually by creating configuration files within the <filename class="directory">/etc/sysconfig/network/</filename> directory.
    </para>

 <section xml:id="sec-network-bridge-yast">
        <title>Configuring a network bridge with YaST</title>
        <para>
            The preferred method for creating a network bridge interface is using the YaST Network Devices module.
        </para>
        <procedure xml:id="proc-network-bridge-yast-steps">
            <title>Creating a bridge interface with YaST</title>
            <step>
                <para>
    Run <menuchoice><guimenu>&yast;</guimenu> <guimenu>System</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu></menuchoice>.
   </para>
            </step>
            <step>
               <para>
    Use <guimenu>Add</guimenu> and change the <guimenu>Device Type</guimenu> to
    <guimenu>Bridge</guimenu>. Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
   </para></step>
            <step>
                <para>
                    Enter a configuration name in the <guimenu>Configuration Name</guimenu> field (for example, <literal>br0</literal>) and click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
                </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>
                    In the <guimenu>Address</guimenu> tab, specify how the network bridge interface obtains its IP configuration (either via <literal>DHCP</literal> or by assigning a <guimenu>Statically Assigned IP Address</guimenu>).
                </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>
                    Switch to the <guimenu>Bridged Devices</guimenu> tab. Select the checkbox next to the physical network card or VLAN interface that you want to include as a port inside the bridge matrix.
                </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>
                    Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to return to the Network Settings overview, then click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to save the configuration and restart the network service.
                </para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sec-network-bridge-manual-generic">
        <title>Manually configure network bridge</title>
        <para>
            If you choose to bypass YaST, you can configure a network bridge manually by modifying the control parameters inside the network directory scripts. In this scenario, we assume a logical bridge interface named <literal>br0</literal> is created to encapsulate a physical interface named <literal>eth0</literal>.
        </para>
        <procedure xml:id="proc-network-bridge-manual-generic-steps">
            <title>Configuring a bridge with wicked interface scripts</title>
            <step>
                <para>
                    Create a new configuration script profile for the virtual bridge target at <filename>/etc/sysconfig/network/ifcfg-br0</filename>:
                </para>
                <screen language="ini">STARTMODE='auto'
BOOTPROTO='static'
IPADDR='<replaceable>IP_ADDRESS_OF_THE_BRIDGE</replaceable>'
BRIDGE='yes'
BRIDGE_PORTS='eth0'
BRIDGE_STP='off'</screen>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>
                    Modify the properties of the underlying physical network card profile (for example, <filename>/etc/sysconfig/network/ifcfg-eth0</filename>). Ensure that any existing IP address attributes are deleted, and disable protocol configuration options so that it acts purely as a physical port layer:
                </para>
                <screen language="ini">STARTMODE='auto'
BOOTPROTO='none'</screen>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>
                    If using a static IP topology, map the default gateway explicitly to the bridge network interface using a dedicated routing file profile at <filename>/etc/sysconfig/network/ifroute-br0</filename>:
                </para>
                <screen language="text">default <replaceable>GATEWAY_IP_ADDRESS</replaceable> - br0</screen>
                <warning xml:id="war-network-bridge-generic-routes">
                    <title>Conflicting Router Configurations</title>
                    <para>
                        Verify that no obsolete routing statements remain active inside your physical interface script files (such as <filename>ifroute-eth0</filename>). Failing to remove default paths from physical slave adapters will create structural routing conflict flags inside the kernel.
                    </para>
                </warning>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>
                    Reload the active networking configuration space to enforce the changes:
                </para>
                <screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl restart network</screen>
            </step>
        </procedure>
    </section>
   </section>
