<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entities;
 ]>
<chapter id="cha.nm">
 <title>Using &nm;</title><indexterm>
 <primary>Internet</primary>
 <secondary>connecting to</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>&nm;</primary></indexterm>
 <para>
  &nm; is the ideal solution for laptops and other portable computers. It
  supports state-of-the-art encryption types and standards for network
  connections, including connections to 802.1X protected networks. 802.1X is
  the <quote>IEEE Standard for Local and Metropolitan Area
  Networks&mdash;Port-Based Network Access Control</quote>. With &nm;, you
  need not worry about configuring network interfaces and switching between
  wired or wireless networks when you are moving. &nm; can automatically
  connect to known wireless networks or manage several network connections
  in parallel&mdash;the fastest connection is then used as default.
  Furthermore, you can manually switch between available networks and manage
  your network connection using an applet in the system tray.
<!-- Background info (German):
http://www.heise.de/netze/artikel/WLAN-und-LAN-sichern-mit-IEEE-802-1X-und-Radius-979513.html -->
 </para>
 <para>
  Instead of only one connection being active, multiple connections may be
  active at once. This enables you to unplug your laptop from an Ethernet
  and remain connected via a wireless connection.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.nm.usecase">
  <title>Use Cases for &nm;</title>

  <para>
   &nm; provides a sophisticated and intuitive user interface, which enables
   users to easily switch their network environment. However, &nm; is not a
   suitable solution in the following cases:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Your computer provides network services for other computers in your
     network, for example, it is a DHCP or DNS server.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Your computer is a &xen; server or your system is a virtual system
     inside &xen;.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.nm.activate">
  <title>Enabling or Disabling &nm;</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&nm;</primary>

  <secondary>enabling</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   On laptop computers, &nm; is enabled by default. However, it can be at
   any time enabled or disabled in the &yast; Network Settings module.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run &yast; and go to <menuchoice> <guimenu>Network Devices</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu> dialog opens. Go to the
     <guimenu>Global Options</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To configure and manage your network connections with &nm;:
    </para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       In the <guimenu>Network Setup Method</guimenu> field, select
       <guimenu>User Controlled with &nm;</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> and close &yast;.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Configure your network connections with &nm; as described in
       <xref linkend="sec.nm.configure"/>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To deactivate &nm; and control the network with your own configuration
    </para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       In the <guimenu>Network Setup Method</guimenu> field, choose
       <guimenu>Controlled by wicked</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Set up your network card with &yast; using automatic configuration
       via DHCP or a static IP address.
      </para>
      <para>
       Find a detailed description of the network configuration with &yast;
       in <xref linkend="sec.basicnet.yast"/>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.nm.configure">
  <title>Configuring Network Connections</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&nm;</primary>

  <secondary>configuring</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   After having enabled &nm; in &yast;, configure your network connections
   with the &nm; front-end available in GNOME. It shows tabs for all types
   of network connections, such as wired, wireless, mobile broadband, DSL,
   and VPN connections.
  </para>

  <para>
   To open the network configuration dialog in GNOME, open the settings menu
   via the status menu and click the <guimenu>Network</guimenu> entry.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>Availability of Options</title>
   <para>
    Depending on your system setup, you may not be allowed to configure
    connections. In a secured environment, some options may be locked or
    require &rootuser; permission. Ask your system administrator for
    details.
   </para>
  </note>

  <figure>
   <title>GNOME Network Connections Dialog</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="nm_gnome_tabs.png" width="70%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="nm_gnome_tabs.png" width="50%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <procedure id="pro.nm.configure.add">
   <title>Adding and Editing Connections</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open the &nm; configuration dialog.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To add a Connection:
    </para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click the <guimenu>+</guimenu> icon in the lower left corner.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select your preferred connection type and follow the instructions.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       When you are finished click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       After having confirmed your changes, the newly configured network
       connection appears in the list of available networks you get by
       opening the Status Menu.
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To edit a connection:
    </para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select the entry to edit.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click on the gear icon to open the <guimenu>Connection
       Settings</guimenu> dialog.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Insert your changes and click <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> to save them.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To Make your connection available as system connection go to the
       <guimenu>Identity</guimenu> tab and set the checkbox <guimenu>Make
       available to other users</guimenu>. For more information about User
       and System Connections, see <xref linkend="sec.nm.sec.types"/>
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <sect2 id="sec.nm.gome.applet.wired">
   <title>Managing Wired Network Connections</title>
   <para>
    If your computer is connected to a wired network, use the &nm; applet to
    manage the connection.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Open the Status Menu and click on <guimenu>Wired</guimenu> to change
      the connection details or to switch it off.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To change the settings click <guimenu>Wired Settings</guimenu> and
      then click on the gear icon.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To switch off all network connections, activate the <guimenu>Airplane
      Mode</guimenu> setting.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.nm.gnome.applet.wireless">
   <title>Managing Wireless Network Connections</title>
   <para>
    Visible wireless networks are listed in the GNOME &nm; applet menu under
    <guimenu>Wireless Networks</guimenu>. The signal strength of each
    network is also shown in the menu. Encrypted wireless networks are
    marked with a shield icon.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Connecting to a visible Wireless Network</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      To connect to a visible wireless network, open the Status Menu and
      click <guimenu>Wi-Fi</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Turn On</guimenu> to enable it.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Select Network</guimenu>, select your Wi-Fi Network and
      click <guimenu>Connect</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      If the network is encrypted, a configuration dialog opens. It shows
      the type of encryption the network uses and text boxes for entering
      the login credentials.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure>
    <title>Connecting to an Invisible Wireless Network</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      To connect to a network that does not broadcast its service set
      identifier (SSID or ESSID) and therefore cannot be detected
      automatically, open the Status Menu and click on
      <guimenu>Wi-Fi</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Wi-Fi Settings</guimenu> to open the detailed settings
      menu.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Make sure your Wi-Fi is enabled and click <guimenu>Connect to Hidden
      Network...</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the dialog that opens, enter the SSID or ESSID in <guimenu>Network
      Name</guimenu> and set encryption parameters if necessary.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    A wireless network that has been chosen explicitly will remain connected
    as long as possible. If a network cable is plugged in during that time,
    any connections that have been set to <guimenu>Stay connected when
    possible</guimenu> will be connected, while the wireless connection
    remains up.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.nm.gnome.applet.accesspoint">
   <title>Configuring Your Wi-Fi/Bluetooth Card as an Access Point</title>
   <para>
    If your Wi-Fi/Bluetooth card supports access point mode, you can use
    &nm; for the configuration.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Open the Status Menu and click <guimenu>Wi-Fi</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Wi-Fi Settings</guimenu> to open the detailed settings
      menu.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Use as Hotspot...</guimenu> and follow the
      instructions.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use the credentials shown in the resulting dialog to connect to the
      hotspot from a remote machine.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.nm.vpn">
   <title>&nm; and VPN</title><indexterm>
   <primary>&nm;</primary>
   <secondary>VPN</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>VPN</primary></indexterm>
   <para>
    &nm; supports several Virtual Private Network (VPN) technologies. For
    each technology, &productname; comes with a base package providing the
    generic support for &nm;. In addition to that, you also need to install
    the respective desktop-specific package for your applet.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>OpenVPN</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To use this VPN technology, install
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <systemitem class="resource">&nm;-openvpn</systemitem> and
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <systemitem class="resource">&nm;-openvpn-gnome</systemitem>.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>vpnc (Cisco)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To use this VPN technology, install
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <systemitem class="resource">&nm;-vpnc</systemitem> and
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <systemitem class="resource">&nm;-vpnc-gnome</systemitem>.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>PPTP (Point-to-Point Tunneling Protocol)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To use this VPN technology, install
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <systemitem class="resource">&nm;-pptp</systemitem> and
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <systemitem class="resource">&nm;-pptp-gnome</systemitem>.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    After you have installed the packages, configure your VPN connection as
    described in <xref linkend="pro.nm.configure.add"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.nm.security">
  <title>&nm; and Security</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&nm;</primary>

  <secondary>security</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   &nm; distinguishes two types of wireless connections, trusted and
   untrusted. A trusted connection is any network that you explicitly
   selected in the past. All others are untrusted. Trusted connections are
   identified by the name and MAC address of the access point. Using the MAC
   address ensures that you cannot use a different access point with the
   name of your trusted connection.
  </para>

  <para>
   &nm; periodically scans for available wireless networks. If multiple
   trusted networks are found, the most recently used is automatically
   selected. &nm; waits for your selection in case that all networks are
   untrusted.
  </para>

  <para>
   If the encryption setting changes but the name and MAC address remain the
   same, &nm; attempts to connect, but first you are asked to confirm the
   new encryption settings and provide any updates, such as a new key.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you switch from using a wireless connection to offline mode,
   NetworkManager blanks the SSID or ESSID. This ensures that the card is
   disconnected.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.nm.sec.types">
   <title>User and System Connections</title>
   <para>
    &nm; knows two types of connections: <literal>user</literal> and
    <literal>system</literal> connections. User connections are connections
    that become available to &nm; when the first user logs in. Any required
    credentials are asked from the user and when the user logs out, the
    connections are disconnected and removed from &nm;. Connections that are
    defined as system connection can be shared by all users and are made
    available right after &nm; is started&mdash;before any users log in. In
    case of system connections, all credentials must be provided at the time
    the connection is created. Such system connections can be used to
    automatically connect to networks that require authorization. For
    information how to configure user or system connections with &nm;, refer
    to <xref linkend="sec.nm.configure"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.nm.sec.store">
   <title>Storing Passwords and Credentials</title>
   <para>
    If you do not want to re-enter your credentials each time you want to
    connect to an encrypted network, you can use the GNOME Keyring Manager
    to store your credentials encrypted on the disk, secured by a master
    password.
   </para>
<!--Whenever any GNOME application that uses GNOME Keyring
    needs to access passwords or credentials stored there, a check is
    made if the keyring is locked or not. If it is locked, you will be
    prompted for the master password to unlock the keyring.-->
<!--  <phrase os="sled;osuse">For more information about GNOME Keyring, refer to
    <xref linkend="cha.gnome.crypto"
    /></phrase>.-->
   <para>
    &nm; can also retrieve its certificates for secure connections (for
    example, encrypted wired, wireless or VPN connections) from the
    certificate store. For more information, refer to
    <xref
     linkend="cha.certstore"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.nm.faq">
  <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>

  <para>
   In the following, find some frequently asked questions about configuring
   special network options with &nm;.
  </para>

  <qandaset>
   <qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
      How to tie a connection to a specific device?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
      By default, connections in &nm; are device type-specific: they apply
      to all physical devices with the same type. If more than one physical
      device per connection type is available (for example, your machine is
      equipped with two Ethernet cards), you can tie a connection to a
      certain device.
<!-- by explicitly specifying the hardware address (or MAC
	   address) of the device-->
     </para>
     <para>
      To do so in GNOME, first look up the MAC address of your device (use
      the <guimenu>Connection Information</guimenu> available from the
      applet, or use the output of command line tools like
      <command>nm-tool</command> or <command>wicked show all</command>).
      Then start the dialog for configuring network connections and choose
      the connection you want to modify. On the <guimenu>Wired</guimenu> or
      <guimenu>Wireless</guimenu> tab, enter the <guimenu>MAC
      Address</guimenu> of the device and confirm your changes.
     </para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry>
   <qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
      How to specify a certain access point in case multiple access points
      with the same ESSID are detected?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
      When multiple access points with different wireless bands (a/b/g/n)
      are available, the access point with the strongest signal is
      automatically chosen by default. To override this, use the
      <guimenu>BSSID</guimenu> field when configuring wireless connections.
     </para>
     <para>
      The Basic Service Set Identifier (BSSID) uniquely identifies each
      Basic Service Set. In an infrastructure Basic Service Set, the BSSID
      is the MAC address of the wireless access point. In an independent
      (ad-hoc) Basic Service Set, the BSSID is a locally administered MAC
      address generated from a 46-bit random number.
     </para>
     <para>
      Start the dialog for configuring network connections as described in
      <xref linkend="sec.nm.configure"/>. Choose the wireless connection you
      want to modify and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>. On the
      <guimenu>Wireless</guimenu> tab, enter the BSSID.
     </para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry>
   <qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
      How to share network connections to other computers?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
      The primary device (the device which is connected to the Internet)
      does not need any special configuration. However, you need to
      configure the device that is connected to the local hub or machine as
      follows:
     </para>
     <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Start the dialog for configuring network connections as described in
        <xref linkend="sec.nm.configure"/>. Choose the connection you want
        to modify and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>. Switch to the
        <guimenu>IPv4 Settings</guimenu> tab and from the
        <guimenu>Method</guimenu> drop-down box, choose <guimenu>Shared to
        other computers</guimenu>. That will enable IP traffic forwarding
        and run a DHCP server on the device. Confirm your changes in &nm;.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        As the DCHP server uses port <literal>67</literal>, make sure that
        it is not blocked by the firewall: On the machine sharing the
        connections, start &yast; and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Security
        and Users</guimenu> <guimenu>Firewall</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
        Switch to the <guimenu>Allowed Services</guimenu> category. If
        <guimenu>DCHP Server</guimenu> is not already shown as
        <guimenu>Allowed Service</guimenu>, select <guimenu>DCHP
        Server</guimenu> from <guimenu>Services to Allow</guimenu> and click
        <guimenu>Add</guimenu>. Confirm your changes in &yast;.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </orderedlist>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry>
   <qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
      How to provide static DNS information with automatic (DHCP, PPP, VPN)
      addresses?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
      In case a DHCP server provides invalid DNS information (and/or
      routes), you can override it. Start the dialog for configuring network
      connections as described in <xref linkend="sec.nm.configure"/>. Choose
      the connection you want to modify and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
      Switch to the <guimenu>IPv4 Settings</guimenu> tab, and from the
      <guimenu>Method</guimenu> drop-down box, choose <guimenu>Automatic
      (DHCP) addresses only</guimenu>. Enter the DNS information in the
      <guimenu>DNS Servers</guimenu> and <guimenu>Search Domains</guimenu>
      fields. To <guimenu>Ignore automatically obtained routes</guimenu>
      click <guimenu>Routes</guimenu> and activate the respective check box.
      Confirm your changes.
     </para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry>
   <qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
      How to make &nm; connect to password protected networks before a user
      logs in?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
      Define a <literal>system connection</literal> that can be used for
      such purposes. For more information, refer to
      <xref
       linkend="sec.nm.sec.types"/>.
     </para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry>
  </qandaset>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.nm.trouble">
  <title>Troubleshooting</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&nm;</primary>

  <secondary>troubleshooting</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Connection problems can occur. Some common problems related to &nm;
   include the applet not starting or a missing VPN option. Methods for
   resolving and preventing these problems depend on the tool used.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>&nm; Desktop Applet Does Not Start</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The applets starts automatically if the network is set up for &nm;
      control. If the applet does not start, check if &nm; is enabled in
      &yast; as described in <xref linkend="sec.nm.activate"/>. Then make
      sure that the &nm;-gnome package is also installed.
     </para>
     <para>
      If the desktop applet is installed but is not running for some reason,
      start it manually. If the desktop applet is installed but is not
      running for some reason, start it manually with the command
      <command>nm-applet</command>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>&nm; Applet Does Not Include the VPN Option</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Support for &nm;, applets, and VPN for &nm; is distributed in separate
      packages. If your &nm; applet does not include the VPN option, check
      if the packages with &nm; support for your VPN technology are
      installed. For more information, see
      <xref
       linkend="sec.nm.vpn"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>No Network Connection Available</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you have configured your network connection correctly and all other
      components for the network connection (router, etc.) are also up and
      running, it sometimes helps to restart the network interfaces on your
      computer. To do so, log in to a command line as &rootuser; and run
      <command>systemctl restart wicked.services</command>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.nm.more">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   More information about &nm; can be found on the following Web sites and
   directories:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>&nm; Project Page</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="http://projects.gnome.org/NetworkManager/"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Package Documentation</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Also check out the information in the following directories for the
      latest information about &nm; and the GNOME applet:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/NetworkManager/</filename>,
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/NetworkManager-gnome/</filename>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
