<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
          [
          <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
          <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
          %entities;
]>
<sect1 id="sec.nm.gnome">
 <title>Using the GNOME &nm; Applet</title><indexterm>

 <primary>&nm;</primary>

 <secondary>GNOME &nm; applet</secondary></indexterm>

<!--taroth 2012-06-05: link by vuntz: 
 http://library.gnome.org/users/gnome-help/stable/net.html.en-->

 <para>
  In GNOME, &nm; can be controlled with the GNOME &nm; applet. If the
  network is set up for &nm; control, the applet usually starts
  automatically with the desktop environment and is shown as an icon in the
  system tray.
 </para>

 <para>
  If your system tray does not show any network connection icon, the applet
  is probably not started. Press <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
  <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter <command>nm-applet</command> to
  start it manually.
 </para>

 <sect2 id="sec.nm.gome.applet.wired">
  <title>Managing Wired Network Connections</title>
  <para>
   If your computer is connected to an existing network with a network
   cable, use the &nm; applet to choose the network connection.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Left-click the applet icon to show a menu with available networks. The
     currently used connection is selected in the menu.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To switch to another network, choose it from the list.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To switch off all network connections, both wired and wireless,
     right-click the applet icon and deactivate <guimenu>Enable
     Networking</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.nm.gnome.applet.wireless">
  <title>Managing Wireless Network Connections</title>
  <para>
   Available visible wireless networks are listed in the GNOME &nm; applet
   menu under <guimenu>Wireless Networks</guimenu>. The signal strength of
   each network is also shown in the menu. Encrypted wireless networks are
   marked with a shield icon.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <title>Connecting to a Wireless Network</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     To connect to a wireless network, left-click the applet icon and select
     an entry from the list of available wireless networks.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If the network is encrypted, a dialog opens. It shows the type of
     encryption the network uses (<guimenu>Wireless Security</guimenu>) and
     holds a number of text boxes according to the respective encryption and
     authentication settings. Enter the appropriate credentials.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To connect to a network that does not broadcast its service set
     identifier (SSID or ESSID) and therefore cannot be detected
     automatically, left-click the &nm; icon and choose <guimenu>Connect to
     Hidden Wireless Network</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the dialog that opens, enter the SSID or ESSID in <guimenu>Network
     Name</guimenu> and set encryption parameters if necessary.
    </para>
<!-- <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="nm_gnome_wireless_hidden.png" width="55%"
        format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="nm_gnome_wireless_hidden.png" width="45%"
        format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>-->
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To disable wireless networking, right-click the applet icon and
     deactivate <guimenu>Enable Wireless</guimenu>. This can be useful if
     you are on a plane or in any other environment where wireless
     networking is not allowed.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
<!--taroth 2010-06-29: information by bin li <bili@novell.com> -check and
   integrate for next revision: 
   some small thing need to be noted in user's UI, which is different to 11.2.
   2) The state (networking, wireless, ...) is now remembered after reboots, right-click the applet icon, 
   from the pop menu, select the check box to determine enable or not.-->
  <para>
   A wireless network that has been chosen explicitly will remain connected
   as long as possible. If a network cable is plugged in during that time,
   any connections that have been set to <guimenu>Stay connected when
   possible</guimenu> will be connected, while the wireless connection
   remains up.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.nm.gnome.applet.accesspoint">
  <title>Configuring Your Wi-Fi/Bluetooth Card as an Access Point</title>
  <para>
   If your Wi-Fi/Bluetooth card supports access point mode, you can use &nm;
   for configuration.
  </para>
  <note>
   <title>Availability of Options</title>
   <para>
    Depending on your system setup, you may not be allowed to configure
    connections. In a secured environment, some options might be locked or
    require &rootuser; permission. Ask your system administrator for
    details.
   </para>
  </note>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the &nm; applet and select <guimenu>Create New Wireless
     Network</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="con_gaccesspoint.png" width="61%"
        format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="con_gaccesspoint.png" width="61%"
        format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter a <guimenu>Network Name</guimenu> and set the encryption to use
     with the <guimenu>Wireless Security</guimenu> drop-down box.
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>Unprotected Wireless Networks Are a Security Risk</title>
     <para>
      If you set <guimenu>Wireless Security</guimenu> to
      <option>None</option>, everybody can connect to your network, reuse
      your connectivity and intercept your network connection. To restrict
      access to your access point and to secure your connection, use
      encryption. You can choose between various WEP and WPA&ndash;based
      encryption.
     </para>
    </important>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
