<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entities;
 ]>
<sect1 id="sec.nm.kde">
 <title>Using K&nm;</title>

 <para>
  <indexterm>
  <primary>&nm;</primary>
  <secondary>K&nm;</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <remark>taroth 2011-08-10: bnc#708709: stick with K&nm; - SLE 11 SP2 will not ship plasmoid</remark>
  The KDE front-end for &nm; is the K&nm; applet. If the network has been
  set up for &nm; control, the applet usually starts automatically with the
  desktop environment and is shown as an icon in the system tray.
  </para>

 <para>
  If your system tray does not show any network connection icon, the applet
  is probably not started. Press <keycombo><keycap function="alt"/>
  <keycap>F2</keycap> </keycombo> and enter
  <command>knetworkmanager</command> to start it manually.
 </para>

 <para>
  K&nm; only shows wireless networks that you have configured a connection
  for. It hides connections when you are out of range of a wireless network,
  or when the network cable is disconnected, thus always giving you a clear
  view of which connections may be used.
 </para>

 <sect2 id="sec.nm.kde.applet.wired">
  <title>Managing Wired Network Connections</title>
  <para>
   If your computer is connected to an existing network with a network
   cable, use K&nm; to choose the network connection.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Left-click the applet icon to show a menu with available networks. The
     connection currently being used is selected in the menu and marked as
     <guimenu>Active</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If you want to use a different configuration with the wired network,
     click <guimenu>Manage Connections</guimenu> and add another wired
     connection as described in <xref linkend="pro.nm.configure"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the K&nm; icon and select the newly configured connection to
     activate it.
    </para>
   </step>
<!--taroth 0901006: not (yet) available in KNM<step>
    <para>
     To switch off all network connections, both wired and wireless,
     right-click the applet icon and uncheck <guimenu>Enable
      Networking</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>-->
  </procedure>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.nm.kde.applet.wireless">
  <title>Managing Wireless Network Connections</title>
  <para>
   By default, K&nm; only shows wireless networks that you have configured a
   connection for&mdash;provided they are both available and visible. To
   connect to a wireless network for the first time, proceed as follows:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <title>Connecting to a Wireless Network</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Left-click the applet icon and select <guimenu>Create Network
     Connection</guimenu>. K&nm; shows a list of available visible wireless
     networks, including details about signal strength and security.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To connect to a visible network, select the network from the list and
     click <guimenu>Connect</guimenu>. If the network is encrypted, a dialog
     opens. Choose the type of <guimenu>Security</guimenu> the network uses
     and enter the appropriate credentials.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To connect to a network that does not broadcast its service set
     identifier (SSID or ESSID) and therefore cannot be detected
     automatically, select <guimenu>Connect to Other Network with WLAN
     interface</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the dialog that opens, enter the SSID or ESSID and set encryption
     parameters, if necessary.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Confirm your changes and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. &nm; now
     activates the new connection.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To terminate a connection and to disable wireless networking, click the
     applet icon and uncheck <guimenu>Enable Wireless</guimenu>. This can be
     useful if you are on a plane or in any other environment where wireless
     networking is not allowed.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   A wireless network that has been chosen explicitly will remain connected
   as long as possible. If a network cable is plugged in during that time,
   any connections that have been set to <guimenu>Connect
   Automatically</guimenu> will be connected, while the wireless connection
   remains up.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.nm.kde.applet.accesspoint">
  <title>Configuring Your Wireless Card as an Access Point</title>
  <para>
   If your wireless card supports access point mode, you can use &nm; for
   configuration.
  </para>
  <note>
   <title>Availability of Options</title>
   <para>
    Depending on your system setup, you may not be allowed to configure
    connections. In a secured environment, some options might be locked or
    require &rootuser; permission. Ask your system administrator for
    details.
   </para>
  </note>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the K&nm; applet and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Create Network
     Connection</guimenu> <guimenu>New Ad-Hoc Network</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the following configuration dialog, enter a name for your network in
     the <guimenu>SSID</guimenu> field.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="nm_kde_adhoc.png" width="61%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="nm_kde_adhoc.png" width="61%" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Set the encryption on the <guimenu>Wireless Security</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>Unprotected Wireless Networks Are a Security Risk</title>
     <para>
      If you set <guimenu>Security</guimenu> to <option>None</option>,
      everybody can connect to your network, reuse your connectivity and
      intercept your network connection. To restrict access to your access
      point and to secure your connection, use encryption. You can choose
      between various WEP and WPA&ndash;based encryptions. If you are not
      sure which technology is best for you, read
      <xref linkend="sec.wireless.wlan.func.auth"/>.
     </para>
    </important>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>IP Address</guimenu> tab, make sure the
     <guimenu>Configure</guimenu> option is set to <guimenu>Shared</guimenu>
     (which is the default option for ad-hoc networks).
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Confirm your configuration with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect2>

<!--taroth 2010-03-05: as I just learned from Will, the customization options are
 still available, but only if opened from the tray icon -->

 <sect2 id="sec.nm.kde.applet.custom">
  <title>Customizing K&nm;</title>
  <para>
   You can customize some aspects of K&nm;: the number of icons displayed in
   the system tray, which tool tips to show and how to store your password
   and credentials for network connections. For more information about the
   last aspect, refer to <xref linkend="sec.nm.sec.store"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   To explore the options available, right-click the &nm; system tray icon,
   select <guimenu>Manage Connections</guimenu> and click
   <guimenu>Other</guimenu> on the left-hand side of the configuration
   dialog.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <title>Configuring Multiple Tray Icons for K&nm;</title>
   <para>
    As K&nm; can keep multiple connections active at once, you might wish to
    be informed about the connection status for several connections at one
    glance. You can do so by using multiple &nm; icons in your system tray,
    each representing a different group of connection types (for example,
    one icon for wired connections, another icon for wireless connections).
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the configuration dialog, switch to the <guimenu>Tray Icon</guimenu>
     tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>More Icons</guimenu>. A new icon entry appears in the
     list.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the network connection types you want to be represented by this
     icon and group them under the respective icon.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_knm_custom.png" width="61%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="kde_knm_custom.png" width="61%" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Confirm your changes.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   Now the system tray shows multiple &nm; icons from which you then can
   access the connection types tied to that icon.
  </para>
  <para>
   When configuring a network connection as described in
   <xref
    linkend="pro.nm.configure"/>, K&nm; also allows you to
   customize the icon displayed for this connection. To change the icon,
   click the icon button next to <guimenu>Connection Name</guimenu> and in
   the following dialog, select the icon of your choice. After confirming
   your changes, the new icon is displayed in the list of available
   connections you get by clicking the K&nm; icon in the system tray.
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
