<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!-- 2014-08-14, tiwai:
     pm-utils was dropped.  The corresponding commands are with systemd,
     "systemctl suspend", "systemctl hibernate", etc.  There are hooks in
     /usr/lib/systemd/systemd-sleep, see systemd-suspend.service(8) man
     page.

     ke:
     I removed pm-utils references.  Maybe, we should mention the
     systemd backgorund in the future.
-->
<chapter id="cha.pmanage">
 <title>Power Management</title><indexterm id="idx.power_management"
  class="startofrange">
 <primary>power management</primary></indexterm><indexterm id="idx.laptops_power_management"
  class="startofrange">
 <primary>laptops</primary>
 <secondary>power management</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>power management</primary>
 <secondary>ACPI</secondary></indexterm>
 <para arch="zseries" os="sles">
  The features and hardware described in this chapter do not exist on IBM
  &zseries;, making this chapter irrelevant for these platforms.
 </para>
 <para>
  Power management is especially important on laptop computers, but is also
  useful on other systems. ACPI (Advanced Configuration and Power Interface)
  is available on all modern computers (laptops, desktops, and servers).
  Power management technologies require suitable hardware and BIOS routines.
  Most laptops and many modern desktops and servers meet these requirements.
  It is also possible to control CPU frequency scaling to save power or
  decrease noise.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.pmanage.save">
  <title>Power Saving Functions</title>

  <para>
   Power saving functions are not only significant for the mobile use of
   laptops, but also for desktop systems. The main functions and their use
   in ACPI are:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Standby<indexterm>
     <primary>power management</primary>
     <secondary>standby</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      not supported.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Suspend (to memory)<indexterm>
     <primary>power management</primary>
     <secondary>suspend</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This mode writes the entire system state to the RAM. Subsequently, the
      entire system except the RAM is put to sleep. In this state, the
      computer consumes very little power. The advantage of this state is
      the possibility of resuming work at the same point within a few
      seconds without having to boot and restart applications. This function
      corresponds to the ACPI state <literal>S3</literal>.
<!-- The support of
      this state is still under development and therefore largely depends on
      the hardware. -->
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Hibernation (suspend to disk)<indexterm>
     <primary>power management</primary>
     <secondary>hibernation</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      In this operating mode, the entire system state is written to the hard
      disk and the system is powered off. There must be a swap partition at
      least as big as the RAM to write all the active data. Reactivation
      from this state takes about 30 to 90 seconds. The state prior to the
      suspend is restored. Some manufacturers offer useful hybrid variants
      of this mode, such as RediSafe in IBM Thinkpads. The corresponding
      ACPI state is <literal>S4</literal>. In Linux, suspend to disk is
      performed by kernel routines that are independent from ACPI.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Battery Monitor<indexterm>
     <primary>power management</primary>
     <secondary>battery monitor</secondary></indexterm>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      ACPI checks the battery charge status and provides information about
      it. Additionally, it coordinates actions to perform when a critical
      charge status is reached.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Automatic Power-Off</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Following a shutdown, the computer is powered off. This is especially
      important when an automatic shutdown is performed shortly before the
      battery is empty.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Processor Speed Control</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      In connection with the CPU, energy can be saved in three different
      ways: frequency and voltage scaling (also known as
      <phrase role="productname">PowerNow!</phrase> or
      <phrase role="productname">Speedstep</phrase>), throttling and putting
      the processor to sleep (C-states). Depending on the operating mode of
      the computer, these methods can also be combined.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.pmanage.acpi">
  <title>Advanced Configuration and Power Interface (ACPI)</title><indexterm id="idx.power_management_ACPI" class="startofrange">

  <primary>power management</primary>

  <secondary>ACPI</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   ACPI was designed to enable the operating system to set up and control
   the individual hardware components. ACPI supersedes both Power Management
   Plug and Play (PnP) and Advanced Power Management (APM). It delivers
   information about the battery, AC adapter, temperature, fan and system
   events, like <quote>close lid</quote> or <quote>battery low.</quote>
  </para>

  <para>
   The BIOS provides tables containing information about the individual
   components and hardware access methods. The operating system uses this
   information for tasks like assigning interrupts or activating and
   deactivating components. Because the operating system executes commands
   stored in the BIOS, the functionality depends on the BIOS implementation.
   The tables ACPI can detect and load are reported in journald. See
   <xref
   linkend="cha.journalctl"/> for more information on viewing the
   journal log messages. See <xref linkend="sec.pmanage.probs"/> for more
   information about troubleshooting ACPI problems.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.pmanage.powernow">
   <title>Controlling the CPU Performance</title>
   <para>
    The CPU can save energy in three ways:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Frequency and Voltage Scaling
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Throttling the Clock Frequency (T-states)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Putting the Processor to Sleep (C-states)
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    Depending on the operating mode of the computer, these methods can be
    combined. Saving energy also means that the system heats up less and the
    fans are activated less frequently.
   </para>
   <para>
    Frequency scaling and throttling are only relevant if the processor is
    busy, because the most economic C-state is applied anyway when the
    processor is idle. If the CPU is busy, frequency scaling is the
    recommended power saving method. Often the processor only works with a
    partial load. In this case, it can be run with a lower frequency.
    Usually, dynamic frequency scaling controlled by the kernel on-demand
    governor is the best approach.
   </para>
   <para>
    Throttling should be used as the last resort, for example, to extend the
    battery operation time despite a high system load. However, some systems
    do not run smoothly when they are throttled too much. Moreover, CPU
    throttling does not make sense if the CPU has little to do.
   </para>
   <para>
    For in-depth information, refer to <xref linkend="cha.tuning.power"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.pmanage.probs">
   <title>Troubleshooting</title>
   <para>
    There are two different types of problems. On one hand, the ACPI code of
    the kernel may contain bugs that were not detected in time. In this
    case, a solution will be made available for download. More often, the
    problems are caused by the BIOS. Sometimes, deviations from the ACPI
    specification are purposely integrated in the BIOS to circumvent errors
    in the ACPI implementation of other widespread operating systems.
    Hardware components that have serious errors in the ACPI implementation
    are recorded in a blacklist that prevents the Linux kernel from using
    ACPI for these components.
   </para>
   <para>
    The first thing to do when problems are encountered is to update the
    BIOS. If the computer does not boot at all, one of the following boot
    parameters may be helpful:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>pci=noacpi</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Do not use ACPI for configuring the PCI devices.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>acpi=ht</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Only perform a simple resource configuration. Do not use ACPI for
       other purposes.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>acpi=off</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Disable ACPI.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <warning>
    <title>Problems Booting without ACPI</title>
    <para>
     Some newer machines (especially SMP systems and AMD64 systems) need
     ACPI for configuring the hardware correctly. On these machines,
     disabling ACPI can cause problems.
    </para>
   </warning>
   <para>
    Sometimes, the machine is confused by hardware that is attached over USB
    or FireWire. If a machine refuses to boot, unplug all unneeded hardware
    and try again.
   </para>
   <para>
    Monitor the boot messages of the system with the command <command>dmesg
    -T <option>| grep -2i acpi</option></command> (or all messages, because
    the problem may not be caused by ACPI) after booting. If an error occurs
    while parsing an ACPI table, the most important table&mdash;the DSDT
    (<emphasis>Differentiated System Description Table</emphasis>)&mdash;can
    be replaced with an improved version. In this case, the faulty DSDT of
    the BIOS is ignored. The procedure is described in
    <xref linkend="sec.powersave.faq"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    In the kernel configuration, there is a switch for activating ACPI debug
    messages. If a kernel with ACPI debugging is compiled and installed,
    detailed information is issued.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you experience BIOS or hardware problems, it is always advisable to
    contact the manufacturers. Especially if they do not always provide
    assistance for Linux, they should be confronted with the problems.
    Manufacturers will only take the issue seriously if they realize that an
    adequate number of their customers use Linux.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.pmanage.info">
    <title>For More Information</title>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/ACPI-HOWTO/"/> (detailed ACPI
       HOWTO, contains DSDT patches)
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="http://www.acpi.info"/> (Advanced Configuration &amp;
       Power Interface Specification)
      </para>
     </listitem>
<!--taroth 2014-06-06: website no longer availabe, did quick research but could not find 
      any new one/location, therefore commenting
      <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="http://www.lesswatts.org/projects/acpi/"/> (the
       ACPI4Linux project at Sourceforge)
      </para>
     </listitem>
     -->
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="http://acpi.sourceforge.net/dsdt/index.php"/> (DSDT
       patches by Bruno Ducrot)
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.power_management_ACPI"/>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.pmanage.silenthd">
  <title>Rest for the Hard Disk</title>

  <para>
   In Linux, the hard disk can be put to sleep entirely if it is not needed
   or it can be run in a more economic or quieter mode. On modern laptops,
   you do not need to switch off the hard disks manually, because they
   automatically enter an economic operating mode whenever they are not
   needed. However, if you want to maximize power savings, test some of the
   following methods, using the <command>hdparm</command> command.
  </para>

  <para>
   It can be used to modify various hard disk settings. The option
   <option>-y</option> instantly switches the hard disk to the standby mode.
   <option>-Y</option> puts it to sleep. <command>hdparm <option>-S
   x</option></command> causes the hard disk to be spun down after a certain
   period of inactivity. Replace <replaceable>x</replaceable> as follows:
   <literal>0</literal> disables this mechanism, causing the hard disk to
   run continuously. Values from <literal>1</literal> to
   <literal>240</literal> are multiplied by 5 seconds. Values from
   <literal>241</literal> to <literal>251</literal> correspond to 1 to 11
   times 30 minutes.
  </para>

  <para>
   Internal power saving options of the hard disk can be controlled with the
   option <literal>-B</literal>. Select a value from <literal>0</literal> to
   <literal>255</literal> for maximum saving to maximum throughput. The
   result depends on the hard disk used and is difficult to assess. To make
   a hard disk quieter, use the option <literal>-M</literal>. Select a value
   from <literal>128</literal> to <literal>254</literal> for quiet to fast.
  </para>

  <para>
   Often, it is not so easy to put the hard disk to sleep. In Linux,
   numerous processes write to the hard disk, waking it up repeatedly.
   Therefore, it is important to understand how Linux handles data that
   needs to be written to the hard disk. First, all data is buffered in the
   RAM. This buffer is monitored by the
   <systemitem class="daemon">pdflush</systemitem> daemon. When the data
   reaches a certain age limit or when the buffer is filled to a certain
   degree, the buffer content is flushed to the hard disk. The buffer size
   is dynamic and depends on the size of the memory and the system load. By
   default, pdflush is set to short intervals to achieve maximum data
   integrity. It checks the buffer every 5 seconds and writes the data to
   the hard disk. The following variables are interesting:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename>/proc/sys/vm/dirty_writeback_centisecs</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Contains the delay until a pdflush thread wakes up (in hundredths of a
      second).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename>/proc/sys/vm/dirty_expire_centisecs</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Defines after which timeframe a dirty page should be written out
      latest. Default is <literal>3000</literal>, which means 30 seconds.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename>/proc/sys/vm/dirty_background_ratio</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Maximum percentage of dirty pages until pdflush begins to write them.
      Default is <literal>5</literal>%.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename>/proc/sys/vm/dirty_ratio</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      When the dirty page exceeds this percentage of the total memory,
      processes are forced to write dirty buffers during their time slice
      instead of continuing to write.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <warning>
   <title>Impairment of the Data Integrity</title>
   <para>
    Changes to the <systemitem class="daemon">pdflush</systemitem> daemon
    settings endanger the data integrity.
   </para>
  </warning>

<!-- bg: laptop-mode: http://www.samwel.tk/laptop_mode/ -->

  <para>
   Apart from these processes, journaling file systems, like
   <systemitem
   class="filesystem">Btrfs</systemitem>,
   <systemitem class="filesystem"
    >Ext3</systemitem>,
   <systemitem class="filesystem">Ext4</systemitem> and others write their
   metadata independently from
   <systemitem
   class="daemon">pdflush</systemitem>, which also prevents
   the hard disk from spinning down. <phrase os="sled">To avoid this, a
   special kernel extension has been developed for mobile devices. To make
   use of the extension, install the
   <systemitem class="resource">laptop-mode-tools</systemitem> package and
   see
   <filename>/usr/src/linux/Documentation/laptops/laptop-mode.txt</filename>
   for details.</phrase>
  </para>

  <para>
   Another important factor is the way active programs behave. For example,
   good editors regularly write hidden backups of the currently modified
   file to the hard disk, causing the disk to wake up. Features like this
   can be disabled at the expense of data integrity.
  </para>

  <para>
   In this connection, the mail daemon postfix makes use of the variable
   <systemitem>POSTFIX_LAPTOP</systemitem>. If this variable is set to
   <literal>yes</literal>, postfix accesses the hard disk far less
   frequently.
  </para>

  <para os="sled">
<!-- does not seem to exist on SLES -->
   In &productname; these technologies are controlled by
   <systemitem>laptop-mode-tools</systemitem>.
  </para><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.power_management"/><indexterm
   class="endofrange" startref="idx.laptops_power_management"/>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.powersave.faq">
  <title>Troubleshooting</title>

  <para>
   All error messages and alerts are logged in the system journal that can
   be queried with the command <command>journalctl</command> (see
   <xref linkend="cha.journalctl"/> for more information). The following
   sections cover the most common problems.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.powersave.faq.cpufreq">
   <title>CPU Frequency Does Not Work</title>
   <para>
    Refer to the kernel sources to see if your processor is supported. You
    may need a special kernel module or module option to activate CPU
    frequency control. If the
    <systemitem class="resource">kernel-source</systemitem> package is
    installed, this information is available in
    <filename>/usr/src/linux/Documentation/cpu-freq/*</filename>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.powersave.info">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/SDB:Suspend_to_RAM"/>&mdash;How to
     get Suspend to RAM working
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://old-en.opensuse.org/Pm-utils"/>&mdash;How to modify
     the general suspend framework
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
