<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha.planning"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Planning for &productname;</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.planning.start">
  <title>Considerations for Deployment of a &sls;</title>

  <para>
   The implementation of an operating system either in an existing IT
   environment or as a completely new rollout must be carefully prepared. At
   the beginning of the planning process, you should try to define the
   project goals and necessary features. This must always be done
   individually for each project, but the questions to answer should include
   the following:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     How many installations should be done? Depending on this, the best
     deployment methods differ.
<!-- cwickert 2016-04-14: FIXME DEPLOY_REWRITE
      See also <xref linkend="cha.deployment"/>.
     -->
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem os="sles">
    <para>
     Will the system run as physical host or as a virtual machine?
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Will the system be in a hostile environment? Have a look at
     <xref linkend="cha.security"/> to get an overview of consequences.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     How will you get regular updates? All patches are provided online for
     registered users. Find the registration and patch support database at
     <link xlink:href="http://download.suse.com/"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Do you need help for your local installation? &suse; provides training,
     support, and consulting for all topics pertaining to &sls;. Find more
     information about this at
     <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/server/"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Do you need third-party products? Make sure that the required product
     is also supported on the desired platform. &suse; can provide help to
     support software on different platforms when needed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.planning.deploy">
  <title>Deployment of &sls;</title>

  <para>
   To make sure that your system will run flawlessly, always try to use
   certified hardware. The hardware certification process is an ongoing
   process and the database of certified hardware is updated regularly. Find
   the search form for certified hardware at
   <link xlink:href="http://www.suse.com/yessearch/Search.jsp"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Depending on the number of desired installations, it is beneficial to use
   installation servers or even completely automatic installations.
<!-- cwickert 2016-04-14: FIXME DEPLOY_REWRITE
    Have a look at <xref linkend="cha.deployment"/> for more information.
   -->
   When using &xen; virtualization technologies, network root file systems
   or network storage solutions like iSCSI should be considered.
<!-- See also <xref
    linkend="cha.inst.system.iscsi"/> -->
  </para>

  <para>
   &sls; provides you with a broad variety of services. Find an overview of
   the documentation in this book in <xref linkend="pre.sle"/>. Most of the
   needed configurations can be made with &yast;, the &suse; configuration
   utility. In addition, many manual configurations are described in the
   corresponding chapters.
  </para>

  <para>
   In addition to the plain software installation, you should consider
   training the end users of the systems and help desk staff.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.planning.running">
  <title>Running &sls;</title>

  <para>
   The &sls; operating system is a well-tested and stable system.
   Unfortunately, this does not prevent hardware failures or other causes
   for downtime or data loss. For any serious computing task where data loss
   could occur, a regular backup should be done.
  </para>

  <para>
   For optimal security and data safety, you should make regular updates of
   all the operated machines. If you have a mission critical server, you
   should run a second identical (pre-production) machine where you can
   apply all changes for testing purposes before doing so in production.
   This also gives you the possibility of switching machines in the case of
   hardware failure.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
