<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha-planning"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Planning for &productname;</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    This chapter describes some basic considerations before installing
    &productname;.
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker/>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-planning-start">
  <title>Considerations for deployment of <phrase os="sles">a &sls;</phrase><phrase os="slemicro">&slem;</phrase></title>

  <para>
   The implementation of an operating system either in an existing IT
   environment or as a completely new roll out must be carefully prepared. At
   the beginning of the planning process, you should try to define the project
   goals and necessary features. This must always be done individually for each
   project, but the questions to answer should include the following:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     How many installations should be done? Depending on this, the best
     deployment methods differ.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem os="sles">
    <para>
     Will the system run as physical host or as a virtual machine?
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Will the system be in a hostile environment? Have a look at
     <xref os="sles;sled;osuse"
      linkend="cha-security"/> to get an
     overview of consequences.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     How will you get regular updates? All patches are provided online for
     registered users. Find the registration and patch support database at
     <link xlink:href="http://download.suse.com/"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Do you need help for your local installation? &suse; provides training,
     support, and consulting for all topics pertaining to &sls;. Find more
     information about this at
     <link
      xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/server/"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Do you need third-party products? Make sure that the required product is
     also supported on the desired platform. &suse; can provide help to support
     software on different platforms when needed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-planning-deploy">
  <title>Deployment of <phrase os="sles">&sls;</phrase><phrase os="slemicro">&slem;</phrase></title>

  <para>
   To make sure that your system will run flawlessly, always try to use
   certified hardware. The hardware certification process is an ongoing process
   and the database of certified hardware is updated regularly. Find the search
   form for certified hardware at
   <link
    xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/yessearch/Search.jsp"/>.
  </para>

  <para os="sles;sled;osuse">
   Depending on the number of desired installations, it is beneficial to use
   installation servers or even completely automatic
   installations.<phrase os="sles"> When using &xen; or &kvm; virtualization
   technologies, network root file systems or network storage solutions like
   iSCSI should be considered.</phrase>
  </para>

  <para os="slemicro">
   In case you intend to install only several nodes of &slema;, you can choose
   the manual installation or you can directly deploy raw images. For a
   large-scale deployment it is recommended to use the automatic installation
   by using &ay;, &susemgr;, or wherever you can easily copy the raw images to
   the desired machines, you can also use the raw images for a large-scale
   deployment.
  </para>

  <para>
   <phrase os="sles">&sls;</phrase><phrase os="slemicro">&slem;</phrase>
   provides you with a broad variety of services.<phrase os="sles;sled;osuse">
   Find an overview of the documentation in this book in
   <xref linkend="pre-sle"/>. Most of the needed configurations can be made
   with &yast;, the &suse; configuration utility. In addition, many manual
   configurations are described in the corresponding chapters.</phrase>
  </para>

  <para>
   In addition to the plain software installation, you should consider training
   the end users of the systems and help desk staff.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>Terminology</title>
   <para>
    In the following sections, the system to hold your new &productname;
    installation is called <emphasis>target system</emphasis> or
    <emphasis>installation target</emphasis>. The term
    <emphasis>repository</emphasis> (previously called <quote>installation
    source</quote>) is used for all sources of installation data. This includes
    physical media, such as CD, DVD, or &usbflashdrive;, and network servers
    distributing the installation data in your network.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-planning-running">
  <title>Running <phrase os="sles">&sls;</phrase><phrase os="slemicro">&slem;</phrase></title>

  <para>
   The <phrase os="sles">&sls;</phrase><phrase os="slemicro">&slem;</phrase>
   operating system is a well-tested and stable system. Unfortunately, this
   does not prevent hardware failures or other causes for downtime or data
   loss. For any serious computing task where data loss could occur, a regular
   backup should be done.
  </para>

  <para>
   For optimal security and data safety, you should make regular updates of all
   the operated machines. If you have a mission critical server, you should run
   a second identical (pre-production) machine that you can use to test all
   changes. This also gives you the possibility of switching machines in the
   case of hardware failure.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-planning-registering">
  <title>Registering &productname;</title>

  <para>
   To get technical support and product updates, you need to register and
   activate your &suse; product with the &scc;. We recommend to register during
   the installation, since this will enable you to install the system with the
   latest updates and patches available. However, if you are offline or want to
   skip the registration step, you can register at any time later from the
   installed system.
  </para>

  <para>
   In case your organization does not provide a local registration server,
   registering &sle; requires a &scc; account. In case you do not have one yet,
   go to the &scc; home page (<link xlink:href="https://scc.suse.com/"/>) to
   create one.
  </para>

  <para os="sles;sled">
   During the installation you will be asked to enter your registration code.
   For details, see <xref linkend="sec-yast-install-scc-registration"/>.
  </para>

  <para os="slemicro">
   During the manual installation you will be asked to enter your registration
   code. For details, refer to <xref linkend="sec-registration"/>. If you
   deploy &slema; raw images, you need to register your system after the
   installation, for details refer to
   <xref linkend="sec-images-registration"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you deploy your instances automatically using &ay;, you can register the
   system during the installation by providing the respective information in
   the &ay; control file. For details, see
   <xref
    linkend="CreateProfile-Register"/>.
  </para>

  <para os="sles;sled">
   For registering an already installed system, see
   <xref
    linkend="sec-yast-software-register"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 os="sles;sled" xml:id="sec-planning-leanos">
  <title>Changes in installation from &sls; version &product-ga;</title>

  <para>
   Starting with &productname; 15, all &sle;-based products are installed using
   a &leanos; from a single set of installation media for each supported
   architecture.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-planning-leanos-products">
   <title>&leanos; for &sle;-based products</title>
   <para>
    As of &productname; &productnumber;, this includes the following base
    products:
   </para>
   <informaltable>
    <tgroup cols="2">
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>Product Name</entry>
       <entry>Supported Platforms</entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>&sls;</entry>
       <entry>&x86-64;; &aarch64;; &power;; &zseries;</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>&slehpc;</entry>
       <entry>&x86-64;; &aarch64;</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>&slert;</entry>
       <entry>&x86-64;</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>&sles4sap;</entry>
       <entry>&x86-64;; &power;</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>&sled;</entry>
       <entry>&x86-64;</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>&susemgr; Server</entry>
       <entry>&x86-64;; &power;; &zseries;</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>&susemgrproxy;</entry>
       <entry>&x86-64;</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>&smr; Branch Server</entry>
       <entry>&x86-64;</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>&ses;</entry>
       <entry>&x86-64;; &arm;; &intel64;</entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </informaltable>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-planning-leanos-install-internet">
   <title>Installing with Internet access</title>
   <para>
    If you are installing onto a computer or VM that has access to the
    Internet, then to install any of the products listed above, it is only
    necessary to download the <filename>&installmedia;</filename> image for the
    desired architecture.
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>Installing &susemgr;</title>
    <para>
     To install any &susemgr; products, the target machine must have direct
     access to the &scc; or to an &rmt; server.
    </para>
   </note>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-planning-leanos-install-offline">
   <title>Offline installation</title>
   <para>
    Except for &susemgr;, you do not require access to the Internet, or to the
    &scc; or to an &rmt; server, to install the other listed products.
   </para>
   <para>
    For offline installation, additionally download the
    <filename>&packagemedia;</filename> image for the desired architecture.
   </para>
   <para>
    There is an additional, second Packages medium, but this contains only
    source code and is not required for installation.
   </para>
   <tip>
    <title>Full media size</title>
    <para>
     The size of the full installation media &installmedia; exceeds the
     capacity of a dual layer DVD. Therefore you can only boot it from a USB
     flash drive.
    </para>
   </tip>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-planning-qu-media">
   <title>Quarterly updated media</title>
   <!-- cwickert 2020-11-18: The following is based on the text from
    https://www.suse.com/download/sles/ -->
   <para>
    For the installation media and the &vmguest; images, &suse; offers two
    variants:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The first, containing <literal>GM</literal> in the file name, consists of
      the package set as shipped on the first customer shipment date.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The second, identified by a <literal>QU</literal> followed by a number in
      the file name, contains the same package set but includes all maintenance
      updates of the packages that have been released in the meantime.
      Quarterly updated media are refreshed every three months, with the first
      coming three months after the <literal>GM</literal> release.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    You only need either the <literal>GM</literal> or the <literal>QU</literal>
    media, not both. Which version to select depends on your needs and
    preferences. If you have newer hardware, the QU version might be the better
    choice. The installation procedure is identical for both variants.
   </para>
   <para>
    For both variants it is recommended to install the latest updates released
    after creation of the images during or immediately after installation.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
