<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<appendix version="5.0" xml:id="sec-containers-terminology"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Terminology</title>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry xml:id="Container">
   <term>Container</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A <emphasis>container</emphasis> is a running instance based on a
     particular container image. Each <emphasis>container</emphasis> can be
     distinguished by a unique container ID.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry xml:id="vle-docker-cgroup">
   <term>Control groups</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Control groups</emphasis>, also called
     <literal>cgroups</literal> , are a Linux kernel feature that allows
     aggregating or partitioning tasks (processes) and all their children into
     hierarchically-organized groups, to manage their resource limits.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Container image</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A <emphasis>container image</emphasis> is an unchangeable, static file
     that includes executable code so it can run an isolated process on IT
     infrastructure. The image is comprised of system libraries, system tools,
     and other platform settings a program needs to run on a containerization
     platform. A container image is compiled from file system layers built on
     top of a parent or base image.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Base image</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A <emphasis>base image</emphasis> is an image that does not have a parent
     image. In a Dockerfile, a base image is identified by the <literal>FROM
     scratch</literal> directive.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Parent image</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The image that serves as the basis for another container image. In other
     words, if an image is not a base image, it is derived from a parent image.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Namespaces</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &deng; uses Linux <emphasis>namespaces</emphasis> for its containers,
     which isolates resources reserved for particular containers.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Orchestration</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In a production environment, you typically need a cluster with many
     containers on each cluster node. The containers must cooperate and you
     need a framework that enables you to automatically manage the containers.
     The act of automatic container management is called container
     orchestration and is typically handled by Kubernetes.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Registry</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A <emphasis>registry</emphasis> is storage for already-created images. It
     typically contains several <emphasis>repositories</emphasis>. There are
     two types of registries:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       public registry: Any (usually registered) user can download and use
       images. A typical example of a public registry is
       <link xlink:href="https://hub.docker.com/">Docker Hub</link>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       private registry: Access is restricted to particular users, or from a
       particular private network.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Repository</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A <emphasis>repository</emphasis> is storage for images in a
     <emphasis>registry</emphasis>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
</appendix>
