<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-security">
 <title>Security and Confidentiality</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
  </dm:docmanager>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    This chapter introduces basic concepts of computer security.
    Threats and basic mitigation techniques are described. The chapter
    also provides references to other chapters, guides and websites with
    further information.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-security-overview">
  <title>Overview</title>
  <para>
   One main characteristic of Linux is its ability to handle multiple
   users at the same time (multiuser) and to allow these users to
   simultaneously perform tasks (multitasking) on the same computer.
   To users, there is no difference between working with data stored
   locally and data stored in the network.
  </para>
  <para>
   Due to the multiuser capability, data from different users has to be stored
   separately to guarantee security and privacy. Also important is the ability
   to keep data available in spite of a lost or damaged data medium, for
   example a hard disk.
  </para>
  <para>
   This chapter is primarily focused on confidentiality and privacy. But
   a comprehensive security concept includes a regularly updated,
   workable, and tested backup. Without a backup, restoring data after
   it has been tampered with or after a hardware failure is very hard.
  </para>
  <para>
   Use a <emphasis>defense-in-depth</emphasis> approach to security:
   Assume that no single threat mitigation can fully protect your
   systems and data, but multiple layers of defense will make an attack
   much harder. Components of a defense-in-depth strategy can be the
   following:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Hashing passwords (for example with PBKDF2, bcrypt, or scrypt) and
     salting them
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Encrypting data (for example with AES)</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Logging, monitoring, and intrusion detection</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Firewall</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Antivirus scanner</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Defined and documented emergency procedures</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Backups</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Physical security</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Audits, security scans, and intrusion tests</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   &productname; includes software that addresses the requirements of
   the list above. The following sections provide starting points for
   securing your system.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-security-passwords">
  <title>Passwords</title>
  <para>
   On a Linux system, only hashes of passwords are stored. Hashes are
   one-way algorithms that make it easy to encrypt data. At the same
   time, hash algorithms make it very hard to compute the original
   secret from the hash.
  </para>
  <para>
   The hashes are stored in the file <filename>/etc/shadow</filename>,
   which cannot be read by normal users. Because restoring passwords is
   possible with powerful computers, hashed passwords should not be
   visible to regular users.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <emphasis>National Institute of Standards and
   Technology</emphasis> (<emphasis>NIST</emphasis>) publishes a
   guideline for passwords, which is available at <link
   xlink:href="https://pages.nist.gov/800-63-3/sp800-63b.html#sec5"
   />
  </para>
  <para>
   For details about how to set a password policy, see <xref
   linkend="sec-security-yast-security-password" />. For general
   information about authentication on Linux, see <xref
   linkend="part-auth" />.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-security-integrity">
  <title>System Integrity</title>
  <para>
   If it is possible to physically access a computer, the firmware and
   boot process can be manipulated to gain access as soon as an
   authorized person boots the machine. While not all computers can be locked
   into inaccessible rooms, your first step should be physically locking the
   server room.
  </para>
  <para>
   Consider taking the following additional measures:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Configure your system so it cannot be booted from a removable
     device, either by removing the drives entirely or by setting a
     UEFI password and configuring the UEFI to allow booting from a
     hard disk only.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To make the boot procedure more tamper-resistant, enable the UEFI
     <emphasis>secure boot</emphasis> feature.
     For more information about Secure Boot, see <xref linkend="cha-uefi"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Linux systems are started by a boot loader that usually allows
     passing additional options to the booted kernel. You can prevent others
     from using such parameters during boot by setting an additional
     password for the boot loader. This is crucial to system
     security. Not only does the kernel itself run with &rootuser;
     permissions, but it is also the first authority to grant
     &rootuser; permissions at system start-up.
    </para>
    <para>
     For more information about setting a password in the boot loader, see
     <xref linkend="sec-grub2-password"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Enable hard disk encryption. For more information, see
     <xref linkend="cha-security-cryptofs"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Use AIDE to detect any changes in your system configuration. For
     more information, see <xref linkend="cha-aide" />.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-security-file-access">
  <title>File Access</title>
  <para>
   Because of the <emphasis>everything is a file</emphasis> approach in
   Linux, file permissions are important for controlling access to most
   resources. This means that by using file permissions, you can define
   access to regular files and directories as well as hardware devices.
   By default, most hardware devices are only accessible for
   &rootuser;. However, some devices, for example serial ports, can be
   accessible for normal users.
  </para>
  <para>
   As a general rule, always work with the most restrictive privileges
   possible for a given task. For example, it is definitely not
   necessary to be &rootuser; to read or write e-mail. If the mail
   program has a bug, this bug could be exploited for an attack that
   acts with exactly the permissions of the program at the time of the
   attack. By following the above rule, minimize the possible damage.
  </para>
  <para>
   For details, see <xref linkend="sec-security-acls-traditional" /> and
   <xref linkend="sec-security-acls-intro" />.
  </para>
  <para>
   &aa; <phrase os="osuse;sles">and SELinux allow</phrase><phrase
   os="sled">allows</phrase> you to set constraints for applications and
   users. For details, see <xref linkend="part-apparmor" /><phrase
   os="sles;osuse"> and <xref linkend="part-selinux" /></phrase>.
  </para>
  <para>
   If there is a chance that hard disks could be accessed outside of the
   installed operating system, for example by booting a live system or removing
   the hardware, encrypt the data. &productname; allows you to encrypt
   partitions containing data and the operating system. For details, see <xref
   linkend="cha-security-cryptofs" />.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-security-network">
  <title>Networking</title>
  <para>
   Securing network services is a crucial task. Aim to secure
   as many layers of the <emphasis>OSI model</emphasis> as possible.
  </para>
  <para>
   All communication should be authenticated and encrypted with
   up-to-date cryptographic algorithms on the transport or application
   layer. Use a Virtual Private Network (VPN) as an additional secure
   layer on physical networks.
  </para>
  <para>
   &productname; provides many options for securing your network:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Use <command>openssl</command> to create X509 certificates. These certificates can be
     used for encryption and authentication of many services.
     You can set up your own <emphasis>certificate authority</emphasis>
     (<emphasis>CA</emphasis>) and use it as a source of trust in your
     network. For details, see <command>man openssl</command>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Usually, at least parts of networks are exposed to the public
     Internet. Reduce attack surfaces by closing ports with firewall
     rules and by uninstalling or at least disabling unrequired
     services. For details, see <xref linkend="cha-security-firewall"
     />.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Use OpenVPN to secure communication channels over insecure
     physical networks. For details, see <xref
     linkend="cha-security-vpnserver" />.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Use strong authentication for network services. For details, see
     <xref linkend="part-auth" />.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-security-vulnerabilities">
  <title>Software Vulnerabilities</title>
  <para>
   Software vulnerabilities are issues in software that can be
   exploited to obtain unauthorized access or misuse systems.
   Vulnerabilities are especially critical if they affect remote
   services, such as HTTP servers. Computer systems are very complex,
   therefore they always include certain vulnerabilities.
  </para>
  <para>
   When such issues become known, they must usually be fixed in the
   software by software developers. The resulting update must then be
   installed by system administrators in a timely and safe manner on
   affected systems.
  </para>
  <para>
   Vulnerabilities are usually announced on centralized
   databases, for example the <emphasis>National Vulnerability
   Database</emphasis>, which is maintained by the US government.
   You can subscribe to feeds to stay informed about newly
   discovered vulnerabilities. In some cases the problems induced by
   the bugs can be mitigated until a software update is provided.
   Vulnerabilities are assigned a <emphasis>Common Vulnerabilities
   and Exposures</emphasis> (<emphasis>CVE</emphasis>) number and a
   <emphasis>Common Vulnerability Scoring System</emphasis>
   (<emphasis>CVSS</emphasis>) score. The score helps identify
   the severity of vulnerabilities.
  </para>
  <para>
   &suse; provides a feed of security advisories. It is available at
   <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/en-us/support/update/" />.
   There is also a list of security updates by CVE number available at
   <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/en-us/security/cve/" />.
  </para>
  <note os="sles;sled">
   <title>Backports and Version Numbers</title>
   <para>
    &suse; employs the practice of applying the important source code
    fixes onto older stable versions of software
    (<emphasis>backporting</emphasis>). Therefore, even if the version
    number of a software in &productname; is lower than that of the
    latest version number from the upstream project, the software
    version in &productname; may already contain the latest fixes for
    vulnerabilities.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more information, see <xref linkend="cha-update-backport"/>.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   In general, administrators should be prepared for severe
   vulnerabilities in their systems. This includes hardening all
   computers as far as possible. Also, we recommend to have predefined
   procedures in place for quickly installing updates for severe
   vulnerabilities.
  </para>
  <para>
   To reduce the damage of possible attacks, use restrictive file
   permissions. See <xref linkend="sec-security-acls-traditional" />.
  </para>
  <para>
   Other useful links:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <link xlink:href=
     "http://lists.opensuse.org/opensuse-security-announce/" />,
     mailing list with &opensuse; security announcements
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <link xlink:href= "https://nvd.nist.gov/home"/>, the National
     Vulnerability Database
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <link xlink:href="https://cve.mitre.org/" />, MITRE's CVE database
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para><link
    xlink:href="https://www.bsi.bund.de/DE/Service/Aktuell/Cert_Bund_Meldungen/cert_bund_meldungen_node.html"
    />, <emphasis>German Federal Office for Information
    Security</emphasis> vulnerability feed</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
    <link
    xlink:href="https://www.first.org/cvss/"
    />, information about the Common Vulnerability Scoring System
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-security-malware">
  <title>Malware</title>
  <para>
   <emphasis>Malware</emphasis> is software that is intended to
   interrupt the normal functioning of a computer or steal data. This
   includes viruses, worms, ransomware, or rootkits. Sometimes malware
   uses software vulnerabilities to attack a computer. However, in many
   cases it is accidentally executed by a user, especially when
   installing third-party software from unknown sources. &productname;
   provides an extensive list of programs (packages) in its download
   repositories. This reduces the need to download third-party
   software. All packages provided by &suse; are signed. The package
   manager of &productname; checks the signatures of packages after the
   download to verify their integrity.
  </para>
  <para>
   The command <command>rpm</command>&nbsp;<option>--checksig
   <replaceable>RPM_FILE</replaceable></option> shows whether the
   checksum and the signature of a package are correct.
   You can find the signing key on the first DVD of &productname; and
   on most key servers worldwide.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can use the &clamav; antivirus software to detect malware on your
   system. &clamav; can be integrated into several services, for example
   mail servers and HTTP proxies. This can be used to filter malware
   before it reaches the user.
  </para>
  <para>
   Restrictive user privileges can reduce the risk of accidental
   code execution.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-security-tips">
  <title>Important Security Tips</title>

  <para>
   The following tips are a quick summary of the sections above:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Stay informed about the latest security issues. Get and install
     the updated packages recommended by security announcements as
     quickly as possible.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Avoid using &rootuser; privileges whenever possible. Set
     restrictive file permissions.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Only use encrypted protocols for network communication.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Disable any network services you do not absolutely require.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Conduct regular security audits. For example, scan your network for
     open ports.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Monitor the integrity of files on your systems with
     <literal>AIDE</literal> (Advanced Intrusion Detection
     Environment).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Take proper care when installing any third-party software.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check all your backups regularly.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check your log files, for example with logwatch.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Configure the firewall to block all ports that are not explicitly
     whitelisted.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Design your security measures to be redundant.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Use encryption where possible, for example for hard disks of mobile
     computers.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-security-general-report">
  <title>Reporting Security Issues</title>

  <para>
   If you discover a security-related problem, first check the
   available update packages. If no update is available, write an
   e-mail to <email>security@suse.de</email>. Include a detailed
   description of the problem and the version number of the package
   concerned. We encourage you to encrypt e-mails with GPG.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can find a current version of the SUSE GPG key at
   <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/security/contact/"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
