<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
       xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
       version="5.0" 
       xml:id="cha-security-fips">
 <title>Enabling FIPS 140-2</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
     The Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) Publication 140-2 is 
     a U.S. government standard for validating the quality of cryptographic 
     modules. An implementation of an approved cryptographic algorithm is 
     FIPS 140-2-compliant only after it has passed National Institute of 
     Standards and Technology (NIST) validation. This chapter provides 
     guidance on whether admins should enable FIPS mode in &sle;, how to 
     enable it, and links to resources with detailed information, such as 
     certified modules, and relevant publications.
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 
<sect1 xml:id="sec-fips-concept">
  <title>FIPS 140-2 timeline</title>
  <para>
    The FIPS 140-2 standard was finalized in 2002, and is valid until 
    September 22, 2026. On September 21, 2021, the Cryptographic Module 
    Validation Program (CMVP) stopped accepting new modules for validation.
  </para>
  <para>
    The FIPS 140-3 standard was accepted in March 2019, and will replace 
    140-2. CMVP has been accepting new module submissions for validation 
    since September 2020 for FIPS 140-3.
  </para>
  <para>
     See  
     <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/security/certifications/"/> for a list of certified modules.
     (NIST, see
     <link xlink:href="https://csrc.nist.gov/projects/cryptographic-module-validation-program"/>).
   </para>
</sect1>
    
     
<sect1 xml:id="sec-fips-use-case">
  <title>When to enable FIPS</title>
  <para>
    FIPS does not provide system-wide protection TODO
  </para>  
  <para>
    The use case for enabling FIPS is simple: run your &slea; server in FIPS 
    mode it when it is required to meet compliance rules. Otherwise, don't 
    enable it. 
  </para>
  <para>
     When you are not required to meet compliance rules, running your servers 
     in FIPS mode is most likely not a good idea. These are some of the reasons to not use FIPS mode:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        FIPS is restrictive. It enforces the use of specific validated 
        cryptographic algorithms, and specific certified binaries that 
        implement these validated algorithms. You must use only the certified 
        binaries.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Upgrades may break functionality.        
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Server and clients must use only approved binaries.
      </para>
    </listitem>    
    <listitem>
      <para>
         The approval process is very long, so certified binaries are always
         several releases behind.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Certified binaries, such as ssh, sshd, and sftp-server, run their own
        self-checks at startup, and run only when these checks succeed. 
        This creates some small performance degradation.
      </para>
    </listitem>    
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Administering FIPS is complex and requires significant 
        expertise.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect1>
                                                                               
 
<sect1 xml:id="sec-fips-install">
  <title>Installing FIPS</title>
  <para>
    It is best to install the 
    <package>patterns-server-enterprise-fips</package> pattern on a new 
    installation. Then, after the installation is complete, enable FIPS by 
    running the steps in <xref linkend="sec-fips-enable"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
    You may install <package>patterns-server-enterprise-fips</package>
    on a running system, but then it is likely you will have to make 
    adjustments, such as regenerating keys, and audit the system to ensure
    it is compliant.
  </para>
</sect1>    
    
<sect1 xml:id="sec-fips-enable">
  <title>Enabling FIPS</title>

<!-- The file paths for the two READMEs are different than in earlier 
  releases. In SLE 15 SP2 and older the path is /usr/share/doc/packages/openssh/
  cschroder Jan 13, 2022 -->  
<para>
  Enabling FIPS takes a few steps. First, read the
  <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/openssh-common/README.FIPS</filename> and
  <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/openssh-common/README.SUSE</filename>   
  files, from the <package>openssh-common</package> package. These contain 
  important information about FIPS on &sle;.
  </para>
  <para>
    Check if FIPS is already enabled:
  </para>
  <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>sysctl -a | grep fips</command>
crypto.fips_enabled = 0</screen>
  <para>
  <literal>crypto.fips_enabled = 0</literal> indicates that it is not enabled. A return value of 1 means that it is enabled.
  </para>  
  <para>
    Then edit <filename>/etc/default/grub</filename>. If 
    <filename>/boot</filename> is not on a separate partition, add
    <literal>fips=1</literal> to 
    <literal>GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX_DEFAULT</literal>, like the following
    example:
  </para>
  <screen>GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX_DEFAULT="splash=silent mitigations=auto quiet fips=1"</screen>
  <para>
    If <filename>/boot</filename> is on a separate partition, specify which 
    partition, like the following example, substituting the name of your boot
    partition:
  </para>
  <screen>GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX_DEFAULT="splash=silent mitigations=auto quiet fips=1 boot=<replaceable>/dev/sda1"</replaceable></screen>
  <para>
    Save your changes, and rebuild your GRUB configuration and initramfs 
    image:
  </para>
  <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>grub2-mkconfig -o /boot/grub2/grub.cfg</command>
&prompt.sudo;<command>mkinitrd</command></screen>
  <para>
  Reboot, then verify your changes. The following example shows that
  FIPS is enabled:
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>sysctl -a | grep fips</command>
crypto.fips_enabled = 1</screen>
  <para>
  After enabling FIPS it is possible that your system will not boot. If this  
  happens, reboot to bring up the GRUB menu. Press <keycap>E</keycap> to edit 
  your boot entry, and delete the <literal>fips</literal> entry from the
  <literal>linux</literal> line. Press the <keycap>F10</keycap> key to boot. 
  This is a temporary change, and most likely the problem is an error in
  <filename>/etc/default/grub</filename>. Correct it, rebuild GRUB and 
  initramfs, then reboot.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>  