<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.security.acls">
 <title>Access Control Lists in Linux</title>
 <info>
      <abstract>
        <para>
    POSIX ACLs (access control lists) can be used as an expansion of the
    traditional permission concept for file system objects. With ACLs,
    permissions can be defined more flexibly than with the traditional
    permission concept.
   </para>
      </abstract>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
          </dm:bugtracker>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="idx.ACLs">
 <primary>ACLs</primary></indexterm><indexterm xml:id="idx.file_systems_access_control_lists" class="startofrange">
 <primary>file systems</primary>
 <secondary>ACLs</secondary></indexterm><indexterm xml:id="idx.permissions_ACLs" class="startofrange">
 <primary>permissions</primary>
 <secondary>ACLs</secondary></indexterm>
 <para>
  The term <emphasis>POSIX ACL</emphasis> suggests that this is a true POSIX
  (<emphasis>portable operating system interface</emphasis>) standard. The
  respective draft standards POSIX 1003.1e and POSIX 1003.2c have been
  withdrawn for several reasons. Nevertheless, ACLs (as found on many
  systems belonging to the Unix family) are based on these drafts and the
  implementation of file system ACLs (as described in this chapter) follows
  these two standards, as well.
 </para>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.security.acls.traditional">
  <title>Traditional File Permissions</title>

  <para>
   Find detailed information about the traditional file permissions in the
   GNU Coreutils Info page, Node <emphasis>File permissions</emphasis>
   (<command>info coreutils "File permissions"</command>). More advanced
   features are the setuid, setgid, and sticky bit.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.acls.traditional.setuid">
   <title>The setuid Bit</title>
   <para>
    In certain situations, the access permissions may be too restrictive.
    Therefore, Linux has additional settings that enable the temporary
    change of the current user and group identity for a specific action. For
    example, the <command>passwd</command> program normally requires root
    permissions to access <filename>/etc/passwd</filename>. This file
    contains some important information, like the home directories of users
    and user and group IDs. Thus, a normal user would not be able to change
    <filename>passwd</filename>, because it would be too dangerous to grant
    all users direct access to this file. A possible solution to this
    problem is the <emphasis>setuid</emphasis> mechanism. setuid (set user
    ID) is a special file attribute that instructs the system to execute
    programs marked accordingly under a specific user ID. Consider the
    <command>passwd</command> command:
   </para>
<screen>-rwsr-xr-x  1 root shadow 80036 2004-10-02 11:08 /usr/bin/passwd</screen>
   <para>
    You can see the <literal>s</literal> that denotes that the setuid bit is
    set for the user permission. By means of the setuid bit, all users
    starting the <command>passwd</command> command execute it as
    <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.acls.traditional.setgid">
   <title>The setgid Bit</title>
   <para>
    The setuid bit applies to users. However, there is also an equivalent
    property for groups: the <emphasis>setgid</emphasis> bit. A program for
    which this bit was set runs under the group ID under which it was saved,
    no matter which user starts it. Therefore, in a directory with the
    setgid bit, all newly created files and subdirectories are assigned to
    the group to which the directory belongs. Consider the following example
    directory:
   </para>
<screen>drwxrws--- 2 &exampleuser; archive 48 Nov 19 17:12  backup</screen>
   <para>
    You can see the <literal>s</literal> that denotes that the setgid bit is
    set for the group permission. The owner of the directory and members of
    the group <systemitem class="groupname">archive</systemitem> may access
    this directory. Users that are not members of this group are
    <quote>mapped</quote> to the respective group. The effective group ID of
    all written files will be
    <systemitem class="groupname">archive</systemitem>. For example, a
    backup program that runs with the group ID
    <systemitem class="groupname">archive</systemitem> is able to access
    this directory even without root privileges.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.acls.traditional.sticky">
   <title>The Sticky Bit</title>
   <para>
    There is also the <emphasis>sticky bit</emphasis>. It makes a difference
    whether it belongs to an executable program or a directory. If it
    belongs to a program, a file marked in this way is loaded to RAM to
    avoid needing to get it from the hard disk each time it is used. This
    attribute is used rarely, because modern hard disks are fast enough. If
    this bit is assigned to a directory, it prevents users from deleting
    each other's files. Typical examples include the
    <filename>/tmp</filename> and <filename>/var/tmp</filename> directories:
   </para>
<screen>drwxrwxrwt 2 root root 1160 2002-11-19 17:15 /tmp</screen>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.security.acls.intro">
  <title>Advantages of ACLs</title>

  <para>
   Traditionally, three permission sets are defined for each file object on
   a Linux system. These sets include the read (<literal>r</literal>), write
   (<literal>w</literal>), and execute (<literal>x</literal>) permissions
   for each of three types of users&mdash;the file owner, the group, and
   other users. In addition to that, it is possible to set the <emphasis>set
   user id</emphasis>, the <emphasis>set group id</emphasis>, and the
   <emphasis>sticky</emphasis> bit. This lean concept is fully adequate for
   most practical cases. However, for more complex scenarios or advanced
   applications, system administrators formerly needed to use a number of
   workarounds to circumvent the limitations of the traditional permission
   concept.
  </para>

  <para>
   ACLs can be used as an extension of the traditional file permission
   concept. They allow the assignment of permissions to individual users or
   groups even if these do not correspond to the original owner or the
   owning group. Access control lists are a feature of the Linux kernel and
   are currently supported by ReiserFS, Ext2, Ext3, JFS, and XFS. Using
   ACLs, complex scenarios can be realized without implementing complex
   permission models on the application level.
  </para>

  <para>
   The advantages of ACLs are evident if you want to replace a Windows
   server with a Linux server. Some of the connected workstations may
   continue to run under Windows even after the migration. The Linux system
   offers file and print services to the Windows clients with Samba. With
   Samba supporting access control lists, user permissions can be configured
   both on the Linux server and in Windows with a graphical user interface
   (only Windows NT and later). With <command>winbindd</command>, part of
   the Samba suite, it is even possible to assign permissions to users only
   existing in the Windows domain without any account on the Linux server.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.security.acls.defs">
  <title>Definitions</title><indexterm>

  <primary>ACLs</primary>

  <secondary>definitions</secondary></indexterm>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>User Class</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The conventional POSIX permission concept uses three
      <emphasis>classes</emphasis> of users for assigning permissions in the
      file system: the owner, the owning group, and other users. Three
      permission bits can be set for each user class, giving permission to
      read (<literal>r</literal>), write (<literal>w</literal>), and execute
      (<literal>x</literal>).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>ACL</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <indexterm>
      <primary>ACLs</primary>
      <secondary>access</secondary>
      </indexterm> The user and group access permissions for all kinds of
      file system objects (files and directories) are determined by means of
      ACLs.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Default ACL</term>
    <listitem><indexterm>
     <primary>ACLs</primary>
     <secondary>default</secondary></indexterm>
     <para>
      Default ACLs can only be applied to directories. They determine the
      permissions a file system object inherits from its parent directory
      when it is created.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>ACL Entry</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Each ACL consists of a set of ACL entries. An ACL entry contains a
      type, a qualifier for the user or group to which the entry refers, and
      a set of permissions. For some entry types, the qualifier for the
      group or users is undefined.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.security.acls.handle">
  <title>Handling ACLs</title><indexterm>

  <primary>ACLs</primary>

  <secondary>handling</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>ACLs</primary>

  <secondary>structure</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   <xref linkend="tab.entrytype"/> summarizes the six possible types of ACL
   entries, each defining permissions for a user or a group of users. The
   <emphasis>owner</emphasis> entry defines the permissions of the user
   owning the file or directory. The <emphasis>owning group</emphasis> entry
   defines the permissions of the file's owning group. The superuser can
   change the owner or owning group with <command>chown</command> or
   <command>chgrp</command>, in which case the owner and owning group
   entries refer to the new owner and owning group. Each <emphasis>named
   user</emphasis> entry defines the permissions of the user specified in
   the entry's qualifier field. Each <emphasis>named group</emphasis> entry
   defines the permissions of the group specified in the entry's qualifier
   field. Only the named user and named group entries have a qualifier field
   that is not empty. The <emphasis>other</emphasis> entry defines the
   permissions of all other users.
  </para>

  <para>
   The <emphasis>mask</emphasis> entry further limits the permissions
   granted by named user, named group, and owning group entries by defining
   which of the permissions in those entries are effective and which are
   masked. If permissions exist in one of the mentioned entries as well as
   in the mask, they are effective. Permissions contained only in the mask
   or only in the actual entry are not effective&mdash;meaning the
   permissions are not granted. All permissions defined in the owner and
   owning group entries are always effective. The example in
   <xref linkend="tab.mask"/> demonstrates this mechanism.
  </para>

  <para>
   There are two basic classes of ACLs: A <emphasis>minimum</emphasis> ACL
   contains only the entries for the types owner, owning group, and other,
   which correspond to the conventional permission bits for files and
   directories. An <emphasis>extended</emphasis> ACL goes beyond this. It
   must contain a mask entry and may contain several entries of the named
   user and named group types.
  </para>

  <table xml:id="tab.entrytype">
   <title>ACL Entry Types</title>
   <tgroup cols="2">
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Type
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Text Form
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        owner
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>user::rwx</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        named user
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>user:name:rwx</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        owning group
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>group::rwx</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        named group
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>group:name:rwx</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        mask
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>mask::rwx</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        other
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>other::rwx</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>

  <table xml:id="tab.mask">
   <title>Masking Access Permissions</title>
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Entry Type
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Text Form
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Permissions
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        named user
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>user:geeko:r-x</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>r-x</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        mask
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>mask::rw-</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>rw-</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para/>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        effective permissions:
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>r--</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.acls.handle.fmbits">
   <title>ACL Entries and File Mode Permission Bits</title><indexterm>
   <primary>ACLs</primary>
   <secondary>permission bits</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    <xref linkend="fig.acls.map.mini"/> and
    <xref linkend="fig.acls.map.ext"/> illustrate the two cases of a minimum
    ACL and an extended ACL. The figures are structured in three
    blocks&mdash;the left block shows the type specifications of the ACL
    entries, the center block displays an example ACL, and the right block
    shows the respective permission bits according to the conventional
    permission concept (for example, as displayed by <command>ls</command>
    <option>-l</option>). In both cases, the <emphasis>owner
    class</emphasis> permissions are mapped to the ACL entry owner.
    <emphasis>Other class</emphasis> permissions are mapped to the
    respective ACL entry. However, the mapping of the <emphasis>group
    class</emphasis> permissions is different in the two cases.
   </para>
   <figure xml:id="fig.acls.map.mini">
    <title>Minimum ACL: ACL Entries Compared to Permission Bits</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="acls_map_mini.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="acls_map_mini.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    In the case of a minimum ACL&mdash;without mask&mdash;the group
    class permissions are mapped to the ACL entry owning group. This is
    shown in <xref linkend="fig.acls.map.mini"/>. In the case of an extended
    ACL&mdash;with mask&mdash;the group class permissions are mapped
    to the mask entry. This is shown in <xref linkend="fig.acls.map.ext"/>.
   </para>
   <figure xml:id="fig.acls.map.ext">
    <title>Extended ACL: ACL Entries Compared to Permission Bits</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="acls_map_ext.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="acls_map_ext.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <remark>Oops. We need to change the example users in the pngs! -rwalter</remark>
   <para>
    This mapping approach ensures the smooth interaction of applications,
    regardless of whether they have ACL support. The access permissions that
    were assigned by means of the permission bits represent the upper limit
    for all other <quote>fine adjustments</quote> made with an ACL. Changes
    made to the permission bits are reflected by the ACL and vice versa.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.acls.handle.accacl">
   <title>A Directory with an ACL</title><indexterm>
   <primary>ACLs</primary>
   <secondary>access</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    With <command>getfacl</command> and <command>setfacl</command> on the
    command line, you can access ACLs. The usage of these commands is
    demonstrated in the following example.
   </para>
   <para>
    Before creating the directory, use the <command>umask</command> command
    to define which access permissions should be masked each time a file
    object is created. The command <command>umask</command>
    <option>027</option> sets the default permissions by giving the owner
    the full range of permissions (<literal>0</literal>), denying the group
    write access (<literal>2</literal>), and giving other users no
    permissions at all (<literal>7</literal>). <command>umask</command>
    actually masks the corresponding permission bits or turns them off. For
    details, consult the <command>umask</command> man page.
   </para>
   <para>
    <command>mkdir mydir</command> creates the <filename>mydir</filename>
    directory with the default permissions as set by
    <command>umask</command>. Use <command>ls</command> <option>-dl
    mydir</option> to check whether all permissions were assigned correctly.
    The output for this example is:
   </para>
<screen>drwxr-x--- ... tux project3 ... mydir</screen>
   <para>
    With <command>getfacl</command> <option>mydir</option>, check the
    initial state of the ACL. This gives information like:
   </para>
<screen># file: mydir 
# owner: tux 
# group: project3 
user::rwx 
group::r-x 
other::---</screen>
   <para>
    <indexterm>
    <primary>commands</primary>
    <secondary>getfacl</secondary>
    </indexterm> The first three output lines display the name, owner, and
    owning group of the directory. The next three lines contain the three
    ACL entries owner, owning group, and other. In fact, in the case of this
    minimum ACL, the <command>getfacl</command> command does not produce any
    information you could not have obtained with <command>ls</command>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Modify the ACL to assign read, write, and execute permissions to an
    additional user <literal>geeko</literal> and an additional group
    <literal>mascots</literal> with:
   </para>
<screen>setfacl -m user:geeko:rwx,group:mascots:rwx mydir</screen><indexterm>
   <primary>commands</primary>
   <secondary>setfacl</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    The option <option>-m</option> prompts <command>setfacl</command> to
    modify the existing ACL. The following argument indicates the ACL
    entries to modify (multiple entries are separated by commas). The final
    part specifies the name of the directory to which these modifications
    should be applied. Use the <command>getfacl</command> command to take a
    look at the resulting ACL.
   </para>
<screen># file: mydir 
# owner: tux 
# group: project3 
user::rwx 
user:geeko:rwx 
group::r-x
group:mascots:rwx 
mask::rwx 
other::---</screen>
   <para>
    <indexterm>
    <primary>ACLs</primary>
    <secondary>masks</secondary>
    </indexterm> In addition to the entries initiated for the user
    <literal>geeko</literal> and the group <literal>mascots</literal>, a
    mask entry has been generated. This mask entry is set automatically so
    that all permissions are effective. <command>setfacl</command>
    automatically adapts existing mask entries to the settings modified,
    unless you deactivate this feature with <literal>-n</literal>. The mask
    entry defines the maximum effective access permissions for all entries
    in the group class. This includes named user, named group, and owning
    group. The group class permission bits displayed by
    <command>ls</command> <option>-dl mydir</option> now correspond to the
    <literal>mask</literal> entry.
   </para>
<screen>drwxrwx---+ ... tux project3 ... mydir</screen>
   <para>
    The first column of the output contains an additional
    <literal>+</literal> to indicate that there is an
    <emphasis>extended</emphasis> ACL for this item.
   </para>
   <para>
    According to the output of the <command>ls</command> command, the
    permissions for the mask entry include write access. Traditionally, such
    permission bits would mean that the owning group (here
    <literal>project3</literal>) also has write access to the directory
    <filename>mydir</filename>.
   </para>
   <para>
    However, the effective access permissions for the owning group
    correspond to the overlapping portion of the permissions defined for the
    owning group and for the mask&mdash;which is <literal>r-x</literal>
    in our example (see <xref linkend="tab.mask"/>). As far as the effective
    permissions of the owning group in this example are concerned, nothing
    has changed even after the addition of the ACL entries.
   </para>
   <para>
    Edit the mask entry with <command>setfacl</command> or
    <command>chmod</command>. For example, use <command>chmod</command>
    <option>g-w mydir</option>. <command>ls</command> <option>-dl
    mydir</option> then shows:
   </para>
<screen>drwxr-x---+ ... tux project3 ... mydir</screen>
   <para>
    <command>getfacl</command> <option>mydir</option> provides the following
    output:
   </para>
<screen># file: mydir 
# owner: tux 
# group: project3 
user::rwx 
user:geeko:rwx          # effective: r-x
group::r-x 
group:mascots:rwx       # effective: r-x 
mask::r-x 
other::---</screen>
   <para>
    After executing the <command>chmod</command> command to remove the write
    permission from the group class bits, the output of the
    <command>ls</command> command is sufficient to see that the mask bits
    must have changed accordingly: write permission is again limited to the
    owner of <filename>mydir</filename>. The output of the
    <command>getfacl</command> confirms this. This output includes a comment
    for all those entries in which the effective permission bits do not
    correspond to the original permissions, because they are filtered
    according to the mask entry. The original permissions can be restored at
    any time with <command>chmod</command> <option>g+w mydir</option>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.acls.handle.defacl">
   <title>A Directory with a Default ACL</title><indexterm>
   <primary>ACLs</primary>
   <secondary>default</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Directories can have a default ACL, which is a special kind of ACL
    defining the access permissions that objects in the directory inherit
    when they are created. A default ACL affects both subdirectories and
    files.
   </para>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.security.acls.handle.defacl.eff">
    <title>Effects of a Default ACL</title><indexterm>
    <primary>ACLs</primary>
    <secondary>effects</secondary></indexterm>
    <para>
     There are two ways in which the permissions of a directory's default
     ACL are passed to the files and subdirectories:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A subdirectory inherits the default ACL of the parent directory both
       as its default ACL and as an ACL.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A file inherits the default ACL as its ACL.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     All system calls that create file system objects use a
     <literal>mode</literal> parameter that defines the access permissions
     for the newly created file system object. If the parent directory does
     not have a default ACL, the permission bits as defined by the
     <literal>umask</literal> are subtracted from the permissions as passed
     by the <literal>mode</literal> parameter, with the result being
     assigned to the new object. If a default ACL exists for the parent
     directory, the permission bits assigned to the new object correspond to
     the overlapping portion of the permissions of the
     <literal>mode</literal> parameter and those that are defined in the
     default ACL. The <literal>umask</literal> is disregarded in this case.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.security.acls.handle.defacl.prac">
    <title>Application of Default ACLs</title>
    <para>
     The following three examples show the main operations for directories
     and default ACLs:
    </para>
    <orderedlist spacing="normal">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Add a default ACL to the existing directory
       <filename>mydir</filename> with:
      </para>
<screen>setfacl -d -m group:mascots:r-x mydir</screen>
      <para>
       The option <literal>-d</literal> of the <command>setfacl</command>
       command prompts <command>setfacl</command> to perform the following
       modifications (option <literal>-m</literal>) in the default ACL.
      </para>
      <para>
       Take a closer look at the result of this command:
      </para>
<screen>getfacl mydir

# file: mydir 
# owner: tux 
# group: project3 
user::rwx 
user:geeko:rwx 
group::r-x
group:mascots:rwx 
mask::rwx 
other::--- 
default:user::rwx
default:group::r-x 
default:group:mascots:r-x 
default:mask::r-x
default:other::---</screen>
      <para>
       <command>getfacl</command> returns both the ACL and the default ACL.
       The default ACL is formed by all lines that start with
       <literal>default</literal>. Although you merely executed the
       <command>setfacl</command> command with an entry for the
       <literal>mascots</literal> group for the default ACL,
       <command>setfacl</command> automatically copied all other entries
       from the ACL to create a valid default ACL. Default ACLs do not have
       an immediate effect on access permissions. They only come into play
       when file system objects are created. These new objects inherit
       permissions only from the default ACL of their parent directory.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In the next example, use <command>mkdir</command> to create a
       subdirectory in <filename>mydir</filename>, which inherits the
       default ACL.
      </para>
<screen>mkdir mydir/mysubdir

getfacl mydir/mysubdir 

# file: mydir/mysubdir 
# owner: tux 
# group: project3 
user::rwx 
group::r-x 
group:mascots:r-x 
mask::r-x
other::--- 
default:user::rwx 
default:group::r-x
default:group:mascots:r-x 
default:mask::r-x 
default:other::---</screen>
      <para>
       As expected, the newly-created subdirectory
       <filename>mysubdir</filename> has the permissions from the default
       ACL of the parent directory. The ACL of <filename>mysubdir</filename>
       is an exact reflection of the default ACL of
       <filename>mydir</filename>. The default ACL that this directory will
       hand down to its subordinate objects is also the same.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use <command>touch</command> to create a file in the
       <filename>mydir</filename> directory, for example,
       <command>touch</command> <option>mydir/myfile</option>.
       <command>ls</command> <option>-l mydir/myfile</option> then shows:
      </para>
<screen>-rw-r-----+ ... tux project3 ... mydir/myfile</screen>
      <para>
       The output of <command>getfacl</command>
       <option>mydir/myfile</option> is:
      </para>
<screen># file: mydir/myfile 
# owner: tux 
# group: project3
user::rw- 
group::r-x          # effective:r-- 
group:mascots:r-x   # effective:r-- 
mask::r-- 
other::---</screen>
      <para>
       <command>touch</command> uses a <literal>mode</literal> with the
       value <literal>0666</literal> when creating new files, which means
       that the files are created with read and write permissions for all
       user classes, provided no other restrictions exist in
       <command>umask</command> or in the default ACL (see
       <xref linkend="sec.security.acls.handle.defacl.eff"/>). In effect,
       this means that all access permissions not contained in the
       <literal>mode</literal> value are removed from the respective ACL
       entries. Although no permissions were removed from the ACL entry of
       the group class, the mask entry was modified to mask permissions not
       set in <literal>mode</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
       This approach ensures the smooth interaction of applications (such as
       compilers) with ACLs. You can create files with restricted access
       permissions and subsequently mark them as executable. The
       <command>mask</command> mechanism guarantees that the right users and
       groups can execute them as desired.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.acls.handle.alg">
   <title>The ACL Check Algorithm</title><indexterm>
   <primary>ACLs</primary>
   <secondary>check algorithm</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    A check algorithm is applied before any process or application is
    granted access to an ACL-protected file system object. As a basic rule,
    the ACL entries are examined in the following sequence: owner, named
    user, owning group or named group, and other. The access is handled in
    accordance with the entry that best suits the process. Permissions do
    not accumulate.
   </para>
   <para>
    Things are more complicated if a process belongs to more than one group
    and would potentially suit several group entries. An entry is randomly
    selected from the suitable entries with the required permissions. It is
    irrelevant which of the entries triggers the final result <quote>access
    granted</quote>. Likewise, if none of the suitable group entries contain
    the required permissions, a randomly selected entry triggers the final
    result <quote>access denied</quote>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.security.acls.future">
  <title>ACL Support in Applications</title><indexterm>

  <primary>ACLs</primary>

  <secondary>support</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   ACLs can be used to implement very complex permission scenarios that meet
   the requirements of modern applications. The traditional permission
   concept and ACLs can be combined in a smart manner. The basic file
   commands (<command>cp</command>, <command>mv</command>,
   <command>ls</command>, etc.) support ACLs, as do Samba and Nautilus.
  </para>

  <para>
   Unfortunately, many editors and file managers still lack ACL support.
   When copying files with Emacs, for instance, the ACLs of these files are
   lost.
   <remark condition="clarity">
    2014-02-12 - fs: FIXME Emacs will support ACLs with version 24.4
                     As of Alpha 3 24.3 is shipped, check later if this
                     is till the case 
   </remark>
   When modifying files with an editor, the ACLs of files are sometimes
   preserved and sometimes not, depending on the backup mode of the editor
   used. If the editor writes the changes to the original file, the ACL is
   preserved. If the editor saves the updated contents to a new file that is
   subsequently renamed to the old file name, the ACLs may be lost, unless
   the editor supports ACLs. Except for the <command>star</command>
   archiver, there are currently no backup applications that preserve ACLs.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.security.acls.info">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   For more information about ACLs, see the man pages for
   <command>getfacl(1)</command>, <command>acl(5)</command>, and
   <command>setfacl(1)</command>.
  </para><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.file_systems_access_control_lists"/><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.permissions_ACLs"/><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.ACLs"/>
 </sect1>
</chapter>