<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.0"
         xml:lang="en"
         xml:id="cha-ssh">

 <title>Securing network operations with OpenSSH</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    OpenSSH is the SSH (secure shell) implementation that ships with &sls;,
    for securing network operations such as remote administration, file
    transfers, and tunneling insecure protocols. SSH encrypts all traffic
    between two hosts, including authentication, to protect against
    eavesdropping and connection hijacking. This chapter covers basic
    operations, plus host key rotation and certificate authentication, which
    are useful for managing larger SSH deployments.
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
   </dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-overview">
  <title>OpenSSH overview</title>
  <para>
   SSH is a network protocol that provides end-to-end protection for
   communications between the computers on your network, or between
   computers on your network and systems outside your network. You may
   open an SSH session to any other computer, as long as you have a login
   and the correct authentication methods for the remote computer.
  </para>
  <para>
   SSH is a client-server protocol. Any host running the
   <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem>
   daemon can accept SSH connections from any other host. Every host running
   <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem> can have their own
   custom configurations, such as limiting who can have access, and which
   authentication methods are allowed.
  </para>
   <para>
   Authentication and encryption are provided by encryption key pairs. Each
   key pair has a public key and a private key. Public keys encrypt, and
   private keys decrypt. Public keys are meant to be freely shared, while
   private keys must be protected and not shared. When a private key is
   compromised, anyone who has possession of it can masquerade as the
   original key owner.
  </para>
  <para>
   SSH provides very strong protection, because the server and client
   must both authenticate to each other. When a client first attempts to
   open an SSH session, the server presents its public host key. If the
   client already possesses a copy of this key (stored in
   <filename>~/.ssh/known_hosts</filename> on the client machine), the
   client knows to trust the server. If the client does not have the
   appropriate host key, it is asked whether it should trust the server:
  </para>
  <screen>The authenticity of host '192.168.22.219 (192.168.22.219)'
   can't be established. ECDSA key fingerprint is
   SHA256:yXf6pjV26N0fegvEYIt3HgG95s3Q1X6WYRhtHLF99pUo.
   Are you sure you want to continue connecting (yes/no/[fingerprint])?
  </screen>
  <para>
   The user can type yes, no, or paste their copy of the host key
   fingerprint for comparison.
  </para>
  <note>
   <title>Matching host key fingerprints</title>
   <para>
    Distributing copies of your host key fingerprints to your users
    enables them to verify that they are receiving the correct host
    keys. When they paste their copy of a host key fingerprint,
    <command>ssh</command> compares the fingerprints, and accepts the
    offered host key when the fingerprints match. This ensures a more
    accurate match than a visual comparison.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can't rely on users to use correct verification methods. If the
    fingerprints do not match, the user can still type
    <literal>yes</literal>, or copy the fingerprint in the message, and
    complete the connection. A stronger alternative is to use
    certificate authentication, which provides a global authentication
    mechansism, and does not require perfect behavior from users
    (see <xref linkend="sec-ssh-certificate-auth"/>).
   </para>
  </note>
   <para>
   If the public keys of a host have changed, the connection is denied with
   a scary warning:
  </para>
  <screen>@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@
@    WARNING: REMOTE HOST IDENTIFICATION HAS CHANGED!     @
@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@
IT IS POSSIBLE THAT SOMEONE IS DOING SOMETHING NASTY!
Someone could be eavesdropping on you right now (man-in-the-middle attack)!
It is also possible that a host key has just been changed.
The fingerprint for the ECDSA key sent by the remote host is
SHA256:keNu/rJFWmpQu9B0SjIuo8NLjbeDY/x3Tktpl7oDJqo.
Please contact your system administrator.
Add correct host key in /home/geeko/.ssh/known_hosts to get rid of this message.
Offending ECDSA key in /home/geeko/.ssh/known_hosts:210
You can use following command to remove the offending key:
ssh-keygen -R 192.168.121.219 -f /home/geeko/.ssh/known_hosts
ECDSA host key for 192.168.121.219 has changed and you have requested strict
checking.
Host key verification failed.</screen>
  <para>
   The remedy is to delete the offending key from
   <filename>~/.ssh/known_hosts</filename> with the command given
   in the scary warning, then re-connect and accept the new host key.
   <!-- see TODO and TODO for key management methods that do not require
   users to verify or accept new host keys -->
  </para>
  <para>
   The <package>openssh</package> package installs the server, client,
   file transfer commands, and some utilities.
  </para>
  <para>
   OpenSSH supports several different types of authentication:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Password authentication</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Uses any system login and password on the remote machine. This is the
      simplest and most flexible authentication because you can open an SSH
      session from anywhere, on any machine. It is also the least secure,
      because it is vulnerable to password-cracking and keystroke logging.
      </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Public key authentication</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Authenticates with your personal SSH keys, rather than a login and
      password. This is less flexible than password authentication,
      because you can open SSH sessions only from a machine that holds
      your private identity key. It is much stronger because it is not
      vulnerable to password cracking or keystroke logging; an attacker must
      possess your private key and know its passphrase.
     </para>
     <para>
       See <xref linkend="sec-ssh-gnome-keyring"/> to learn how to use
       <command>gnome-keyring</command> for automated public key
       authentication in GNOME sessions.
      </para>
      <para>
       See <xref linkend="sec-ssh-authentic-agent"/> to learn how to use
       <literal>ssh-agent</literal> for automated public key
       authentication in console sessions.
      </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
     <term>Passphrase-less public key authentication</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Public key authentication, paired with private identity keys that do
       not have passphrases. This is useful for automated services, like
       scripts and cron jobs. You must protect private keys, because anyone
       who gains access to them can easily masquerade as the key owner.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Certificate authentication</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       OpenSSH supports certification authentication, for easier key
       management, stronger authentication, and large-scale SSH deployments.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>

 <para>
  &productname; installs the OpenSSH package by default, providing the
  following commands:
 </para>

 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><command>ssh</command></term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The client command for initiating an SSH connection to a remote host.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><command>scp</command></term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Secure file copy from or to a remote host.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><command>sftp</command></term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Secure file transfer between a client and an SFTP server.
     (Note that the SFTP protocol (SSH FTP) is not related to FTPS or
     FTPES (FTP over SSL/TLS), but was written independently.)
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><command>ssh-add</command></term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Add private key identities to the authentication agent,
     <literal>ssh-agent</literal>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
   <term><command>ssh-agent</command></term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Manages a user's private identity keys and their passphrases, for
     public key authentication. <literal>ssh-agent</literal> holds the
     passphrases in memory and applies them as needed, so that users do not
     have to re-type their passphrases to authenticate.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><command>ssh-copy-id</command></term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Securely transfer a public key to a remote host, to set up
     public key authentication.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-server-config">
 <title>Server hardening</title>
 <para>
  OpenSSH ships with a usable default server configuration, but there are
  additional steps you can take to secure your server.
 </para>
 <important>
  <title>Maintaining access to a remote SSH server</title>
  <para>
   When you make changes to any SSH server, either have physical
   access to the machine, or keep an active root SSH session open until
   you have tested your changes, and everything works correctly. Then you can revert or correct your changes if something goes wrong.
  </para>
 </important>
 <para>
  The default server configuration file, <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</filename>,
  contains the default configuration, and all the defaults are commented
  out. Override any default item by entering your own configuration item,
  uncommented, like the following example that sets a different listening
  port, and specifies the listening IPv4 address on a multi-homed host:
 </para>
 <screen>
#Port 22
Port <replaceable>2022</replaceable>

#ListenAddress 0.0.0.0
ListenAddress <replaceable>192.168.10.100</replaceable></screen>

<important>
 <title>Update /etc/services</title>
 <para>
  When you use non-standard listening ports, first check the
  <filename>/etc/services</filename> file for unused ports.
  Select any unused port above 1024. Then document the ports you are using
  in <filename>/etc/services</filename>.
 </para>
</important>

 <para>
  It is a best practice to disallow root logins. Instead, log into the
  remote machine as an unprivileged user, then use <command>sudo</command>
  to run commands as root. If you really want to allow root logins, the
  following server configuration example shows how to configure the server
  to accept only public-key authentication
  (<xref linkend="sec-ssh-public-key-auth"/>) for the root user with the
  <literal>PermitRootLogin prohibit-password</literal> and
  <literal>PasswordAuthentication</literal> options.
 </para>
 <para>
  The following settings for <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</filename>
  strengthen access controls:
 </para>
 <example xml:id="ex-sshd-conf">
  <title>Example sshd.conf</title>
  <programlisting>
# Check if the file modes and ownership of the user’s files and
# home directory are correct before allowing them to login
StrictModes yes

# If your machine has more than one IP address, define which address or
# addresses it listens on
ListenAddress <replaceable>192.168.10.100</replaceable>

# Allow only members of the listed groups to log in
AllowGroups <replaceable>ldapadmins backupadmins</replaceable>

# Or, deny certain groups. If you use both, DenyGroups is read first
DenyGroups <replaceable>users</replaceable>

# Allow or deny certain users. If you use both, DenyUsers is read first
AllowUsers <replaceable>user1 user2@example.com user3</replaceable>
DenyUsers <replaceable>user4 user5@192.168.10.10</replaceable>

# Allow root logins only with public key authentication
PermitRootLogin prohibit-password

# Disable password authentication and allow only public key authentication
# for all users
PasswordAuthentication no

# Length of time the server waits for a user to log in and complete the
# connection. The default is 120 seconds:
LoginGraceTime <replaceable>60</replaceable>

# Limit the number of failed connection attempts. The default is 6
MaxAuthTries <replaceable>4</replaceable>
</programlisting>
</example>

 <para>
  After changing <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</filename>, run the syntax
  checker:
 </para>
 <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>sshd -t</command></screen>
 <para>
  The syntax checker only checks for correct syntax, and does not find
  configuration errors. When you are finished, reload the configuration:
 </para>
 <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>systemctl reload sshd.server</command></screen>
 <para>
  Check the server's key directories for correct permissions.
 </para>
 <para>
  <filename>/etc/ssh</filename> should be mode 0755/drwxr-xr-x, owned by
  root:root.
 </para>
 <para>
  Private keys should be 0600/-rw-------, owned by root:root.
 </para>
 <para>
  Public keys should be 0644/-rw-r--r--, owned by root:root.
 </para>

 <!-- not sure if this should be included, it seems redundant with
 sshd_config. cjs 27 June 2022 -->
 <!--
 <para>
  You may restrict logins from subnets with PAM (Pluggable Authentication
  Modules). The following steps configure remote login restrictions for
  certain users. These restrictions affect all OpenSSH commands,
  including <command>ssh</command>
  (<xref linkend="sec-ssh-password-auth"/>),
  <command>scp</command> (<xref linkend="sec-ssh-copy"/>), and
  <command>sftp</command> (<xref linkend="sec-ssh-sftp"/>).
  </para>
  <procedure xml:id="pro-ssh-restrict-logins">
   <title>Configuring remote login restrictions</title>
   <para>
    Perform the following steps to configure user remote login restrictions:
    </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Edit the file <filename>/etc/pam.d/sshd</filename> and append the
     following at the end of the <literal>auth</literal> block:
    </para>
    <screen>auth required pam_access.so</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Edit the file <filename>/etc/security/access.conf</filename> to
     configure individual restrictions. In this example the users &rootuser;
     and &exampleuser; are restricted to the &exampledomain1ip;.0/&subnetmask;
     network, while the &exampleuserII; user can only login from within the
     &exampledomain2ip;.0/&subnetmask; network:
    </para>
<screen>
+ : root : <replaceable>&exampledomain1ip;.0</replaceable>/<replaceable>&subnetmask;</replaceable>
+ : &exampleuser_plain; : <replaceable>&exampledomain1ip;.0</replaceable>/<replaceable>&subnetmask;</replaceable>
+ : &exampleuserII_plain; : <replaceable>&exampledomain2ip;.0</replaceable>/<replaceable>&subnetmask;</replaceable>
- : ALL : ALL</screen>
   <para>
    Do not forget the last line which denies access for all other users from
    all sources, and be careful not to lock yourself out of the system.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more configuration options, refer to the examples in
    <filename>/etc/security/access.conf</filename>, and to
    <command>man access.conf</command>.
   </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <warning>
   <title>Do not use pam-config</title>
   <para>
    Do not use the <command>pam-config</command> utility here. It only
    supports <systemitem>git pam_access</systemitem> as a global module. The
    configuration above is not suitable to be used globally for all services
    and can completely deny access to the system.
   </para>
 </warning>-->
 </sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-password-auth">
  <title>Password authentication</title>
  <para>
   With password authentication, all you need is the login and password of
   a user on the remote machine, and
   <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem> set up and running on the
   remote machine. You do not need any personal SSH keys. In the following
   example, user &exampleuserIII_plain; opens an SSH session to the host
   &exampleserver;:
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>ssh &exampleuserIII_plain;@&exampleserver;</command>
</screen>
  <para>
   &exampleuserIII_plain; will be prompted to enter the remote password.
   Type <literal>exit</literal> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap> to close an
   SSH session.
  </para>
  <para>
   If the user name is the same on both machines, you can omit it, and then
   using <command>ssh <replaceable>HOST_NAME</replaceable></command> is
   sufficient. After a successful authentication, you can work on the
   command line or use interactive applications, such as &yast; in text
   mode.
  </para>
  <para>
   You may also run non-interactive commands (log in, run the command, then
   the session closes all in one command) on remote systems using the
   <command>ssh <replaceable>USER_NAME HOST COMMAND</replaceable></command>
   syntax.
   <replaceable>COMMAND</replaceable> must be properly quoted. Multiple
   commands can be concatenated as on a local shell:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.user;<command>ssh &exampleuserIII_plain;@&exampleserver; "df -h &amp;&amp; du -sh  /home"</command>
&prompt.user;<command>ssh &exampleuserIII_plain;@&exampleserver; "sudo nano /etc/ssh/sshd_config"</command></screen>

  <para>
   When you run <command>sudo</command> on the remote machine, you will be
   prompted for the <command>sudo</command> password.
  </para>
  </sect1>

   <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-authentic-gen-key">
   <title>Managing user and host encryption keys</title>
   <para>
     There are several key types to choose from: DSA, RSA, ECDSA, ECDSA-SK,
     Ed25519, and Ed25519-SK. DSA was deprecated several years ago, and was
     disabled in OpenSSH 7.0 and should not be used. RSA is the most
     universal as it is older, and more widely used. (As of OpenSSH
     8.2, RSA is deprecated for host keys. Use ECDSA or Ed25519 for host
     keys.)
   </para>
   <para>
     Ed25519 and ECDSA are stronger and faster. Ed25519 is
     considered to be the strongest. If you must support older clients
     that do not support Ed25519 or ECDSA, create host keys in all three
     formats.
   </para>
   <note>
     <title>Older clients are unsafe</title>
     <para>
       Some older SSH clients do not support ECDSA and ED25519. ECDSA and
       ED25519 were released with OpenSSH 6.5 in 2014. It is
       important to keep security services updated, and, if possible,
       to not allow unsafe old clients.
     </para>
   </note>
   <para>
     SSH keys serve two purposes: authenticating servers to clients, and
     authenticating clients to servers (see
     <xref linkend="sec-ssh-public-key-auth"/>). Server host keys are stored
     in <filename>/etc/ssh</filename>. Users' personal keys are stored in
     <filename>/home/<replaceable>user</replaceable>/.ssh</filename>.
    </para>
    <para>
     <filename>/home/<replaceable>user</replaceable>/.ssh</filename> is
     created when the user creates a new SSH key.
   </para>
   <para>
     Host keys must not have passphrases.
   </para>
   <para>
     In most cases, private user keys should have strong passphrases.
   </para>

   <sect2 xml:id="sec-create-ssh-key-client">
     <title>Creating user SSH key pairs</title>
      <para>
       The following procedure shows how to create user OpenSSH encryption
       keys.
      </para>
     <procedure xml:id="pro-create-ssh-client-keys">
     <title>Creating default and customized keys</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      To generate a user key pair with the default parameters (RSA, 3072
      bits), use the <command>ssh-keygen</command> command with no options.
      Protect your private key with a strong passphrase:
     </para>
     <screen>&prompt.user;<command>ssh-keygen</command>
Generating public/private rsa key pair.
Enter file in which to save the key (/home/tux/.ssh/id_rsa):
Enter passphrase (empty for no passphrase):
Enter same passphrase again:
Your identification has been saved in id_rsa
Your public key has been saved in id_rsa.pub
The key fingerprint is:
SHA256:z0uJIuc7Doy07bFTe1ppZHLVrkD/bWWlBAF/PcHjblU user@host2
The key's randomart image is:
+---[RSA 3072]----+
|          ..o... |
|           o . +E|
|        . . o +.=|
|       . o . o o+|
|  .   . S . . o +|
| . =  .= * + . = |
|  o *.o.= * . +  |
|   ..Bo+.. . .   |
|    oo==  .      |
+----[SHA256]-----+</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Create an RSA key pair with a longer bit length:
      </para>
      <screen>&prompt.user;<command>ssh-keygen -b 4096</command></screen>
      <para>
        OpenSSH RSA keys can be a maximum of 16,384 bits. However, longer bit
        lengths are not necessarily more desirable. See the GnuPG FAQ for
        more information, <link xlink:href="https://www.gnupg.org/faq/gnupg-faq.html#no_default_of_rsa4096"/>.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
       You may create as many user keys as you want, for accessing
       different servers. Each key pair must have a unique name, and  optionally, a comment. These help you remember what each
       key pair is for. Create an RSA key pair with a custom name and a
       comment:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.user;<command>ssh-keygen -f <replaceable>backup-server-key -C "infrastructure backup server"</replaceable></command>
      </screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
       Create an Ed25519 key pair with a custom name and a comment:
     </para>
     <screen>&prompt.user;<command>ssh-keygen -t ed25519 -f <replaceable>ldap-server-key -C "Internal LDAP server"</replaceable></command>
     </screen>
     <para>
       Ed25519 keys are fixed at 256 bits, which is equivalent in
       cryptographic strength to RSA 4096.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

   <sect2 xml:id="sec-create-ssh-host-keys">
    <title>Creating SSH server host keys</title>
    <para>
      Host keys are managed a little differently. A host key must not
      have a passphrase, and the key pairs are stored in
      <filename>/etc/ssh</filename>.
      OpenSSH automatically generates a set of host keys when it is
      installed, like the following example:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.user;<command>ls -l /etc/ssh</command>
total 608
-rw------- 1 root root 577834 2021-05-06 04:48 moduli
-rw-r--r-- 1 root root   2403 2021-05-06 04:48 ssh_config
-rw-r----- 1 root root   3420 2021-05-06 04:48 sshd_config
-rw------- 1 root root   1381 2022-02-10 06:55 ssh_host_dsa_key
-rw-r--r-- 1 root root    604 2022-02-10 06:55 ssh_host_dsa_key.pub
-rw------- 1 root root    505 2022-02-10 06:55 ssh_host_ecdsa_key
-rw-r--r-- 1 root root    176 2022-02-10 06:55 ssh_host_ecdsa_key.pub
-rw------- 1 root root    411 2022-02-10 06:55 ssh_host_ed25519_key
-rw-r--r-- 1 root root     96 2022-02-10 06:55 ssh_host_ed25519_key.pub
-rw------- 1 root root   2602 2022-02-10 06:55 ssh_host_rsa_key
-rw-r--r-- 1 root root    568 2022-02-10 06:55 ssh_host_rsa_key.pub</screen>

    <para>
      <command>ssh-keygen</command> has a special option, <option>-A</option>,
      for creating new host keys. This creates new keys for each of the key
      types for which host keys do not exist, with the default key file
      path, an empty passphrase, default bit size for the key type, and an
      empty comment. The following example creates a complete new
      set of host keys by first deleting the existing keys, then creating a
      new set:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>rm /etc/ssh/ssh_host*</command>
&prompt.sudo;<command>ssh-keygen -A</command></screen>
    <para>
      You can replace selected key pairs by first deleting only the
      keys you want to replace, because <command>ssh-keygen -A</command>
      does not replace existing keys.
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>Do not use DSA keys</title>
      <para>
        <command>ssh-keygen -A</command> creates DSA keys, even though
        they have been deprecated as unsafe for several years. In OpenSSH
        7.0 they are still created, but disabled by not being listed in
        <filename>sshd_config</filename>. You may safely delete DSA keys.
      </para>
    </important>
    <para>
     When you want to rotate host keys
     (see <xref linkend="sec-ssh-sshdserver-rotation"/>), you must create
     the new keys individually, because they must exist at the same time as
     your old host keys. Your users will authenticate with the old keys,
     and then receive the list of new keys. They need unique names,
     to not conflict with the old keys. The following example creates new
     RSA and Ed25519 host keys, labeled with the year and month they were
     created. Remember, the new host keys must not have passphrases:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.user;<command>cd /etc/ssh</command>
&prompt.sudo;<command>ssh-keygen -b 4096 -f "<replaceable>SSH_HOST_RSA_2022_02</replaceable>"</command>
&prompt.sudo;<command>ssh-keygen -t ed25519 -f "<replaceable>SSH_HOST_ED25519_2022_02</replaceable>"</command></screen>
    <para>
      You may name your new keys whatever you want.
    </para>
   </sect2>
  </sect1>

   <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-sshdserver-rotation">
   <title>Rotating host keys</title>
   <para>
    As of version 6.8, OpenSSH includes a protocol extension that
    supports host key rotation. SSH server admins must periodically
    retire old host keys and create new keys, for example if a key has been
    compromised, or it is time to upgrade to stronger keys. Before OpenSSH
    6.8, if <literal>StrictHostKeyChecking</literal>
    was set to <literal>yes</literal> in <filename>ssh_config</filename>
    on user machines, users would see a warning that the host key had
    changed, and were not allowed to connect. Then the users would have to
    manually delete the server's public key from their
    <filename>known_hosts</filename> file, reconnect, and manually accept the
    new key. Any automated SSH connections, such as scheduled backups, would
    fail.
   </para>
   <para>
     The new host key rotation scheme provides a method to distribute new
     keys without service interruptions. When clients connect, the server
     sends them a list of new keys. Then the next time they log in they are
     asked if they wish to accept the changes. Give users a few days to
     connect and receive the new keys, and then you can remove the old keys.
     The users' <filename>known_hosts</filename> files are automatically
     updated, with new keys added and the old keys removed.
   </para>
    <para>
      Setting up host key rotations requires creating new keys on the server,
      some changes to <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</filename> on the
      server, and to <filename>/etc/ssh/ssh_config</filename> on the clients.
   </para>
   <para>
     First, create your new key or keys. The following example creates a new
     RSA key and a new Ed25519 key, with unique names and comments. A useful
     convention is to name them with the creation date. Remember, a host key
     must not have a passphrase:
   </para>
   <screen>&prompt.root;<command>ssh-keygen -t rsa -f ssh_host_rsa_2022-01 -C "main server"</command>
Generating public/private rsa key pair.
Enter passphrase (empty for no passphrase):
Enter same passphrase again:
Your identification has been saved in ssh_host_rsa_2022-01
Your public key has been saved in ssh_host_rsa_2022-01.pub
The key fingerprint is:
SHA256:F1FIF2aqOz7D3mGdsjzHpH/kjUWZehBN3uG7FM4taAQ main server
The key's randomart image is:
+---[RSA 3072]----+
|         .Eo*.oo |
|          .B .o.o|
|          o . .++|
|         . o ooo=|
|        S . o +*.|
|         o o.oooo|
|       .o ++oo.= |
|       .+=o+o + .|
|       .oo++..   |
+----[SHA256]-----+

&prompt.root;<command>ssh-keygen -t ed25519 -f ssh_host_ed25519_2022-01 -C "main server"</command>
Generating public/private ed25519 key pair.
Enter passphrase (empty for no passphrase):
Enter same passphrase again:
Your identification has been saved in ssh_host_ed25519_2022-01
Your public key has been saved in ssh_host_ed25519_2022-01.pub
The key fingerprint is:
SHA256:2p9K0giXv7WsRnLjwjs4hJ8EFcoX1FWR4nQz6fxnjxg main server
The key's randomart image is:
+--[ED25519 256]--+
|   .+o ...o+     |
| . .... o *      |
|  o..  o = o     |
|  ..   .. o      |
|   o. o S  .     |
|  . oo.*+   E o  |
|   + ++==..  = o |
|    = +oo= o. . .|
|     ..=+o=      |
+----[SHA256]-----+</screen>

   <para>
     Record the fingerprints, for users to verify the new keys.
   </para>
   <para>
     Add the new key names to <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</filename>, and
     uncomment any existing keys that are in use:
   </para>
   <screen>## Old keys
HostKey /etc/ssh/ssh_host_rsa_key
HostKey /etc/ssh/ssh_host_ed25519_key
HostKey /etc/ssh/ssh_host_ecdsa_key

## New replacement keys
HostKey /etc/ssh/ssh_host_rsa_2022-01
HostKey /etc/ssh/ssh_host_ed25519_2022-01</screen>

    <para>
      Save your changes, then restart <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem>:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.root;<command>systemctl restart sshd.service</command>
    </screen>
    <para>
      The <filename>/etc/ssh/ssh_config</filename> file on user machines must
      include the following settings:
    </para>
    <screen>UpdateHostKeys ask
StrictHostKeyChecking yes</screen>
    <para>
      Test connecting from a client by opening an SSH session to the server
      to receive the new keys list. Log out, then log back in. When you log
      back in you should see something like the following message:
    </para>
    <screen>The server has updated its host keys.
These changes were verified by the server's existing trusted key.
Deprecating obsolete hostkey: ED25519
SHA256:V28d3VpHgjsCoV04RBCZpLo5c0kEslCZDVdIUnCvqPI
Deprecating obsolete hostkey:
RSA SHA256:+NR4DVdbsUNsqJPIhISzx+eqD4x/awCCwijZ4a9eP8I
Accept updated hostkeys? (yes/no):yes</screen>
    <para>
      You may set <literal>UpdateHostKeys ask</literal> to
      <literal>UpdateHostKeys yes</literal> to apply the changes
      automatically, and avoid asking users to approve the changes.
    </para>
    <para>
      For more information:
    </para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <xref linkend="sec-ssh-authentic-gen-key"/>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <link xlink:href="http://blog.djm.net.au/2015/02/key-rotation-in-openssh-68.html"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       man 5 ssh_config, man 5 sshd_config
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-public-key-auth">
  <title>Public key authentication</title>
  <para>
   Public key authentication uses your own personal identity key to
   authenticate, rather than a user account password.
  </para>
  <para>
   The following example shows how to create a new personal
   RSA key pair with a comment, so you know what it is for. First change to
   your <filename>~/.ssh</filename> directory (or create it if it does not
   exist), then create the new key pair. Give it a strong passphrase, and
   write the passphrase in a safe place:
  </para>
  <screen>&prompt.user;<command>cd ~/.ssh</command>
&prompt.user;<command>ssh-keygen -C <replaceable>"web server1"</replaceable> -f <replaceable>id-web1</replaceable> -t rsa -b <replaceable>4096</replaceable></command>
</screen>
  <para>
   Next, copy your new public key to the machine you want access to. You
   must already have a user account on this machine, and SSH access to
   copy it over the network:
  </para>
  <screen>&prompt.user;<command>ssh-copy-id -i <replaceable>id-web1 user@web1</replaceable></command></screen>
  <para>
   Then try logging in with your new key:
  </para>
  <screen>&prompt.user;<command>ssh -i <replaceable>id-web1 user@web1</replaceable></command>
Enter passphrase for key 'id-web1':
Last login: Sat Jul 11 11:09:53 2022 from 192.168.10.122
Have a lot of fun...</screen>
  <para>
   You should be asked for your private key passphrase, and not the
   password for your user account.
  </para>
  <para>
   To be effective, public key authentication should be enforced on
   the remote machine, and password authentication not allowed (see
   <xref linkend="ex-sshd-conf"/>). If you do not have public key
   authentication access on the remote machine already, you cannot copy your
   new public key with <command>ssh-copy-id</command>, and must use other
   means, such as manually copying it from a USB stick to the
   <filename>~/.ssh/authorized_keys</filename> file of the remote
   user account.
  </para>
 </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-passphrase-less-auth">
  <title>Passphrase-less public key authentication</title>
  <para>
    This is public key authentication without a passphrase. Create
    your new private identity keys without a passphrase, and then use them
    the same way as passphrase-protected keys. This is useful for automated
    services, such as scripts and cron jobs. However, anyone who succeeds in
    stealing the private key can easily masquerade as you, so you need to be
    very protective of a passphrase-less private key.
  </para>
  <para>
   An alternative to using keys without passphrases is
   <literal>gnome-keyring</literal>, which
   remembers and applies your private keys and passphrases for you.
   <literal>gnome-keyring</literal> is for GNOME desktop sessions
   (<xref linkend="sec-ssh-gnome-keyring"/>).
  </para>
  <para>
   For console sessions, use <literal>ssh-agent</literal>
   (<xref linkend="sec-ssh-authentic-agent"/>).
  </para>
 </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-certificate-auth">
  <title>OpenSSH certificate authentication</title>
  <para>
   OpenSSH introduced certificate authentication in OpenSSH 5.4.
   Certificate authentication is similar to public key authentication,
   except hosts and users authenticate to each other with digitally-signed
   encryption certificates instead of encryption keys. Certificate
   authentication provides central management for server and user
   certificates, eliminating the need to manually copy user public keys to
   multiple hosts. It increases security by giving more control to
   administrators, and less to users.
  </para>
  <para>
   Certificates consist of a public encryption key, a user-defined identity
   string, zero or more user names or host names, and other options.
   User and host public keys are signed by a Certificate Authority (CA)
   private signing key to create an encryption certificate. Users and hosts
   trust the public CA key, rather than trusting individual user and host
   public encryption keys.
  </para>
  <para>
   Traditional OpenSSH public key authentication requires copying user
   public keys to every SSH server they need access to (to the appropriate
   <filename>~/.ssh/authorized_keys</filename> files), and relying on
   users to verify new SSH server host keys before accepting them (stored
   in <filename>~/.ssh/known_hosts</filename>). This is
   error-prone and complicated to manage. Another disadvantage is OpenSSH
   keys never expire. When you need to revoke a particular public key, you
   have to find and remove all of its copies on your network.
  </para>
  <para>
   Automating the whole process (for example, with Ansible) is virtually a
   necessity. Large organizations, such as Meta
   (see <link xlink:href="https://engineering.fb.com/2016/09/12/security/scalable-and-secure-access-with-ssh/"/>),
   automate the process completely, so they can revoke and replace
   certificates, and even certificate authorities, as often as they want
   without disrupting operations.
  </para>
  <para>
   A prerequisite is the ability to open SSH sessions to all hosts on your
   network, and perform tasks like editing configuration files and restarting <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem>.
  </para>
  <para>
   Setting up an OpenSSH certificate authority involves the following steps:
  </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para>
   Set up a secure trusted server to host your certificate authority,
   for signing host and user keys. Create a new key pair for signing
   keys. The private key signs user and host keys, and the public key is
   copied to all users who are allowed access to the server.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para>
   Receive and sign host public keys, then distribute the new host
   certificates to their respective hosts. Host certificates go in
   <filename>/etc/ssh</filename>, just like host keys.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para>
   Receive and sign user public keys, then distribute the new user
   certificates to their owners. User certificates go in
   <filename>~/.ssh</filename>, just like user keys.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     Edit configuration files on servers and users' machines, and stop and
     start <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem> on hosts as
     necessary.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para>
   Revoke certificates as needed, for example when you suspect a certificate
   has been compromised, a user has left your organization, or a server has
   been retired. Revoking a certificate is considerably simpler than finding
   and removing all relevant public key copies.
  </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    Users and server admins create and protect their own OpenSSH keys. It is
    safe to freely share public keys. It is safe to transfer the new
    certificates by insecure methods, such as email, because they require
    their private keys to validate.
   </para>
   <para>
   Note that SSH certificates follow the OpenPGP standard, rather than
   SSL/TLS, and that the certificate format is OpenPGP, not X.509.
  </para>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-ssh-certificate-create-signing-keys">
  <title>Setting up a new certificate authority</title>
  <para>
   This section describes how to set up a new certificate
   authority (CA). Give careful consideration to organizing
   your CA, to keep it manageable and efficient.
  </para>
  <important>
   <title>Protect your certificate authority</title>
   <para>
    It is extremely important to protect the machine that hosts
    your certificate authority. Your CA is literally the key to
    your entire network. Anyone who gains access to your CA can
    create their own certificates and freely access your network
    resources, or even compromise your servers and the CA itself.
    A common practice is to use a dedicated machine that is started only
    when you need to sign keys.
   </para>
  </important>
   <para>
    It is a best practice to create one signing key for servers,
    and another signing key for clients. If you have a large number of
    certificates to manage, it can be helpful to create your
    CAs for hosts and clients on separate machines. If you prefer
    using a single machine, give each CA its own directory.
    The examples in this section use <filename>/ca-ssh-hosts</filename>
    and <filename>/ca-ssh-users</filename>. The example machine is
    <replaceable>ca.example.com</replaceable>.
   </para>
   <para>
    If your security policy requires
    keeping copies of users' and host's public keys, store them in their own
    subdirectories, for easier tracking and avoiding key name collisions.
   </para>
   <important>
    <title>RSA signing keys deprecated</title>
    <para>
     OpenSSH 8.2, released February 2020, deprecates RSA signing keys.
     Use Ed25519 or ECDSA.
    </para>
   </important>
   <para>
    The following examples create two signing keys, one for signing
    host keys, and one for user keys. Give them strong passphrases:
  </para>
  <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>ssh-keygen -t ed25519 -f <replaceable>/ca-ssh-hosts/ca-host-sign-key -C "signing key for host certificates"</replaceable></command>
Generating public/private ed25519 key pair.
Enter passphrase (empty for no passphrase):
Enter same passphrase again:
Your identification has been saved in ca-host-sign-key
Your public key has been saved in ca-host-sign-key.pub
The key fingerprint is:
SHA256:STuQ7HgDrPcEa7ybNIW0n6kPbj28X5HN8GgwllBbAt0
 signing key for host certificates
The key's randomart image is:
+--[ED25519 256]--+
|      o+o..      |
|   . . o.=E      |
|    = + B .      |
|   + O + = B     |
|  . O * S = +    |
|   o B + o .     |
|    =o=   .      |
|   o.*+  .       |
|   .=.o+.        |
+----[SHA256]-----+
</screen>

  <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>ssh-keygen -t ed25519 -f <replaceable>/ca-ssh-users/ca-user-sign-key -C "signing key for user certificates"</replaceable></command>
Generating public/private ed25519 key pair.
Enter passphrase (empty for no passphrase):
Enter same passphrase again:
Your identification has been saved in ca-user-sign-key
Your public key has been saved in ca-user-sign-key.pub
The key fingerprint is:
SHA256:taYj8tTnjkzgfHRvQ6HTj8a37PY6rwv96V1x+GHRjIk signing key for user certificates
The key's randomart image is:
+--[ED25519 256]--+
|                 |
|             . +.|
|          . E o.o|
|         . + . ..|
|      . S * o .+.|
|     o + + = +..+|
|    . = * . O + o|
|     + = = o =oo+|
|      . o.o  oOX=|
+----[SHA256]-----+
 </screen>
 <para>
  Copy your public user signing key (be sure you are copying the PUBLIC
  key) to <filename>/etc/ssh</filename> on all hosts running SSH servers.
  Then enter the full path of the public user signing key to
  <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</filename> on the hosts:
 </para>
 <screen>TrustedUserCAKeys <replaceable>/etc/ssh/ca-user-sign-key.pub</replaceable>
</screen>
 <para>
  Then restart <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem>.
 </para>
</sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-ssh-certificate-create-host-certs">
  <title>Creating host certificates</title>
  <para>
   The following example signs a host public key to create a host
   certificate for a database server:
  </para>
  <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>ssh-keygen -s <replaceable>/ca-ssh-hosts/ca-host-sign-key</replaceable></command> \
   <command>-n <replaceable>&wsII;,&wsIIname;</replaceable> -I <replaceable>"db-server host cert"</replaceable></command> \
   <command>-h -V +4w <replaceable>/etc/ssh/ssh_host_ed25519_key.pub</replaceable></command>
Enter passphrase:
Signed host key /etc/ssh/ssh_host_ed25519_key-cert.pub: id
"db-server host cert" serial 0 for venus,venus.example.com
valid from 2022-08-08T14:20:00 to 2022-09-05T15:21:19
    </screen>
      <para>
       If there is more than one host key on a server, sign all of them.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <option>-s</option> is your private signing key.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <option>-n</option> is your list of principals. For host
       certificates, the principals are the machine's host name
       and fully-qualified domain name.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <option>-I</option> is the identity string. This is any
       comment or description you want. The string is logged, to help you
       quickly find relevant log entries.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <option>-h</option> creates a host certificate.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <option>-V</option> sets the expiration date for the certificate. In
      the example, the certificate expires in four weeks. (See
      the "-V validity_interval" section of
      <command>man 1 ssh-keygen</command> for allowed time formats.)
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    Verify that your new certificate is built the way you want:
   </para>
   <screen>&prompt.user;<command>ssh-keygen -Lf /etc/ssh/ssh_host_ed25519_key-cert.pub</command>
 /etc/ssh/ssh_host_ed25519_key-cert.pub:
        Type: ssh-ed25519-cert-v01@openssh.com host certificate
        Public key: ED25519-CERT SHA256:/
         U7C+qABXYyuvueUuhFKzzVINq3d7IULRLwBstvVC+Q
        Signing CA: ED25519 SHA256:
         STuQ7HgDrPcEa7ybNIW0n6kPbj28X5HN8GgwllBbAt0 (using ssh-ed25519)
        Key ID: "db-server host cert"
        Serial: 0
        Valid: from 2022-08-08T14:20:00 to 2022-09-05T15:21:19
        Principals:
                venus
                venus.example.com
        Critical Options: (none)
        Extensions: (none)
    </screen>
   <para>
    Add the full path of the new host certificate to
    <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</filename>, to make it
    available to clients:
   </para>
   <screen>HostCertificate <replaceable>/etc/ssh/ssh_host_ed25519_key-cert.pub</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    Restart <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem> to load your
    changes:
   </para>
   <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>systemctl restart sshd.service</command></screen>
   <para>
    See
    <xref linkend="sec-ssh-certificate-user-config"/> to learn how to
    configure clients to accept host certificates.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-ssh-certificate-user-config">
   <title>CA configuration for users</title>
   <para>
    The following example shows how to configure clients to trust your CA
    rather than individual keys. The example grants access to a single
    server. This entry must be on a single unbroken  line in your users'
    <filename>~/.ssh/known_hosts</filename> files. Move the original
    <filename>~/.ssh/known_hosts</filename> file, and create a new
    file that contains only the CA configuration. Or, create a global
    configuration in <filename>/etc/ssh/ssh_known_hosts</filename>, which
    has the advantage of being un-editable by unprivileged users:
   </para>
   <screen>@cert-authority db,db.example.com ssh-ed25519
 AAAAC3NzaC1lZDI1NTE5AAAAIH1pF6DN4BdsfUKWuyiGt/leCvuZ/fPu
 YxY7+4V68Fz0 signing key for user certificates
   </screen>
    <para>
     List each server the user is allowed to access in a comma-delimited
     list, for example
     <literal><replaceable>&wsII;,&wsIIname;,&wsIII;,&wsIIIname;</replaceable></literal>. You may also
     grant access to all servers in domains with wildcards, for example
     <literal>*.example.com,*.example2.com</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Try connecting to the server. You should be prompted for the password
     of the remote account, without being prompted to verify the host
     certificate.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-ssh-certificate-user-certs">
   <title>Creating user certificates</title>
   <para>
    Sign the user's public key:
   </para>
   <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>ssh-keygen <replaceable>/ca-ssh-hosts/ca-user-sign-key -I "suzanne's cert" -n &exampleuserIII_plain; -V +52w user-key.pub</replaceable></command>
 Signed user key .ssh/ed25519key-cert.pub: id "suzanne's cert" serial 0
 for suzanne valid from 2022-09-14T12:57:00 to 2023-09-13T12:58:21
</screen>
   <para>
    The principal on user certificates is always the username. Store the
    user's certificate in <filename>~/.ssh</filename> on the user's machine.
   </para>
   <para>
    User certificates replace the <filename>~/.ssh/authorized_keys</filename> files. Remove this file from a user account on the remote
    machine, then try opening an SSH session to that account. You should be
    able to log  in without being prompted for a password. (Remember, the
    server should have a
    <literal>TrustedUserCAKeys /etc/ssh/<replaceable>ca-user-sign-key.pub</replaceable></literal>
    line in its
    <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</filename> file, so that the server
    knows to trust your certificate authority.)
   </para>
   <para>
    Additionally, look for <literal>Accepted publickey for
     <replaceable>&exampleuserIII_plain;</replaceable></literal> messages in
    your log files.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-ssh-certificate-revoke-host-keys">
   <title>Revoking host keys</title>
   <para>
    When you need to revoke a certificate because a server has been
    compromised or retired, add the certificate's corresponding
    public key to a file on every client, for example
    <filename>/etc/ssh/revoked-host-key</filename>:
   </para>
   <screen>ssh-ed25519-cert-v01@openssh.com
    AAAAIHNzaC1lZDI1NTE5LWNlcnQtdjAxQG9wZW5zc2guY29tAAAAIK6hyvFAhFI+0hkKehF/
    506fD1VdcW29ykfFJn1CPK9lAAAAIAawaXbbEFiQOAe5LGclrCHSLWbEeUauK5+CAuhTJyz0
    AAAAAAAAAAAAAAACAAAAE2RiLXNlcnZlciBob3N0IGNlcnQAAAAeAAAABXZlbnVzAAAAEXZl
    bnVzLmV4YW1wbGUuY29tAAAAAGMabhQAAAAAYz9YgQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAADMAAAALc3No
    LWVkMjU1MTkAAAAgfWkXoM3gF2x9Qpa7KIa3+V4K+5n98+5jFjv7hXrwXPQAAABTAAAAC3Nz
    aC1lZDI1NTE5AAAAQI+mbJsQjt/9bLiURse8DF3yTa6Yk3HpoE2uf9FW/
    KeLsw2wPeDv0d6jv49Wgr5T3xHYPf+VPJQW35ntFiHTlQg= root@db
   </screen>
   <para>
    This file must be named in <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</filename>:
   </para>
   <screen>RevokedKeys /etc/ssh/revoked_keys</screen>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-gnome-keyring">
  <title>Automated public key logins with gnome-keyring</title>
  <para>
   The <package>gnome-keyring</package> package is installed and enabled
   by default when the GNOME desktop environment is installed.
   <literal>gnome-keyring</literal> is integrated with your
   system login, automatically unlocking your secrets storage at login.
   When you change your login password, <literal>gnome-keyring</literal>
   automatically updates itself with your new password.
  </para>
  <para>
   <literal>gnome-keyring</literal> automatically loads all key pairs in
   <filename>~/.ssh</filename>, for each pair that has a
   <filename>*.pub</filename> file. You may manually load other keys with
   the <command>ssh-add</command> command, for example:
  </para>
  <screen>&prompt.user;<command>ssh-add <replaceable>~/.otherkeys/my_key</replaceable></command>
   </screen>
  <para>
   List all loaded keys:
  </para>
  <screen>&prompt.user;<command>ssh-add -L</command></screen>
  <para>
   When you start up your system and then open an SSH session, you will be
   prompted for your private key passphrase.
  </para>
   <para>
    <literal>gnome-keyring</literal> will remember the passphrase for the rest of your
    session. You will not have to re-enter the passphrase until after a system
    restart.
   </para>
 </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-authentic-agent">
   <title>Automated public key logins with ssh-agent</title>
   <para>
    The <package>openssh</package> package
    provides the <command>ssh-agent</command> utility, which retains your
    private keys and passphrases, and automatically applies your passphrases
    for you during the current session.
   </para>
   <para>
    Configure <command>ssh-agent</command> to start automatically and load
    your keys by entering the following lines in your
    <filename>~./profile</filename> file:
   </para>
   <screen>eval "$(ssh-agent)"
ssh-add</screen>
   <para>
    The first line starts <command>ssh-agent</command>, and the second line
    loads all the keys in your <filename>~/.ssh</filename> folder.
    When you open an SSH session that requires public key authentication,
    you will be prompted for the passphrase. After the passphrase has been
    provided once, you will not have to enter it again, until after you
    restart your system.
   </para>
   <para>
    You may configure <filename>~./profile</filename> to load only
    specific keys, like the following example that loads
    <filename>id_rsa</filename> and <filename>id_ed25519</filename>:
   </para>
   <screen>&prompt.user;ssh-add <replaceable>id_rsa id_ed25519</replaceable></screen>

   <sect2 xml:id="sec-ssh-authentic-agent-x">
    <title>Using <command>ssh-agent</command> in an X session</title>
    <para>
     On &productname;, <command>ssh-agent</command> is automatically
     started by the &gnome; display manager. To also invoke
     <command>ssh-add</command> to add your keys to the agent at the
     beginning of an X session, do the following:
    </para>
    <procedure>
     <step>
      <para>
       Log in as the desired user and check whether the file
       <filename>~/.xinitrc</filename> exists.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If it does not exist, use an existing template or copy it from
       <filename>/etc/skel</filename>:
      </para>
<screen>if [ -f ~/.xinitrc.template ]; then mv ~/.xinitrc.template ~/.xinitrc; \
else cp /etc/skel/.xinitrc.template ~/.xinitrc; fi</screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If you have copied the template, search for the following lines and
       uncomment them. If <filename>~/.xinitrc</filename> already existed,
       add the following lines (without comment signs).
      </para>
<screen># if test -S "$SSH_AUTH_SOCK" -a -x "$SSH_ASKPASS"; then
#       ssh-add &lt; /dev/null
# fi</screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       When starting a new X session, you will be prompted for your SSH
       passphrase.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-change-passphrase">
  <title>Changing an SSH private key passphrase</title>
  <para>
   You may change or remove the passphrase from a private key with
   <command>ssh-keygen</command>:
  </para>
  <screen>&prompt.user;<command>ssh-keygen -pf ~/.ssh/<replaceable>server1</replaceable></command>
Enter old passphrase:
Key has comment 'shared videos server1'
Enter new passphrase (empty for no passphrase):
Enter same passphrase again:
Your identification has been saved with the new passphrase.</screen>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-get-key-fingerprint">
  <title>Retrieving a key fingerprint</title>
  <para>
   Use the <command>ssh-keygen</command> to display the public key
   fingerprint. The following example prints the SHA256 hash for a
   ED25519 key:
  </para>
  <screen>&prompt.user;<command>ssh-keygen -lf <replaceable>ldap-server</replaceable></command>
256 SHA256:W45lbmj24ZoASbrqW0q9+NhF04muvfKZ+FkRa2cCiqo comment (ED25519)</screen>
  <para>
   Add the <command>-v</command> flag to display the ASCII art
   representation of the key:
  </para>
  <screen>&prompt.user;<command>ssh-keygen -lvf <replaceable>ldap-server</replaceable></command>
256 SHA256:W45lbmj24ZoASbrqW0q9+NhF04muvfKZ+FkRa2cCiqo comment (ED25519)
+--[ED25519 256]--+
|                 |
|                 |
|    .. .         |
|  .o..+ +        |
| ...o+ BSo+      |
|. ..o.o =X       |
|...o o..* =      |
|o.*.* =+ = .     |
|E*o*+O. o.o      |
+----[SHA256]-----+</screen>
</sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-programm-x">
   <title>Starting X11 applications on a remote host</title>
   <para>
    You can run graphical applications that are installed on a
    remote machine on your local computer.
    <literal>X11Forwarding Yes</literal> must be set in the
    <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</filename> file on the remote machine.
    Then, when you run <command>ssh</command> with the <option>-X</option>
    option, the <envar>DISPLAY</envar> variable is automatically set on the
    remote machine, and all X output is exported to the local machine over
    the SSH connection. At the same time, X applications started remotely
    cannot be intercepted by unauthorized users.
   </para>
   <para>
    A quick test is to run a simple game from the remote machine, such as
    GNOME Mines:
   </para>
   <screen>&prompt.user;<command>ssh &exampleuserII_plain;@&exampleserver;</command>
Password:
Last login: Tue May 10 11:29:06 2022 from 192.168.163.13
Have a lot of fun...

&exampleuserII_plain;@&exampleserver;&prompt.user; <command>gnome-mines</command></screen>
   <para>
     The remote application should appear on your local machine just as
     though it were installed locally. (Note that network lag will affect
     performance.) Close the remote application in the usual way, such as
     clicking the close button. This closes only the application, and your
     SSH session remains open.
   </para>

   <important>
    <title>X11 forwarding does not work on Wayland</title>
    <para>
     X11 forwarding requires the X Windows System, which is the default on
     &slea;, and not the Wayland display server protocol. The X Windows
     System has built-in networking, while Wayland does not. Wayland is not
     supported on &slea;.
    </para>
    <para>
     Use the following command to learn if your system runs X or Wayland:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.user;<command>echo $XDG_SESSION_TYPE</command>
x11</screen>
    <para>
     If Wayland is in use, it looks like the following example:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.user;<command>echo $XDG_SESSION_TYPE</command>
wayland</screen>
    <para>
     The systemd way is to query with <command>loginctl</command>:
    </para>
     <screen>&prompt.user;<command>loginctl show-session "$XDG_SESSION_ID" -p Type</command>
Type=x11

&prompt.user;<command>loginctl show-session "$XDG_SESSION_ID" -p Type</command>
Type=wayland</screen>
   </important>
  </sect1>

  <!-- this section needs improving and expanding -->
  <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-programm-forwarding">
   <title>Agent forwarding</title>
   <para>
    By adding the <option>-A</option> option, the ssh-agent authentication
    mechanism is carried over to the next machine. This way, you can work
    from different machines without having to enter a password, but only if
    you have distributed your public key to the destination hosts and
    properly saved it there. (Refer to
    <xref linkend="sec-ssh-public-key-auth"/> to learn how
    to copy your public keys to other hosts.)
   </para>
   <para>
    <literal>AllowAgentForwarding yes</literal> is the default in
    <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</filename>. Change it to
    <literal>No</literal> to disable it.
   </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-copy">
  <title><command>scp</command>&mdash;secure copy</title>
  <para>
   <command>scp</command> copies files to or from a remote machine.  If
   the user name on &wsI; is different than the user name on
   &exampleserver;, specify the latter using the
   <option><replaceable>USER_NAME</replaceable>&amp;host</option> format. If
   the file should be copied into a directory other than the remote
   user's home directory, specify it as
   &exampleserver;:<replaceable>DIRECTORY</replaceable>. The following
   examples show how to copy a file from a local to a remote machine and
   vice versa.
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.user;scp ~/MyLetter.tex &exampleuser_plain;@&exampleserver;:/tmp <co xml:id="co-scp-local-remote"/>
&prompt.user;scp &exampleuser_plain;@&exampleserver;:/tmp/MyLetter.tex ~ <co xml:id="co-scp-remote-local"/></screen>
<calloutlist>
 <callout arearefs="co-scp-local-remote">
  <para>local to remote</para>
</callout>
 <callout arearefs="co-scp-remote-local">
  <para>remote to local</para>
 </callout>
</calloutlist>
  <tip>
   <title>The <option>-l</option> option</title>
   <para>
    With the <command>ssh</command> command, the option
    <option>-l</option> can be used to specify a remote user (as an
    alternative to the
    <option><replaceable>USER_NAME</replaceable>&amp;host</option>
    format). With <command>scp</command> the option <option>-l</option>
    is used to limit the bandwidth consumed by <command>scp</command>.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
   After the correct password is entered, <command>scp</command> starts the
   data transfer. It displays a progress bar and the time remaining for each
   file that is copied. Suppress all output with the <option>-q</option>
   option.
  </para>

  <para>
   <command>scp</command> also provides a recursive copying feature for
   entire directories. The command
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.user;scp -r src/ sun:backup/</screen>

  <para>
   copies the entire contents of the directory <filename>src</filename>
   including all subdirectories to the <filename>~/backup</filename>
   directory on the host &exampleserver;. If this subdirectory does not
   exist, it is created automatically.
  </para>

  <para>
   The <option>-p</option> option tells <command>scp</command> to leave the
   time stamp of files unchanged. <option>-C</option> compresses the data
   transfer. This minimizes the data volume to transfer, but creates a
   heavier burden on the processors of both machines.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-sftp">
  <title><command>sftp</command>&mdash;secure file transfer</title>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-ssh-sftp-using">
   <title>Using <command>sftp</command></title>
  <para>
   If you want to copy several files from or to different locations,
   <command>sftp</command> is a convenient alternative to
   <command>scp</command>. It opens a shell with a set of commands similar
   to a regular FTP shell. Type <command>help</command> at the sftp-prompt
   to get a list of available commands. More details are available from the
   <command>sftp</command> man page.
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.user;sftp &exampleserver;
Enter passphrase for key '/home/&exampleuser_plain;/.ssh/id_rsa':
Connected to &exampleserver;.
sftp&gt; help
Available commands:
bye                                Quit sftp
cd path                            Change remote directory to 'path'
[...]</screen>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-ssh-sftp-perms">
   <title>Setting permissions for file uploads</title>
   <para>
    As with a regular FTP server, a user can download and upload files to a
    remote machine running an SFTP server
    by using the <command>put</command> command. By default the
    files will be uploaded to the remote host with the same
    permissions as on the local host. There are two options to
    automatically alter these permissions:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Setting a umask</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A umask works as a filter against the permissions of the original
       file on the local host. It can only withdraw permissions:
      </para>
      <informaltable>
       <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="33*"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="33*"/>
        <colspec colnum="3" colname="3" colwidth="33*"/>
        <thead>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            permissions original
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            umask
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            permissions uploaded
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            0666
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            0002
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            0664
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            0600
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            0002
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            0600
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para>
            0775
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            0025
           </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>
            0750
           </para>
          </entry>
         </row>
        </tbody>
       </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>
       To apply a umask on an SFTP server, edit the file
       <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_configuration</filename>. Search for the line
       beginning with <literal>Subsystem sftp</literal> and add the
       <option>-u</option> parameter with the desired setting, for example:
      </para>
<screen>Subsystem sftp /usr/lib/ssh/sftp-server -u 0002</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Explicitly setting the permissions</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Explicitly setting the permissions sets the same permissions for all
       files uploaded via SFTP. Specify a three-digit pattern such as
       <literal>600</literal>, <literal>644</literal>, or
       <literal>755</literal> with <option>-u</option>. When both
       <option>-m</option> and <option>-u</option> are specified,
       <literal>-u</literal> is ignored.
      </para>
      <para>
       To apply explicit permissions for uploaded files on an SFTP server,
       edit the file <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_configuration</filename>.
       Search for the line beginning with <literal>Subsystem sftp</literal>
       and add the <option>-m</option> parameter with the desired setting,
       for example:
      </para>
<screen>Subsystem sftp /usr/lib/ssh/sftp-server -m 600</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>

  <tip>
   <title>Viewing the SSH daemon log file</title>
   <para>
    To watch the log entries from the <systemitem
    class="daemon">sshd</systemitem> use the following command:
   </para>
   <screen>&prompt.sudo;journalctl -u sshd</screen>
   </tip>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-port-forwarding">
  <title>Port forwarding (SSH tunneling)</title>

  <para>
   <command>ssh</command> can also be used to redirect TCP/IP connections.
   This feature, also called <literal>SSH tunneling</literal>, redirects TCP
   connections to a certain port to another machine via an encrypted
   channel.
  </para>

  <para>
   With the following command, any connection directed to &wsI; port 25
   (SMTP) is redirected to the SMTP port on &exampleserver;. This is
   especially useful for those using SMTP servers without SMTP-AUTH or
   POP-before-SMTP features. From any arbitrary location connected to a
   network, e-mail can be transferred to the <quote>home</quote> mail server
   for delivery.
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.root;ssh -L 25:&exampleserver;:25 &wsI;</screen>

  <para>
   Similarly, all POP3 requests (port&nbsp;110) on &wsI; can be
   forwarded to the POP3 port of &exampleserver; with this command:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.root;ssh -L 110:&exampleserver;:110 &wsI;</screen>

  <para>
   Both commands must be executed as &rootuser;, because the connection
   is made to privileged local ports. E-mail is sent and retrieved by
   normal users in an existing SSH connection. The SMTP and POP3 host
   must be set to <literal>localhost</literal> for this to
   work. Additional information can be found in the manual pages for
   each of the programs described above and in the OpenSSH package
   documentation under
   <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/openssh</filename>.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-security-ssh-moreinfo">
  <title>More information</title>

  <para/>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><link xlink:href="https://www.openssh.com"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The home page of OpenSSH
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><link xlink:href="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/OpenSSH"/>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The OpenSSH Wikibook
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>man sshd</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The man page of the OpenSSH daemon
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>man ssh_config</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The man page of the OpenSSH SSH client configuration files
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>man scp</command>
    </term>
    <term><command>man sftp</command>
    </term>
    <term><command>man ssh</command>
    </term>
    <term><command>man ssh-add</command>
    </term>
    <term><command>man ssh-copy-id</command>
    </term>
    <term><command>man ssh-keygen</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Man pages of several binary files to securely copy files
      (<command>scp</command>, <command>sftp</command>), to log in
      (<command>slogin</command>, <command>ssh</command>), and to manage
      keys.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/openssh-common/README.SUSE</filename>
    </term>
    <term>
     <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/openssh-common/README.FIPS</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      &suse; package specific documentation; changes in defaults with
      respect to upstream, notes on FIPS mode etc.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
