<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-xauth">
 <title>X Window System and X authentication</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
   </dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>

 <para>
  Network transparency is one of the
  central characteristics of a Unix system. X, the windowing system of
  Unix operating systems, can use this feature in an impressive
  way. With X, it is no problem to log in to a remote host and start a
  graphical program that is then sent over the network to be displayed on
  your computer.
 </para>
 <para>
  When an X client needs to be displayed remotely using an X server,
  the latter should protect the resource managed by it (the display)
  from unauthorized access. In more concrete terms, certain permissions
  must be given to the client program. With the X Window System, there
  are two ways to do this, called host-based access control and
  cookie-based access control. The former relies on the IP address of
  the host where the client should run. The program to control this is
  <command>xhost</command>. <command>xhost</command> enters the IP
  address of a legitimate client into a database belonging to the X
  server. However, relying on IP addresses for authentication is not
  very secure. For example, if there were a second user working on the
  host sending the client program, that user would have access to the X
  server as well&mdash;like someone spoofing the IP address. Because of
  these shortcomings, this authentication method is not described in
  more detail here, but you can learn about it with
  <command>man</command>&nbsp;<option>xhost</option>.
 </para>
 <para>
  In the case of cookie-based access control, a character string is
  generated that is only known to the X server and to the legitimate
  user, like an ID card of some kind. This cookie is stored on login in
  the file <filename>.Xauthority</filename> in the user's home directory
  and is available to any X client wanting to use the X server to display
  a window. The file <filename>.Xauthority</filename> can be examined by
  the user with the tool <command>xauth</command>. If you rename
  <filename>.Xauthority</filename>, or if you delete the file from your
  home directory by accident, you cannot open any new
  windows or X clients.
 </para>
 <para>
  SSH (secure shell) can be used to encrypt a network connection and
  forward it to an X server transparently. This is also called X
  forwarding. X forwarding is achieved by simulating an X server on the
  server side and setting a DISPLAY variable for the shell on the
  remote host. Further details about SSH can be found in <xref
  linkend="cha-ssh"/>.
 </para>
 <warning>
  <title>X forwarding can be insecure</title>
  <para>
   If you do not consider the computer where you log in to be a secure host,
   do not use X forwarding. If X forwarding is enabled, an attacker could
   authenticate via your SSH connection. The attacker could then intrude
   on your X server and, for example, read your keyboard input.
  </para>
 </warning>
</chapter>
