<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!--PM's doc requirements:
 
 * AD configuration (m)
 
 * Active Directory integration (authentication and authorization, file access)
   (m)
   Plan for documentation integration with Likewise Enterprise (i)
   Document integration with Nautilus and file share access and writes (m)
     -> user must have group of /var/lib/samba/usershares 
        -> don't know how to tell AD about this.
     -> net usershare add: cannot convert name "Everyone" to a SID.

 ===========================================================================

 * Time synchronization: -> in there (done)
 1.NTP in AD environment (d)
 2.Time sync troubleshooting (d)
 @maintainer: first topic could probably also be covered in net_xntp.xml -
 check with maintainer of that file where this would fit best

 ===========================================================================

 This is DONE.
 *  Server based automounting of home directories 
 1.Configuration and usage description (m)
 2.Firewall configuration for SMB support (m)
 3.Kerberos support description (d)

 This is related to #300967: Mount Server Home Directory Automatically with
 Authentication. 
 Everything that's being done there to ensure that the users will be able to
 access their home directories when hosted on CIFS.
 
@maintainer: not sure if the last issue needs to be covered here, most of it
    should probably go to net_samba.xml and maybe part of it to pam.xml
2010-09-02, ke: Mention this feature below (FIXME + fate#300967) and describe
    it in net_samba.xml.  Also check security_pam.xml.  DONE.

-->
<chapter id="cha.security.ad">
 <title>Active Directory Support</title>
 <para>
  Active Directory* (AD) is a directory-service based on LDAP, Kerberos, and
  other services that is used by Microsoft Windows to manage resources,
  services, and people. In an MS Windows network, AD provides information
  about these objects, restricts access to them, and enforces policies.
  &productnamereg; lets you join existing AD domains and integrate your
  Linux machine into a Windows environment.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.security.ad.integrate">
  <title>Integrating Linux and AD Environments</title>

  <para>
   With a Linux client (configured as an Active Directory client) that is
   joined to an existing Active Directory domain, benefit from various
   features not available on a pure &productname; Linux client:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Browsing Shared Files and Folders with SMB</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Nautilus (the GNOME file manager) supports browsing shared resources
      through SMB.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Sharing Files and Folders with SMB</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Nautilus supports sharing folders and files as in Windows.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Accessing and Manipulating User Data on the Windows Server</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Through Nautilus, users are able to access their Windows user data and
      can edit, create, and delete files and folders on the Windows
      server. Users can access their data without having to enter their
      password multiple times.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Offline Authentication</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Users are able to log in and access their local data on the Linux
      machine even if they are offline or the AD server is unavailable for
      other reasons.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Windows Password Change</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This port of AD support in Linux enforces corporate password policies
      stored in Active Directory. The display managers and console support
      password change messages and accept your input. You can even use the
      Linux <command>passwd</command> command to set Windows passwords.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Single-Sign-On through Kerberized Applications</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Many applications of both desktops are Kerberos-enabled
      (<emphasis>kerberized</emphasis>), which means they can transparently
      handle authentication for the user without the need for password
      reentry at Web servers, proxies, groupware applications, or other
      locations.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   A brief technical background for most of these features is given in the
   following section. <phrase os="sled">For directions for file and printer
   sharing, refer to the <xref linkend="book.gnomeuser"/>, where you can learn
   more about AD enablement.</phrase>
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.security.ad.background">
  <title>Background Information for Linux AD Support</title>

  <para>
   Many system components need to interact flawlessly in order to integrate
   a Linux client into an existing Windows Active Directory domain.
   <xref linkend="fig.ad.schema"/> highlights the most prominent ones. The
   following sections focus on the underlying processes of the key events in
   AD server and client interaction.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.ad.schema">
   <title>Active Directory Authentication Schema</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="sled10_ad_schema.svg" width="75%" format="SVG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="sled10_ad_schema.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   To communicate with the directory service, the client needs to share at
   least two protocols with the server:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>LDAP</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      LDAP is a protocol optimized for managing directory information. A
      Windows domain controller with AD can use the LDAP protocol to
      exchange directory information with the clients. To learn more about
      LDAP in general and about the open source port of it, OpenLDAP, refer
      to <xref linkend="cha.security.ldap"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Kerberos</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Kerberos is a third-party trusted authentication service. All its
      clients trust Kerberos's authorization of another client's identity,
      enabling kerberized single-sign-on (SSO) solutions. Windows supports a
      Kerberos implementation, making Kerberos SSO possible even with Linux
      clients. <phrase os="sled;sles">To learn more about Kerberos in Linux,
      refer to <xref
        linkend="cha.security.kerberos"/>.</phrase>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   The following client components process account and authentication data:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Winbind</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The most central part of this solution is the winbind daemon that is a
      part of the Samba project and handles all communication with the AD
      server.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>NSS (<emphasis>Name Service Switch</emphasis>)</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      NSS routines provide name service information. Naming service for both
      users and groups is provided by <filename>nss_winbind</filename>. This
      module directly interacts with the winbind daemon.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>PAM (<emphasis>Pluggable Authentication Modules</emphasis>)</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      User authentication for AD users is done by the
      <filename>pam_winbind</filename> module. The creation of user homes
      for the AD users on the Linux client is handled by
      <filename>pam_mkhomedir</filename>. The
      <filename>pam_winbind</filename> module directly interacts with
      winbindd. To learn more about PAM in general, refer to
      <xref linkend="cha.pam"
      />.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   Applications that are PAM-aware, like the login routines and the GNOME
   display manager, interact with the PAM and NSS layer to authenticate
   against the Windows server. Applications supporting Kerberos authentication
   (such as file managers, Web browsers, or e-mail clients) use the Kerberos
   credential cache to access user's Kerberos tickets, making them part of the
   SSO framework.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.security.ad.background.domain_join">
   <title>Domain Join</title>
   <para>
    During domain join, the server and the client establish a secure
    relation. On the client, the following tasks need to be performed to
    join the existing LDAP and Kerberos SSO environment provided by the
    Window domain controller. The entire join process is handled by the
    &yast; Domain Membership module, which can be run during installation or
    in the installed system:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      The Windows domain controller providing both LDAP and KDC (Key
      Distribution Center) services is located.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      A machine account for the joining client is created in the directory
      service.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      An initial ticket granting ticket (TGT) is obtained for the client and
      stored in its local Kerberos credential cache. The client needs this
      TGT to get further tickets allowing it to contact other services, like
      contacting the directory server for LDAP queries.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      NSS and PAM configurations are adjusted to enable the client to
      authenticate against the domain controller.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    During client boot, the winbind daemon is started and retrieves the
    initial Kerberos ticket for the machine account. winbindd automatically
    refreshes the machine's ticket to keep it valid. To keep track of the
    current account policies, winbindd periodically queries the domain
    controller.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.security.ad.background.logon">
   <title>Domain Login and User Homes</title>
   <para>
    The login manager of GNOME (GDM) has been extended to allow the handling
    of AD domain login. Users can choose to log into the primary domain the
    machine has joined or to one of the trusted domains with which the domain
    controller of the primary domain has established a trust relationship.
   </para>
   <para>
    User authentication is mediated by a number of PAM modules as described
    in <xref
     linkend="sec.security.ad.background"/>. The
    <filename>pam_winbind</filename> module used to authenticate clients
    against Active Directory or NT4 domains is fully aware of Windows error
    conditions that might prohibit a user's login. The Windows error codes
    are translated into appropriate user-readable error messages that PAM
    gives at login through any of the supported methods (GDM, console,
    and SSH):
   </para>
   <remark>rwalter: the terms in this list are capitalized inconsistently. Are they the direct error
    messages or can I make them consistent?</remark>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>Password has expired</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The user sees a message stating that the password has expired and
       needs to be changed. The system prompts for a new password and
       informs the user if the new password does not comply with corporate
       password policies (for example the password is too short, too simple,
       or already in the history). If a user's password change fails, the
       reason is shown and a new password prompt is given.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>Account disabled</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The user sees an error message stating that the account has been
       disabled and to contact the system administrator.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>Account locked out</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The user sees an error message stating that the account has been
       locked and to contact the system administrator.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>Password has to be changed</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The user can log in but receives a warning that the password needs to
       be changed soon. This warning is sent three days before that password
       expires. After expiration, the user cannot log in.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>Invalid workstation</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       When a user is restricted to specific workstations and the current
       &productname; machine is not among them, a message appears that this
       user cannot log in from this workstation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>Invalid logon hours</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       When a user is only allowed to log in during working hours and tries
       to log in outside working hours, a message informs the user that
       logging in is not possible at that time.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>Account expired</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       An administrator can set an expiration time for a specific user
       account. If that user tries to log in after expiration, the user gets
       a message that the account has expired and cannot be used to log in.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    During a successful authentication, <filename>pam_winbind</filename>
    acquires a ticket granting ticket (TGT) from the Kerberos server of
    Active Directory and stores it in the user's credential cache. It also
    renews the TGT in the background, requiring no user interaction.
   </para>
   <para>
    &productname; supports local home directories for AD users. If
    configured through &yast; as described in
    <xref linkend="sec.security.ad.config"/>, user homes are created at the
    first login of a Windows (AD) user into the Linux client. These home
    directories look and feel entirely the same as standard Linux user home
    directories and work independently of the AD domain controller. Using a
    local user home, it is possible to access a user's data on this machine
    (even when the AD server is disconnected) as long as the Linux client
    has been configured to perform offline authentication.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.security.ad.background.offline">
   <title>Offline Service and Policy Support</title>
   <para>
    Users in a corporate environment must have the ability to become roaming
    users (for example, to switch networks or even work disconnected for
    some time). To enable users to log in to a disconnected machine,
    extensive caching was integrated into the winbind daemon. The winbind
    daemon enforces password policies even in the offline state. It tracks
    the number of failed login attempts and reacts according to the policies
    configured in Active Directory. Offline support is disabled by default
    and must be explicitly enabled in the &yast; Domain Membership module.
   </para>
   <para>
    When the domain controller has become unavailable, the user can still
    access network resources (other than the AD server itself) with valid
    Kerberos tickets that have been acquired before losing the connection
    (as in Windows). Password changes cannot be processed unless the domain
    controller is online. While disconnected from the AD server, a user
    cannot access any data stored on this server. When a workstation has
    become disconnected from the network entirely and connects to the
    corporate network again later, &productname; acquires a new Kerberos
    ticket as soon as the user has locked and unlocked the desktop (for
    example, using a desktop screen saver).
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
<?dbfo-need height="15em"?>
 <sect1 id="sec.security.ad.config">
  <title>Configuring a Linux Client for Active Directory</title>

  <para>
   Before your client can join an AD domain, some adjustments must be made
   to your network setup to ensure the flawless interaction of client and
   server.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>DNS</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Configure your client machine to use a DNS server that can forward DNS
      requests to the AD DNS server. Alternatively, configure your machine
      to use the AD DNS server as the name service data source.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>NTP</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To succeed with Kerberos authentication, the client must have its time
      set accurately. It is highly recommended to use a central NTP time
      server for this purpose (this can be also the NTP server running on
      your Active Directory domain controller). If the clock skew between
      your Linux host and the domain controller exceeds a certain limit,
      Kerberos authentication fails and the client is logged in using the
      weaker NTLM (NT LAN Manager) authentication. For more details about
      using active directory for time synchronization, see
      <xref linkend="proc.ad.join"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Firewall</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To browse your network neighborhood, either disable the firewall
      entirely or mark the interface used for browsing as part of the
      internal zone.
     </para>
     <para>
      To change the firewall settings on your client, log in as &rootuser;
      and start the &yast; firewall module. Select
      <guimenu>Interfaces</guimenu>. Select your network interface from the
      list of interfaces and click <guimenu>Change</guimenu>. Select
      <guimenu>Internal Zone</guimenu> and apply your settings with
      <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. Leave the firewall settings with <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Next</guimenu> <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> </menuchoice>. To
      disable the firewall, just check the <guimenu>Disable Firewall
      Automatic Starting</guimenu> option, and leave the firewall module
      with <menuchoice> <guimenu>Next</guimenu> <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>AD Account</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      You cannot log in to an AD domain unless the AD administrator has
      provided you with a valid user account for that domain. Use the AD
      username and password to log in to the AD domain from your Linux
      client.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   To join an AD domain, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure id="proc.ad.join">
   <title>Joining an AD Domain</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log in as &rootuser; and start &yast;.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start <menuchoice> <guimenu>Network Services</guimenu> <guimenu>Windows
     Domain Membership</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the domain to join at <guimenu>Domain or Workgroup</guimenu> in
     the <guimenu>Windows Domain Membership</guimenu> screen (see
     <xref linkend="fig.ad.smbclient"/>). If the DNS settings on your host
     are properly integrated with the Windows DNS server, enter the AD
     domain name in its DNS format
     (<literal>mydomain.mycompany.com</literal>). If you enter the short
     name of your domain (also known as the pre&ndash;Windows 2000 domain
     name), &yast; must rely on NetBIOS name resolution instead of DNS to
     find the correct domain controller.
<!-- 2010-02-05, toba: cannot find the Browse button in SLES 11 SP1,
     commenting out...

     To select from a list of available
     domains instead, use <guimenu>Browse</guimenu> to list the NetBIOS
     domains then select the desired domain.

     -->
    </para>
    <figure id="fig.ad.smbclient">
     <title>Determining Windows Domain Membership</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="ad_sambaclient.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="ad_sambaclient.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Check <guimenu>Also Use SMB Information for Linux
     Authentication</guimenu> to use the SMB source for Linux
     authentication.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Check <guimenu>Create Home Directory on Login</guimenu> to
     automatically create a local home directory for your AD user on the
     Linux machine.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Check <guimenu>Offline Authentication</guimenu> to allow your domain
     users to log in even if the AD server is temporarily unavailable, or if
     you do not have a network connection.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Expert Settings</guimenu>, if you want to change the
     UID and GID ranges for the Samba users and groups. Let DHCP retrieve
     the WINS server only if you need it. This is the case when some of your
     machines are resolved only by the WINS system.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Configure NTP time synchronization for your AD environment by selecting
     <guimenu>NTP Configuration</guimenu> and entering an appropriate server
     name or IP address. This step is obsolete if you have already entered
     the appropriate settings in the stand-alone &yast; NTP configuration
     module.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> and confirm the domain join when prompted
     for it.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Provide the password for the Windows administrator on the AD server and
     click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> (see <xref linkend="fig.ad.join1"/>).
    </para>
    <figure id="fig.ad.join1">
     <title>Providing Administrator Credentials</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="ad_join1.png" width="30%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="ad_join1.png" width="30%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   After you have joined the AD domain, you can log in to it from your
   workstation using the display manager of your desktop or the console.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Domain Name</title>
   <para>
    Joining a domain may not succeed if the domain name ends with
    <literal>.local</literal>. Names ending in <literal>.local</literal> cause
    conflicts with Multicast DNS (MDNS) where <literal>.local</literal> is
    reserved for link-local hostnames.
   </para>
  </important>

  <note>
   <para>
    Currently only a domain administrator account, such as
    <literal>Administrator</literal>, can join &productname; into Active
    Directory.
   </para>
  </note>

 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.security.ad.login">
  <title>Logging In to an AD Domain</title>

  <para>
   Provided your machine has been configured to authenticate against Active
   Directory and you have a valid Windows user identity, you can log in to
   your machine using the AD credentials. Login is supported for GNOME, the
   console, SSH, and any other PAM-aware application.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Offline Authentication</title>
   <para>
    &productname; supports offline authentication, allowing you to log in to
    your client machine even when it is offline. See <xref
    linkend="sec.security.ad.background.offline"/> for details.
   </para>
  </important>

<?dbfo-need height="15em"?>

  <sect2 id="sec.security.ad.login.gui">
   <title>GDM</title>
   <para>
    To authenticate a GNOME client machine against an AD server, proceed as
    follows:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Enter the domain name and the Windows username in the form of
      <replaceable>Domain_Name</replaceable>\<replaceable>Windows_Username</replaceable>
      in the <guimenu>Username</guimenu> fieldand press
      <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Enter your Windows password and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>

   <para>
    If configured to do so, &productname; creates a user home directory on
    the local machine on the first login of each AD authenticated user. This
    allows you to benefit from the AD support of &productname; while still
    having a fully functional Linux machine at your disposal.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.security.ad.login.console">
   <title>Console Login</title>
   <para>
    As well as logging into the AD client machine using a graphical
    front-end, you can log in using the text-based console login or even
    remotely using SSH.
   </para>
   <para>
    To log in to your AD client from a console, enter
    <literal><replaceable>DOMAIN</replaceable>\<replaceable>user</replaceable></literal>
    at the <literal>login:</literal> prompt and provide the password.
   </para>
   <para>
    To remotely log in to your AD client machine using SSH, proceed as
    follows:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      At the login prompt, enter:
     </para>
<screen>ssh <replaceable>DOMAIN</replaceable>\\<replaceable>user</replaceable>@<replaceable>hostname</replaceable></screen>
     <para>
      The <literal>\</literal> domain and login delimiter is escaped with
      another <literal>\</literal> sign.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Provide the user's password.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.security.ad.passwd">
  <title>Changing Passwords</title>

  <para>
   &productname; has the ability to help a user choose a suitable new
   password that meets the corporate security policy. The underlying PAM
   module retrieves the current password policy settings from the domain
   controller, informing the user about the specific password quality
   requirements a user account typically has by means of a message on login.
   Like its Windows counterpart, &productname; presents a message
   describing:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Password history settings
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Minimum password length requirements
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Minimum password age
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Password complexity
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   The password change process cannot succeed unless all requirements have
   been successfully met. Feedback about the password status is given both
   through the display managers and the console.
  </para>

  <para>
   GDM provides feedback about password expiration and the prompt for
   new passwords in an interactive mode. To change passwords in the display
   managers, just provide the password information when prompted.
  </para>

  <para>
   To change your Windows password, you can use the standard Linux utility,
   <command>passwd</command>, instead of having to manipulate this data on
   the server. To change your Windows password, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log in at the console.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter <literal>passwd</literal>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter your current password when prompted.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the new password.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Reenter the new password for confirmation. If your new password does
     not comply with the policies on the Windows server, this feedback is
     given to you and you are prompted for another password.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   To change your Windows password from the GNOME desktop, proceed as
   follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the <guimenu>Computer</guimenu> icon on the left edge of the
     panel.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Control Center</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     From the <guimenu>Personal</guimenu> section, select
     <menuchoice><guimenu>About Me</guimenu> <guimenu>Change
     Password</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter your old password.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter and confirm the new password.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Leave the dialog with <guimenu>Close</guimenu> to apply your settings.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
