<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
  <!ENTITY productnamex "<phrase xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' os='sles;sled;osuse'>&productname;</phrase><phrase xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' os='article'>&sls;</phrase>">
  <!ENTITY productnumberx "<phrase xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' os='sles;sled;osuse'>&productnumber;</phrase><phrase xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' os='article'>15</phrase>">
]>

<!--
  IMPORTANT: When editing this file, make sure to keep the article version
  (art_pcidss.xml) up-to-date.
-->

<appendix xml:id="app-pcidss"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Achieving &pcidssa; compliance</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    To protect customers and the business itself, companies that handle
    credit card payments must keep data as safe and secure as possible.
    Following the &pcidss; helps to secure all areas that are connected to
    payment processes and to implement security-relevant actions to keep the
    data and the computing environment safe.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>

 <!-- Possibly useful resources:
 Positive Research Center (describing PCI-DSS 1.0!)
 + (Part 1) http://blog.ptsecurity.com/2010/07/red-card-specificity-of-pci-dss-in.html
 + (Part 2) http://blog.ptsecurity.com/2010/07/red-card-specificity-of-pci-dss-in_19.html
 + (Part 3) http://blog.ptsecurity.com/2010/08/pci-dss-and-red-hat-enterprise-linux.html
 + (Part 4) http://blog.ptsecurity.com/2010/09/pci-dss-and-red-hat-enterprise-linux.html
 + (Part 5) http://blog.ptsecurity.com/2010/09/pci-dss-and-red-hat-enterprise-linux_03.html
 + (Part 6) http://blog.ptsecurity.com/2010/10/pci-dss-and-red-hat-enterprise-linux.html
 + (Part 7) http://blog.ptsecurity.com/2010/10/pci-dss-and-red-hat-enterprise-linux_20.html
 + (Part 8) http://blog.ptsecurity.com/2010/11/requirement-10-track-and-monitor-all.html
 + (Part 9) http://blog.ptsecurity.com/2010/11/pci-dss-and-red-hat-enterprise-linux.html
 -->

 <para>
  This document aims to provide a basic understanding of how
  &productnamex; can be configured to comply with the &pcidss;.
 </para>
 <para>
  It is important to understand that protecting systems includes
  more than configuration. The entire environment and people involved must
  be taken into account.
 </para>
 <para>
  An essential part of implementing &pcidssa; is the combination of actions:
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Create a secure configuration.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Track and review all changes made to the configuration: who changed what
    at which point in time.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-pcidss-what">
  <title>What is the &pcidssa;?</title>
  <para>
   The &pcidss; (&pcidssa;) is a set of
   requirements to guide a merchant to protect cardholder data. The
   standard covers six main categories with currently 12 requirement topics
   on how to implement, protect, maintain and monitor systems that are involved
   in credit cardholder data processing.
  </para>
  <para>
   &pcidssa; was created and is maintained by the PCI Security Standards
   Council (SSC), which was founded by the five major credit card brands, Visa,
   MasterCard, American Express, Discover, and JCB. In December 2004, &pcidssa;
   1.0 was released to address the growing threat of online credit card
   fraud. The current version, &pcidssa; version 3.2, has been available since
   April 2016.
  </para>

  <orderedlist>
   <title>Build and maintain a secure network and systems</title>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Install and maintain a firewall configuration to protect cardholder
     data
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Do not use vendor-supplied defaults for system passwords and other
     security parameters
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <orderedlist continuation="continues">
   <title>Protect cardholder data</title>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Protect stored cardholder data
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Encrypt transmission of cardholder data across open, public networks
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <orderedlist continuation="continues">
   <title>Maintain a vulnerability management program</title>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Protect all systems against malware and regularly update anti-virus
     software or programs
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Develop and maintain secure systems and applications
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <orderedlist continuation="continues">
   <title>Implement strong access control measures</title>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Restrict access to cardholder data by business need to know
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Identify and authenticate access to system components
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Restrict physical access to cardholder data
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <orderedlist continuation="continues">
   <title>Regularly monitor and test networks</title>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Track and monitor all access to network resources and cardholder data
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Regularly test security systems and processes
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <orderedlist continuation="continues">
   <title>Maintain an information security policy</title>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Maintain a policy that addresses information security for all personnel
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
   Most requirements of &pcidssa; are organizational guidelines that
   help ensure the security of all areas involved with cardholder data.
   There is usually no specific wording of the technical aspects.
  </para>
  <para>
   This means that it is up to auditors to decide which security settings are
   valid for a requirement and which are not. Therefore, the recommendations
   in this document can only provide a starting point for implementing the
   &pcidssa; and are necessarily subject to discussion.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-pcidss-os-relevant">
  <title>Focus of this document: areas relevant to the operating system</title>
  <para>
   The &pcidssa; covers a wide range of aspects related to cardholder data. Not all of
   these aspects concern the operating system and this document will
   not focus on these. Instead, this document focuses on aspects that affect
   OS configuration, including:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     System security
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Access control
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     System maintenance to protect against known vulnerabilities
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   Topics beyond the scope of this document include data processing
   applications, database design, and formal processes outside of the OS
   scope. In particular, requirement 9 (restrict physical access) and
   requirement 12 (maintain a policy) are not discussed extensively in this
   document.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-pcidss-requirement">
  <title>Requirements in detail</title>
  <para>
   The following section goes through relevant parts of the &pcidssa; in
   detail, following the ordering of the standard itself.
  </para>
   <sect2 xml:id="sec-pcidss-requirement-1">
    <title>Requirement 1: Install and maintain a firewall configuration to protect cardholder data</title>
    <para>
     The listed terms in this section are mostly design, documentation and
     formal process requirements. All changes to the firewalls and routers
     need to be approved, documented and verified, and all stakeholders
     need to be involved. The network design includes a DMZ environment,
     access to the Internet, a protected network for database servers,
     traffic filtering rules between network segments, etc.
    </para>
    <para>
     In addition to a dedicated firewall and router, &productnamex;
     comes with a host firewall based on iptables. The system can be easily
     configured to allow only connections on certain inbound ports. With the
     &yast; firewall module it is also possible to define more complex rules.
     For example, to disable connections not coming from certain network
     addresses. This allows integrating the local system firewall into an
     overall firewall design that maximizes network security.
    </para>
    <para>
     In generalized terms, the technical points in requirement 1 are the
     following:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Identify insecure services and protocols.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Limit traffic to and from the system so that unneeded and unwanted
       traffic is directly avoided.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry xml:id="vle-pcidss-insecure-service">
      <term>1.1.6.b Identify insecure services, protocols, and ports allowed;
      and verify that security features are documented for each service</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        This task is embedded in the requirement to identify, document, and
        justify all services and protocols running on a system. Of special
        interest are services and protocols that could lead to a security
        risk. If an insecure service or protocol is used, it must
        be evaluated to understand its potential security impact.
        Services or protocols that are not necessary for the business to
        function should be disabled or removed.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry xml:id="vle-pcidss-firewall">
      <term>
       1.2.1.b Verify that inbound and outbound traffic is limited to
       that which is necessary for the cardholder data environment
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Outbound traffic should only be allowed in specifically defined
        cases. To allow specific traffic, manually add rules for
        outbound traffic.
       </para>
       <para>
        Make the SSH daemon only reachable on the administration
        interface and not on the general network card if possible.
        Define the source addresses that a service allows traffic from.
       </para>
       <para>
        For example, to allow only outbound DNS requests over the
        interface <systemitem>eth0</systemitem> to server
        <systemitem class="ipaddress">10.0.0.1</systemitem>, use:
       </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>firewall-cmd</command> --permanent --direct --add-rule ipv4 filter OUTPUT 23 \
    -d 10.0.0.1/32 -o eth0 -p udp -m udp --dport 53 -j ACCEPT
&prompt.root;<command>firewall-cmd</command> --reload</screen>
       <para>
        To block all other outbound traffic, see <xref linkend="vle-pcidss-deny-all"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry xml:id="vle-pcidss-deny-all">
      <term>
       1.2.1.c Verify that all other inbound and outbound traffic is
       specifically denied
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Deny all outbound and inbound traffic for which no exceptions
        are defined as stated in the previous section. Forwarding is
        usually completely disabled by a kernel parameter and should
        not be enabled for endpoint servers.
       </para>
       <para>
        &firewalld; in &productname; by default blocks all inbound
        traffic.
       </para>
       <para>
        To block all outbound traffic, manually add the following rules:
       </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>firewall-cmd</command> --permanent --direct --add-rule ipv4 filter OUTPUT 0 -m conntrack --ctstate RELATED,ESTABLISHED -j ACCEPT
&prompt.root;<command>firewall-cmd</command> --permanent --direct --add-rule ipv6 filter OUTPUT 0 -m conntrack --ctstate RELATED,ESTABLISHED -j ACCEPT
&prompt.root;<command>firewall-cmd</command> --permanent --direct --add-rule ipv4 filter OUTPUT 99 -j DROP
&prompt.root;<command>firewall-cmd</command> --permanent --direct --add-rule ipv6 filter OUTPUT 99 -j DROP
&prompt.root;<command>firewall-cmd</command> --reload</screen>
       <para>
        In addition, inbound traffic can also be configured for certain
        services via the TCP wrapper configuration file
        <filename>/etc/hosts.deny</filename>.
       </para>
       <para>
        Most of the following tasks are about examining and verifying that the
        defined inbound and outbound rules are really limiting the traffic
        between and within all network segments, like the DMZ and the
        Internet, to a necessary minimum for full system operation.
        </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       1.3.3 Implement anti-spoofing measures to detect and block forged
       source IP addresses from entering the network
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        There are two ways to implement anti-spoofing measurements in
        &productnamex;:
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <formalpara>
          <title><systemitem>iptables</systemitem> rules that only allow input from certain addresses on specified interfaces</title>
          <para>
           The used address space for
           communications can be clearly defined in the system setup. Any use of
           addresses that violates these definitions can be logged and trigger an
           alarm.
          </para>
         </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <formalpara>
          <title>Linux kernel reverse path filtering</title>
          <para>
           This feature discards packet replies that do not go through the
           same interface as the initial packet. This feature
           is enabled by default in &productnamex; and can be checked with
           the following command:
          </para>
         </formalpara>
         <screen>&prompt.user;cat /proc/sys/net/ipv4/conf/all/rp_filter</screen>
         <para>
          When enabled, this returns
          <literal>1</literal>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       1.3.5 Permit only <quote>established</quote> connections into the
       network
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        &firewalld; enables connection tracking via
        <literal>iptables</literal>. Connections to an interface that has
        been marked as external are dropped by default. Only connections that
        are associated with an established connection are allowed.
       </para>
       <para>
        It is possible to define certain services that are allowed to connect
        to an external interface. However, this must be in compliance with
        the general security policy.
       </para>
       <para>
        Keep in mind that the first line of defense against malicious
        connections from the Internet should be a dedicated firewall system
        that handles all traffic and acts as a gatekeeper. Unwanted
        connections should never reach the DMZ network. However, simple
        firewall rules on &productnamex; systems can help avoid
        misconfigurations and act as another line of defense.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       1.3.7 Do not disclose private IP addresses and routing information to
       unauthorized parties
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        A &productnamex; system can also act as a router to forward
        traffic from one interface to another network on a second interface.
        It is possible to use Network Address Translation (NAT) on the
        external interface so that no internal IP address is actually exposed
        to the outside. This is done to mitigate the information an external
        attacker can gather by simply analyzing the network traffic. NAT can
        also be used on virtualization hosts or container-based environments
        that connect to the outside via a specific interface.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 xml:id="sec-pcidss-requirement-2">
    <title>Requirement 2: Do not use vendor-supplied defaults for system passwords and other security parameters</title>
    <para>
     During the installation of &productnamex;, general system
     passwords are already set by the administrator. The setup also uses a
     password checker (<command>cracklib</command>) that identifies weak
     entries against a dictionary. This means that the standard configuration
     already includes customer-defined security options for most services.
    </para>
    <para>
     For more information about OS security, see
     <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"><xref linkend="book-security"/>.</phrase>
     <phrase os="article"><citetitle>&productnamex; Security Guide</citetitle>.</phrase>
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       2.1 Always change vendor-supplied defaults and remove or disable
       unnecessary default accounts before installing a system on the network.
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The configuration of any system service must be evaluated to meet
        the needed security standards. This goes from limiting the used
        protocols to only allow currently secure versions and to disable
        legacy implementations, to the definition of access controls and
        authentication. The default settings of &productnamex; already provide
        good overall security, but they can be tweaked further.
       </para>
       <para>
        For example, the following security settings might be relevant:
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          By default, the SNMP daemon only allows incoming requests to
          <systemitem>localhost</systemitem>. However, the default community
          string is named <literal>public</literal> and should be changed
          before accepting general inbound connections.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          By default, certain insecure upstream settings of the
          <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem> daemon are listed and
          commented out inside the <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem>
          configuration file <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</filename>. For
          example, the insecure protocol version 1 and empty passwords
          (<literal>PermitEmptyPasswords no</literal>) are already disabled.
         </para>
         <para>
          To further increase SSH security, if applicable, deny direct
          <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> access by setting
          <literal>PermitRootLogin</literal> to <literal>no</literal>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
       <para>
        Default settings can be customized by automating system installation
        with an &ay; profile. This allows rolling out new instances of
        &productnamex; and automatically enabling an evaluated configuration.
        This setup procedure can also be automated with the &susemgr;. For
        more information, see the &susemgr; documentation at
        <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/suma/"/>.
       </para>
       <para>
        By default, &productnamex; does not create additional accounts
        apart from the <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>
        administrative user. There are system accounts defined in
        <filename>/etc/passwd</filename>, but they are not activated and
        therefore not directly reachable. This can be validated by checking
        the lines inside the <filename>/etc/shadow</filename> file.
       </para>
       <para>
        In that file, the second column represents the defined password:
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          An asterisk (<literal>*</literal>) means that a password was never
          defined and the account is therefore locked.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          An exclamation mark (<literal>!</literal>) stands for a locked
          account and can appear either alone or in front of a password hash.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       2.2 Develop configuration standards for all system components. Ensure
       that these standards address all known security vulnerabilities and
       are consistent with industry-accepted system hardening standards.
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        As mentioned in the &pcidssa; document, possible sources for
        industry-accepted hardening standards are:
       </para>
       <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>Center for Internet Security (CIS) </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>International Organization for Standardization (ISO)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>SysAdmin Audit Network Security (SANS) Institute</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>National Institute of Standards Technology (NIST)</para>
        </listitem>
       </orderedlist>
       <para>
        As the &pcidssa; requirements are not specified precisely, there is no
        direct relationship between hardening standards and specific
        requirements. However, other hardening resources can also help in
        complying with these specifications, including
        <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"><xref linkend="book-security"/></phrase>.
        <phrase os="article"><citetitle>&productnamex; Security Guide</citetitle>.</phrase>
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       2.2.1 Implement only one primary function per server to prevent
       functions that require different security levels from co-existing on
       the same server. (For example, web servers, database servers, and DNS
       should be implemented on separate servers.)
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        To help separate services, use the variety of virtualization and
        containerization methods included with &productnamex;:
        &kvm;, &xen;, &lxc;, and &docker;.
       </para>
       <para>
        You can also run &productnamex; on third-party virtualization servers
        like &esx; or &hyperv; to achieve service separation.
       </para>
       <para>
        When using the options built in to &productnamex;, see:
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          For information about virtualization, see
          <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"><xref linkend="book-virtualization"/></phrase>
          <phrase os="article"><citetitle>&productnamex; Virtualization
          Guide</citetitle></phrase>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          For information about containerization, see
          <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"><xref linkend="book-container"/></phrase>
          <phrase os="article"><citetitle>&productnamex; &deng;
          Guide</citetitle></phrase>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       2.2.2 Enable only necessary services, protocols, daemons, etc., as
       required for the function of the system.
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        This is directly related to an item of requirement&nbsp;1: To allow only
        services that are really needed and are using secure protocols and
        settings (<xref linkend="vle-pcidss-insecure-service"/>). All parties
        involved must be aware of the dangers of using insecure communication.
        Research, clearly document, and communicate the risk of using insecure
        protocols and services.
       </para>
       <para>
        Enable and disable system services using the following
        <command>systemctl</command> commands:
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <screen>&prompt.user;systemctl status <replaceable>SERVICE</replaceable></screen>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl enable <replaceable>SERVICE</replaceable></screen>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl disable <replaceable>SERVICE</replaceable></screen>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
       <para>
        To list all available services that are installed on the system and
        see their status, use the following command:
       </para>
       <screen>&prompt.user;systemctl list-unit-files --type=service</screen>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       2.2.3.a Inspect configuration settings to verify that security features
       are documented and implemented for all insecure services, daemons, or
       protocols.
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        To add an additional layer of security to insecure services, use VPN
        tunnels (for example, IPsec). With a VPN tunnel, network traffic of
        such services can be isolated and all data is protected against
        eavesdropping, both internally and externally. However, note that the
        communication is still insecure at the endpoints of the VPN tunnel
        and that this is only a workaround.
       </para>
       <para>
        For additional security within &productnamex;, use &selnx; or &aa;.
        However, the setup of these frameworks is beyond the scope of this
        document:
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          For information about &selnx;, see
          <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"><xref linkend="cha-selinux"/>.</phrase>
          <phrase os="article"><citetitle>&productnamex; Security Guide,
          Chapter Configuring &selnx;</citetitle>.</phrase>
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          For information about &aa;, see
          <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"><xref linkend="part-apparmor"/>.</phrase>
          <phrase os="article"><citetitle>&productnamex; Security Guide,
          Part Confining Privileges with &aa;</citetitle>.</phrase>
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       2.2.5.a Select a sample of system components and inspect the
       configurations to verify that all unnecessary functionality (for
       example, scripts, drivers, features, subsystems, file systems, etc.)
       is removed.
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The Linux kernel is the main system component. It consists of a core
        image that is extended by kernel modules which are loaded depending
        on the hardware and system design. For example: Network card drivers
        are automatically loaded depending on the system’s network card. File
        system modules can be enabled to extend the Linux kernel’s file
        system support.
       </para>
       <para>
        The list of loaded kernel modules is usually quite long and includes
        modules that are only used occasionally. The kernel module framework
        allows blacklisting modules and limiting which functionalities are
        loaded.
       </para>
       <para>
        To block modules from being loaded, configure them
        via the directory <filename>/etc/modprobe.d</filename>. For example,
        the kernel module <literal>floppy</literal> is only necessary for
        systems that have a floppy drive. On systems that do not have a
        floppy drive, prevent the module from loading: Create a configuration
        file <filename>/etc/modprobe.d/00-disable-modules.conf</filename>
        with the following content:
       </para>
       <screen>install floppy /bin/true</screen>
       <para>
        The <literal>floppy</literal> module is usually loaded
        during the execution of the initial RAM disk. Therefore, propagate
        this configuration change to the <filename>initrd</filename> file
        using <command>dracut</command> (replace <replaceable>NAME</replaceable>
      with the name of the current initrd and
      <replaceable>KERNELVERSION</replaceable> with the currently running
      kernel).
       </para>
       <screen>&prompt.sudo;/usr/bin/dracut --logfile /var/log/YaST2/mkinitrd.log --force /boot/$initrd-<replaceable>NAME</replaceable> $<replaceable>KERNELVERSION</replaceable></screen>
       <para>
        It is harder to remove or restrict application functionality, as
        functionality is in most cases compiled into the application or
        library itself. Even cases where deleting a file cleanly removes a
        functionality are problematic: If the file was installed from an RPM
        package, it will be reinstalled when the package is updated.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       2.3 Encrypt all non-console administrative access using strong
       cryptography. Use technologies such as SSH, VPN, or TLS for web-based
       management and other non-console administrative access.
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Encrypt all administrative network access: SSH with appropriate
        configuration settings that fit into the security concept should be
        the tool of choice.
       </para>
       <para>
        Administrative access can also be granted
        via a Web site. In this case, the complete connection chain between the
        browser and the server system must be encrypted. This is done via
        TLS and X.509 certificates.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 xml:id="sec-pcidss-requirement-3">
    <title>Requirement 3: Protect stored cardholder data</title>
    <para>
     This section explains how to handle cardholder and
     authentication data securely. The following definitions apply:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis>Cardholder data</emphasis> includes information such as the
       cardholder name and the Primary Account Number (PAN).
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis>Authentication data</emphasis> includes the Personal
       Identification Number (PIN) and the Card Validation Code (CVC2).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     The main difference between cardholder data and authentication data is
     that storing authentication is never allowed. In contrast, data such as
     the PAN can be stored, but must be encrypted and unreadable in case an
     attacker gains access to the stored data.
    </para>
    <para>
     The database design for storing cardholder data is beyond the scope of
     this document. However, data can be encrypted in different ways:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The DBMS can use column-level encryption inside the database
       scheme.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Alternatively, the database files can be encrypted.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       &productnamex; supports full-disk encryption, so that the whole
       database storage is always encrypted. However, access to an encrypted
       disk works the same way as to a non-encrypted disk. This is discussed
       in more detail in requirement 3.4.1.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry xml:id="vle-pcidss-encrypt-disk">
      <term>
       3.4.1.a If disk encryption is used, inspect the configuration and
       observe the authentication process to verify that logical access to
       encrypted file systems is implemented via a mechanism that is separate
       from the native operating system’s authentication mechanism (for
       example, not using local user account databases or general network
       login credentials).
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The guidance description of the &pcidssa; document says the following
        about this requirement: <quote>Full disk encryption helps to protect
        data in the event of physical loss of a disk and therefore may be
        appropriate for portable devices that store cardholder data.</quote>
       </para>
       <para>
        From an administrator’s point of view, a block device encryption with
        the Linux Unified Key Setup (LUKS)/dm-crypt offers an abstraction
        layer that allows the usage of encrypted disks in the same way
        as unencrypted disks.
       </para>
       <para>
        Therefore, access control can only be limited
        with the general ACL permissions that the file system offers. To
        comply with this requirement, the decryption key used must not be
        associated with any general login credentials or authentication
        methods.
       </para>
       <para>
        When using LUKS, this is usually fulfilled: The password needs to
        be entered separately when booting, inserting portable devices or
        manually mounting disks.
       </para>
       <para>
        LUKS is fully integrated into &productnamex; and can be used via
        &yast; to create new partitions.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       3.4.1.c Examine the configurations and observe the processes to verify
       that cardholder data on removable media is encrypted wherever stored.
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        As described in <xref linkend="vle-pcidss-encrypt-disk"/>,
        LUKS/dm-crypt provides full-disk encryption that fulfills this
        requirement. Access to the stored data is only possible via a
        decryption password that must be entered when the disk is mounted.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 xml:id="sec-pcidss-requirement-4">
    <title>Requirement 4: Encrypt transmission of cardholder data across open, public networks</title>
    <para>
     Cardholder data must be encrypted during transmissions over insecure
     networks. Ideally, encrypt all traffic, externally and internally. This
     makes it hard for attackers to gain inside information and privileged
     access to the cardholder data environment.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       4.1 Use strong cryptography and security protocols (for example,
       TLS, IPSEC, SSH, etc.) to safeguard sensitive cardholder data during
       transmission over open, public networks, including the following: (1)
       Only trusted keys and certificates are accepted, (2) The protocol in
       use only supports secure versions or configurations, (3) The
       encryption strength is appropriate for the encryption methodology in
       use.
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Any connection that transmits sensitive information must be
        protected against eavesdropping and tampering.
       </para>
       <para>
        For incoming client requests, use the HTTPS protocol with a secure
        TLS connection. The authentication is done with a public
        X.509 certificate that proves to a certain level that the server is
        the right endpoint the customer is looking for.
       </para>
       <para>
        &productnamex; comes with a set of services and tools that allow
        protected HTTPS connections. For example, this can be done directly
        with the Apache HTTP Server or via <command>stunnel</command>, which
        functions as a proxy to offer TLS encryption functionality.
       </para>
       <para>
        IPsec or other VPN technologies can be used for securing the
        connection between network segments that are connected via a public
        network. Such connections can also be secured with a public X.509
        certificate. For internal usage, it is possible to use a private
        Certificate Authority (CA) to sign X.509 certificates and to keep
        track of trusted keys.
       </para>
       <para>
        In &productnamex;, this can be established directly with
        <phrase role="productname">strongSwan</phrase>, which is a IPsec-based
        VPN solution, or with OpenVPN, which uses a custom security protocol.
       </para>
       <para>
        To administrate the OS, use SSH. For information about configuring
        SSH to provide better security, see
        <xref linkend="sec-pcidss-requirement-1"/> and
        <xref linkend="sec-pcidss-requirement-2"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 xml:id="sec-pcidss-requirement-5">
    <title>Requirement 5: Protect all systems against malware and regularly update anti-virus software or programs</title>
    <para>
     For &pcidssa; compliance, it is necessary to protect against malicious
     software. Third-party anti-virus software is available from the
     major anti-virus software vendors and can be integrated into the Linux
     environment. &productnamex; comes with the open source anti-virus engine
     &clamav;.
    </para>
    <para>
     &clamav; has a limited set of scanning capabilities and limited
     performance compared to third-party products. Hence, expect &clamav; to
     only provide basic protection.
    </para>
    <para>
     On the other hand, &clamav; is shipped with &productnamex; and it can be
     included during server installation. This makes it easy to fulfill this
     requirement, but the drawbacks compared to third-party products need to
     be clearly understood.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 xml:id="sec-pcidss-requirement-6">
    <title>Requirement 6: Develop and maintain secure systems and applications</title>
    <para>
     The major part of this requirement concerns in-house software development,
     documentation, and design questions that are beyond the scope of this
     document. However, &productnamex; provides tools that help keep your
     systems safe:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The software package manager Zypper is a powerful instrument of
       &productnamex;. Among other things, it resolves dependencies of packages,
       products, patterns, and patches, has a locking mechanism to prevent
       package installation, and provides a complete update stack to keep the
       system up-to-date and protected against known security issues.
      </para>
      <para>
       <command>zypper</command> is part of any &productnamex; installation and
       has direct access to the update repositories after system registration.
      </para>
      <para>
       For information about Zypper, see
       <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"><xref linkend="sec-zypper"/>.</phrase>
       <phrase os="article"><citetitle>&productnamex; Administration Guide,
       Chapter Managing Software with Command Line Tools, Section Using
       Zypper</citetitle>.</phrase>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For system management, &suse; provides &susemgr;, which provides an
       efficient way to keep systems up-to-date. It offers seamless
       management of both &productnamex; and &rhel; client systems. This
       is particularly useful in larger system environments, when you need to
       check the current update status of each system and to react to known
       security risks.
      </para>
      <para>
       For information about &susemgr;, see the
       <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/suma/">&susemgr;
       documentation page</link>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       6.2.a Examine policies and procedures related to security patch
       installation to verify processes are defined for: (1) Installation of
       applicable critical vendor-supplied security patches within one month
       of release, (2) Installation of all applicable vendor-supplied
       security patches within an appropriate time frame (for example, within
       three months).
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        To identify patches that need to be installed to secure your system,
        do the following:
       </para>
       <para>
        First, refresh all software repositories, so you have up-to-date information:
       </para>
       <screen>&prompt.sudo;zypper refresh</screen>
       <para>
        Then use the patch-related commands of Zypper:
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Search for important security fixes that have not yet been
          installed:
         </para>
         <screen>&prompt.user;zypper list-patches --category security --severity important</screen>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          It is also possible to search for CVE or SUSE Bugzilla numbers.
          By default, only necessary patches are listed by this command. To
          also show patches that have already been installed, use the
          parameter <option>--all</option>:
         </para>
         <screen>&prompt.user;zypper list-patches --all --cve=CVE-2016-4957</screen>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          To list details of individual patches, use the
          <command>patch-info</command> subcommand:
         </para>
         <screen>&prompt.user;zypper patch-info SUSE-SLE-SERVER-12-SP1-2016-600</screen>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          To install only important security patches, use the
          <command>patch</command> subcommand:
         </para>
         <screen>&prompt.sudo;zypper patch --category security --severity important</screen>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
       <para>
        To perform updates automatically, the parameter
        <option>--non-interactive</option>, which is supported by all
        Zypper subcommands, is helpful.
       </para>
      <para>
       For more information about Zypper, see
       <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"><xref linkend="sec-zypper"/>.</phrase>
       <phrase os="article"><citetitle>&productnamex; Administration Guide,
       Chapter Managing Software with Command Line Tools, Section Using
       Zypper</citetitle>.</phrase>
      </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 xml:id="sec-pcidss-requirement-7">
    <title>Requirement 7: Restrict access to cardholder data by business need to know</title>
    <para>
     OS access control is a complex topic. Again, this &pcidssa; requirement
     is not specified precisely and does not specifically state to what
     degree the restrictions need to be implemented.
     &productnamex; comes with all general Linux tools to limit and
     restrict access to certain system areas and components:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Access can be controlled via specific users and groups of users by using
       the traditional Unix permission settings.
      </para>
      <para>
       For information about managing permissions, see
       <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"><xref linkend="cha-security-acls"/>.</phrase>
       <phrase os="article"><citetitle>&productnamex; Security Guide,
       Chapter Access Control Lists in Linux</citetitle>.</phrase>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A more flexible mechanism for file systems are Access Control Lists
       (ACLs), which offer a more granular approach. &selnx; can be used for
       maximum system separation and to prevent processes from gaining more
       resources and access than allowed.
       &selnx; and &aa; are beyond the scope of this document but should be
       employed to protect critical systems that are likely to be targeted.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         For information about &selnx;, see
         <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"><xref linkend="cha-selinux"/>.</phrase>
         <phrase os="article"><citetitle>&productnamex; Security Guide,
         Chapter Configuring &selnx;</citetitle>.</phrase>
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         For information about &aa;, see
         <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"><xref linkend="part-apparmor"/>.</phrase>
         <phrase os="article"><citetitle>&productnamex; Security Guide,
         Part Confining Privileges with &aa;</citetitle>.</phrase>
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       7.1.2 Restrict access to privileged user IDs to least privileges
       necessary to perform job responsibilities.
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The standard Unix permissions allow setting Read, Write, and
        Execution flags for user and group IDs. A general group called
        <systemitem class="groupname">others</systemitem> or
        <systemitem class="groupname">world</systemitem> defines the access
        for users that do not fit into the first two groups. This provides a
        straightforward way to grant or deny access to file system resources.
       </para>
       <para>
        ACLs provide an extra level of restrictions. It is possible to set
        read-write access for one user ID and only read access for a second
        one. The same goes for group IDs.
       </para>
       <para>
        The commands <command>getfacl</command> and
        <command>setfacl</command> (on &productnamex; shipped with the package
        <package>acl</package>) allow direct modification of file system
        resources. For example, to check and set ACL restrictions of the file
        <filename>/tmp/test.txt</filename> for the user &exampleuserII;:
       </para>
<screen>
&prompt.user;<command>getfacl /tmp/test.txt</command>
# file: /tmp/test.txt
# owner: &exampleuser_plain;
# group: users
user::r--
group::r--
other::r--

&prompt.user;<command>setfacl -m "u:&exampleuserII_plain;:rw" /tmp/test.txt</command>

&prompt.user;<command>getfacl /tmp/test.txt</command>
# file: /tmp/test.txt
# owner: &exampleuser_plain;
# group: users
user::rw-
user:&exampleuserII_plain;:r--
group::r--
mask::r--
other::r--
</screen>
       <para>
        Standard Unix permissions include the so-called Sticky Bit. This
        allows the execution of certain programs with higher privileges than
        the user who is executing those programs. The best example of this
        is the <command>passwd</command> tool, which needs to modify
        <filename>/etc/shadow</filename> to change the user password.
       </para>
       <para>
        For a more gradual approach to explicitly allowing certain operations
        or behaviors to binaries, use extended capabilities. As an example of
        a command that uses extended capabilities by default, consider
        <command>ping</command> (from the package <package>iputils</package>).
       </para>
       <para>
        <command>ping</command> sends ICMP IP packets over the
        network card. To do so, it needs the
        <literal>CAP_NET_RAW</literal> capability to be Effective and
        Permitted (<literal>+ep</literal>):
       </para>
<screen>
&prompt.root;<command>sudo getcap /usr/bin/ping</command>
/usr/bin/ping = cap_net_raw+ep
</screen>
       <para>
        Login access control to the system can be managed using Pluggable
        Authentication Modules (PAM). There are several modules
        available in &productnamex; that allow setups such as
        logging the login time, multiple authentication mechanisms, and
        central databases like NIS, LDAP, or &ad;.
       </para>
      <para>
       For more information about managing permissions, see
       <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"><xref linkend="cha-security-acls"/>.</phrase>
       <phrase os="article"><citetitle>&productnamex; Security Guide,
       Chapter Access Control Lists in Linux</citetitle>.</phrase>
      </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 xml:id="sec-pcidss-requirement-8">
    <title>Requirement 8: Identify and authenticate access to system components</title>
    <para>
     Ideally, use a central database with user information and a unique
     identifier (UID) to grant or deny access to certain system components.
     This makes it easy to give administrators special access to a group of
     servers or a database engineer permission for a certain DBMS system.
    </para>
    <para>
     On a stand-alone server, unique identifiers are managed via the
     standard Linux user and group IDs. These are listed in
     <filename>/etc/passwd</filename> and <filename>/etc/group</filename>.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry xml:id="vle-pcidss-disable-user">
      <term>
       8.1.4 Remove/disable inactive user accounts within 90 days.
      </term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
       In this context, there are many advantages to using a centralized
       infrastructure for user accounts like NIS, LDAP, or &ad;:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         It is easy to identify and automatically disable inactive accounts.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         User accounts only need to be disabled in one place. After their
         access is revoked, the user cannot use any service that relies on
         the centralized account infrastructure.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
       However, if you are using local accounts, these can be checked for
       inactivity when a user is logging in. This module checks the last
       login time recorded in <filename>/var/log/lastlog</filename> and
       calculates the number of days since.
       By default, access is denied when the inactivity reaches 90 days.
      </para>
      <para>
       To list the local account's last login time use the command
       <command>lastlog</command>.
      </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry xml:id="vle-pcidss-lock-user">
      <term>
       8.1.6 Limit repeated access attempts by locking out the user ID after
       not more than six attempts.
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        As stated in <xref linkend="vle-pcidss-disable-user"/>, a centralized
        account infrastructure will have this capability. On &productnamex;
        systems, access attempts can be checked and limited with
        the <systemitem>pam_tally2</systemitem> PAM module. The module is
        executed during login time and checks the recorded failed attempts
        since the last successful login. To check and reset the account
        status, use the tool <command>pam_tally2</command>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       8.1.7 Set the lockout duration to a minimum of 30 minutes or until an
       administrator enables the user ID.
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The PAM module <systemitem>pam_tally2</systemitem> described
        in <xref linkend="vle-pcidss-lock-user"/> can be used to lock an
        account for a given time after a failed login attempt. The parameter
        <literal>unlock_time=1800</literal> must be specified in the PAM
        configuration. By default, only the administrator can
        reactivate a locked account.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry xml:id="vle-pcidss-multi-factor-local">
      <term>
       8.3.1 Incorporate multi-factor authentication for all non-console access
       into the CDE for personnel with administrative access.
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        To authenticate users for administrative access with multiple
        factors, use the following methods:
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Use Pluggable Authentication Modules (PAM): This increases
          flexibility when adding new methods to the authentication process
          and when adjusting it.
         </para>
         <para>
          For third-party one-time password (OTP) products, there is usually
          also a Linux PAM module available.
         </para>
         <para>
          For information about PAM, see
          <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"><xref linkend="cha-pam"/>.</phrase>
          <phrase os="article"><citetitle>&productnamex; Security Guide,
          Chapter Authentication with PAM</citetitle>.</phrase>
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          To add multi-factor authentication for SSH connections, mandate use
          of public keys in addition to passwords.
         </para>
         <para>
          To connect to a system, it is then necessary to prove possession of
          an appropriate private key. At the second stage, you then enter a
          password. This means attackers need to acquire a private key before
          they can even try to brute-force a password prompt.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry xml:id="vle-pcidss-multi-factor-remote">
      <term>
       8.3.2 Incorporate multi-factor authentication for all remote network
       access (both user and administrator, and including third-party access
       for support or maintenance) originating from outside the entity’s
       network.
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        For details, see <xref linkend="vle-pcidss-multi-factor-local"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 xml:id="sec-pcidss-requirement-9">
    <title>Requirement 9: Restrict physical access to cardholder data</title>
    <para>
     Physical access to systems that are involved in processing cardholder
     data are not within the scope of general operating system security.
     Appropriate facility entry controls must be in place to
     allow on-site personnel and visitors to access systems directly.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 xml:id="sec-pcidss-requirement-10">
    <title>Requirement 10: Track and monitor all access to network resources and cardholder data</title>
    <para>
     To track user activities, it is important to have a synchronized time
     reference. This is done via the NTP protocol, which allows servers to keep
     their local time in synchronization with a central system. The central
     NTP server
     inside the cardholder data environment (CDE) should not rely on
     external connections to the Internet to update the system time.
     Alternatively, system time can be updated using DCF77 radio
     transmissions or a GPS receiver.
    </para>
    <para>
     A synchronized time reference makes it easier to correlate events inside
     recorded log files. This reference can include general system log
     entries collected by a central system log server or kernel audit
     messages by the daemon <systemitem class="daemon">audit</systemitem>.
    </para>
    <para>
     For information about auditing, see
     <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"><xref linkend="part-audit"/>.</phrase>
     <phrase os="article"><citetitle>&productnamex;, Security Guide,
     Part &auditguide;</citetitle>.</phrase>
    </para>
    <para>
     All auditing requirements from this section can be fulfilled by defining
     centrally stored auditing rules.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 xml:id="sec-pcidss-requirement-11">
    <title>Requirement 11: Regularly test security systems and processes</title>
    <para>
     Testing the discussed security mechanisms is also a key requirement for
     &pcidssa;. Evaluating the configurations and testing logging mechanisms
     can protect against known security risks and ensure that essential
     information is available to identify possible security breaches.
     Testing capabilities should be considered ahead of time, during system
     design already.
    </para>
    <para>
     To keep track of system integrity, &productnamex; comes with the Advanced
     Intrusion Detection Environment (&aide;). &aide; creates a hash value
     database of all relevant OS files. After initialization, it can be used
     to verify the integrity of all previously saved files. To employ AIDE,
     it is best to regularly create database snapshots and save them to a
     central system on which you can evaluate possible modifications.
    </para>
    <para>
     For more information about &aide;, see
     <phrase os="sles;sled;osuse"><xref linkend="cha-aide"/>.</phrase>
     <phrase os="article"><citetitle>&productnamex; Security Guide,
     Chapter Intrusion Detection with &aide;</citetitle>.</phrase>
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 xml:id="sec-pcidss-requirement-12">
    <title>Requirement 12: Maintain a policy that addresses information security for all personnel</title>
    <para>
     Any organization that handles valuable information should
     have a general security policy. All relevant aspects should be
     included to make it clear for employees and stakeholders what the possible
     risks are and how to avoid them.
    </para>
    <para>
     All security policies should also be evaluated regularly and adjusted to
     keep the protection level as high as possible.
    </para>
   </sect2>
 </sect1>
</appendix>
