<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
         version="5.0" 
         xml:id="cha-configure-cryptctl">
    
  <title>Storage encryption for hosted applications with cryptctl</title>
   <para>
    Databases and similar applications are often hosted on external
    servers that are serviced by third-party staff. Certain data center
    maintenance tasks require third-party staff to directly access affected
    systems. In such cases, privacy requirements necessitate disk encryption.
   </para>
   <para>
    <command>cryptctl</command> allows encrypting sensitive directories using
    LUKS and offers the following additional features:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Encryption keys are located on a central server, which can be located on
      customer premises.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Encrypted partitions are automatically remounted after an unplanned
      reboot.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   <command>cryptctl</command> consists of two components:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A client is a machine that has one or more encrypted partitions but does
     not permanently store the necessary key to decrypt those partitions.
     For example, clients can be cloud or otherwise hosted machines.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The server holds encryption keys that can be requested by clients to
     unlock encrypted partitions.
    </para>
    <para>
     You can also set up the <command>cryptctl</command> server to store
     encryption keys on a KMIP&nbsp;1.3-compatible (Key Management
     Interoperability Protocol) server. In that case, the
     <command>cryptctl</command> server will not store the encryption keys of
     clients and is dependent upon the KMIP-compatible server to provide
     these.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <warning>
   <title><command>cryptctl</command> Server maintenance</title>
   <para>
    Since the <command>cryptctl</command> server manages timeouts for the
    encrypted disks and, depending on the configuration, can also hold
    encryption keys, it
    should be under your direct control and managed only by trusted
    personnel.
   </para>
   <para>
    Additionally, it should be backed up regularly. Losing the server's data
    means losing access to encrypted partitions on the clients.
   </para>
  </warning>
  <para>
   To handle encryption, <command>cryptctl</command> uses LUKS with
   aes-xts-256 encryption and 512-bit keys. Encryption keys are transferred
   using TLS with certificate verification.
  </para>
  <figure xml:id="fig-cryptctl-retrieve">
   <title>Key retrieval with <command>cryptctl</command> (model without connection to KMIP server)</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="cryptctl-keyretrieval.png" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="cryptctl-keyretrieval.svg" width="70%" format="SVG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>The client asks the server for the disk decryption key, the server
     responds</phrase>
    </textobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <note>
   <title>Install <command>cryptctl</command></title>
   <para>
    Before continuing, make sure the package <package>cryptctl</package> is
    installed on all machines you intend to set up as servers or clients.
   </para>
  </note>
  <sect1 xml:id="sec-configure-cryptctl-server">
   <title>Setting up a <command>cryptctl</command> server</title>
   <para>
    Before you can define a machine as a <command>cryptctl</command> client,
    you need to set up a machine as a <command>cryptctl</command> server.
   </para>
   <para>
    Before beginning, choose whether to use a self-signed certificate to
    secure communication between the server and clients. If not, generate a
    TLS certificate for the server and have it signed by a certificate
    authority.
   </para>
   <para>
    Additionally, you can have clients authenticate to the server using
    certificates signed by a certificate authority. To use this extra
    security measure, make sure to have a CA certificate at hand before
    starting this procedure.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      As <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>, run:
     </para>
     <screen>&prompt.root;<command>cryptctl init-server</command></screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Answer each of the following prompts and press <keycap function="enter"/>
      after every answer. If there is a default answer, it is shown in square
      brackets at the end of the prompt.
     </para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>
        Choose a password with at least 10 characters and confirm it. This
        password assumes the role of a master password, able to unlock all
        partitions that are registered on the server.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Specify the path to a PEM-encoded TLS certificate or certificate chain
        file or leave the field empty to create a self-signed certificate. If
        you specify a path, use an absolute path.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        If you want the server to be identified by a host name other than the
        default shown, specify a host name. <command>cryptctl</command> will
        then generate certificates which include the host name.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Specify the IP address that belongs to the network interface that you
        want to listen on for decryption requests from the clients, then set
        a port number (the default is port 3737).
       </para>
       <para>
        The default IP address setting,
        <systemitem class="ipaddress">0.0.0.0</systemitem> means that
        <command>cryptctl</command> will listen on
        all network interfaces for client requests using IPv4.
       </para>
       <!-- IPv6 should work too but not with 0.0.0.0, however: this is
       untested. - sknorr, 2016-12-02 -->
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Specify a directory on the server that will hold the decryption keys
        for clients.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Specify whether clients need to authenticate to the server using a
        TLS certificate. If you choose <guimenu>No</guimenu>, this means that
        clients authenticate using disk UUIDs only. (However, communication
        will be encrypted using the server certificate in any case.)
       </para>
       <para>
        If you choose <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>, pick a PEM-encoded certificate
        authority to use for signing client certificates.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Specify whether to use a KMIP 1.3-compatible server (or multiple such
        servers) to store encryption keys of clients. If you choose this
        option, provide the host names and ports for one or multiple
        KMIP-compatible servers.
       </para>
       <para>
        Additionally, provide a user name, password, a CA certificate for the
        KMIP server, and a client identity certificate for the
        <command>cryptctl</command> server.
       </para>
       <important>
        <title>No easy reconfiguration of KMIP setting</title>
        <para>
         The setting to use a KMIP server cannot easily be changed later. To
         change this setting, both the <command>cryptctl</command> server and
         its clients need to be configured afresh.
        </para>
       </important>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Finally, configure an SMTP server for e-mail notifications for
        encryption and decryption requests or leave the prompt empty to skip
        setting up e-mail notifications.
       </para>
       <note>
        <title>Password-protected servers</title>
        <para>
         <command>cryptctl</command> currently cannot send e-mail using
         authentication-protected SMTP servers. If that is necessary, set up
         a local SMTP proxy.
        </para>
       </note>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        When asked whether to start the <command>cryptctl</command> server,
        enter <literal>y</literal>.
       </para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To check the status of the service
      <systemitem class="daemon">cryptctl-server</systemitem>, use:
     </para>
     <screen>&prompt.root;<command>systemctl status cryptctl-server</command></screen>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    To reconfigure the server later, do either of the following:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Run the command <command>cryptctl init-server</command> again.
      <command>cryptctl</command> will then propose the existing settings as
      the defaults, so that you only need to specify the values that you want
      to change.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Make changes directly in the configuration file
      <filename>/etc/sysconfig/cryptctl-server</filename>.
     </para>
     <para>
      However, to avoid issues, do not change the settings
      <option>AUTH_PASSWORD_HASH</option> and
      <option>AUTH_PASSWORD_SALT</option> manually. The values of these
      options need to be calculated correctly.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sec-configure-cryptctl-client">
   <title>Setting up a <command>cryptctl</command> client</title>
   <para>
    The following interactive setup of <command>cryptctl</command> is
    currently the only setup method.
   </para>
   <para>
    Make sure the following preconditions are fulfilled:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A <command>cryptctl</command> server is available over the network.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      There is a directory to encrypt.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The client machine has an empty partition available that is large
      enough to fit the directory to encrypt.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      When using a self-signed certificate, the certificate
      (<filename>*.crt</filename> file) generated on the server is
      available locally on the client. Otherwise, the certificate authority
      of the server certificate must be trusted by the client.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you set up the server to require clients to authenticate using a
      client certificate, prepare a TLS certificate for the client which is
      signed by the CA certificate you chose for the server.
     </para>
     <remark>
      FIXME: needs openssl command-line-fu, or maybe xref to
      doc-sle/sec.apache2.ssl.certificate - though some parts there are
      somewhat Apache-specific, i.e. confusing here.
      - sknorr, 2017-09-06
     </remark>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      As <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>, run:
     </para>
     <screen>&prompt.root;<command>cryptctl encrypt</command></screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Answer each of the following prompts and press <keycap function="enter"/>
      after every answer. If there is a default answer, it is shown in square
      brackets at the end of the prompt.
     </para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>
        Specify the host name and port to connect to on the
        <command>cryptctl</command> server.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        If you configured the server to have clients authenticate to it using a
        TLS certificate, specify a certificate and a key file for the client.
        The client certificate must be signed by the certificate
        authority chosen when setting up the server.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Specify the absolute path to the server certificate (the
        <filename>*.crt</filename> file).
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Enter the encryption password that you specified when setting up the
        server.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Specify the path to the directory to encrypt. Specify the path to the
        empty partition that will contain the encrypted content of the
        directory.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Specify the number of machines that are allowed to decrypt the
        partition simultaneously.
       </para>
       <para>
        Then specify the timeout in seconds before additional machines are
        allowed to decrypt the partition after the last vital sign was
        received from the client or clients.
       </para>
       <para>
        When a machine unexpectedly stops working and then reboots, it needs to
        be able to unlock its partitions again. That means this timeout
        should be set to a time slightly shorter than the reboot time of the
        client.
       </para>
       <important>
        <title>Timeout length</title>
        <para>
         If the time is set too long, the machine cannot decrypt
         encrypted partitions on the first try. <command>cryptctl</command> will
         then continue to periodically check whether the encryption key has
         become available. However, this will introduce a delay.
        </para>
        <para>
         If the timeout is set too short, machines with a copy of
         the encrypted partition have an increased chance of unlocking the
         partition first.
        </para>
       </important>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To start encryption, enter <literal>yes</literal>.
     </para>
     <para>
      <command>cryptctl</command> will now encrypt the specified directory to
      the previously empty partition and then mount the newly encrypted
      partition. The file system type will be of the same type as the
      original unencrypted file system.
     </para>
     <para>
      Before creating the encrypted partition,
      <command>cryptctl</command> moves the unencrypted content of the
      original directory to a location prefixed with
      <literal>cryptctl-moved-</literal>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To check that the directory is indeed mounted correctly, use:
     </para>
     <screen>
&prompt.user;<command>lsblk -o NAME,MOUNTPOINT,UUID</command>
NAME                        MOUNTPOINT          UUID
[...]
sdc
└─sdc1                                          <replaceable>PARTITION_UUID</replaceable>
  └─cryptctl-unlocked-sdc1  /secret-partition   <replaceable>UNLOCKED_UUID</replaceable>
      </screen>
     <para>
      <command>cryptctl</command> identifies the encrypted partition by its
      UUID. For the previous example, that is the UUID displayed next to
      <literal>sdc1</literal>.
     </para>
     <para>
      On the server, you can check whether the directory was decrypted using
      <command>cryptctl</command>.
     </para>
     <screen>&prompt.root;<command>cryptctl list-keys</command></screen>
     <para>
      For a successfully decrypted partition, you will see output like:
     </para>
     <screen>
2019/06/06 15:50:00 ReloadDB: successfully loaded database of 1 records
Total: 1 records (date and time are in zone EDT)
Used By     When                 UUID  Max.Users  Num.Users  Mount Point
<replaceable>IP_ADDRESS</replaceable>  2019-06-06 15:00:50  <replaceable>UUID</replaceable>  1          1          /secret-partition</screen>
     <para>
      For a partition not decrypted successfully, you will see output like:
     </para>
     <screen>2019/06/06 15:50:00 ReloadDB: successfully loaded database of 1 records
Total: 1 records (date and time are in zone EDT)
Used By      When                 UUID  Max.Users  Num.Users  Mount Point
             2019-06-06 15:00:50  <replaceable>UUID</replaceable>  1          1          /secret-partition</screen>
     <para>See the difference in the empty <literal>Used by</literal> column.</para>
     <para>
      Verify that the UUID shown is that of the previously encrypted partition.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      After verifying that the encrypted partition works, delete the
      unencrypted content from the client. For example, use <command>rm</command>.
      For more
      safety, overwrite the content of the files before deleting them, for
      example, using <command>shred -u</command>.
     </para>
     <important>
      <title><command>shred</command> does not guarantee that data is completely erased</title>
      <para>
       Depending on the type of storage media, using
       <command>shred</command> is not a guarantee that all data is
       completely removed. In particular, SSDs usually employ wear leveling
       strategies that render <command>shred</command> ineffective.
      </para>
     </important>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    The configuration for the connection from client to server is stored in
    <filename>/etc/sysconfig/cryptctl-client</filename> and can be edited
    manually.
   </para>
   <para>
    The server stores an encryption key for the client partition in
    <filename>/var/lib/cryptctl/keydb/<replaceable>PARTITION_UUID</replaceable></filename>.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sec-configure-cryptctl-status">
   <title>Checking partition unlock status using server-side commands</title>
   <para>
    When a <command>cryptctl</command> client is active, it will send a
    <quote>heartbeat</quote> to the <command>cryptctl</command> server every
    10 seconds. If the server does not receive a heartbeat from the client
    for the length of the timeout configured during the client setup, the
    server will assume that the client is offline. It will then allow another
    client to connect (or allow the same client to reconnect after a reboot).
   </para>
   <para>
    To see the usage status of all keys, use:
   </para>
   <screen>
&prompt.root;<command>cryptctl list-keys</command>
   </screen>
   <para>
    The information under <literal>Num. Users</literal> shows whether the key
    is currently in use. To see more detail on a single key, use:
   </para>
   <screen>
&prompt.root;<command>cryptctl show-key <replaceable>UUID</replaceable></command>
   </screen>
   <para>
    This command will show information about mount point, mount options,
    usage options, the last retrieval of the key, and the last three
    heartbeats from clients.
   </para>
   <para>
    Additionally, you can use <command>journalctl</command> to find logs of
    when keys were retrieved.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sec-configure-cryptctl-unlock">
   <title>Unlocking encrypted partitions manually</title>
   <para>
    There are two ways of unlocking a partition manually, both of which are run
    on a client:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Online unlocking</title>
      <para>
       Online unlocking allows circumventing timeout or user limitations.
       This method can be used when there is a network connection between
       client and server but the client could not (yet) unlock the partition
       automatically. This method will unlock all encrypted
       partitions on a machine.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <para>
      To use it, run <command>cryptctl online-unlock</command>. Be prepared to
      enter the password specified when setting up the server.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Offline unlocking</title>
      <para>
       This method can be used when a client cannot or must not be brought
       online to communicate with its server. The encryption key from the
       server must still be available. This method is meant as a last resort
       only and can only unlock a single partition at a time.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <para>
      To use it, run <command>cryptctl offline-unlock</command>. The
      server's key file for the requisite partition
      (<filename>/var/lib/cryptctl/keydb/<replaceable>PARTITION_UUID</replaceable></filename>)
      needs to be available on the client.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sec-configure-cryptctl-lock">
   <title>Maintenance downtime procedure</title>
   <para>
    To ensure that partitions cannot be decrypted during a maintenance
    downtime, turn off the client and disable the
    <command>cryptctl</command> server. You can do so by either:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Stopping the service
      <systemitem class="daemon">cryptctl-server</systemitem>:
     </para>
     <screen>
&prompt.root;<command>systemctl stop cryptctl-server</command>
     </screen>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Unplugging the <command>cryptctl</command> server from the network.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-configure-cryptctl-more">
  <title>More information</title>
  <para>
   For more information, also see the project home page
   <link xlink:href="https://github.com/SUSE/cryptctl/"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 </chapter>
