<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.pam">
 <title>Authentication with PAM</title><indexterm class="startofrange"
  id="idx.Authentifizierung_PAM">
 <primary>authentication</primary>
 <secondary>PAM</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>Pluggable Authentication Modules</primary>
 <see>PAM</see></indexterm><indexterm class="startofrange" id="idx.PAM">
 <primary>PAM</primary></indexterm>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   Linux uses PAM (pluggable authentication modules) in the authentication
   process as a layer that mediates between user and application. PAM
   modules are available on a systemwide basis, so they can be requested by
   any application. This chapter describes how the modular authentication
   mechanism works and how it is configured.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <sect1 id="sec.security.pam.whatis">
  <title>What is PAM?</title>

  <para>
   System administrators and programmers often want to restrict access to
   certain parts of the system or to limit the use of certain functions of
   an application. Without PAM, applications must be adapted every time a
   new authentication mechanism, such as LDAP, Samba, or Kerberos, is
   introduced. This process, however, is rather time-consuming and
   error-prone. One way to avoid these drawbacks is to separate applications
   from the authentication mechanism and delegate authentication to
   centrally managed modules. Whenever a newly required authentication
   scheme is needed, it is sufficient to adapt or write a suitable
   <emphasis>PAM module</emphasis> for use by the program in question.
  </para>

  <para>
   The PAM concept consists of:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis>PAM modules</emphasis>, which are a set of shared libraries
     for a specific authentication mechanism.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A <emphasis>module stack</emphasis> with of one or more PAM modules.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A PAM-aware <emphasis>service</emphasis> which needs authentication by
     using a module stack or PAM modules. Usually a service is a familiar
     name of the corresponding application, like <command>login</command> or
     <command>su</command>. The service name <literal>other</literal> is a
     reserved word for default rules.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Module arguments</emphasis>, with which the execution of a
     single PAM module can be influenced.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A mechanism evaluating each <emphasis>result</emphasis> of a single PAM
     module execution. A positive value executes the next PAM module. The
     way a negative value is dealt with, depends on the configuration:
     <quote>no influence, proceed</quote> up to <quote>terminate
     immediately</quote> and anything in between are valid options.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.pam.struc.files">
  <title>Structure of a PAM Configuration File</title>

  <para>
   PAM can be configured in two ways:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>File based configuration (<filename>/etc/pam.conf</filename>)</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The configuration of each service is stored in
      <filename>/etc/pam.conf</filename>. However, for maintenance and
      usability reasons, this configuration scheme is not used in
      &productname;.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Directory based configuration (<filename>/etc/pam.d/</filename>)</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Every service (or program) that relies on the PAM mechanism has its
      own configuration file in the <filename>/etc/pam.d/</filename>
      directory. For example, the service for
      <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem> can be found in the
      <filename>/etc/pam.d/sshd</filename> file.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   The files under <filename>/etc/pam.d/</filename> define the PAM modules
   used for authentication. Each file consists of lines, which define a
   service, and each line consists of a maximum of four components:
  </para>

<screen><replaceable>TYPE</replaceable>  <replaceable>CONTROL</replaceable>
 <replaceable>MODULE_PATH</replaceable>  <replaceable>MODULE_ARGS</replaceable></screen>

  <para>
   The components have the following meaning:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><replaceable>TYPE</replaceable>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Declares the type of the service. PAM modules are processed as stacks.
      Different types of modules have different purposes. For example, one
      module checks the password, another verifies the location from which
      the system is accessed, and yet another reads user-specific settings.
      PAM knows about four different types of modules:
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>auth</literal>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Check the user's authenticity, traditionally by querying a
         password. However, this can also be achieved with the help of a
         chip card or through biometrics (for example, fingerprints or iris
         scan).
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>account</literal>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Modules of this type check if the user has general permission to
         use the requested service. As an example, such a check should be
         performed to ensure that no one can log in with the user name of an
         expired account.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>password</literal>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         The purpose of this type of module is to enable the change of an
         authentication token. In most cases, this is a password.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>session</literal>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Modules of this type are responsible for managing and configuring
         user sessions. They are started before and after authentication to
         log login attempts and configure the user's specific environment
         (mail accounts, home directory, system limits, etc.).
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><replaceable>CONTROL</replaceable>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Indicates the behavior of a PAM module. Each module can have the
      following control flags:
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>required</literal>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         A module with this flag must be successfully processed before the
         authentication may proceed. After the failure of a module with the
         <literal>required</literal> flag, all other modules with the same
         flag are processed before the user receives a message about the
         failure of the authentication attempt.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>requisite</literal>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Modules having this flag must also be processed successfully, in
         much the same way as a module with the <literal>required</literal>
         flag. However, in case of failure a module with this flag gives
         immediate feedback to the user and no further modules are
         processed. In case of success, other modules are subsequently
         processed, like any modules with the <literal>required</literal>
         flag. The <literal>requisite</literal> flag can be used as a basic
         filter checking for the existence of certain conditions that are
         essential for a correct authentication.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>sufficient</literal>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         After a module with this flag has been successfully processed, the
         requesting application receives an immediate message about the
         success and no further modules are processed, provided there was no
         preceding failure of a module with the <literal>required</literal>
         flag. The failure of a module with the
         <literal>sufficient</literal> flag has no direct consequences, in
         the sense that any subsequent modules are processed in their
         respective order.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>optional</literal>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         The failure or success of a module with this flag does not have any
         direct consequences. This can be useful for modules that are only
         intended to display a message (for example, to tell the user that
         mail has arrived) without taking any further action.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>include</literal>
       </term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         If this flag is given, the file specified as argument is inserted
         at this place.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><replaceable>MODULE_PATH</replaceable>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Contains a full file name of a PAM module. It does not need to be
      specified explicitly, as long as the module is located in the default
      directory <filename>/lib/security</filename> (for all 64-bit platforms
      supported by &productnamereg;, the directory is
      <filename>/lib64/security</filename>).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><replaceable>MODULE_ARGS</replaceable>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Contains a space-separated list of options to influence the behavior
      of a PAM module, such as <option>debug</option> (enables debugging) or
      <option>nullok</option> (allows the use of empty passwords).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   In addition, there are global configuration files for PAM modules under
   <filename>/etc/security</filename>, which define the exact behavior of
   these modules (examples include <filename>pam_env.conf</filename> and
   <filename>time.conf</filename>). Every application that uses a PAM module
   actually calls a set of PAM functions, which then process the information
   in the various configuration files and return the result to the
   requesting application.
  </para>

  <para>
   To simplify the creation and maintenance of PAM modules, common default
   configuration files for the types <literal>auth</literal>,
   <literal>account</literal>, <literal>password</literal>, and
   <literal>session</literal> modules have been introduced. These are
   retrieved from every application's PAM configuration. Updates to the
   global PAM configuration modules in <filename>common-*</filename> are
   thus propagated across all PAM configuration files without requiring the
   administrator to update every single PAM configuration file.
  </para>

  <para>
   The global PAM configuration files are maintained using the
   <command>pam-config</command> tool. This tool automatically adds new
   modules to the configuration, changes the configuration of existing ones
   or deletes modules (or options) from the configurations. Manual
   intervention in maintaining PAM configurations is minimized or no longer
   required.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>64-Bit and 32-Bit Mixed Installations</title>
   <para>
    When using a 64-bit operating system, it is possible to also include a
    runtime environment for 32-bit applications. In this case, make sure
    that you also install the 32-bit version of the PAM modules.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.pam.struc.format">
  <title>The PAM Configuration of sshd</title>

  <para>
   Consider the PAM configuration of sshd as an example:
  </para>

  <example id="dat.pam.sshd">
   <title>PAM Configuration for sshd (<filename>/etc/pam.d/sshd</filename>)</title>
<screen>#%PAM-1.0 <co id="co.security.pam.sshd.pam-line"/>
auth     requisite      pam_nologin.so                              <co id="co.security.pam.sshd.pam_nologin"/>
auth     include        common-auth                                 <co id="co.security.pam.sshd.common-auth"/>
account  requisite      pam_nologin.so                              <xref xrefstyle="select:nopage" linkend="co.security.pam.sshd.pam_nologin"/>
account  include        common-account                              <xref xrefstyle="select:nopage" linkend="co.security.pam.sshd.common-auth"/>
password include        common-password                             <xref linkend="co.security.pam.sshd.common-auth" xrefstyle="select:nopage"/>
session  required       pam_loginuid.so                             <co id="co.security.pam.sshd.pam_loginuid"/>
session  include        common-session                              <xref linkend="co.security.pam.sshd.common-auth" xrefstyle="select:nopage"/>
session  optional       pam_lastlog.so   silent noupdate showfailed <co id="co.security.pam.sshd.lastlog"/></screen>
   <calloutlist>
    <callout arearefs="co.security.pam.sshd.pam-line">
     <para>
      Declares the version of this configuration file for PAM 1.0. This is
      merely a convention, but could be used in the future to check the
      version.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="co.security.pam.sshd.pam_nologin">
     <para>
      Checks, if <filename>/etc/nologin</filename> exists. If it does, no
      user other than <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> may log
      in.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="co.security.pam.sshd.common-auth">
     <para>
      Refers to the configuration files of four module types:
      <filename>common-auth</filename>, <filename>common-account</filename>,
      <filename>common-password</filename>, and
      <filename>common-session</filename>. These four files hold the default
      configuration for each module type.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="co.security.pam.sshd.pam_loginuid">
     <para>
      Sets the login uid process attribute for the process that was
      authenticated.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="co.security.pam.sshd.lastlog">
     <para>
      Displays information about the last login of a user.
     </para>
    </callout>
   </calloutlist>
  </example>

  <para>
   By including the configuration files instead of adding each module
   separately to the respective PAM configuration, you automatically get an
   updated PAM configuration when an administrator changes the defaults.
   Formerly, you needed to adjust all configuration files manually for all
   applications when changes to PAM occurred or a new application was
   installed. Now the PAM configuration is made with central configuration
   files and all changes are automatically inherited by the PAM
   configuration of each service.
  </para>

  <para>
   The first include file (<filename>common-auth</filename>) calls three
   modules of the <literal>auth</literal> type:
   <systemitem
   class="library">pam_env.so</systemitem>,
   <systemitem
   class="library">pam_gnome_keyring.so</systemitem> and
   <systemitem
   class="library" >pam_unix.so</systemitem>. See
   <xref
   linkend="dat.pam.common-auth"/>.
  </para>

  <example id="dat.pam.common-auth">
   <title>Default Configuration for the <literal>auth</literal> Section (<filename>common-auth</filename>)</title>
<screen>auth  required  pam_env.so                   <co id="co.security.pam.sshd.pam_env"/>
auth  optional	pam_gnome_keyring.so         <co id="co.security.pam.sshd.gnome"/>
auth  required  pam_unix.so  try_first_pass <co id="co.security.pam.sshd.pam_unix"/></screen>
  </example>

  <calloutlist>
   <callout arearefs="co.security.pam.sshd.pam_env">
    <para>
     <systemitem class="library">pam_env.so</systemitem> loads
     <filename>/etc/security/pam_env.conf</filename> to set the environment
     variables as specified in this file. It can be used to set the
     <envar>DISPLAY</envar> variable to the correct value, because the
     <systemitem class="library">pam_env</systemitem> module knows about the
     location from which the login is taking place.
    </para>
   </callout>
   <callout arearefs="co.security.pam.sshd.gnome">
    <para>
     <systemitem class="library">pam_gnome_keyring.so</systemitem> checks
     the user's login and password against the GNOME keyring
    </para>
   </callout>
   <callout arearefs="co.security.pam.sshd.pam_unix">
    <para>
     <systemitem class="library">pam_unix</systemitem> checks the user's
     login and password against <filename>/etc/passwd</filename> and
     <filename>/etc/shadow</filename>.
    </para>
   </callout>
  </calloutlist>

  <para>
   The whole stack of <literal>auth</literal> modules is processed before
   <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem> gets any feedback about
   whether the login has succeeded. All modules of the stack having the
   <literal>required</literal> control flag must be processed successfully
   before <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem> receives a message
   about the positive result. If one of the modules is not successful, the
   entire module stack is still processed and only then is
   <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem> notified about the negative
   result.
  </para>

  <para>
   As soon as all modules of the <literal>auth</literal> type have been
   successfully processed, another include statement is processed, in this
   case, that in <xref linkend="dat.pam.common-account"/>.
   <filename>common-account</filename> contains only one module,
   <literal>pam_unix</literal>. If <literal>pam_unix</literal> returns the
   result that the user exists, sshd receives a message announcing this
   success and the next stack of modules (<literal>password</literal>) is
   processed, shown in <xref linkend="dat.pam.common-password"/>.
  </para>

  <example id="dat.pam.common-account">
   <title>Default Configuration for the <literal>account</literal> Section (<filename>common-account</filename>)</title>
<screen>account  required  pam_unix.so  try_first_pass</screen>
  </example>

  <example id="dat.pam.common-password">
   <title>Default Configuration for the <literal>password</literal> Section (<filename>common-password</filename>)</title>
<screen>password  requisite  pam_cracklib.so	
password  optional   pam_gnome_keyring.so  use_authtok
password  required   pam_unix.so  use_authtok nullok shadow try_first_pass</screen>
  </example>

  <para>
   Again, the PAM configuration of
   <systemitem class="daemon">sshd</systemitem> involves only an include
   statement referring to the default configuration for
   <literal>password</literal> modules located in
   <filename>common-password</filename>. These modules must successfully be
   completed (control flags <literal>requisite</literal> and
   <literal>required</literal>) whenever the application requests the change
   of an authentication token.
  </para>

  <para>
   Changing a password or another authentication token requires a security
   check. This is achieved with the <filename>pam_cracklib</filename>
   module. The <filename>pam_unix</filename> module used afterwards carries
   over any old and new passwords from <filename>pam_cracklib</filename>, so
   the user does not need to authenticate again after changing the password.
   This procedure makes it impossible to circumvent the checks carried out
   by <filename>pam_cracklib</filename>. Whenever the
   <literal>account</literal> or the <literal>auth</literal> type are
   configured to complain about expired passwords, the
   <literal>password</literal> modules should also be used.
  </para>

  <example id="dat.pam.common-session">
   <title>Default Configuration for the <literal>session</literal> Section (<filename>common-session</filename>)</title>
<screen>session  required  pam_limits.so	
session	 required  pam_unix.so	try_first_pass 
session	 optional  pam_umask.so	
session	 optional  pam_systemd.so
session	 optional  pam_gnome_keyring.so	auto_start only_if=gdm,gdm-password,lxdm,lightdm 
session	 optional  pam_env.so</screen>
  </example>

  <para>
   As the final step, the modules of the <literal>session</literal> type
   (bundled in the <filename>common-session</filename> file) are called to
   configure the session according to the settings for the user in question.
   The <filename>pam_limits</filename> module loads the file
   <filename>/etc/security/limits.conf</filename>, which may define limits
   on the use of certain system resources. The <filename>pam_unix</filename>
   module is processed again. The <filename>pam_umask</filename> module can
   be used to set the file mode creation mask. Since this module carries the
   <literal>optional</literal> flag, a failure of this module would not
   affect the successful completion of the entire session module stack. The
   <literal>session</literal> modules are called a second time when the user
   logs out.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.pam.struc.conf">
  <title>Configuration of PAM Modules</title>

  <para>
   Some of the PAM modules are configurable. The configuration files are
   located in <filename>/etc/security</filename>. This section briefly
   describes the configuration files relevant to the sshd
   example&mdash;<filename>pam_env.conf</filename> and
   <filename>limits.conf</filename>.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.pam.struc.conf.pamenv">
   <title>pam_env.conf</title>
   <para>
    <filename>pam_env.conf</filename> can be used to define a standardized
    environment for users that is set whenever the
    <systemitem>pam_env</systemitem> module is called. With it, preset
    environment variables using the following syntax:
   </para>
<screen><replaceable>VARIABLE</replaceable>  [DEFAULT=<replaceable>value</replaceable>]  [OVERRIDE=<replaceable>value</replaceable>]</screen>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><replaceable>VARIABLE</replaceable>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Name of the environment variable to set.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><systemitem>[DEFAULT=&lt;value&gt;]</systemitem>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Default <replaceable>value</replaceable> the administrator wants to
       set.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><systemitem>[OVERRIDE=&lt;value&gt;]</systemitem>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Values that may be queried and set by
       <systemitem>pam_env</systemitem>, overriding the default value.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    A typical example of how <systemitem>pam_env</systemitem> can be used is
    the adaptation of the <envar>DISPLAY</envar> variable, which is changed
    whenever a remote login takes place. This is shown in
    <xref linkend="dat.pam.pamenv"/>.
   </para>
   <example id="dat.pam.pamenv">
    <title>pam_env.conf</title>
<screen>
REMOTEHOST  DEFAULT=localhost          OVERRIDE=@{PAM_RHOST}
DISPLAY     DEFAULT=${REMOTEHOST}:0.0  OVERRIDE=${DISPLAY}
</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    The first line sets the value of the <envar>REMOTEHOST</envar> variable
    to <literal>localhost</literal>, which is used whenever
    <filename>pam_env</filename> cannot determine any other value. The
    <envar>DISPLAY</envar> variable in turn contains the value of
    <envar>REMOTEHOST</envar>. Find more information in the comments in
    <filename>/etc/security/pam_env.conf</filename>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

<!-- pam_mount is a stand-alone package -->

  <sect2 id="sec.pam.struc.conf.pammount">
   <title>pam_mount.conf.xml</title>
   <para>
    The purpose of <systemitem>pam_mount</systemitem> is to mount user home
    directories during the login process, and to unmount them during logout
    in an environment where a central file server keeps all the home
    directories of users. With this method, it is not necessary to mount a
    complete <filename>/home</filename> directory where all the user home
    directories would be accessible. Instead, only the home directory of the
    user who is about to log in, is mounted.
   </para>
   <para>
    After installing <systemitem>pam_mount</systemitem>, a template for
    <filename>pam_mount.conf.xml</filename> is available in
    <filename>/etc/security</filename>. The description of the various
    elements can be found in the manual page <command>man 5
    pam_mount.conf</command>.
   </para>
   <para>
    A basic configuration of this feature can be done with &yast;. Select
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu> <guimenu>Windows Domain
    Membership</guimenu> <guimenu>Expert Settings</guimenu></menuchoice> to
    add the file server; see <xref linkend="sec.samba.client.inst"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.pam.struc.pamlimits">
   <title>limits.conf</title>
   <para>
    System limits can be set on a user or group basis in
    <filename>limits.conf</filename>, which is read by the
    <systemitem>pam_limits</systemitem> module. The file allows you to set
    hard limits, which may not be exceeded at all, and soft limits, which
    may be exceeded temporarily. For more information about the syntax and
    the options, see the comments in
    <filename>/etc/security/limits.conf</filename>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.pam.pam-config">
  <title>Configuring PAM Using pam-config</title>

  <para>
   The <command>pam-config</command> tool helps you configure the global PAM
   configuration files (<filename>/etc/pam.d/common-*</filename>) as well as
   several selected application configurations. For a list of supported
   modules, use the <command>pam-config --list-modules</command> command.
   Use the <command>pam-config</command> command to maintain your PAM
   configuration files. Add new modules to your PAM configurations, delete
   other modules or modify options to these modules. When changing global
   PAM configuration files, no manual tweaking of the PAM setup for
   individual applications is required.
  </para>

  <para>
   A simple use case for <command>pam-config</command> involves the
   following:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Auto-generate a fresh Unix-style PAM configuration.</title>
     <para>
      Let pam-config create the simplest possible setup which you can extend
      later on. The <command>pam-config --create</command> command creates a
      simple Unix authentication configuration. Pre-existing configuration
      files not maintained by pam-config are overwritten, but backup copies
      are kept as <literal>*.pam-config-backup</literal>.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </step>
   <step>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Add a new authentication method.</title>
     <para>
      Adding a new authentication method (for example, LDAP) to your stack
      of PAM modules comes down to a simple <command>pam-config --add
      --ldap</command> command. LDAP is added wherever appropriate across
      all <filename>common-*-pc</filename> PAM configuration files.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </step>
   <step>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Add debugging for test purposes.</title>
     <para>
      To make sure the new authentication procedure works as planned, turn
      on debugging for all PAM-related operations. The <command>pam-config
      --add --ldap-debug</command> turns on debugging for LDAP-related PAM
      operations. Find the debugging output in the &systemd; journal (see
      <xref
      linkend="cha.journalctl"/>).
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </step>
   <step>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Query your setup.</title>
     <para>
      Before you finally apply your new PAM setup, check if it contains all
      the options you wanted to add. The <command>pam-config --query
      --<replaceable>module</replaceable></command> lists both the type and
      the options for the queried PAM module.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </step>
   <step>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Remove the debug options.</title>
     <para>
      Finally, remove the debug option from your setup when you are entirely
      satisfied with the performance of it. The <command>pam-config --delete
      --ldap-debug</command> command turns off debugging for LDAP
      authentication. In case you had debugging options added for other
      modules, use similar commands to turn these off.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   For more information on the <command>pam-config</command> command and the
   options available, refer to the manual page of
   <command>pam-config(8)</command>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.pam.manual-config">
  <title>Manually Configuring PAM</title>

  <remark condition="generic">
   2011-07-18 - fs: Fate #310739
  </remark>

  <para>
   If you prefer to manually create or maintain your PAM configuration
   files, make sure to disable <command>pam-config</command> for these
   files.
  </para>

  <para>
   When you create your PAM configuration files from scratch using the
   <command>pam-config --create</command> command, it creates symbolic links
   from the <filename>common-<replaceable>*</replaceable></filename> to the
   <filename>common-<replaceable>*</replaceable>-pc</filename> files.
   <command>pam-config</command> only modifies the
   <filename>common-<replaceable>*</replaceable>-pc</filename> configuration
   files. Removing these symbolic links effectively disables pam-config,
   because pam-config only operates on the
   <filename>common-<replaceable>*</replaceable>-pc</filename> files and
   these files are not put into effect without the symbolic links.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.pam.info">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   In the <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/pam</filename> directory after
   installing the <systemitem>pam-doc</systemitem> package, find the
   following additional documentation:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>READMEs</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      In the top level of this directory, there is the
      <filename>modules</filename> subdirectory holding README files about
      the available PAM modules.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>The Linux-PAM System Administrators' Guide</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This document comprises everything that the system administrator
      should know about PAM. It discusses a range of topics, from the syntax
      of configuration files to the security aspects of PAM.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>The Linux-PAM Module Writers' Manual</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This document summarizes the topic from the developer's point of view,
      with information about how to write standard-compliant PAM modules.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>The Linux-PAM Application Developers' Guide</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This document comprises everything needed by an application developer
      who wants to use the PAM libraries.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>The PAM Manual Pages</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      PAM in general as well as the individual modules come with manual
      pages that provide a good overview of the functionality of all the
      components.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist><indexterm
   class="endofrange" startref="idx.PAM"/><indexterm class="endofrange"
   startref="idx.Authentifizierung_PAM"/>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
