<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
       version="5.0"
       xml:id="cha-security-fips">
 <title>Enabling compliance with FIPS 140-2</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
     If your organization does any work for the United States federal
     government, it is likely that your cryptography applications (such
     as openSSL, GnuTLS, and OpenJDK) will be required to be in
     compliance with Federal Information Processing Standards (FIPS)
     140-2. FIPS 140-2 is a security accreditation program for validating
     cryptographic modules produced by private companies. If your
     organization is not required by compliance rules to run &sle; in
     FIPS mode, it is most likely best to not do it. This chapter
     provides guidance on enabling FIPS mode, and links to resources with
     detailed information.
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>

<sect1 xml:id="sec-fips-concept">
  <title>FIPS 140-2 overview</title>

  <warning>
    <title>FIPS requires expertise</title>
    <para>
      Administering FIPS is complex and requires significant expertise.
      Implementing it correctly, testing, and troubleshooting all require
      a high degree of knowledge.
    </para>
  </warning>

  <para>
    Every vendor that develops and maintains cryptographic applications, and
    wants them to be tested for FIPS compliance, must submit them to the
    Cryptographic Module Validation Program (CMVP) (see
    <link xlink:href="https://csrc.nist.gov/projects/cryptographic-module-validation-program"/>).
  </para>
  <para>
    There are currently two FIPS cryptographic standards, FIPS 140-2 and FIPS
    140-3. The FIPS 140-2 standard was finalized in 2002, and is valid until
    September 22, 2026. The FIPS 140-3 standard was approved in March 2019,
    and is replacing 140-2. CMVP is no longer accepting modules for
    FIPS 140-2 testing, but only FIPS 140-3.
  </para>
  <para>
    &suse; maintains a list of certified modules at
    <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/security/certifications/"/>, along with a lot of other useful information.
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="sec-fips-use-case">
  <title>When to enable FIPS mode</title>
  <para>
    The use case for enabling FIPS mode on &sle; is simple: run your
    server in FIPS mode it when it is required to meet compliance rules.
  </para>
  <para>
     When you are not required to meet compliance rules, running your systems
     in FIPS mode is most likely not a good idea. These are some of the reasons to not use FIPS mode:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        FIPS is restrictive. It enforces the use of specific validated
        cryptographic algorithms, and specific certified binaries that
        implement these validated algorithms. You must use only the certified
        binaries.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Upgrades may break functionality.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
         The approval process is very long, so certified binaries are always
         several releases behind the newest release.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Certified binaries, such as ssh, sshd, and sftp-server, run their own
        self-checks at startup, and run only when these checks succeed.
        This creates some small performance degradation.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Administering FIPS is complex and requires significant expertise.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="sec-fips-install">
  <title>Installing FIPS</title>
  <para>
    It is best to install the
    <package>patterns-base-fips</package> pattern on a new
    installation. Then, after the installation is complete, enable FIPS mode
    by running the steps in <xref linkend="sec-fips-enable"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
    You may install <package>patterns-base-fips</package>
    and enable FIPS mode on a running system, but then it is likely you will
    have to make adjustments, such as regenerating keys, and auditing your
    setup to ensure it is set up correctly.
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="sec-fips-enable">
  <title>Enabling FIPS mode</title>

<!-- The file paths for the two READMEs are different than in earlier
  releases. In SLE 15 SP2 and older the path is /usr/share/doc/packages/openssh/
  cschroder Jan 13, 2022 -->
<para>
  Enabling FIPS takes a few steps. First, read the
  <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/openssh/README.FIPS</filename> and
  <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/openssh/README.SUSE</filename>
  files, from the <package>openssh</package> package. These contain
  important information about FIPS on &sle;.
  </para>
  <para>
    Check if it is already enabled:
  </para>
  <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>sysctl -a | grep fips</command>
crypto.fips_enabled = 0</screen>
  <para>
  <literal>crypto.fips_enabled = 0</literal> indicates that it is not enabled. A return value of 1 means that it is enabled.
  </para>
  <para>
    Then edit <filename>/etc/default/grub</filename>. If
    <filename>/boot</filename> is not on a separate partition, add
    <literal>fips=1</literal> to
    <literal>GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX_DEFAULT</literal>, like the following
    example:
  </para>
  <screen>GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX_DEFAULT="splash=silent mitigations=auto quiet fips=1"</screen>
  <para>
    If <filename>/boot</filename> is on a separate partition, specify which
    partition, like the following example, substituting the name of your boot
    partition:
  </para>
  <screen>GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX_DEFAULT="splash=silent mitigations=auto quiet fips=1 boot=<replaceable>/dev/sda1"</replaceable></screen>
  <para>
    Save your changes, and rebuild your GRUB configuration and initramfs
    image (replace <replaceable>NAME</replaceable>
      with the name of the current initrd and
      <replaceable>KERNELVERSION</replaceable> with the currently running
      kernel):
  </para>
  <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>grub2-mkconfig -o /boot/grub2/grub.cfg</command>
&prompt.sudo;<command>mkinitrd</command></screen>
  <para>
  Reboot, then verify your changes. The following example shows that
  FIPS is enabled:
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>sysctl -a | grep fips</command>
crypto.fips_enabled = 1</screen>
  <para>
  After enabling FIPS it is possible that your system will not boot. If this
  happens, reboot to bring up the GRUB menu. Press <keycap>E</keycap> to edit
  your boot entry, and delete the <literal>fips</literal> entry from the
  <literal>linux</literal> line. Press the <keycap>F10</keycap> key to boot.
  This is a temporary change, and most likely the problem is an error in
  <filename>/etc/default/grub</filename>. Correct it, rebuild GRUB and
  initramfs, then reboot.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-fips-samba-cifs">
  <title>MD5 not supported in Samba/CIFS</title>
  <para>
   According to the FIPS standards, MD5 is not a secure hashing
   algorithm, and it must not be used for authentication. If you run a
   FIPS-compliant network environment, and you have clients or servers
   that run in FIPS-compliant mode, you must use a Kerberos service for
   authenticating Samba/CIFS users. This is necessary as all other Samba
   authentication modes include MD5.
  </para>
  <para>
   See the &samba; section of the &storage_guide; for more information on
   running a &samba; server.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
