<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!--PM's doc requirements:

 * AD configuration (m)

 * Active Directory integration (authentication and authorization, file access)
   (m)
   Plan for documentation integration with Likewise Enterprise (i)
   Document integration with Nautilus and file share access and writes (m)
     -> user must have group of /var/lib/samba/usershares
        -> don't know how to tell AD about this.
     -> net usershare add: cannot convert name "Everyone" to a SID.

 ===========================================================================

 * Time synchronization: -> in there (done)
 1.NTP in AD environment (d)
 2.Time sync troubleshooting (d)
 @maintainer: first topic could probably also be covered in net_xntp.xml -
 check with maintainer of that file where this would fit best

 ===========================================================================

 This is DONE.
 *  Server based automounting of home directories
 1.Configuration and usage description (m)
 2.Firewall configuration for SMB support (m)
 3.Kerberos support description (d)

 This is related to #300967: Mount Server Home Directory Automatically with
 Authentication.
 Everything that's being done there to ensure that the users will be able to
 access their home directories when hosted on CIFS.

@maintainer: not sure if the last issue needs to be covered here, most of it
    should probably go to net_samba.xml and maybe part of it to pam.xml
2010-09-02, ke: Mention this feature below (FIXME + fate#300967) and describe
    it in net_samba.xml.  Also check security_pam.xml.  DONE.

-->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.security.ad">
 <title>&ad; Support</title>
 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
          </dm:bugtracker>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <para>
  &ad;* (&ada;) is a directory-service based on LDAP, Kerberos, and
  other services. It is used by Microsoft&thrdmrk; Windows&thrdmrk; to manage
  resources, services, and people. In a Microsoft Windows network, &ad; provides
  information about these objects, restricts access to them, and enforces
  policies.
  &productnamereg; lets you join existing &ad; domains and integrate your
  Linux machine into a Windows environment.
 </para>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.security.ad.integrate">
  <title>Integrating Linux and &ad; Environments</title>

  <para>
   With a Linux client (configured as an &ad; client) that is
   joined to an existing &ad; domain, benefit from various
   features not available on a pure &productname; Linux client:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Browsing Shared Files and Directories with SMB</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      &nautilus; (previously called Nautilus) supports browsing shared resources
      through SMB.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Sharing Files and Directories with SMB</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      &nautilus; supports sharing directories and files as in Windows.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Accessing and Manipulating User Data on the Windows Server</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Through &nautilus;, users can access their Windows user data and
      can edit, create, and delete files and directories on the Windows
      server. Users can access their data without having to enter their
      password multiple times.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Offline Authentication</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Users can log in and access their local data on the Linux
      machine even if they are offline or the &ad; server is unavailable for
      other reasons.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Windows Password Change</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This port of &ad; support in Linux enforces corporate password policies
      stored in &ad;. The display managers and console support
      password change messages and accept your input. You can even use the
      Linux <command>passwd</command> command to set Windows passwords.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Single-Sign-On through Kerberized Applications</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <remark>sknorr, 2014-08-27: "kerberized"? can we avoid that?</remark>
      Many desktop applications are Kerberos-enabled
      (<emphasis>kerberized</emphasis>), which means they can transparently
      handle authentication for the user without the need for password
      reentry at Web servers, proxies, groupware applications, or other
      locations.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   The following section contains technical background for most of the
   previously named features.
   <phrase os="sled;osuse">For more information about file and
   printer sharing using &ad;, see <xref linkend="book.gnomeuser"/>.</phrase>
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.security.ad.background">
  <title>Background Information for Linux &ad; Support</title>

  <para>
   Many system components need to interact flawlessly to integrate
   a Linux client into an existing Windows &ad; domain.
   <xref linkend="fig.ad.schema"/> highlights the most prominent components
   in the case of Winbind-based &ad; authentication. The following sections
   focus on the underlying processes of the key events in &ad; server and
   client interaction.
  </para>

  <figure xml:id="fig.ad.schema">
   <title>Schema of Winbind-based &ad; Authentication</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="sled10_ad_schema.svg" width="60%" format="SVG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="sled10_ad_schema.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   To communicate with the directory service, the client needs to share at
   least two protocols with the server:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>LDAP</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      LDAP is a protocol optimized for managing directory information. A
      Windows domain controller with &ad; can use the LDAP protocol to
      exchange directory information with the clients. To learn more about
      LDAP in general and about the open source port of it, OpenLDAP, refer
      to <xref linkend="cha.security.ldap"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Kerberos</term>
    <listitem>
     <para> Kerberos is a third-party trusted authentication service.
            All its clients trust Kerberos's authorization of another
            client's identity, enabling kerberized single-sign-on (SSO)
            solutions. Windows supports a Kerberos implementation,
            making Kerberos SSO possible even with Linux clients. To
            learn more about Kerberos in Linux, refer to <xref
              linkend="cha.security.kerberos"/>. </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   Depending on which &yast; module you use to set up Kerberos authentication,
   different client components process account and authentication data:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Solutions Based on SSSD</term>
    <listitem>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The <systemitem class="daemon">sssd</systemitem> daemon is the
        central part of this solution. It handles all communication with the
        &ad; server.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        To gather name service information,
        <systemitem class="daemon">sssd_nss</systemitem> is used.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        To authenticate users, the
        <systemitem class="resource">pam_sss</systemitem> module for PAM
        is used. The creation of user homes for the &ad; users on the Linux
        client is handled by <filename>pam_mkhomedir</filename>.
       </para>
       <para>
        For more information about PAM, see <xref linkend="cha.pam"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Solution Based On Winbind (Samba)</term>
    <listitem>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The <systemitem class="daemon">winbindd</systemitem> daemon is the
        central part of this solution. It handles all communication with the
        &ad; server.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        To gather name service information,
        <systemitem class="daemon">nss_winbind</systemitem> is used.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        To authenticate users, the
        <systemitem class="resource">pam_winbind</systemitem> module for PAM
        is used. The creation of user homes for the &ad; users on the Linux
        client is handled by <filename>pam_mkhomedir</filename>.
       </para>
       <para>
        For more information about PAM, see <xref linkend="cha.pam"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   Applications that are PAM-aware, like the login routines and the &gnome;
   display manager, interact with the PAM and NSS layer to authenticate
   against the Windows server. Applications supporting Kerberos
   authentication (such as file managers, Web browsers, or e-mail clients)
   use the Kerberos credential cache to access user's Kerberos tickets,
   making them part of the SSO framework.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.ad.background.domain_join">
   <title>Domain Join</title>
   <para>
    During domain join, the server and the client establish a secure
    relation. On the client, the following tasks need to be performed to
    join the existing LDAP and Kerberos SSO environment provided by the
    Windows domain controller. The entire join process is handled by the
    &yast; Domain Membership module, which can be run during installation
    or in the installed system:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      The Windows domain controller providing both LDAP and KDC (Key
      Distribution Center) services is located.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      A machine account for the joining client is created in the directory
      service.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      An initial ticket granting ticket (TGT) is obtained for the client and
      stored in its local Kerberos credential cache. The client needs this
      TGT to get further tickets allowing it to contact other services, like
      contacting the directory server for LDAP queries.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      NSS and PAM configurations are adjusted to enable the client to
      authenticate against the domain controller.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    During client boot, the winbind daemon is started and retrieves the
    initial Kerberos ticket for the machine account. winbindd automatically
    refreshes the machine's ticket to keep it valid. To keep track of the
    current account policies, winbindd periodically queries the domain
    controller.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.ad.background.logon">
   <title>Domain Login and User Homes</title>
   <para>
    The login manager of &gnome; (GDM) has been extended to allow the handling
    of &ad; domain login. Users can choose to log in to the primary domain the
    machine has joined or to one of the trusted domains with which the
    domain controller of the primary domain has established a trust
    relationship.
   </para>
   <para>
    User authentication is mediated by several PAM modules as described
    in <xref linkend="sec.security.ad.background"/>. If there are errors, the
    error codes are translated into user-readable error messages that PAM
    gives at login through any of the supported methods (GDM, console, and
    SSH):
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>Password has expired</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The user sees a message stating that the password has expired and
       needs to be changed. The system prompts for a new password and
       informs the user if the new password does not comply with corporate
       password policies (for example the password is too short, too simple,
       or already in the history). If a user's password change fails, the
       reason is shown and a new password prompt is given.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>Account disabled</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The user sees an error message stating that the account has been
       disabled and to contact the system administrator.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>Account locked out</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The user sees an error message stating that the account has been
       locked and to contact the system administrator.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>Password has to be changed</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The user can log in but receives a warning that the password needs to
       be changed soon. This warning is sent three days before that password
       expires. After expiration, the user cannot log in.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>Invalid workstation</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       When a user is restricted to specific workstations and the current
       &productname; machine is not among them, a message appears that
       this user cannot log in from this workstation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>Invalid logon hours</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       When a user is only allowed to log in during working hours and tries
       to log in outside working hours, a message informs the user that
       logging in is not possible at that time.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>Account expired</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       An administrator can set an expiration time for a specific user
       account. If that user tries to log in after expiration, the user gets
       a message that the account has expired and cannot be used to log in.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    During a successful authentication, the client
    acquires a ticket granting ticket (TGT) from the Kerberos server of
    &ad; and stores it in the user's credential cache. It also
    renews the TGT in the background, requiring no user interaction.
   </para>
   <para>
    &productname; supports local home directories for &ad; users. If
    configured through &yast; as described in
    <xref linkend="sec.security.ad.config"/>, user home directories are
    created when a Windows/&ad; user first logs in to the Linux client. These
    home directories look and feel identical to standard Linux user home
    directories and work independently of the &ad; Domain Controller.
   </para>
   <para>
    Using a
    local user home, it is possible to access a user's data on this machine
    (even when the &ad; server is disconnected) as long as the Linux client
    has been configured to perform offline authentication.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.ad.background.offline">
   <title>Offline Service and Policy Support</title>
   <para>
    Users in a corporate environment must have the ability to become roaming
    users (for example, to switch networks or even work disconnected for
    some time). To enable users to log in to a disconnected machine,
    extensive caching was integrated into the winbind daemon. The winbind
    daemon enforces password policies even in the offline state. It tracks
    the number of failed login attempts and reacts according to the policies
    configured in &ad;. Offline support is disabled by default
    and must be explicitly enabled in the &yast; Domain Membership
    module.
   </para>
   <para>
    When the domain controller has become unavailable, the user can still
    access network resources (other than the &ad; server itself) with valid
    Kerberos tickets that have been acquired before losing the connection
    (as in Windows). Password changes cannot be processed unless the domain
    controller is online. While disconnected from the &ad; server, a user
    cannot access any data stored on this server. When a workstation has
    become disconnected from the network entirely and connects to the
    corporate network again later, &productname; acquires a new Kerberos
    ticket when the user has locked and unlocked the desktop (for
    example, using a desktop screen saver).
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.security.ad.config">
  <title>Configuring a Linux Client for &ad;</title>

  <para>
   Before your client can join an &ad; domain, some adjustments must be made
   to your network setup to ensure the flawless interaction of client and
   server.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>DNS</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Configure your client machine to use a DNS server that can forward DNS
      requests to the &ad; DNS server. Alternatively, configure your machine
      to use the &ad; DNS server as the name service data source.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>NTP</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To succeed with Kerberos authentication, the client must have its time
      set accurately. It is highly recommended to use a central NTP time
      server for this purpose (this can be also the NTP server running on
      your &ad; domain controller). If the clock skew between
      your Linux host and the domain controller exceeds a certain limit,
      Kerberos authentication fails and the client is logged in using the
      weaker NTLM (NT LAN Manager) authentication. For more details about
      using &ad; for time synchronization, see
      <xref linkend="proc.ad.join"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Firewall</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To browse your network neighborhood, either disable the firewall
      entirely or mark the interface used for browsing as part of the
      internal zone.
     </para>
     <para>
      <remark>sknorr, 2014-08-26: Should better be a procedure.</remark>
      To change the firewall settings on your client, log in as
      &rootuser; and start the &yast; firewall module. Select
      <guimenu>Interfaces</guimenu>. Select your network interface from the
      list of interfaces and click <guimenu>Change</guimenu>. Select
      <guimenu>Internal Zone</guimenu> and apply your settings with
      <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. Leave the firewall settings with <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Next</guimenu> <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> </menuchoice>. To
      disable the firewall, check the <guimenu>Disable Firewall Automatic
      Starting</guimenu> option, and leave the firewall module with
      <menuchoice> <guimenu>Next</guimenu> <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>&ad; Account</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      You cannot log in to an &ad; domain unless the &ad; administrator has
      provided you with a valid user account for that domain. Use the &ad;
      user name and password to log in to the &ad; domain from your Linux
      client.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.ad.configure.choose">
   <title>
    Choosing Which &yast; Module to Use for Connecting to &ad;
   </title>
   <para>
    &yast; contains multiple modules that allow connecting to an &ad;:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title><guimenu>User Logon Management</guimenu></title>
      <para>
       Use both an identity service (usually LDAP) and a user authentication
       service (usually Kerberos). This option is based on SSSD and in the
       majority of cases is best suited for joining &ad; domains.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <para>
      This module is described in the following in
      <xref linkend="sec.security.ad.sssd"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title><guimenu>Windows Domain Membership</guimenu></title>
      <para>
       Join an &ad; (which entails use of Kerberos and LDAP). This option is
       based on <command>winbind</command> and is best suited for joining an
       &ad; domain if support for NTLM or cross-forest trusts is necessary.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <para>
      This module is described in following in
      <xref linkend="sec.security.ad.winbind"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title><guimenu>LDAP and Kerberos Authentication</guimenu></title>
      <para>
       Allows setting up LDAP identities and Kerberos authentication
       independently from each other and provides fewer options. While this
       module also uses SSSD, it is not as well suited for connecting to &ad;
       as the previous two options.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <para>
      This module is described in
      <xref linkend="sec.security.auth.yast.client"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.ad.sssd">
   <title>
    Joining &ad; Using
    <guimenu>User Logon Management</guimenu>
   </title>
   <para>
    To join an &ad; domain using SSSD and the
    <guimenu>User Logon Management</guimenu> module of &yast;, proceed as
    follows:
   </para>

   <procedure xml:id="pro.security.ad.join.sssd">
    <title>
     Joining an &ad; Domain Using <guimenu>User Logon Management</guimenu>
    </title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Open &yast;.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To be able to use DNS auto-discovery later, set up the &ad; Domain
      Controller (the &ad; server) as the name server for your client.
     </para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>
        In &yast;, click <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Select <guimenu>Hostname/DNS</guimenu>, then enter the IP address of
        the &ad; Domain Controller into the text box <guimenu>Name Server
        1</guimenu>.
       </para>
       <para>
        Save the setting with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      From the &yast; main window, start the module <guimenu>User Logon
      Management</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <para>
      The module opens with an overview showing different network properties
      of your computer and the authentication method currently in use.
     </para>
     <figure xml:id="fig.security.logonmanagement">
      <title>Main Window of <guimenu>User Logon Management</guimenu></title>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="ad-overview.png" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="ad-overview.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <textobject role="description">
        <phrase>
         Overview window showing the computer name, IP address, and its
         authentication setting.
        </phrase>
       </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </figure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To start editing, click <guimenu>Change Settings</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Now join the domain.
     </para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>
        Click <guimenu>Join Domain</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        In the appearing dialog, specify the correct
        <guimenu>Domain name</guimenu>. Then specify the services to use for
        identity data and authentication: Select <guimenu>Microsoft Active
        Directory</guimenu> for both.
       </para>
       <para>
        Ensure that <guimenu>Enable the domain</guimenu> is activated.
       </para>
       <para>
        Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step performance="optional">
       <para>
        Usually, you can keep the default settings in the
        following dialog. However, there are reasons to make changes:
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <formalpara>
          <title>
           If the Local Host Name Does Not Match the Host Name Set on the
           Domain Controller
          </title>
          <para>
           <remark>
            FIXME: Do we need "hostname" or "hostname -f" in the following? As
            much as I saw from the UI of AD Administrative Center, it identified
            computers by their simple host name only. - sknorr, 2016-09-14
           </remark>
           Find out if the host name of your computer matches what the name
           your computer is known as to the &ad; Domain Controller. In a
           terminal, run the command <command>hostname</command>, then compare
           its output to the configuration of the &ad; Domain Controller.
          </para>
         </formalpara>
         <para>
          If the values differ, specify the host name from the &ad;
          configuration under <guimenu>AD hostname</guimenu>. Otherwise, leave
          the appropriate text box empty.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <formalpara>
          <title>If You Do Not Want to Use DNS Auto-Discovery</title>
          <para>
           Specify the <guimenu>Host names of Active Directory
           servers</guimenu> that you want to use. If there are multiple
           Domain Controllers, separate their host names with commas.
          </para>
         </formalpara>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
       <remark>
        Cache Credentials for Offline Use -> might be helpful for identity
        data but probably not possible or good for authentication. Right?
        Treat Users and Groups As Case Sensitive - use case? Read All
        Entities from Backend Database -- hguo mentioned this, and enabled it
        but mentioned it was not exactly necessary. - sknorr, 2016-09-14
       </remark>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        To continue, click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
       </para>
       <para>
        If not all software is installed already, the computer will now
        install missing software. It will then check whether the configured
        &ad; Domain Controller is available.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        If everything is correct, the following dialog should now show that
        it has discovered an <guimenu>Active Directory Server</guimenu> but
        that you are <guimenu>Not yet enrolled</guimenu>.
       </para>
       <para>
        In the dialog, specify the <guimenu>Username</guimenu> and
        <guimenu>Password</guimenu> of the &ad; administrator account
        (usually <literal>Administrator</literal>).
       </para>
       <para>
        To make sure that the current domain is enabled for Samba, activate
        <guimenu>Overwrite Samba configuration to work with this AD</guimenu>.
       </para>
       <para>
        To enroll, click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
       </para>
       <!-- FIXME: "enroll" v/ "join": which is better? -->
       <figure xml:id="fig.security.logonmanagement.enroll">
        <title>Enrolling into a Domain</title>
        <mediaobject>
         <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="ad-enroll.png" format="PNG"/>
         </imageobject>
         <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="ad-enroll.png" width="60%" format="PNG"/>
         </imageobject>
         <textobject role="description">
          <phrase></phrase>
         </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
       </figure>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        You should now see a message confirming that you have enrolled
        successfully. Finish with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      After enrolling, configure the client using the window
      <guimenu>Manage Domain User Logon</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <figure xml:id="fig.security.logonmanagement.configure">
      <title>Configuration Window of <guimenu>User Logon Management</guimenu></title>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="ad-config.png" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="ad-config.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <textobject role="description">
        <phrase></phrase>
       </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </figure>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>
        To allow logging in to the computer using login data provided by &ad;,
        activate <guimenu>Allow Domain User Logon</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step performance="optional">
       <para>
        Optionally, under <guimenu>Enable domain data source</guimenu>,
        activate additional data sources such as information on which users are
        allowed to use <command>sudo</command> or which network drives are
        available.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        To allow &ad; users to have home directories, activate
        <guimenu>Create Home Directories</guimenu>. The path for home
        directories can be set in multiple ways&mdash;on the client, on
        the server, or both ways:
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          To configure the home directory paths on the Domain Controller, set
          an appropriate value for the attribute
          <literal>UnixHomeDirectory</literal> for each user. Additionally,
          make sure that this attribute replicated to the global catalog. For
          information on achieving that under Windows, see
          <link xlink:href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/kb/248717"/>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          To configure home directory paths on the client in such a way that
          precedence will be given to the path set on the domain controller,
          use the option <literal>fallback_homedir</literal>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          To configure home directory paths on the client in such a way that
          the client setting will override the server setting, use
          <literal>override_homedir</literal>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
       <para>
        As settings on the Domain Controller are outside of the scope of this
        documentation, only the configuration of the client-side options will be
        described in the following.
       </para>
       <para>
        From the side bar, select
        <menuchoice><guimenu>Service Options</guimenu>
        <guimenu>Name switch</guimenu></menuchoice>, then click
        <guimenu>Extended Options</guimenu>. From that window, select either
        <literal>fallback_homedir</literal> or
        <literal>override_homedir</literal>, then click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
       </para>
       <para>
        Specify a value. To have home directories follow the format
        <filename>/home/<replaceable>USER_NAME</replaceable></filename>, use
        <literal>/home/%u</literal>.
        For more information about possible variables, see the man page
        <literal>sssd.conf</literal> (<command>man 5 sssd.conf</command>),
        section
        <citetitle>override_homedir</citetitle>.
       </para>
       <para>
        Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Save the changes by clicking <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. Then make sure that
      the values displayed now are correct. To leave the dialog, click
      <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.ad.winbind">
   <title>
    Joining &ad; Using
    <guimenu>Windows Domain Membership</guimenu>
   </title>
   <para>
    To join an &ad; domain using <command>winbind</command> and the
    <guimenu>Windows Domain Membership</guimenu> module of &yast;, proceed as
    follows:
   </para>

  <procedure xml:id="proc.ad.join">
   <title>
    Joining an &ad; Domain Using <guimenu>Windows Domain Membership</guimenu>
   </title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log in as &rootuser; and start &yast;.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start <menuchoice> <guimenu>Network Services</guimenu> <guimenu>Windows
     Domain Membership</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the domain to join at <guimenu>Domain or Workgroup</guimenu> in
     the <guimenu>Windows Domain Membership</guimenu> screen (see
     <xref linkend="fig.ad.smbclient"/>). If the DNS settings on your host
     are properly integrated with the Windows DNS server, enter the &ad;
     domain name in its DNS format
     (<literal>mydomain.mycompany.com</literal>). If you enter the short
     name of your domain (also known as the pre&ndash;Windows 2000 domain
     name), &yast; must rely on NetBIOS name resolution instead of DNS to
     find the correct domain controller.
<!-- 2010-02-05, toba: cannot find the Browse button in SLES 11 SP1,
     commenting out...

     To select from a list of available
     domains instead, use <guimenu>Browse</guimenu> to list the NetBIOS
     domains then select the desired domain.

     -->
    </para>
    <figure xml:id="fig.ad.smbclient">
     <title>Determining Windows Domain Membership</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="ad_sambaclient.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="ad_sambaclient.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To use the SMB source for Linux authentication, activate
     <guimenu>Also Use SMB Information for Linux Authentication</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To automatically create a local home directory for &ad; users on the
     Linux machine, activate <guimenu>Create Home Directory on
     Login</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Check <guimenu>Offline Authentication</guimenu> to allow your domain
     users to log in even if the &ad; server is temporarily unavailable, or if
     you do not have a network connection.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To change the UID and GID ranges for the Samba users and groups, select
     <guimenu>Expert Settings</guimenu>. Let DHCP retrieve
     the WINS server only if you need it. This is the case when some
     machines are resolved only by the WINS system.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Configure NTP time synchronization for your &ad; environment by selecting
     <guimenu>NTP Configuration</guimenu> and entering an appropriate server
     name or IP address. This step is obsolete if you have already entered
     the appropriate settings in the stand-alone &yast; NTP configuration
     module.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> and confirm the domain join when prompted
     for it.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Provide the password for the Windows administrator on the &ad; server and
     click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> (see <xref linkend="fig.ad.join1"/>).
    </para>
    <figure xml:id="fig.ad.join1">
     <title>Providing Administrator Credentials</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="ad_join1.png" width="30%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="ad_join1.png" width="30%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   After you have joined the &ad; domain, you can log in to it from your
   workstation using the display manager of your desktop or the console.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Domain Name</title>
   <para>
    Joining a domain may not succeed if the domain name ends with
    <literal>.local</literal>. Names ending in <literal>.local</literal>
    cause conflicts with Multicast DNS (MDNS) where
    <literal>.local</literal> is reserved for link-local host names.
   </para>
  </important>

  <note>
   <title>Only Administrators Can Enroll a Computer</title>
   <para>
    Only a domain administrator account, such as
    <literal>Administrator</literal>, can join &productname; into Active
    Directory.
   </para>
  </note>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.ad.connection">
   <title>Checking &ad; Connection Status</title>
   <para>
    To check whether you are successfully enrolled in an &ad; domain,
    use the following commands:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>klist</command> shows whether the current user has a valid
      Kerberos ticket.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>getent passwd</command> shows published LDAP data for all
      users.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.security.ad.login">
  <title>Logging In to an &ad; Domain</title>

  <para>
   Provided your machine has been configured to authenticate against Active
   Directory and you have a valid Windows user identity, you can log in to
   your machine using the &ad; credentials. Login is supported for &gnome;, the
   console, SSH, and any other PAM-aware application.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Offline Authentication</title>
   <para>
    &productname; supports offline authentication, allowing you to log in
    to your client machine even when it is offline. See
    <xref linkend="sec.security.ad.background.offline"/> for details.
   </para>
  </important>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.ad.login.gui">
   <title>GDM</title>
   <para>
    To authenticate a &gnome; client machine against an &ad; server, proceed as
    follows:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Not listed</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the text box <guimenu>Username</guimenu>,
      enter the domain name and the Windows user name in this form:
      <literal><replaceable>DOMAIN_NAME</replaceable>\<replaceable>USER_NAME</replaceable></literal>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Enter your Windows password.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    If configured to do so, &productname; creates a user home directory
    on the local machine on the first login of each user authenticated via &ad;.
    This allows you to benefit from the &ad; support of &productname; while
    still having a fully functional Linux machine at your disposal.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.ad.login.console">
   <title>Console Login</title>
   <para>
    Besides logging in to the &ad; client machine using a graphical front-end,
    you can log in using the text-based console or even remotely using SSH.
   </para>
   <para>
    To log in to your &ad; client from a console, enter
    <literal><replaceable>DOMAIN_NAME</replaceable>\<replaceable>USER_NAME</replaceable></literal>
    at the <literal>login:</literal> prompt and provide the password.
   </para>
   <para>
    To remotely log in to your &ad; client machine using SSH, proceed as
    follows:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      At the login prompt, enter:
     </para>
<screen>ssh <replaceable>DOMAIN_NAME</replaceable>\\<replaceable>USER_NAME</replaceable>@<replaceable>HOST_NAME</replaceable></screen>
     <para>
      The <literal>\</literal> domain and login delimiter is escaped with
      another <literal>\</literal> sign.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Provide the user's password.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.security.ad.passwd">
  <title>Changing Passwords</title>

  <para>
   &productname; helps the user choose a suitable new
   password that meets the corporate security policy. The underlying PAM
   module retrieves the current password policy settings from the domain
   controller, informing the user about the specific password quality
   requirements a user account typically has by means of a message on login.
   Like its Windows counterpart, &productname; presents a message
   describing:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Password history settings
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Minimum password length requirements
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Minimum password age
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Password complexity
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   The password change process cannot succeed unless all requirements have
   been successfully met. Feedback about the password status is given both
   through the display managers and the console.
  </para>

  <para>
   GDM provides feedback about password expiration and the prompt for new
   passwords in an interactive mode. To change passwords in the display
   managers, provide the password information when prompted.
  </para>

  <para>
   To change your Windows password, you can use the standard Linux utility,
   <command>passwd</command>, instead of having to manipulate this data on
   the server. To change your Windows password, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log in at the console.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter <literal>passwd</literal>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter your current password when prompted.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the new password.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Reenter the new password for confirmation. If your new password does
     not comply with the policies on the Windows server, this feedback is
     given to you and you are prompted for another password.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   To change your Windows password from the &gnome; desktop, proceed as
   follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the <guimenu>Computer</guimenu> icon on the left edge of the
     panel.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Control Center</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     From the <guimenu>Personal</guimenu> section, select
     <menuchoice><guimenu>About Me</guimenu> <guimenu>Change
     Password</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter your old password.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter and confirm the new password.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Leave the dialog with <guimenu>Close</guimenu> to apply your settings.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
