<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.security.firewall">
 <title>Masquerading and Firewalls</title>
 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
          </dm:bugtracker>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <indexterm>
 <primary>security</primary>
 <secondary>firewalls</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>firewalls</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>firewalls</primary>
 <secondary>packet filters</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>packet filters</primary>
 <see>firewalls</see></indexterm>
 <para>
  Whenever Linux is used in a network environment, you can use the kernel
  functions that allow the manipulation of network packets to maintain a
  separation between internal and external network areas. The Linux
  <systemitem>netfilter</systemitem> framework provides the means to
  establish an effective firewall that keeps different networks apart. With
  the help of iptables&mdash;a generic table structure for the definition
  of rule sets&mdash;precisely control the packets allowed to pass a
  network interface. Such a packet filter can be set up quite easily with
  the help of &susefirewall; and the corresponding &yast; module.
 </para><indexterm>
 <primary>firewalls</primary>
 <secondary>&susefirewall;</secondary></indexterm>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.security.firewall.iptables">
  <title>Packet Filtering with iptables</title>

  <para>
   The components <systemitem>netfilter</systemitem> and
   <systemitem>iptables</systemitem> are responsible for the filtering and
   manipulation of network packets and for network address
   translation (NAT). The filtering criteria and any actions associated with
   them are stored in chains, which must be matched one after another by
   individual network packets as they arrive. The chains to match are stored
   in tables. The <command>iptables</command> command allows you to alter
   these tables and rule sets.
  </para>

  <para>
   The Linux kernel maintains three tables, each for a particular category
   of functions of the packet filter:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>filter</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This table holds the bulk of the filter rules, because it implements
      the <emphasis>packet filtering</emphasis> mechanism in the stricter
      sense, which determines whether packets are let through
      (<literal>ACCEPT</literal>) or discarded (<literal>DROP</literal>),
      for example.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>nat</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This table defines any changes to the source and target addresses of
      packets. Using these functions also allows you to implement
      <emphasis>masquerading</emphasis>, which is a special case of NAT used
      to link a private network with the Internet.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>mangle</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The rules held in this table make it possible to manipulate values
      stored in IP headers (such as the type of service).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   These tables contain several predefined chains to match packets:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>PREROUTING</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This chain is applied to incoming packets.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>INPUT</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This chain is applied to packets destined for the system's internal
      processes.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>FORWARD</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This chain is applied to packets that are only routed through the
      system.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>OUTPUT</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This chain is applied to packets originating from the system itself.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>POSTROUTING</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This chain is applied to all outgoing packets.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   <xref linkend="fig.fire.table"/> illustrates the paths along which a
   network packet may travel on a given system. For the sake of simplicity,
   the figure lists tables as parts of chains, but in reality these chains
   are held within the tables themselves.
  </para>

  <para>
   In the simplest case, an incoming packet destined for the system itself
   arrives at the <literal>eth0</literal> interface. The packet is first
   referred to the <literal>PREROUTING</literal> chain of the
   <literal>mangle</literal> table then to the <literal>PREROUTING</literal>
   chain of the <literal>nat</literal> table. The following step, concerning
   the routing of the packet, determines that the actual target of the
   packet is a process of the system itself. After passing the
   <literal>INPUT</literal> chains of the <literal>mangle</literal> and the
   <literal>filter</literal> table, the packet finally reaches its target,
   provided that the rules of the <literal>filter</literal> table are
   actually matched.
  </para>

  <figure xml:id="fig.fire.table">
   <title>iptables: A Packet's Possible Paths</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata width="75%" fileref="fire_tables.svg" format="SVG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata width="65%" fileref="fire_tables.png" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.security.firewall.masq">
  <title>Masquerading Basics</title><indexterm>

  <primary>routing</primary>

  <secondary>masquerading</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>masquerading</primary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>IP addresses</primary>

  <secondary>masquerading</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>NAT</primary>

  <see>masquerading</see></indexterm>

  <para>
   Masquerading is the Linux-specific form of NAT (network address
   translation). It can be used to connect a small LAN (where hosts use IP
   addresses from the private range&mdash;see
   <xref linkend="sec.basicnet.addresses.route"/>) with the Internet (where
   official IP addresses are used). For the LAN hosts to be able to connect
   to the Internet, their private addresses are translated to an official
   one. This is done on the router, which acts as the gateway between the
   LAN and the Internet. The underlying principle is a simple one: The
   router has more than one network interface, typically a network card and
   a separate interface connecting with the Internet. While the latter links
   the router with the outside world, one or several others link it with the
   LAN hosts. With these hosts in the local network connected to the network
   card (such as <literal>eth0</literal>) of the router, they can send any
   packets not destined for the local network to their default gateway or
   router.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Using the Correct Network Mask</title>
   <para>
    When configuring your network, make sure both the broadcast address and
    the netmask are the same for all local hosts. Failing to do so prevents
    packets from being routed properly.
   </para>
  </important>

  <para>
   As mentioned, whenever one of the LAN hosts sends a packet destined for
   an Internet address, it goes to the default router. However, the router
   must be configured before it can forward such packets. For security
   reasons, this is not enabled in a default installation. To enable it, set
   the variable <systemitem>IP_FORWARD</systemitem> in the file
   <filename>/etc/sysconfig/sysctl</filename> to
   <systemitem>IP_FORWARD=yes</systemitem>.
  </para>

  <para>
   The target host of the connection can see your router, but knows nothing
   about the host in your internal network where the packets originated.
   This is why the technique is called masquerading. Because of the address
   translation, the router is the first destination of any reply packets.
   The router must identify these incoming packets and translate their
   target addresses, so packets can be forwarded to the correct host in the
   local network.
  </para>

  <para>
   With the routing of inbound traffic depending on the masquerading table,
   there is no way to open a connection to an internal host from the
   outside. For such a connection, there would be no entry in the table. In
   addition, any connection already established has a status entry assigned
   to it in the table, so the entry cannot be used by another connection.
  </para>

  <para>
   As a consequence of all this, you might experience some problems with a
   number of application protocols, such as ICQ, cucme, IRC (DCC, CTCP), and
   FTP (in PORT mode). Web browsers, the standard FTP program, and many
   other programs use the PASV mode. This passive mode is much less
   problematic as far as packet filtering and masquerading are concerned.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.security.firewall.fw">
  <title>Firewalling Basics</title><indexterm>

  <primary>firewalls</primary>

  <secondary>packet filters</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   <emphasis>Firewall</emphasis> is probably the term most widely used to
   describe a mechanism that provides and manages a link between networks
   while also controlling the data flow between them. Strictly speaking, the
   mechanism described in this section is called a <emphasis>packet
   filter</emphasis>. A packet filter regulates the data flow according to
   certain criteria, such as protocols, ports, and IP addresses. This allows
   you to block packets that, according to their addresses, are not supposed
   to reach your network. To allow public access to your Web server, for
   example, explicitly open the corresponding port. However, a packet filter
   does not scan the contents of packets with legitimate addresses, such as
   those directed to your Web server. For example, if incoming packets were
   intended to compromise a CGI program on your Web server, the packet
   filter would still let them through.
  </para>

  <para>
   A more effective but more complex mechanism is the combination of several
   types of systems, such as a packet filter interacting with an application
   gateway or proxy. In this case, the packet filter rejects any packets
   destined for disabled ports. Only packets directed to the application
   gateway are accepted. This gateway or proxy pretends to be the actual
   client of the server. In a sense, such a proxy could be considered a
   masquerading host on the protocol level used by the application. One
   example for such a proxy is Squid, an HTTP and FTP proxy server. To use
   Squid, the browser must be configured to communicate via the proxy. Any
   HTTP pages or FTP files requested are served from the proxy cache and
   objects not found in the cache are fetched from the Internet by the
   proxy.
  </para>

  <para>
   The following section focuses on the packet filter that comes with
   &productname;. For further information about packet filtering and
   firewalling, read the Firewall HOWTO included in the
   <systemitem class="resource">howto</systemitem> package. If this package
   is installed, read the HOWTO with
  </para>

<screen>less /usr/share/doc/howto/en/txt/Firewall-HOWTO.gz</screen>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.security.firewall.SuSE">
  <title>&susefirewall;</title><indexterm>

  <primary>firewalls</primary>

  <secondary>&susefirewall;</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>masquerading</primary>

  <secondary>configuring with &susefirewall;</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   &susefirewall; is a script that reads the variables set in
   <filename>/etc/sysconfig/&susefirewallfiles;</filename> to generate a
   set of iptables rules. It defines three security zones, although only the
   first and the second one are considered in the following sample
   configuration:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>External Zone</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Given that there is no way to control what is happening on the
      external network, the host needs to be protected from it. In most
      cases, the external network is the Internet, but it could be another
      insecure network, such as a Wi-Fi.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Internal Zone</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This refers to the private network, usually the LAN. If the
      hosts on this network use IP addresses from the private range (see
      <xref linkend="sec.basicnet.addresses.route"/>), enable network
      address translation (NAT), so hosts on the internal network can access
      the external one. All ports are open in the internal zone. The main
      benefit of putting interfaces into the internal zone (rather than
      stopping the firewall) is that the firewall still runs, so when you
      add new interfaces, they will be put into the external zone by
      default. That way an interface is not accidentally <quote>open</quote>
      by default.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Demilitarized Zone (DMZ)</guimenu></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      While hosts located in this zone can be reached both from the external
      and the internal network, they cannot access the internal network
      themselves. This setup can be used to put an additional line of
      defense in front of the internal network, because the DMZ systems are
      isolated from the internal network.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   Any kind of network traffic not explicitly allowed by the filtering rule
   set is suppressed by iptables. Therefore, each of the interfaces with
   incoming traffic must be placed into one of the three zones. For each of
   the zones, define the services or protocols allowed. The rule set is only
   applied to packets originating from remote hosts. Locally generated
   packets are not captured by the firewall.
  </para>

  <para>
   The configuration can be performed with &yast; (see
   <xref linkend="sec.security.firewall.SuSE.yast"/>). It can also be made
   manually in the file
   <filename>/etc/sysconfig/&susefirewallfiles;</filename>, which is well
   commented. Additionally, several example scenarios are available in
   <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/&susefirewallfiles;/EXAMPLES</filename>.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.firewall.SuSE.yast">
   <title>Configuring the Firewall with &yast;</title>
   <para>
    The &yast; dialogs for the graphical configuration can be accessed
    from the &yast; control center. Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Security
    and Users</guimenu> <guimenu>Firewall</guimenu></menuchoice>. The
    configuration is divided into seven sections that can be accessed
    directly from the tree structure on the left side.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Start-Up</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Set the start-up behavior in this dialog. In a default installation,
       &susefirewall; is started automatically. You can also start and
       stop the firewall here. To implement your new settings in a running
       firewall, use <guimenu>Save Settings and Restart Firewall
       Now</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Interfaces</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       All known network interfaces are listed here. To remove an interface
       from a zone, select the interface, press <guimenu>Change</guimenu>,
       and choose <guimenu>No Zone Assigned</guimenu>. To add an interface
       to a zone, select the interface, press <guimenu>Change</guimenu> and
       choose any of the available zones. You may also create a special
       interface with your own settings by using <guimenu>Custom</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Allowed Services</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       You need this option to offer services from your system to a zone
       from which it is protected. By default, the system is only protected
       from external zones. Explicitly allow the services that should be
       available to external hosts. After selecting the desired zone in
       <guimenu>Allowed Services for Selected Zone</guimenu>, activate the
       services from the list.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Masquerading</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Masquerading hides your internal network from external networks (such
       as the Internet) while enabling hosts in the internal network to
       access the external network transparently. Requests from the external
       network to the internal one are blocked and requests from the
       internal network seem to be issued by the masquerading server when
       seen externally. If special services of an internal machine need to
       be available to the external network, add special redirect rules for
       the service.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Broadcast</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In this dialog, configure the UDP ports that allow broadcasts. Add
       the required port numbers or services to the appropriate zone,
       separated by spaces. See also the file
       <filename>/etc/services</filename>.
      </para>
      <para>
       The logging of broadcasts that are not accepted can be enabled here.
       This may be problematic, because Windows hosts use broadcasts to know
       about each other and so generate many packets that are not accepted.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>IPsec Support</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Configure whether the IPsec service should be available to the
       external network in this dialog. Configure which packets are trusted
       under <guimenu>Details</guimenu>.
      </para>
      <para>
       There is another functionality under <guimenu>Details</guimenu>:
       IPsec packets are packed in an encrypted format, so they need to be
       decrypted and you can configure the way the firewall will handle the
       decrypted packets. If you select <guimenu>Internal Zone</guimenu>,
       the decrypted IPsec packets will be trusted as if they came from the
       Internal Zone - although they could possibly come from the external
       one. Choose <guimenu>Same Zone as Original Source Network</guimenu>
       to avoid this situation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Logging Level</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       There are two rules for logging: accepted and not accepted packets.
       Packets that are not accepted are DROPPED or REJECTED. Select from
       <guimenu>Log All</guimenu>, <guimenu>Log Only Critical</guimenu>, or
       <guimenu>Do Not Log Any</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><guimenu>Custom Rules</guimenu></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Here, set special firewall rules that allow connections, matching
       specified criteria such as source network, protocol, destination
       port, and source port. Configure such rules for external, internal,
       and demilitarized zones.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    When finished with the firewall configuration, exit this dialog with
    <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. A zone-oriented summary of your firewall
    configuration then opens. In it, check all settings. All services,
    ports, and protocols that have been allowed and all custom rules are
    listed in this summary. To modify the configuration, use
    <guimenu>Back</guimenu>. Press <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> to save your
    configuration.
   </para>
   
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.security.firewall.SuSE.yast.ports">
    <title>Opening Ports</title>
    <para> In case your network interfaces are located in a firewall
          zone where network traffic is blocked on most ports, services
          that manage their network traffic via a blocked por, will not
          work. A commonly used service is for example SSH, which uses
          port 22, which is blocked by default on interfaces located in
          the external or demilitarized zone. To make SSH work, you need
          to open port 22 in the firewall configuration. This can be
          done with the &yast; module <guimenu>Firewall</guimenu>. </para>

    <figure>
     <title>Firewall Configuration: Allowed Services</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="y2_firewall_allowed_services.png" width="75%" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="y2_firewall_allowed_services.png" width="75%" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <important>
     <title>Automatic Firewall Configuration</title>
     <para> After the installation, &yast; automatically starts a
            firewall on all configured interfaces. If a server is
            configured and activated on the system, &yast; can modify
            the automatically generated firewall configuration with the
            options <guimenu>Open Ports on Selected Interface in
              Firewall</guimenu> or <guimenu>Open Ports on
              Firewall</guimenu> in the server configuration modules.
            Some server module dialogs include a <guimenu>Firewall
              Details</guimenu> button for activating additional
            services and ports. The &yast; firewall configuration module
            can be used to activate, deactivate, or reconfigure the
            firewall. </para>
    </important>

    <procedure>
     <title>Manually Open Firewall Ports with &yast;</title>
     <step>
      <para>
       Open <menuchoice> <guimenu>&yast;</guimenu> <guimenu>Security and
       Users</guimenu> <guimenu>Firewall</guimenu></menuchoice> and switch to
       the <guimenu>Allowed Services</guimenu> tab. 
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select a zone at <guimenu>Allow Services for Selected Zone</guimenu> in
       which to open the port. It is not possible to open a port for several
       zones at once.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select a service from <guimenu>Service to Allow</guimenu> and choose
       <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to add it to the list of <guimenu>Allowed
       Services</guimenu>. The port this service uses will be unblocked. 
      </para>
      <para>
       In case your service is not listed, you need to manually specify the
       port(s) to unblock. Choose <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> to open a dialog
       where you can specify TCP, UPD, RPC ports and IP
       protocols. Refer to the help section in this dialog for details.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Choose <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to display a summary of your
       changes. Modify them by choosing <guimenu>Back</guimenu> or apply them
       by choosing <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
   
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.firewall.SuSE.man">
   <title>Configuring Manually</title>
   <para>
    The following paragraphs provide step-by-step instructions for a
    successful configuration. Each configuration item is marked as to
    whether it is relevant to firewalling or masquerading. Use port range
    (for example, <literal>500:510</literal>) whenever appropriate. Aspects
    related to the DMZ (demilitarized zone) as mentioned in the
    configuration file are not covered here. They are applicable only to a
    more complex network infrastructure found in larger organizations
    (corporate networks), which require extensive configuration and in-depth
    knowledge about the subject.
   </para>
   <para>
    To enable &susefirewall;, use <command>sudo systemctl enable
    &susefirewallfiles;</command> or use the &yast; module
    &ycc_runlevel;.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><systemitem>FW_DEV_EXT</systemitem> (firewall, masquerading) </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The device linked to the Internet. For a modem connection, enter
       <literal>ppp0</literal>. DSL connections use <literal>dsl0</literal>.
       Specify <literal>auto</literal> to use the interface that corresponds
       to the default route.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><systemitem>FW_DEV_INT</systemitem> (firewall, masquerading) </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The device linked to the internal, private network (such as
       <literal>eth0</literal>). Leave this blank if there is no internal
       network and the firewall protects only the host on which it runs.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><systemitem>FW_ROUTE</systemitem> (firewall, masquerading) </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If you need the masquerading function, set this to
       <literal>yes</literal>. Your internal hosts will not be visible to
       the outside, because their private network addresses (e.g.,
       <literal>192.168.x.x</literal>) are ignored by Internet routers.
      </para>
      <para>
       For a firewall without masquerading, set this to
       <literal>yes</literal> if you want to allow access to the internal
       network. Your internal hosts need to use officially registered IP
       addresses in this case. Normally, however, you should
       <emphasis>not</emphasis> allow access to your internal network from
       the outside.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><systemitem>FW_MASQUERADE</systemitem> (masquerading) </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Set this to <literal>yes</literal> if you need the masquerading
       function. This provides a virtually direct connection to the Internet
       for the internal hosts. It is more secure to have a proxy server
       between the hosts of the internal network and the Internet.
       Masquerading is not needed for services that a proxy server provides.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><systemitem>FW_MASQ_NETS</systemitem> (masquerading) </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Specify the hosts or networks to masquerade, leaving a space between
       the individual entries. For example:
      </para>
<screen>FW_MASQ_NETS="192.168.0.0/24 192.168.10.1"</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><systemitem>FW_PROTECT_FROM_INT</systemitem> (firewall) </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Set this to <literal>yes</literal> to protect your firewall host from
       attacks originating in your internal network. Services are only
       available to the internal network if explicitly enabled. Also see
       <systemitem>FW_SERVICES_INT_TCP</systemitem> and
       <systemitem>FW_SERVICES_INT_UDP</systemitem>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><systemitem>FW_SERVICES_EXT_TCP</systemitem> (firewall) </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Enter the TCP ports that should be made available. Leave this blank
       for a normal workstation at home that should not offer any services.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><systemitem>FW_SERVICES_EXT_UDP</systemitem> (firewall) </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Leave this blank unless you run a UDP service and want to make it
       available to the outside. The services that use UDP include DNS
       servers, IPsec, TFTP, DHCP and others. In that case, enter the UDP
       ports to use.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
<!-- fate#100068 -->
     <term><systemitem>FW_SERVICES_ACCEPT_EXT</systemitem> (firewall) </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       List services to allow from the Internet. This is a more generic form
       of the <systemitem>FW_SERVICES_EXT_TCP</systemitem> and
       <systemitem>FW_SERVICES_EXT_UDP</systemitem> settings, and more
       specific than <systemitem>FW_TRUSTED_NETS</systemitem>. The notation
       is a space-separated list of
       <option><replaceable>net</replaceable>,<replaceable>protocol</replaceable>[,<replaceable>dport</replaceable>][,<replaceable>sport</replaceable>]</option>,
       for example <literal>0/0,tcp,22</literal> or
       <literal>0/0,tcp,22,,hitcount=3,blockseconds=60,recentname=ssh</literal>,
       which means: allow a maximum of three SSH connects per minute from
       one IP address.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><systemitem>FW_SERVICES_INT_TCP</systemitem> (firewall) </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       With this variable, define the services available for the internal
       network. The notation is the same as for
       <systemitem>FW_SERVICES_EXT_TCP</systemitem>, but the settings are
       applied to the <emphasis>internal</emphasis> network. The variable
       only needs to be set if <systemitem>FW_PROTECT_FROM_INT</systemitem>
       is set to <literal>yes</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><systemitem>FW_SERVICES_INT_UDP</systemitem> (firewall) </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       See <systemitem>FW_SERVICES_INT_TCP</systemitem>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
<!-- fate#100068 -->
     <term><systemitem>FW_SERVICES_ACCEPT_INT</systemitem> (firewall) </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       List services to allow from internal hosts. See
       <systemitem>FW_SERVICES_ACCEPT_EXT.</systemitem>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
<!-- Bug 380696 -->
<!-- 11.0 -->
     <term><systemitem>FW_SERVICES_ACCEPT_RELATED_*</systemitem> (firewall) </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This is how the &susefirewall; implementation considers packets
       <literal>RELATED</literal> by netfilter.
      </para>
      <para>
       For example, to allow finer grained filtering of Samba broadcast
       packets, <literal>RELATED</literal> packets are not accepted
       unconditionally. Variables starting with
       <systemitem>FW_SERVICES_ACCEPT_RELATED_</systemitem> allow
       restricting <literal>RELATED</literal> packets handling to certain
       networks, protocols and ports.
      </para>
      <para>
       This means that adding connection tracking modules (conntrack
       modules) to <systemitem>FW_LOAD_MODULES</systemitem> does not
       automatically result in accepting the packets tagged by those
       modules. Additionally, you must set variables starting with
       <systemitem>FW_SERVICES_ACCEPT_RELATED_</systemitem> to a suitable
       value.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><systemitem>FW_CUSTOMRULES</systemitem> (firewall)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Uncomment this variable to install custom rules. Find examples in
       <filename>/etc/sysconfig/scripts/&susefirewallfiles;-custom</filename>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    <indexterm>
    <primary>log files</primary>
    <secondary>messages</secondary>
    </indexterm> After configuring the firewall, test your setup. The
    firewall rule sets are created by entering <command>systemctl start
    &susefirewallfiles;</command> as
    <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>. Then use
    <command>telnet</command>, for example, from an external host to see
    whether the connection is actually denied. After that, review the output
    of <command>journalctl</command> (see <xref linkend="cha.journalctl"/>),
    where you should see something like this:
   </para>
<screen>Mar 15 13:21:38 linux kernel: SFW2-INext-DROP-DEFLT IN=eth0
OUT= MAC=00:80:c8:94:c3:e7:00:a0:c9:4d:27:56:08:00 SRC=192.168.10.0
DST=192.168.10.1 LEN=60 TOS=0x10 PREC=0x00 TTL=64 ID=15330 DF PROTO=TCP
SPT=48091 DPT=23 WINDOW=5840 RES=0x00 SYN URGP=0
OPT (020405B40402080A061AFEBC0000000001030300)</screen>
   <para>
    Other packages to test your firewall setup are Nmap (portscanner) or
    OpenVAS (Open Vulnerability Assessment System). The documentation of
    Nmap is found at <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/nmap</filename> after
    installing the package and the documentation of openVAS resides at
    <link xlink:href="http://www.openvas.org"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.security.firewall.info">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   The most up-to-date information and other documentation about the
   <systemitem>&susefirewall;</systemitem> package is found in
   <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/&susefirewallfiles;</filename>. The
   home page of the netfilter and iptables project,
   <link xlink:href="http://www.netfilter.org"/>, provides a large
   collection of documents in many languages.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
