<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!--
 Contact:
 - Howard Guo <hguo@suse.de>

-->
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0" xml:id="sec.security.yastvpn">
 <title>Setting Up a VPN Server or Client Using &yast;</title>

 <para>
  Using &yast;, you can also set up a VPN server. However, the &yast; module
  does not support OpenVPN. Instead, it provides support for the IPsec protocol
  (as implemented in the software
  <phrase role="productname">StrongSwan</phrase>). Similarly to OpenVPN, IPsec
  is widely supported VPN scheme.
 </para>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.security.yastvpn.server">
  <title>Setting Up the Server</title>

  <procedure xml:id="pro.security.yastvpn.server">
   <title>Setting Up an IPsec Server</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     To start the &yast; VPN module, select
     <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
     <guimenu>VPN Gateways and Clients</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Under <guimenu>Global Configuration</guimenu>, activate
     <guimenu>Enable VPN Daemon</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To create a new VPN, click <guimenu>New VPN</guimenu>, then enter a name
     for the connection.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Under <guimenu>Type</guimenu>, select <guimenu>Gateway (Server)</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Then choose the scenario:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The scenarios <guimenu>Secure communication with a pre-shared
       key</guimenu> and <guimenu>Secure communication with a
       certificate</guimenu> are best suited to Linux client setups.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The scenario <guimenu>Provide access to Android, iOS, Mac OS X
       clients</guimenu> sets up a configuration that is natively supported by
       modern of Android, iOS, and macOS. It is based on a pre-shared key setup
       with an additional user name and password authentication.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The scenario <guimenu>Provide access to Windows 7, Windows 8
       clients</guimenu> is a configuration that is natively supported by
       Windows and Blackberry devices. It is based on a certificate setup
       with an additional user name and password authentication.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     For this example, choose <guimenu>Secure communication with a pre-shared
     key</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To specify the key, click <guimenu>Edit Credentials</guimenu>. Activate
     <guimenu>Show key</guimenu>, then type the secret key. Confirm with
     <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Choose whether and how to limit access within your VPN under
     <guimenu>Provide VPN clients access to</guimenu>. To enable only certain
     IP ranges, specify these in CIDR format, separated by commas in
     <guimenu>Limited CIDRs</guimenu>. For more information about the CIDR
     format, see
     <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classless_Inter-Domain_Routing"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Under <guimenu>Clients' address pool</guimenu>, specify the format of IP
     addresses your VPN should provide to its clients.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To finish, click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. The &yast; VPN module will now
     automatically add and enable firewall rules to allow clients to connect to
     the new VPN.
    </para>
    <para>
      To view the connection status,
     in the following confirmation window, click <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>.
     You will then see the output of
     <command>systemctl status</command> for your VPN which allows you to check
     if the VPN is running and configured correctly.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
