<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.0" xml:id="cha-security-freeradius">
 <title>Setting up a freeRADIUS server</title>
 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
        </dm:bugtracker>
	<dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <para>
        The RADIUS (Remote Authentication Dial-In User Service) protocol has 
        long been a standard service for manage network access. It provides 
        authentication, authorization, and accounting (AAA) for very 
        large businesses such as Internet service providers and cellular 
        network providers, and is also popular for small networks. It 
        authenticates users and devices, authorizes those users and
        devices for certain network services, and tracks use of services for
        billing and auditing. You do not have to use all three of the AAA 
        protocols, but only the ones you need. For example, you may not need 
        accounting but only client authentication, or perhaps all you want is accounting, and client authorization is managed by something else.
    </para>
    <para>
        It is extremely efficient and manages thousands of requests on modest 
        hardware. Of course, it works for all network protocols and not just 
        dial-up, but the name remains the same.
    </para>
    <para>
        RADIUS operates in a distributed architecture, sitting separately 
        from the Network Access Server (NAS). User access data is stored on a 
        central RADIUS server that is available to multiple NAS. The NAS 
        provide the physical access to the network, such as a managed 
        Ethernet switch, or wireless access point.
    </para>
    <para>
        FreeRADIUS is the open source RADIUS implementation, and is the most 
        widely-used RADIUS server. In this chapter you will learn how to 
        install and test a FreeRADIUS server. Because of the numerous 
        possible use cases, after your initial setup is working correctly 
        your next stop is the official documentation,
        which is detailed and thorough (see
        <link xlink:href="https://freeradius.org/documentation/"/>).
    </para>
  <sect1 xml:id="sec-test-radiusd">
    <title>Installation and testing on &sle;</title>
    <para>
        The following steps set up a simple test system. When you have 
        verified that the server is operating correctly and you are ready to 
        create a production configuration, you will have several undo steps 
        to perform before starting your production configuration.
    </para>
    <para>
        First install the <systemitem class="resource">freeradius-server</systemitem> and 
        <systemitem class="resource">freeradius-server-utils</systemitem> 
        packages. Then enter <filename>/etc/raddb/certs</filename> and run 
        the <filename>bootstrap</filename> script to create a set of test 
        certificates:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.root;<command>zypper in freeradius-server freeradius-server-utils</command>
&prompt.root;<command>cd /etc/raddb/certs</command>
&prompt.root;<command>./bootstrap</command></screen>
    <para>
        The README in the <filename>certs</filename> directory contains a 
        great deal of useful information. When the 
        <filename>bootstrap</filename> script has completed, start the server
        in debugging mode:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.root;<command>radiusd -X</command>
[...]
Listening on auth address * port 1812 bound to server default
Listening on acct address * port 1813 bound to server default
Listening on auth address :: port 1812 bound to server default
Listening on acct address :: port 1813 bound to server default
Listening on auth address 127.0.0.1 port 18120 bound to server inner-tunnel
Listening on proxy address * port 54435
Listening on proxy address :: port 58415
Ready to process requests
</screen>

    <para>
        When you see the "Listening" and "Ready to process requests" lines, 
        your server has started correctly. If it does not start, read the 
        output carefully because it tells you what went wrong. You may direct 
        the output to a text file with <command>tee</command>:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.user;<command>radiusd -X | tee radiusd.text</command></screen>
    <para>
        The next step is to test authentication with a test client and user.
        The client is a client of the RADIUS server, such as a wireless 
        access point or switch. Clients are configured in
        <filename>/etc/raddb/client.conf</filename>. Human users are 
        configured in 
        <filename>/etc/raddb/mods-config/files/authorize</filename>.
    </para>
    <para>
        Open
        <filename>/etc/raddb/mods-config/files/authorize</filename> and 
        uncomment the following lines:
    </para>
        <screen>bob   Cleartext-Password := "hello"
Reply-Message := "Hello, %{User-Name}" </screen>
    <para>
        A test client, <literal>client localhost</literal>, is provided in
        <filename>/etc/raddb/client.conf</filename>, with a secret of
        <literal>testing123</literal>. Open a second terminal, and as an
        unprivileged user use the <command>radtest</command> command to log 
        in as bob:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.user;<command>radtest bob hello 127.0.0.1 0 testing123</command>
Sent Access-Request Id 241 from 0.0.0.0:35234 to 127.0.0.1:1812 length 73
        User-Name = "bob"
        User-Password = "hello"
        NAS-IP-Address = 127.0.0.1
        NAS-Port = 0
        Message-Authenticator = 0x00
        Cleartext-Password = "hello"
Received Access-Accept Id 241 from 127.0.0.1:1812 to 0.0.0.0:0 length 20
</screen>
    <para>
        In your <literal>radius -X</literal> terminal, a successful login looks
        like this:
    </para>
    <screen>(3) pap: Login attempt with password
(3) pap: Comparing with "known good" Cleartext-Password
(3) pap: User authenticated successfully
(3)     [pap] = ok
[...]
(3) Sent Access-Accept Id 241 from 127.0.0.1:1812 to 127.0.0.1:35234 length 0
(3) Finished request
Waking up in 4.9 seconds.
(3) Cleaning up request packet ID 241 with timestamp +889
</screen>
    <para>
        Now run one more login test from a different computer on your 
        network. Create a client configuration on your server by uncommenting 
        and modifying the following entry in 
        <filename>clients.conf</filename>, using the IP address of your test
        machine:
    </para>
    <screen>client private-network-1 }
  ipaddr          = <replaceable>192.0.2.0/24</replaceable>
  secret          = testing123-1
  {
  </screen>

    <para>
        On the client machine, install 
        <systemitem class="resource">freeradius-server-utils</systemitem>. Try logging in from the client as <literal>bob</literal>, using the <command>radtest</command> command. It 
        is better to use the IP address of the RADIUS server rather than the 
        hostname because it is faster:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.user;<command>radtest bob hello &wsIip; 0 testing123-1</command>
        </screen>

    <para>
        If your test logins fail, review all the output to learn what went 
        wrong. There are several test users and test clients provided. The 
        configuration files are full of useful information, and we recommend 
        studying them. When you are satisfied with your testing and ready to 
        create a production configuration, remove all the test certificates 
        in <filename>/etc/raddb/certs</filename> and replace them with your 
        own certificates, comment out all the test users and clients, and 
        stop <command>radiusd</command> by pressing
        <keycombo><keycap function="control"/><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>. Manage
        the <literal>radiusd.service</literal> with 
        <command>systemctl</command>, just like any other service.
    </para>
    <para>
        To learn how to fit a FreeRADIUS server in your network, see
        <link xlink:href="https://freeradius.org/documentation/"/>
        and
        <link xlink:href="https://networkradius.com/freeradius-documentation/"/>
        for in-depth references and howtos.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
