<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.security.yast_security">
 <title>Configuring Security Settings with &yast;</title>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   The &yast; module <guimenu>Security Center and Hardening</guimenu> offers
   a central clearinghouse to configure security-related settings for
   &productname;. Use it to configure security aspects such as settings for
   the login procedure and for password creation, for boot permissions, user
   creation or for default file permissions. Launch it from the &yast;
   Control Center by <menuchoice><guimenu>Security and Users</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Security Center and Hardening</guimenu> </menuchoice>. The
   <guimenu>Security Center</guimenu> dialog always starts with the
   <guimenu>Security Overview</guimenu>, and other configuration dialogs are
   available from the right pane.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <sect1 id="sec.security.yast_security.overview">
  <title><guimenu>Security Overview</guimenu></title>

  <para>
   The <guimenu>Security Overview</guimenu> displays a comprehensive list of
   the most important security settings for your system. The security status
   of each entry in the list is clearly visible. A green check mark
   indicates a secure setting while a red cross indicates an entry as being
   insecure. Click <guimenu>Help</guimenu> to open an overview of the
   setting and information on how to make it secure. To change a setting,
   click on the corresponding link in the Status column. Depending on the
   setting, the following entries are available:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Enable</guimenu>/<guimenu>Disable</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Click this entry to toggle the status of the setting to either
      enabled or disabled.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Configure</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Click this entry to launch another &yast; module for
      configuration. You will return to the Security Overview when leaving
      the module.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Unknown</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A setting's status is set to unknown when the associated service is
      not installed. Such a setting does not represent a potential security
      risk.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <figure id="fig.yast_security.overview">
   <title>&yast; Security Center and Hardening - Security Overview</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata width="75%" fileref="yast2_security_overview_gtk.png" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="yast2_security_overview_gtk.png" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.security.yast_security.predefined_configs">
  <title><guimenu>Predefined Security Configurations</guimenu></title>

  <para>
   &productname; comes with three <guimenu>Predefined Security
   Configurations</guimenu>. These configurations affect all the settings
   available in the <guimenu>Security Center</guimenu> module. Each
   configuration can be modified to your needs using the dialogs available
   from the right pane. Choose between the following sets:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Home Workstation</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This setting is designed for a computer that has no network connection
      at all (including a connection to the Internet). It provides the least
      secure configuration of the predefined settings.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Networked Workstation</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A configuration for a workstation with any kind of network connection
      (including a connection to the Internet).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Network Server</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Security settings designed for a machine providing network services
      such as a Web server, file server, name server, etc. This set provides
      the most secure configuration of the predefined settings.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Custom Settings</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A pre-selected <guimenu>Custom Settings</guimenu> (when opening the
      <guimenu>Predefined Security Configurations</guimenu> dialog)
      indicates that one of the predefined sets has been modified. Actively
      choosing this option does not change the current configuration&mdash;you
      will need to change it using the <guimenu>Security Overview</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.security.yast_security.password">
  <title><guimenu>Password Settings</guimenu></title>

  <para>
   Passwords that are easy to guess are a major security issue. The
   <guimenu>Password Settings</guimenu> dialog provides the means to ensure
   that only secure passwords can be used.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Check New Passwords</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      By activating this option, a warning will be issued if new passwords
      appear in a dictionary, or if they are proper names (proper nouns).
<!-- in SLE11, "<guimenu>Minimum Acceptable Password Length</guimenu>"
      comes later! -->
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Test for Complicated Passwords</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      When this option is checked, any new password is checked that it
      consists of a mixture of characters, digits and special characters. If
      it fails to pass this test, a warning is issued upon the entering of
      the new password.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Number of Passwords to Remember</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      When password expiration is activated (via <guimenu>Password
      Age</guimenu>), this setting stores the given number of a user's
      previous passwords, preventing their reuse.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Password Encryption Method</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Choose a password encryption algorithm. Normally there is no need to
      change the default (Blowfish).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Minimum Acceptable Password Length</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If the user chooses a password with a length shorter than specified
      here, a warning will be issued.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Password Age</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Activate password expiration by specifying a minimum and a maximum
      time limit (in days). By setting the minimum age to a value greater
      than <literal>0</literal> days, you can prevent users from immediately
      changing their passwords again (and in doing so circumventing the
      password expiration). Use the values <literal>0</literal> and
      <literal>99999</literal> to deactivate password expiration.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Days Before Password Expires Warning</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      When a password expires, the user receives a warning in advance.
      Specify the number of days prior to the expiration date that the
      warning should be issued.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.security.yast_security.boot">
  <title><guimenu>Boot Settings</guimenu></title>

  <para>
   Configure which users will be able to shut down the machine via the
   graphical login manager in this dialog. You can also specify how
   <keycombo> <keycap function="control"/> <keycap function="alt"/>
   <keycap function="delete"/> </keycombo> will be interpreted.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.security.yast_security.login">
  <title><guimenu>Login Settings</guimenu></title>

  <para>
   This dialog lets you configure security-related login settings:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Delay after Incorrect Login Attempt</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      In order to make it difficult to guess a user's password by repeatedly
      logging in, it is recommended to delay the display of the login prompt
      that follows an incorrect login. Specify the value in seconds. Make
      sure that users who have mistyped their passwords do not need to wait
      too long.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Record Successful Login Attempts</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      With this option turned on, the last successful login attempt is
      recorded in <filename>/var/log/lastlog</filename> and displayed when
      logging in. This data is also used by the command
      <command>finger</command>.
     </para>
     <note>
      <para>
       Note that logging to <filename>/var/log/wtmp</filename> is not
       affected by this option. This file collects login dates, login times
       and reboot dates. The content of <filename>/var/log/wtmp</filename>
       can be displayed by using the command <command>last</command>.
      </para>
     </note>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Allow Remote Graphical Login</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      When checked, the graphical login manager (gdm) can be
      accessed from the network. This is a potential security risk.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.security.yast_security.user">
  <title><guimenu>User Addition</guimenu></title>

  <para>
   Set minimum and maximum values for user and group IDs. These default
   settings would rarely need to be changed.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.security.yast_security.misc">
  <title><guimenu>Miscellaneous Settings</guimenu></title>

  <para>
   Other security settings that don't fit the above-mentioned categories are
   listed here:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>File Permissions</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      &productname; comes with three predefined sets of file permissions for
      system files. These permission sets define whether a regular user may
      read log files or start certain programs. <guimenu>Easy</guimenu> file
      permissions are suitable for stand-alone machines. These settings
      allow regular users to, for example, read most system files. See the
      file <filename>/etc/permissions.easy</filename> for the complete
      configuration. The <guimenu>Secure</guimenu> file permissions are
      designed for multiuser machines with network access. A thorough
      explanation of these settings can be found in
      <filename>/etc/permissions.secure</filename>. The
      <guimenu>Paranoid</guimenu> settings are the most restrictive ones and
      should be used with care. See
      <filename>/etc/permissions.paranoid</filename> for more information.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>User Launching updatedb</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The program <command>updatedb</command> scans the system and creates a
      database of all file locations which can be queried with the command
      <command>locate</command>. When <command>updatedb</command> is run as
      user nobody, only world-readable files will be added to the database.
      When run as user &rootuser;, almost all files (except the ones root is
      not allowed to read) will be added.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Current Directory in root's Path</guimenu> /
     <guimenu>Current Directory in Path of Regular Users</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Whenever a program is called without specifying the full path to the
      executable, the system looks in the user's search path (defined by the
      variable <envar>$PATH</envar>) for the executable. By default the
      current directory is not added to the search path. This setting
      ensures that, for example, <filename>/bin/ls</filename> and not the
      trojan horse <filename>/<replaceable>current
      directory</replaceable>/ls</filename> is executed when entering
      <command>ls</command>. In order to start a program in the current
      directory the command must be prefixed with <filename>./</filename>.
      When activating these options, the current directory
      (<filename>.</filename>) is appended to the search path. It is
      recommended you not change the default.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Enable Magic SysRq Keys</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The magic SysRq key is a keycombo that enables you to have some
      control over the system even when it has crashed. The complete
      documentation can be found at
      <filename>/usr/src/linux/Documentation/sysrq.txt</filename> (requires
      installation of the <systemitem>kernel-source</systemitem> package).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
