<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.selinux">
 <title>Configuring &selnx; on &sle; 11 SP2</title>
 <para>
  Since &sle; 11 SP2, the &selnx; framework is supported on SUSE Linux
  Enterprise. In this article you’ll learn how to set it up and how to
  manage &selnx; on SLE 11 SP2 once it has been installed. The following
  topics are covered in this article:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    &selnx; backgrounds
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Understanding &selnx;
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Setting up &selnx; on SLE 11 SP2
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Managing &selnx; on SLE 11 SP2
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <sect1>
  <title>&selnx; backgrounds</title>

  <para>
   &selnx; was developed as an additional Linux security solution that uses
   the security framework in the Linux kernel. The purpose was to allow for
   a more granular security policy that goes beyond what is offered by the
   default existing permissions of Read Write and Execute, and also beyond
   assigning permissions to the different capabilities that are available on
   Linux. &selnx; does this by trapping all syscalls that reach the kernel,
   and denying them by default. This means that on a system that has &selnx;
   enabled and nothing else configured, nothing will work. To allow your
   system to do anything, as an administrator you will need to write rules
   and put them in a policy.
  </para>

  <para>
   An example explains why a solution such as &selnx; (or its counterpart
   AppArmor) is needed.
  </para>

  <para>
   <quote>One morning, I found out that my server was hacked. The server was
   running SLES 10 SP 3 server, which was patched up to the latest level. A
   firewall was configured on it and no unnecessary services were offered by
   this server. Further analysis learned that the hacker had come in through
   a flaky PHP script that was a part of one of the Apache virtual hosts
   that were running on this server. The intruder had managed to get access
   to a shell, using the <systemitem class="username">wwwrun</systemitem>
   account that was used by the Apache Web server. As this
   <systemitem class="username">wwwrun</systemitem> user, the intruder had
   created several scripts in the <filename>/var/tmp</filename> and the
   <filename>/tmp</filename> directories, which were a part of a botnet that
   was launching a Distributed Denial of Service attack against different
   servers on the planet.</quote>
  </para>

  <para>
   The interesting thing about this hack is that it occurred on a server
   where nothing was really wrong. All permissions where set OK, but the
   intruder had managed to get into the system. What becomes clearly evident
   from this example is that in some cases additional security is
   needed&mdash;a security that goes beyond what is offered by using
   &selnx;. As a less complete and less complex alternative, AppArmor can be
   used.
  </para>

  <para>
   AppArmor confines specific processes in their abilities to read/write and
   execute files (and other things). Its view is mostly that things that
   happen inside a process cannot escape.
  </para>

  <para>
   &selnx; instead uses labels attached to objects (e.g. files, binaries,
   network sockets) and uses them to determine privilege boundaries, thereby
   building up a level of confinement that can span more than a process or
   even the whole system.
  </para>

  <para>
   &selnx; was developed by the US National Security Agency (NSA), and since
   the beginning Red Hat has been heavily involved in its development. The
   first version of &selnx; was offered in the era of <trademark>Red Hat
   Enterprise Linux 4</trademark>, around the year 2006. In the beginning it
   offered support for essential services only, but over the years it has
   developed into a system that offers many rules that are collected in
   policies to offer protection to a broad range of services.
  </para>

  <para>
   &selnx; was developed in accordance with some certification standards
   like Common Criteria and FIPS 140. Because some customers specifically
   requested solutions that met these standards, &selnx; rapidly became
   relatively popular.
  </para>

  <para>
   As an alternative to &selnx;, Immunix, a company that was purchased by
   Novell in 2005, had developed AppArmor. AppArmor was built on top of the
   same security principles as &selnx;, but took a completely different
   approach, where it was possible to restrict services to exactly what they
   needed to do by using an easy to use wizard-driven procedure.
   Nevertheless, AppArmor has never reached the same status as &selnx;, even
   if there are some good arguments to secure a server with AppArmor rather
   than with &selnx;.
  </para>

  <para>
   Because more and more governmental organizations currently are requesting
   &selnx; to be present in the Linux distributions they are using, SUSE is
   offering support for the &selnx; framework in the latest versions of
   &sle; Server. This doesn’t mean that SUSE is about to switch from
   AppArmor to &selnx; soon, for SUSE it is important that the customer can
   choose the security solution that fits his needs best.
  </para>

  <sect2>
   <title>Support Status</title>
   <para>
    Currently, the &selnx; framework is supported in &sle; 11 SP2. This
    means that you can expect that &sle; is offering all binaries and
    libraries you need to be able to use &selnx; on your server without any
    problems. A policy however is not included and you will also miss some
    binaries that you might be familiar with from using other Linux
    distributions. Some of these binaries are available at
    <ulink url="http://software.opensuse.org"/>. It is however not a good
    idea to install them on your &sle; system as they haven’t been tested
    and therefore might cause additional problems to the system. Currently,
    &selnx; support is at a fairly early stage on &sle; and this means that
    unexpected behavior may occur. To limit this risk as much as possible,
    it is a good idea to use only the binaries that have been provided by
    default on SLES 11 SP2.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Understanding &selnx; Components</title>
   <para>
    Before starting the configuration of &selnx;, you should know a bit
    about how &selnx; is organized. Three components play a role:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The security framework in the Linux kernel
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The &selnx; libraries and binaries
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The &selnx; policy
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    &sle; 11 SP2 and later comes with the standard support for &selnx; in
    the Linux kernel, and the tools that are needed to manage the &selnx;
    solution. You will shortly learn how to install these tools on your
    server. The most important part of the work of the administrator with
    regards to &selnx; is managing the policy.
   </para>
   <para>
    In the &selnx; policy, security labels are applied to different objects
    on a Linux server. These objects typically are users, ports, processes
    and files. Using these security labels, rules are created that define
    what is and what isn’t allowed on a server. Remember, by default
    &selnx; denies all syscalls and by creating the appropriate rules you
    can allow the syscalls that you trust again. Rules should therefore
    exist for all programs that you want to use on a system. Alternatively,
    you might want to configure parts of a system to run in unconfined mode,
    which means that specific ports, programs, users, files and directories
    are not protected at all by &selnx;. This mode is useful if you just
    want to use SELinux to protect some essential services, while you aren't
    specifically worried about other services. To get a really secure
    system, you should try to avoid this.
   </para>
   <para>
    To ensure the appropriate protection of your system, you need an &selnx;
    policy. This must be a tailor-made policy in which all files are
    provided with a label, and all services and users have a security label
    as well to express which files and directories can be accessed by which
    user and processed on the server. Developing such a policy is a
    tremendous amount of work. In &sle;, no policy is available yet. If you
    want to use &selnx;, you have to take care of creating your own policy.
   </para>
   <para>
    The complexity of &selnx; is also one of the main arguments against
    using it. Because a typical Linux system is so very complex, it is easy
    to oversee something and leave an opening that intruders can abuse to
    get into your system. And even if it is set up completely the way it
    should be, it still is very hard for an administrator to overlook all
    aspects with &selnx;. With regards to the complexity, AppArmor takes a
    completely different approach and works with automated procedures that
    allow the administrator to set up AppArmor protection and understand
    exactly what is happening.
   </para>
   <para>
    In &sle; 11 SP2, the &selnx; framework is supported and provided. The
    &selnx; policy is not. Therefore, as an administrator that wishes to use
    &selnx; on &sle;, you will have to create your own policy, or use one of
    the standard policies that are available for free. Do notice though that
    a freely available &selnx; policy might work on your server, but it will
    never offer complete protection for all aspects of security on your
    server! Also, SUSE does not support these open source policies, which is
    obvious because they haven’t been developed by SUSE and they do not
    match SUSE. But in its current state you can use &selnx; to protect
    &sle; Server.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>The Policy</title>

  <para>
   As mentioned, the policy is the key component in &selnx;. It defines
   rules that specify which objects can access which files, directories,
   ports and processes on a system. To do this, a security context is
   defined for all of these. On an &selnx; system where the policy has been
   applied to label the file system, you can use the <command>ls
   -Z</command> command on any directory to find the security context for
   the files in that directory.
   <xref linkend="ex.selnx.con.set"
                xrefstyle="select:label quotedtitle nopage"/>
   shows the security context settings for the directories in the
   <filename>/</filename> directory of an SLES 11 SP2 system with an
   &selnx;-labeled file system.
  </para>

  <example id="ex.selnx.con.set">
   <title>Showing security context settings using ls -Z</title>
<screen>mmi:/ # ls -Z
system_u:object_r:default_t .autorelabel
system_u:object_r:file_t .viminfo
system_u:object_r:bin_t bin
system_u:object_r:boot_t boot
system_u:object_r:device_t dev
system_u:object_r:etc_t etc
system_u:object_r:home_root_t home
system_u:object_r:lib_t lib
system_u:object_r:lib_t lib64
system_u:object_r:lost_found_t lost+found
system_u:object_r:mnt_t media
system_u:object_r:mnt_t mnt
system_u:object_r:usr_t opt
system_u:object_r:proc_t proc
system_u:object_r:default_t root
system_u:object_r:bin_t sbin
system_u:object_r:security_t selinux
system_u:object_r:var_t srv
system_u:object_r:sysfs_t sys
system_u:object_r:tmp_t tmp
system_u:object_r:usr_t usr
system_u:object_r:var_t var
system_u:object_r:httpd_sys_content_t www</screen>
  </example>

  <para>
   The most important line in the security context is the context type. This
   is the part of the security context that ends in _t. It tells &selnx;
   which kind of access the object is allowed. In the policy, rules are
   specified to define which type of user or which type of role has access
   to which type of context. For example, this can happen by using a rule
   like the following:
  </para>

<screen>allow user_t bin_t:file {read execute gettattr};</screen>

  <para>
   This example rule states that the user who has the context type
   <systemitem class="username">user_t</systemitem> (this user is referred
   to as the source object) is allowed to access the file with the context
   type <filename>bin_t</filename> (the target), using the permissions read,
   execute and getattr. Later in this article you will learn how to use a
   standard policy to apply this kind of security context settings to the
   file system on your server.
  </para>

  <para>
   The standard policy that you are going to use contains a huge amount of
   rules. To make it more manageable, policies are often applied as modular
   policies. This allows the administrator to work with independent modules
   that allow the administrator to switch protection on or off for different
   parts of the system. When compiling the policy for your system, you will
   have a choice to either work with a modular policy, or a monolithic
   policy, where one huge policy is used to protect everything on your
   system. It is strongly recommended to use a modular policy and not a
   monolithic policy. Modular policies are much easier to manage.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Installing &selnx; on &sle; 11 SP2</title>

  <para>
   <remark>Not sure if this is a section2</remark>
   You can install all SELinux components while performing the installation
   of your SUSE Linux Enterprise system, or afterwards. Installation
   consists of the following steps:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Install all &selnx; packages
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Enable GRUB boot options
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Install a policy
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Installing &selnx; Packages and modifying GRUB</title>

  <para>
   The easiest way to make sure that all &selnx; components are installed is
   by using YaST2. The procedure described below shows what to do on an
   installed SLES 11 SP2 server.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log in to your server as <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>
     and start YaST2.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Software</guimenu> <guimenu>Software
     Management</guimenu> </menuchoice>
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     <menuchoice> <guimenu>Select View</guimenu> <guimenu>Patterns</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> and select the entire C/C++ Compiler and Tools software
     category for installation.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     <menuchoice> <guimenu>Select View</guimenu> <guimenu>Search</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> and make sure that Search in Name, Keywords and Summary
     are selected. Now enter the keyword selinux and click
     <guimenu>Search</guimenu>. You now see a list of packages.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Make sure that all the packages you’ve found are selected and click
     <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to install them.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <figure id="fig.packages.yast">
   <title>Selecting all &selnx; Packages in YaST2</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="pdf">
     <imagedata fileref="selnx_policy_compiler.png" width="85%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="selnx_policy_compiler.png" width="95%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   After installing the &selnx; packages, you have to modify the GRUB boot
   loader. To do this, from YaST select <guimenu>System > Boot
   loader</guimenu>. On the Section Management tab, you'll now see the
   current GRUB configuration. Select the label that starts with
   <guimenu>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 11 SP2</guimenu> and click
   <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>. Now select the line that contains the Optional
   Kernel Command Line Parameters and add the following to the end of this
   line: <literal>security=selinux</literal> <literal>selinux=1</literal>
   <literal>enforcing=0</literal>
  </para>

  <para>
   These options are used for the following purposes:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>security=selinux</literal>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option tells the kernel to use &selnx; and not AppArmor
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>selinux=1</literal>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option switches on SELinux
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>enforcing=0</literal>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option puts &selnx; in permissive mode. In this mode, &selnx; is
      fully functional, but doesn’t enforce any of the security settings
      in the policy. Use this mode for configuring your system, and once it
      is fully operational, change it to <literal>enforcing=1</literal> to
      switch on &selnx; protection on your server.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   After installing the &selnx; packages and enabling the &selnx; GRUB boot
   options, reboot your server to activate the configuration. You may notice
   that while rebooting, an error is displayed mentioning that the policy
   file could not be loaded. At this point in the configuration the error is
   normal and you can safely ignore it. It will disappear once you have
   compiled the policy.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Compiling the Policy</title>

  <para>
   As mentioned, the policy is an essential component of &selnx; but no
   default policy is available for &sle;. This means that you’ll need to
   get a policy from somewhere else. The best choice is to get a policy from
   the openSUSE download site at
   <ulink url="http://software.opensuse.org"/>. In the Package Search bar
   presented at this site, type <literal>selinux-policy</literal> to get
   access to a list of all open source policy packages presented at
   <ulink url="http://openSUSE.org"/>.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.policy.package">
   <title>Get an open source policy package from http://software.opensuse.org</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="pdf">
     <imagedata fileref="selnx_se_policy_compiler.png" width="85%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="selnx_se_policy_compiler.png" width="95%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   Don’t click the Direct Install link, but select <guimenu>Show other
   versions</guimenu>. The current policy packages provided for SLE 11 are
   in an unstable state, but still they are the best available option
   because they match the layout of the file system on SLE better than the
   default policy for openSUSE 12.x. Many items have changed in the openSUSE
   12.x file system as compared to the SLE file system, so open the SUSE
   SLE-11 SP1 link, accept the unstable package and click <guimenu>Source to
   download</guimenu> the policy source file and save it to disk. This gives
   you a file with the name
   <filename>selinux-policy-2.20081210-12.2.src.rpm</filename> (the exact
   name of the file might be slightly different because of the version
   number that is included in the filename).
  </para>

  <para>
   After downloading the source RPM, you can apply the following steps to
   install it to your server:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Extract the archive from the source RPM, using
    </para>
<screen>rpm2cpio selinux-policy- >version>.src.rpm | cpio -idmv</screen>
    <para>
     This gives you a tarball in the current directory, with the name
     <filename>refpolicy-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.tar.bz2.</filename>
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Extract the contents of the tarball to the directory
     <filename>/etc/selinux/refpolicy</filename>. Use
    </para>
<screen>tar xvf refpolicy-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.tar.bz2 -C /etc/selinux</screen>
    <para>
     to do this.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Make sure that in the directory <filename>/etc/selinux</filename> there
     is a file with the name <filename>config</filename> that has the
     following contents:
    </para>
<screen>SELINUX=permissive
SELINUXTYPE=refpolicy</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Edit the configuration file
     <filename>/etc/selinux/refpolicy/build.conf</filename> and make sure it
     includes the following parameters:
    </para>
<screen>DISTRO = suse
UNK_PERMS = allow
DIRECT_INITRC = y
MONOLITHIC = n</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Make sure that you are in the directory
     <filename>/etc/selinux/refpolicy</filename> and from that directory,
     run the <command>make load command</command>. This command will take a
     while to complete.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Use the <command>mkinitrd</command> command to re-create the
     <filename>initrd</filename> file. This is needed to guarantee proper
     booting of the server with the policy.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Once make load has completed, reboot your server.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   Before doing anything else, at this point you should use the command
   <command>semanage fcontext -a -e /dev /lib/udev/devices</command>. This
   is to set a context for a critical directory that is not taken care of by
   the policy by default.
  </para>

  <para>
   At this point all prerequisites have been met and you are ready to start
   file system labeling. To do this, use the command <command>restorecon -Rv
   /</command>. This command starts the <command>/sbin/setfiles</command>
   command to label all files on your system. To do this, the input file
   <filename>/etc/selinux/refpolicy/contexts/files/file_contexts</filename>
   is used. Because there currently is no &selnx; policy for SUSE Linux
   Enteprise, this is a delicate part of the configuration. The
   <filename>file_contexts</filename> file has to match your actual file
   system as much as possible, so if it goes wrong, it is likely to go wrong
   at this point. This can lead to a completely unbootable system. If that
   happens, tune the contents of the <filename>file_contexts</filename> file
   to match the structure of the file system your server is using. Before
   doing this, make sure to read the rest of this article so that you fully
   understand how context type is applied to files and directories (and
   don't forget to make a backup of the <filename>file_contexts</filename>
   file before starting). At the end of this article you'll find tips that
   help you in troubleshooting &selnx; and creating a system that fully
   works with your &selnx; policy.
  </para>

  <para>
   Note: if while using semanage you get a message that complains about the
   user nobody's home directory, you can change the login shell of user
   <systemitem class="username"
                >nobody</systemitem> to
   <filename>/sbin/nologin</filename>. This makes sure that the user
   nobody's settings match the current policy settings.
  </para>

  <para>
   After another reboot &selnx; should be operational. To verify this, use
   the command <command>sestatus -v</command>. It should give you an output
   that looks like the output in
   <xref linkend="ex.selnx.sestatus" xrefstyle="select:label quotedtitle nopage"
            />.
  </para>

  <example id="ex.selnx.sestatus">
   <title>After labeling the file system you can verify that &selnx; is functional using <command>sestatus -v</command></title>
<screen>sestatus -v          
mmi:/ # sestatus -v
SELinux status:                 enabled
SELinuxfs mount:                /selinux
Current mode:                   permissive
Mode from config file:          permissive
Policy version:                 26
Policy from config file:        refpolicy
                
Process contexts:
Current context:                root:staff_r:staff_t
Init context:                   system_u:system_r:init_t
/sbin/mingetty                  system_u:system_r:sysadm_t
/usr/sbin/sshd                  system_u:system_r:sshd_t
                
File contexts:
Controlling term:               root:object_r:user_devpts_t
/etc/passwd                     system_u:object_r:etc_t
/etc/shadow                     system_u:object_r:shadow_t
/bin/bash                       system_u:object_r:shell_exec_t
/bin/login                      system_u:object_r:login_exec_t
/bin/sh                         system_u:object_r:bin_t -> system_u:object_r:shell_exec_t
/sbin/agetty                    system_u:object_r:getty_exec_t
/sbin/init                      system_u:object_r:init_exec_t
/sbin/mingetty                  system_u:object_r:getty_exec_t
/usr/sbin/sshd                  system_u:object_r:sshd_exec_t
/lib/libc.so.6                  system_u:object_r:lib_t -> system_u:object_r:lib_t
/lib/ld-linux.so.2              system_u:object_r:lib_t -> system_u:object_r:ld_so_t</screen>
  </example>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Configuring &selnx;</title>

  <para>
   At this point you have a completely functional &selnx; system and it is
   time to further configure the system. In the current status, &selnx; is
   operational but not in enforcing mode. This means that it doesn’t limit
   you in doing anything, it just logs everything that it should be doing if
   it were in enforcing mode. This is good, because based on the log files
   you can find what it is that it would prevent you from doing. As a first
   test, it is a good idea to put &selnx; in enforcing mode and find out if
   you can still use your server after doing so. To do this, open the
   <filename>/etc/selinux/config file</filename> (or the
   <filename>/boot/grub/menu.lst</filename> file) and make sure that the
   option <option>enforcing=1</option> is set. Reboot your server and see if
   it still comes up the way you expect it to. If it does, leave it like
   that and start modifying the server in a way that everything works as
   expected. Chances are though that you won’t even be able to boot the
   server properly. If that is the case, switch back to the mode where
   &selnx; is not enforcing and start tuning your server.
  </para>

  <sect2>
   <title>Verifying the installation</title>
   <para>
    Before you start tuning your server, it is a good idea to verify the
    &selnx; installation. You have already used the command
    <command>sestatus -v</command> to view the current mode, process, and
    file contexts. Next, use <command>semanage boolean -l</command>, which
    shows a list of all Boolean switches that are available, and at the same
    time verifies that you can access the policy.
    <xref linkend="ex.selnx.ls.bool"/> shows part of the output of this
    command.
   </para>
   <example id="ex.selnx.ls.bool">
    <title>Use <command>semanage boolean -l</command> to get a list of Booleans and verify policy access</title>
<screen>mmi:~ # semanage boolean -l
SELinux boolean                          Description
ftp_home_dir                   -> off   ftp_home_dir
mozilla_read_content           -> off   mozilla_read_content
spamassassin_can_network       -> off   spamassassin_can_network
httpd_can_network_relay        -> off   httpd_can_network_relay
openvpn_enable_homedirs        -> off   openvpn_enable_homedirs
gpg_agent_env_file             -> off   gpg_agent_env_file
allow_httpd_awstats_script_anon_write -> off   allow_httpd_awstats_script_anon_write
httpd_can_network_connect_db   -> off   httpd_can_network_connect_db
allow_user_mysql_connect       -> off   allow_user_mysql_connect
allow_ftpd_full_access         -> off   allow_ftpd_full_access
samba_domain_controller        -> off   samba_domain_controller
httpd_enable_cgi               -> off   httpd_enable_cgi
virt_use_nfs                   -> off   virt_use_nfs</screen>
    <para>
     Another command that should produce output at this stage is
     <command>semanage fcontext -l</command> . This command shows the
     default file context settings as provided by the policy (see
     <xref linkend="ex.selnx.fcon"
                        xrefstyle="select:label quotedtitle nopage"/>
     for partial output of this command).
    </para>
   </example>
   <example id="ex.selnx.fcon">
    <title>Use <command>semanage fcontext -l</command> to get file context information</title>
<screen>/var/run/usb(/.*)?                                 all files          system_u:object_r:hotplug_var_run_t
/var/run/utmp                                      regular file       system_u:object_r:initrc_var_run_t
/var/run/vbe.*                                     regular file       system_u:object_r:hald_var_run_t
/var/run/vmnat.*                                   socket             system_u:object_r:vmware_var_run_t
/var/run/vmware.*                                  all files          system_u:object_r:vmware_var_run_t
/var/run/vpnc(/.*)?                                all files          system_u:object_r:vpnc_var_run_t
/var/run/watchdog\.pid                             regular file       system_u:object_r:watchdog_var_run_t
/var/run/winbindd(/.*)?                            all files          system_u:object_r:winbind_var_run_t
/var/run/wnn-unix(/.*)                             all files          system_u:object_r:canna_var_run_t
/var/run/wpa_supplicant(/.*)?                      all files          system_u:object_r:NetworkManager_var_run_t
/var/run/wpa_supplicant-global                     socket             system_u:object_r:NetworkManager_var_run_t
/var/run/xdmctl(/.*)?                              all files          system_u:object_r:xdm_var_run_t
/var/run/yiff-[0-9]+\.pid                          regular file       system_u:object_r:soundd_var_run_t</screen>
   </example>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Managing &selnx;</title>

  <para>
   Now that the base &selnx; configuration is operational, it’s time to
   start configuring it in a way that secures your server. Let’s remind
   ourselfs what &selnx; is all about first. In &selnx;, an additional set
   of rules is used to define exactly which process or user can access which
   files, directories, or ports. To do this, &selnx; applies a context to
   every file, directory, process, and port. This context is a security
   label that defines how this file, directory, process, or port should be
   treated. These context labels are used by the &selnx; policy, which
   defines exactly what should be done with the context labels. By default,
   the policy blocks all non-default access, which means that, as an
   administrator, you have to enable all features that are non-default on
   your server.
  </para>

  <sect2>
   <title>Displaying the Security Context</title>
   <para>
    As mentioned, files, folders, and ports can be labeled. Within each
    label, different contexts are used. To be able to perform your daily
    administration work, the type context is what you’re most interested
    in. As an administrator, you’ll mostly work with the type context.
    Many commands allow you to use the <option>-Z</option> option to show a
    list of current context settings. In
    <xref
                    linkend="ex.selnx.def.con." xrefstyle="select:label quotedtitle nopage"/>
    you can see what the context settings are for the directories in the
    root directory.
   </para>
   <example id="ex.selnx.def.con.">
    <title>The default context for directories in the root directory</title>
<screen>[root@hnl /]# ls -Z
dr-xr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:bin_t:s0       bin
dr-xr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:boot_t:s0      boot
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:cgroup_t:s0    cgroup
drwxr-xr-x+ root root unconfined_u:object_r:default_t:s0 data
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:device_t:s0    dev
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:etc_t:s0       etc
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:home_root_t:s0 home
dr-xr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:lib_t:s0       lib
dr-xr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:lib_t:s0       lib64
drwx------. root root system_u:object_r:lost_found_t:s0 lost+found
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:mnt_t:s0       media
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:autofs_t:s0    misc
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:mnt_t:s0       mnt
drwxr-xr-x. root root unconfined_u:object_r:default_t:s0 mnt2
drwxr-xr-x. root root unconfined_u:object_r:default_t:s0 mounts
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:autofs_t:s0    net
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:usr_t:s0       opt
dr-xr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:proc_t:s0      proc
drwxr-xr-x. root root unconfined_u:object_r:default_t:s0 repo
dr-xr-x---. root root system_u:object_r:admin_home_t:s0 root
dr-xr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:bin_t:s0       sbin
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:security_t:s0  selinux
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:var_t:s0       srv
-rw-r--r--. root root unconfined_u:object_r:swapfile_t:s0 swapfile
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:sysfs_t:s0     sys
drwxrwxrwt. root root system_u:object_r:tmp_t:s0       tmp
-rw-r--r--. root root unconfined_u:object_r:etc_runtime_t:s0 tmp2.tar
-rw-r--r--. root root unconfined_u:object_r:etc_runtime_t:s0 tmp.tar
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:usr_t:s0       usr
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:var_t:s0       var</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    In the listing above, you can see the complete context for all
    directories. It consists of a user, a role, and a type. The s0 setting
    indicates the security level in Multi Level Security environments. These
    environments are not discussed in this article, so just make sure that
    it is set to s0 and you'll be fine. The Context Type defines what kind
    of activity is permitted in the directory. Compare, for example, the
    <filename>/root</filename> directory, which has the
    <filename>admin_home_t</filename> context type, and the
    <filename>/home</filename> directory, which has the
    <filename>home_root_t</filename> context type. In the &selnx; policy,
    different kinds of access are defined for these context types.
   </para>
   <para>
    Security labels are not only associated with files, but also with other
    items, such as ports and processes. In
    <xref linkend="ex.selnx.set.proc"
                    xrefstyle="select:label quotedtitle nopage"/>
    for example you can see the context settings for processes on your
    server.
   </para>
   <example id="ex.selnx.set.proc">
    <title>Showing &selnx; settings for processes</title>
<screen>mmi:/ # ps Zaux
LABEL                           USER       PID %CPU %MEM    VSZ   RSS TTY      STAT START   TIME COMMAND
system_u:system_r:init_t        root         1  0.0  0.0  10640   808 ?        Ss   05:31   0:00 init [5]
system_u:system_r:kernel_t      root         2  0.0  0.0      0     0 ?        S    05:31   0:00 [kthreadd]
system_u:system_r:kernel_t      root         3  0.0  0.0      0     0 ?        S    05:31   0:00 [ksoftirqd/0]
system_u:system_r:kernel_t      root         6  0.0  0.0      0     0 ?        S    05:31   0:00 [migration/0]
system_u:system_r:kernel_t      root         7  0.0  0.0      0     0 ?        S    05:31   0:00 [watchdog/0]
system_u:system_r:sysadm_t      root      2344  0.0  0.0  27640   852 ?        Ss   05:32   0:00 /usr/sbin/mcelog --daemon --config-file /etc/mcelog/mcelog.conf
system_u:system_r:sshd_t        root      3245  0.0  0.0  69300  1492 ?        Ss   05:32   0:00 /usr/sbin/sshd -o PidFile=/var/run/sshd.init.pid
system_u:system_r:cupsd_t       root      3265  0.0  0.0  68176  2852 ?        Ss   05:32   0:00 /usr/sbin/cupsd
system_u:system_r:nscd_t        root      3267  0.0  0.0 772876  1380 ?        Ssl  05:32   0:00 /usr/sbin/nscd
system_u:system_r:postfix_master_t root   3334  0.0  0.0  38320  2424 ?        Ss   05:32   0:00 /usr/lib/postfix/master
system_u:system_r:postfix_qmgr_t postfix  3358  0.0  0.0  40216  2252 ?        S    05:32   0:00 qmgr -l -t fifo -u
system_u:system_r:crond_t       root      3415  0.0  0.0  14900   800 ?        Ss   05:32   0:00 /usr/sbin/cron
system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t    root      3437  0.0  0.0  16468  1040 ?        S    05:32   0:00 /usr/sbin/smartd
system_u:system_r:sysadm_t      root      3441  0.0  0.0  66916  2152 ?        Ss   05:32   0:00 login -- root
system_u:system_r:sysadm_t      root      3442  0.0  0.0   4596   800 tty2     Ss+  05:32   0:00 /sbin/mingetty tty2</screen>
   </example>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Selecting the &selnx; Mode</title>
   <para>
    In &selnx;, three different modes can be used:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Enforcing:</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This is the default mode. &selnx; protects your server according to
       the rules in the policy, and &selnx; logs all of its activity to the
       audit log.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Permissive:</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This mode is useful for troubleshooting. If set to Permissive,
       &selnx; does not protect your server, but it still logs everything
       that happens to the log files. Also, in permissive mode, the Linux
       kernel still maintains the &selnx; labels in the file system. This is
       good, because this prevents your system from relabeling everything
       after turning &selnx; on again.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Disabled:</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This mode is to be deactivated. In disabled mode, &selnx; is switched
       off completely and no logging occurs. The file system labels however
       are not removed from the file system.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    You have already read how you can set the current &selnx; mode from GRUB
    while booting using the enforcing boot parameter.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Modifying &selnx; Context Types</title>
   <para>
    An important part of the work of an administrator is setting context
    types on files to ensure appropriate working of &selnx;.
   </para>
   <para>
    If a file is created within a specific directory, it inherits the
    context type of the parent directory by default. If, however, a file is
    moved from one location to another location, it retains the context type
    that it had in the old location.
   </para>
   <para>
    To set the context type for files, you can use the <command>semanage
    fcontext</command> command. With this command, you write the new context
    type to the policy, but it doesn’t change the actual context type
    immediately! To apply the context types that are in the policy, you need
    to run the <command>restorecon</command> command afterwards.
   </para>
   <para>
    The challenge when working with <command>semanage fcontext</command> is
    to find out which context you actually need. You can use
    <command>semanage fcontext -l</command> to show a list of all contexts
    in the policy, but it might be a bit hard to find out the actual context
    you need from that list as it is rather long (see
    <xref linkend="ex.selnx.semanage" xrefstyle="select:label quotedtitle nopage"
                />).
   </para>
   <example id="ex.selnx.semanage">
    <title>Showing Displaying default file contexts with <command>semanage fcontext -l</command></title>
<screen>[root@hnl ~]# semanage fcontext -l | less
&selnx; fcontext                                   type               Context
              
/                                                  directory          system_u:object_r:root_t:s0
/.*                                                all files          system_u:object_r:default_t:s0
/[^/]+                                             regular file       system_u:object_r:etc_runtime_t:s0
/\.autofsck                                        regular file       system_u:object_r:etc_runtime_t:s0
/\.autorelabel                                     regular file       system_u:object_r:etc_runtime_t:s0
/\.journal                                         all files          X:>>None>>
/\.suspended                                       regular file       system_u:object_r:etc_runtime_t:s0
/a?quota\.(user|group)                             regular file       system_u:object_r:quota_db_t:s0
/afs                                               directory          system_u:object_r:mnt_t:s0
/bin                                               directory          system_u:object_r:bin_t:s0
/bin/.*                                            all files          system_u:object_r:bin_t:s0</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    There are three ways to find out which context settings are available
    for your services:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Install the service and look at the default context settings that are
      used. This is the easiest and recommended option.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Consult the man page for the specific service. Some services have a
      man page that ends in _selinux, which contains all the information you
      need to find the correct context settings.
     </para>
     <para>
      After finding the specific context setting you need, you just have to
      apply it using <command>semanage fcontext</command>. This command
      takes <command>-t</command> context type as its first argument,
      followed by the name of the directory or file to which you want to
      apply the context settings. To apply the context to everything that
      already exists in the directory where you want to apply the context,
      you add the regular expression <literal>(/.*)?</literal> to the name
      of the directory. This means: optionally, match a slash followed by
      any character. The examples section of the semanage man page has some
      useful usage examples for semanage.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use <command>seinfo -t</command> to display a list of all contexts
      types that are available on your system, combined with grep to find
      the context type you need for a specific purpose. The amount of
      information provided with <command>seinfo -t</command> is a bit
      overwhelming, about 3,000 contexts type are available by default!
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Applying File Contexts</title>
   <para>
    To help you apply the &selnx; context properly, the following procedure
    shows how to set a context using <command>semanage fcontext</command>
    and <command>restorecon</command>. You will notice that at first
    attempt, the Web server with a non-default document root doesn’t work.
    After changing the &selnx; context it will
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use <command>mkdir /web</command> and then go to that directory using
      <command>cd /web</command>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use a text editor to create the file
      <filename>/web/index.html</filename> that contains the text welcome to
      my Web site.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Open the file <filename>/etc/apache2/default-server.conf</filename>
      with an editor, and change the DocumentRoot line to
      <literal>DocumentRoot /web</literal>
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the Apache Web server, using <command>service apache2
      start</command>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use <command>w3m localhost</command> to open a session to your local
      Web server. You will receive a Connection refused message. Press
      <keycap
                            function="enter">Enter</keycap>,
      and then <command>q</command> to quit w3m.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use <command>ls -Z /srv/www</command> to find the current context type
      for the default Apache DocumentRoot, which is
      <filename>/srv/www/htdocs</filename>. It should be set to
      <filename>httpd_sys_content_t</filename>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use <command>semanage fcontext -a -f “”-t httpd_sys_content_t
      ‘/web(/.*) ?’</command> to set the new context in the policy and
      press <keycap function="enter"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Now use <command>restorecon /web</command> to apply the new context
      type.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use <command>ls -Z /web</command> to show the context of the files in
      the directory <filename>/web</filename>. You’ll see that the new
      context type has been set properly to the <filename>/web</filename>
      directory, but not to its contents.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use <command>restorecon -R /web</command> to apply the new context
      recursively to the <filename>/web</filename> directory. The type
      context has now been set correctly.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Restart the Web server, using <command>service apache2
      restart</command>. You should now be able to access the contents of
      the <filename>/web</filename> directory.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Configuring &selnx; Policies</title>
   <para>
    The easiest way to change the behavior of the policy is by working with
    Booleans. These are on-off switches that you can use to change the
    settings in the policy. To find out which Booleans are available, you
    can use the <command>semanage boolean -l</command> command. It will show
    you a long list of Booleans, with a short description of what each of
    these Booleans will do for you. Once you have found the Boolean you want
    to set, you can use <command>setsebool -P</command>, followed by the
    name of the Boolean that you want to change. It is important to use the
    <option>-P</option> option at all times when using setsebool. This
    option writes the setting to the policy file on disk, and this is the
    only way to make sure that the Boolean is applied automatically after a
    reboot.
   </para>
   <para>
    The procedure below gives an example of changing Boolean settings
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      From a root shell, type <command>semanage boolean -l | grep
      ftp</command>. This shows a list of Booleans that are related to FTP
      servers.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use <command>setsebool allow_ftpd_anon_write off</command> to switch
      off this Boolean. Notice that it doesn’t take much time to write the
      change. Use <command>semanage boolean -l|grep ftpd_anon</command> to
      verify that the Boolean is indeed turned on.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Reboot your server.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Check again to see if the <command>allow_ftpd_anon_write</command>
      Boolean is still turned on. As it hasn’t yet been written to the
      policy, you’ll notice that it is off right now.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use <command>setsebool -P allow_ftpd_anon_write</command> on to switch
      the Boolean and write the setting to the policy.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Working with &selnx; Modules</title>
   <para>
    You have compiled &selnx; as modular. This means that the policy that
    implements &selnx; features is not just one huge policy, but it consists
    of many smaller modules. Each module covers a specific part of the
    &selnx; configuration. The concept of the &selnx; module was introduced
    to make it easier for third party vendors to make their services
    compatible with &selnx;. To get an overview of the &selnx; modules, you
    can use the <command>semodule -l</command> command. This command shows a
    list of all current modules in use by SELinux and their version numbers.
   </para>
   <para>
    As an administrator, you can switch modules on or off. This can be
    useful if you want to disable only a part of &selnx; and not everything
    to run a specific service without &selnx; protection. Especially in the
    case of &sle;, where there is not a completely supported &selnx; policy
    yet, it can make sense to switch off all modules that you don’t need
    so that you can focus on the services that really do need &selnx;
    protection. To switch off an &selnx; module, use <command>semodule -d
    modulename</command>. If you want to switch it on again, you can use
    <command>semodule -e modulename</command>. Using this command will
    change the current state of the module in the
    <filename>/etc/selinux/refpolicy/policy/modules.conf</filename> file.
    Alternatively, you could also edit this file by hand.
   </para>
   <para>
    To handle policy modules properly, it helps to understand what you’re
    dealing with. In the end, a policy module is a compiled policy file that
    you can load using the <command>semodule -e</command> command. You can
    recognize these files by the extension they use:
    *<filename>.pp</filename> (which stands for Policy Package). In some
    cases it can be useful to modify modules to have them do exactly what
    you need them to do. Three different kinds of files are used as input
    files for policy modules and you can find them in subdirectories of the
    <filename>/etc/selinux/refpolicy/policy/modules</filename> directory:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <filename>*.te</filename> files contain transition rules. These rules
      tell the policy how to deal with specific subprocesses that are
      started. You won´t often change these as an administrator.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <filename>*.if</filename> files define what exactly the policy should
      be doing. As an administrator you don´t typically change the contents
      of these files.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <filename>*.fc</filename> files contain the labeling instructions that
      apply to this policy. As an administrator, you might want to change
      the contents of the <filename>.fc</filename> files to modify the
      default behavior of policies.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    In
    <xref linkend="ex.selnx.li.apachefc"
                    xrefstyle="select:label quotedtitle nopage"/>
    below you can see the first 20 lines of the
    <filename>apache.fc</filename> file. This is the file that contains the
    default file contexts that are used for the Apache server.
   </para>
   <example id="ex.selnx.li.apachefc">
    <title>The first 20 lines from the <filename>apache.fc</filename> file</title>
<screen>/etc/apache(2)?(/.*)? gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_config_t,s0)
       /etc/apache-ssl(2)?(/.*)? gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_config_t,s0)
       /etc/htdig(/.*)? gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_sys_content_t,s0)
       /etc/httpd -d gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_config_t,s0) /etc/httpd/conf.*
       gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_config_t,s0) /etc/httpd/logs
       gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_log_t,s0) /etc/httpd/modules
       gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_modules_t,s0) /etc/vhosts --
       gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_config_t,s0) /srv/([^/]*/)?www(/.*)?
       gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_sys_content_t,s0) /srv/gallery2(/.*)?
       gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_sys_content_t,s0) /usr/bin/htsslpass --
       gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_helper_exec_t,s0) /usr/lib/apache-ssl/.+ --
       gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_exec_t,s0) /usr/lib/cgi-bin(/.*)?
       gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_sys_script_exec_t,s0)
       /usr/lib(64)?/apache(/.*)? gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_modules_t,s0)
       /usr/lib(64)?/apache2/modules(/.*)?
       gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_modules_t,s0)</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    In the <filename>fc</filename> file, you’ll be able to recognize
    different elements. First is the name of the directory or file to which
    the file context will apply. As you can see, variables can be used (as
    is the case in the first line that starts with
    <varname>HOME_DIR</varname>), and typically, regular expressions will be
    used as well. Next, the gen_context command tells the policy to which
    context the files related to the policy module should be set. This is
    the same context setting that you can see when using <command>ls
    -Z</command> on the file or directory.
   </para>
   <para>
    As an administrator, you don’t typically change the contents of the
    policy files that come from the &selnx; Policy RPM. You would rather use
    <command>semanage fcontext</command> to change file contexts. If you are
    using <command>audit2allow</command> to generate policies for your
    server, you might want to change the policy files after all. If you want
    to change the contents of any of the policy module files, you’ll need
    to compile the changes into a new policy module file. To do this, copy
    or link the &selnx; Makefile from
    <filename>/etc/selinux/refpolicy</filename> to the directory that
    contains the policy module input files and run the following command to
    compile the module:
   </para>
<screen>make &amp;&amp; make install &amp;&amp; make load</screen>
   <para>
    Once the make command has completed, you can manually load the modules
    into the system, using <command>semodule -e</command>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Troubleshooting &selnx;</title>

  <para>
   By default, if &selnx; is the reason why something isn’t working, a log
   message to this effect is sent to the
   <filename>/var/log/audit/audit.log</filename> file. That is, if the
   auditd service is running. If you see an empty
   <filename>/var/log/audit</filename>, start the auditd service using
   <command>service auditd start</command> and put it in the runlevels of
   your system, using <command>insserv auditd</command>. In
   <xref linkend="ex.selnx.li.auditlog"
                xrefstyle="select:label quotedtitle nopage"/>
   you can see a partial example of the contents of
   <filename>/var/log/audit/audit.log</filename>
  </para>

  <example id="ex.selnx.li.auditlog">
   <title>Example lines from <filename>/etc/audit/audit.log</filename></title>
<screen>type=DAEMON_START msg=audit(1348173810.874:6248): auditd start, ver=1.7.7 format=raw kernel=3.0.13-0.27-default auid=0 pid=4235 subj=system_u:system_r:auditd_t res=success
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.081:292): avc:  denied  { write } for  pid=3426 comm="smartd" name="smartmontools" dev=sda6 ino=581743 scontext=system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:var_lib_t tclass=dir
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.081:293): avc:  denied  { remove_name } for  pid=3426 comm="smartd" name="smartd.WDC_WD2500BEKT_75PVMT0-WD_WXC1A21E0454.ata.state~" dev=sda6 ino=582390 scontext=system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:var_lib_t tclass=dir
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.081:294): avc:  denied  { unlink } for  pid=3426 comm="smartd" name="smartd.WDC_WD2500BEKT_75PVMT0-WD_WXC1A21E0454.ata.state~" dev=sda6 ino=582390 scontext=system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:var_lib_t tclass=file
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.081:295): avc:  denied  { rename } for  pid=3426 comm="smartd" name="smartd.WDC_WD2500BEKT_75PVMT0-WD_WXC1A21E0454.ata.state" dev=sda6 ino=582373 scontext=system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:var_lib_t tclass=file
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.081:296): avc:  denied  { add_name } for  pid=3426 comm="smartd" name="smartd.WDC_WD2500BEKT_75PVMT0-WD_WXC1A21E0454.ata.state~" scontext=system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:var_lib_t tclass=dir
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.081:297): avc:  denied  { create } for  pid=3426 comm="smartd" name="smartd.WDC_WD2500BEKT_75PVMT0-WD_WXC1A21E0454.ata.state" scontext=system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:var_lib_t tclass=file
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.081:298): avc:  denied  { write open } for  pid=3426 comm="smartd" name="smartd.WDC_WD2500BEKT_75PVMT0-WD_WXC1A21E0454.ata.state" dev=sda6 ino=582390 scontext=system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:var_lib_t tclass=file
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.081:299): avc:  denied  { getattr } for  pid=3426 comm="smartd" path="/var/lib/smartmontools/smartd.WDC_WD2500BEKT_75PVMT0-WD_WXC1A21E0454.ata.state" dev=sda6 ino=582390 scontext=system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:var_lib_t tclass=file
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.309:300): avc:  denied  { append } for  pid=1316 comm="syslog-ng" name="acpid" dev=sda6 ino=582296 scontext=system_u:system_r:syslogd_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:apmd_log_t tclass=file
            </screen>
  </example>

  <para>
   At first look, the lines in <filename>audit.log</filename> are a bit hard
   to read. However, on closer examination they are not that hard to
   understand. Every line can be broken down into some default sections.
   Let’s have a look at the different sections in the last line:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>type=AVC</literal>:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      every &selnx;-related audit log line starts with the type
      identification <literal>type=AVC</literal>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>msg=audit(1348173901.309:300)</literal>: </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This is the time stamp, which unfortunately is written in epoch time,
      the number of seconds that have passed since Jan 1, 1970. You can use
      <command>date -d</command> on the part up to the dot in the epoch time
      notation to find out when the event has happened:
     </para>
<screen>mmi:~ # date -d @1348173901
Thu Sep 20 16:45:01 EDT 2012</screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>avc: denied { append }</literal>:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      the specific action that was denied. In this case the system has
      denied the appending of data to a file. While browsing through the
      audit log file, you can see other system actions, such as write open,
      getattr and more.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>for pid=1316</literal>:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      the process ID of the command or process that initiated the action
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>comm=”syslog-ng”</literal>:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      the specific command that was associated with that PID
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>name=”acpid”</literal>:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      the name of the subject of the action
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>dev=sda6 ino=582296</literal>:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      the block device and inode number of the file that was involved
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>scontext=system_u:system_r:syslogd_t</literal>:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      the source context, which is the context of the initiator of the
      action
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>tclass=file</literal>:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      a class identification of the subject
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   Instead of interpreting the events in audit.log yourself, there is
   another approach. You can use the <command>audit2allow</command> command,
   which helps analyze the cryptic log messages in
   <filename>/var/log/audit/audit.log</filename>. An audit2allow
   troubleshooting session always consists of three different commands.
   First, you would use <command>audit2allow -w -a</command> to present the
   audit information in a more readable way. The <command>audit2allow -w
   -a</command> by default works on the audit.log file. If you want to
   analyze a specific message in the audit.log file, copy it to a temporary
   file and analyze that, using <command>audit2allow -w -i
   filename</command>:
  </para>

  <example>
   <title>Analyzing audit messages using audit2allow</title>
<screen>mmi:/var/log/audit # audit2allow -w -i testfile
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.309:300): avc:  denied  { append } for  pid=1316
comm="syslog-ng" name="acpid" dev=sda6 ino=582296
scontext=system_u:system_r:syslogd_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:apmd_log_t tclass=file</screen>
  </example>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>This was caused by:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Missing type enforcement (TE) allow rule.
     </para>
     <para>
      You can use <command>audit2allow</command> to generate a loadable
      module to allow this access.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   To find out which specific rule has denied access, you can use
   <command>audit2allow -a</command> to show the enforcing rules from all
   events that were logged to the <filename>audit.log </filename> file, or
   <command>audit2allow -i filename</command> to show it for messages that
   you have stored in a specific file:
  </para>

  <example>
   <title>Using audit2allow to see which lines have denied access</title>
<screen>mmi:/var/log/audit # audit2allow -i testfile
                                
#============= syslogd_t ==============
allow syslogd_t apmd_log_t:file append;</screen>
  </example>

  <para>
   As the last part, use <command>audit2allow -a -M mymodule</command> to
   create an &selnx; module with the name mymodule that you can load in
   order to allow the access that was previously denied. If you want to do
   this for all events that have been logged to the audit.log, use the
   <option>-a -M</option> command arguments. To do it only for specific
   messages that are in a specific file, use <option>-i -M</option> as in
   the example below:
  </para>

  <example>
   <title>Use audit2allow to create a policy module that will allow the action that was previously denied</title>
<screen>mmi:/var/log/audit # audit2allow -i testfile -M blah
******************** IMPORTANT ***********************
To make this policy package active, execute:
                
semodule -i blah.pp</screen>
  </example>

  <para>
   As indicated by the <command>audit2allow</command> command, you can now
   run this module by using the <command>semodule -i</command> command,
   followed by the name of the module that <command>audit2allow</command>
   has just created for you.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Switching to Enforcing Mode</title>

  <para>
   With everything you've done so far, you still cannot switch SELinux to
   enforcing mode. This is because of a misconfiguration in the context
   types for some files. If you switch to enforcing mode now, you can see
   that many AVC denied messages are written that are related to the tmpfs,
   and following these messages your system hangs with the message
   <quote>“INIT: Id “1” respawning too fast”</quote>.
  </para>

  <example>
   <title>The messages that you'll see, just before the system stops, look as follows:</title>
<screen>[ 5.595812] type=1400 audit(1361363803.588:3): avc: denied { read write }
                for pid=431 comm=”sh” name=”console” dev=tmpfs ino=2513
                scontext=system_u:system_r:sysadm_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:tmpfs_t
                tclass=chr_file
                [ 5.607734] type=1400 audit(1361363803.604:4): avc: denied { read write } for
                pid=431 comm=”sh” path=”/dev/console” dev=tmpfs ino=2513
                scontext=system_u:system_r:sysadm_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:tmpfs_t
                tclass=chr_file</screen>
  </example>

  <para>
   As you will see, this message is repeated several times.
  </para>

  <para>
   To fix this problem, reboot your computer in permissive mode. Copy the
   <filename>/var/log/audit/audit.log</filename> file to a temporary file
   (like <filename>/var/log/audit/audit.2allow</filename>) and remove all
   lines with the exception of the lines that contain the audit log messages
   for the errors listed above. Assuming that the name of the log file that
   you've created is <filename>audit.2allow</filename>, you should now run
   the following command: <command>audit2allow -i audit.2allow -M
   bootme</command>.
  </para>

  <para>
   This creates a policy module file with the name
   <filename>bootme.pe</filename>. Make sure that this module is included in
   your &selnx; configuration by using <command>semodule -i
   bootme.pp</command>. Now reboot your computer in enforcing mode. You will
   be able to boot and log in as root in your &selnx;-protected system. If
   this is not the case, you'll have to repeat this procedure until you have
   no more messages in your <filename>audit.log</filename> that refer to
   <filename>path=”/dev/console” dev=tmpfs</filename>. This may involve
   several reboots.
  </para>

  <para>
   From here, the fine tuning begins. You will notice that many items on
   your system don't work yet. You'll have to fix them one by one. The
   approach for fixing all of these errors is by using audit2allow as
   described in the above example, and by setting the appropriate context on
   files and directories on your system. Until a supported version of the
   &selnx; policy is provided with SUSE Linux Enterprise, you'll have to
   follow this approach to get it to work. At least using this procedure
   does allow you to configure a computer with the very detailed security
   settings that are offered with &selnx; and will make your system more
   secure than when using other solutions.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
