<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.selinux">
 <title>Configuring &selnx;</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  In this chapter, you will learn how to set up and manage &selnx; on
  &productname;. The following topics are covered:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Why Use &selnx;?
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Understanding &selnx;
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Setting up &selnx;
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Managing &selnx;
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.selinux.why">
  <title>Why Use &selnx;?</title>

  <para>
   &selnx; was developed as an additional Linux security solution that uses
   the security framework in the Linux kernel. The purpose was to allow for
   a more granular security policy that goes beyond what is offered by the
   default existing permissions of Read, Write, and Execute, and also beyond
   assigning permissions to the different capabilities that are available on
   Linux. &selnx; does this by trapping all system calls that reach the
   kernel, and denying them by default. This means that on a system that has
   &selnx; enabled and nothing else configured, nothing will work. To allow
   your system to do anything, as an administrator you will need to write
   rules and put them in a policy.
  </para>

  <para>
   An example explains why a solution such as &selnx; (or its counterpart
   &aa;) is needed:
  </para>

  <para>
   <quote>One morning, I found out that my server was hacked. The server was
   running a fully patched &slsa; installation. A firewall was configured on
   it and no unnecessary services were offered by this server. Further
   analysis learned that the hacker had come in through a flaky PHP script
   that was a part of one of the Apache virtual hosts that were running on
   this server. The intruder had managed to get access to a shell, using the
   <systemitem class="username">wwwrun</systemitem> account that was used by
   the Apache Web server. As this
   <systemitem class="username">wwwrun</systemitem> user, the intruder had
   created several scripts in the <filename>/var/tmp</filename> and the
   <filename>/tmp</filename> directories, which were a part of a botnet that
   was launching a Distributed Denial of Service attack against a number of
   servers.</quote>
  </para>

  <para>
   The interesting thing about this hack is that it occurred on a server
   where nothing was really wrong. All permissions where set OK, but the
   intruder had managed to get into the system. What becomes clearly evident
   from this example is that in some cases additional security is
   needed&mdash;a security that goes beyond what is offered by using
   &selnx;. As a less complete and less complex alternative, &aa; can be
   used.
  </para>

  <para>
   &aa; confines specific processes in their abilities to read/write and
   execute files (and other things). Its view is mostly that things that
   happen inside a process cannot escape.
  </para>

  <para>
   &selnx; instead uses labels attached to objects (e.g. files, binaries,
   network sockets) and uses them to determine privilege boundaries, thereby
   building up a level of confinement that can span more than a process or
   even the whole system.
  </para>

  <para>
   &selnx; was developed by the US National Security Agency (NSA), and since
   the beginning Red Hat has been heavily involved in its development. The
   first version of &selnx; was offered in the era of <trademark>Red Hat
   Enterprise Linux 4</trademark>, around the year 2006. In the beginning it
   offered support for essential services only, but over the years it has
   developed into a system that offers many rules that are collected in
   policies to offer protection to a broad range of services.
  </para>

  <para>
   &selnx; was developed in accordance with some certification standards
   like Common Criteria and FIPS 140. Because some customers specifically
   requested solutions that met these standards, &selnx; rapidly became
   relatively popular.
  </para>

  <para>
   As an alternative to &selnx;, Immunix, a company that was purchased by
   Novell in 2005, had developed &aa;. &aa; was built on top of the same
   security principles as &selnx;, but took a completely different approach,
   where it was possible to restrict services to exactly what they needed to
   do by using an easy to use wizard-driven procedure. Nevertheless, &aa;
   has never reached the same status as &selnx;, even if there are some good
   arguments to secure a server with &aa; rather than with &selnx;.
  </para>

  <para>
   Because many organizations are requesting &selnx; to be present in the
   Linux distributions they are using, &suse; is offering support for the
   &selnx; framework in &productname;. This does not mean that the default
   installation of &productname; will switch from &aa; to &selnx; in the
   near future.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.selinux.support">
   <title>Support Status</title>
   <para>
    The &selnx; framework is supported on &productname;. This means that
    &productnameshort; offers all binaries and libraries you need to be able
    to use &selnx; on your server. It also includes a reference policy and
    reference policy minimum base module. You may miss some software that
    you may be familiar with from other Linux distributions.
   </para>
   <para>
    <remark>sknorr, 2014-08-22: Still true? This was written for 11 SP2.</remark>
    <remark>tbazant, 2015-10-19: Still true.</remark>
    &selnx; support is at a fairly early stage in &productname;, which means
    that unexpected behavior may occur. To limit this risk as much as
    possible, it is best to use only the binaries that have been provided by
    default on &productname;.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.selinux.component">
   <title>Understanding &selnx; Components</title>
   <para>
    Before starting the configuration of &selnx;, you should know a bit
    about how &selnx; is organized. Three components play a role:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The security framework in the Linux kernel
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The &selnx; libraries and binaries
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The &selnx; policy
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    The default kernel of &productname; supports &selnx; and the tools that
    are needed to manage it. The most important part of the work of the
    administrator with regard to &selnx; is managing the policy.
   </para>
   <para>
    In the &selnx; policy, security labels are applied to different objects
    on a Linux server. These objects typically are users, ports, processes
    and files. Using these security labels, rules are created that define
    what is and what is not allowed on a server. Remember, by default
    &selnx; denies all system calls and by creating the appropriate rules
    you can allow the system calls that you trust again. Rules should
    therefore exist for all programs that you want to use on a system.
    Alternatively, you may want to configure parts of a system to run in
    unconfined mode, which means that specific ports, programs, users, files
    and directories are not protected at all by &selnx;. This mode is useful
    if you only want to use &selnx; to protect some essential services,
    while you are not specifically worried about other services. To get a
    really secure system, you should avoid this.
   </para>
   <para>
    To ensure the appropriate protection of your system, you need an &selnx;
    policy. This must be a tailor-made policy in which all files are
    provided with a label, and all services and users have a security label
    as well to express which files and directories can be accessed by which
    user and processed on the server. Developing such a policy is a
    tremendous amount of work.
   </para>
   <para>
    The complexity of &selnx; is also one of the main arguments against
    using it. Because a typical Linux system is so very complex, it is easy
    to overlook something and leave an opening that intruders can abuse to
    get into your system. And even if it is set up completely the way it
    should be, it still is very hard for an administrator to overlook all
    aspects with &selnx;. With regard to the complexity, &aa; takes a
    completely different approach and works with automated procedures that
    allow the administrator to set up &aa; protection and understand exactly
    what is happening.
   </para>
   <para>
    Note that a freely available &selnx; policy might work on your server,
    but is unlikely to offer the same protection as a custom policy. &suse;
    also does not support third-party policies.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.selinux.policy">
  <title>Policy</title>

  <para>
   As mentioned, the policy is the key component in &selnx;. It defines
   rules that specify which objects can access which files, directories,
   ports and processes on a system. To do this, a security context is
   defined for all of these. On an &selnx; system where the policy has been
   applied to label the file system, you can use the <command>ls
   -Z</command> command on any directory to find the security context for
   the files in that directory.
   <xref linkend="ex.selnx.con.set" xrefstyle="select:label quotedtitle nopage"/>
   shows the security context settings for the directories in the
   <filename>/</filename> directory of a &productname; system with an
   &selnx;-labeled file system.
  </para>

  <example xml:id="ex.selnx.con.set">
   <title>Security Context Settings Using <command>ls -Z</command></title>
<screen>ls -Z
system_u:object_r:default_t .autorelabel
system_u:object_r:file_t .viminfo
system_u:object_r:bin_t bin
system_u:object_r:boot_t boot
system_u:object_r:device_t dev
system_u:object_r:etc_t etc
system_u:object_r:home_root_t home
system_u:object_r:lib_t lib
system_u:object_r:lib_t lib64
system_u:object_r:lost_found_t lost+found
system_u:object_r:mnt_t media
system_u:object_r:mnt_t mnt
system_u:object_r:usr_t opt
system_u:object_r:proc_t proc
system_u:object_r:default_t root
system_u:object_r:bin_t sbin
system_u:object_r:security_t selinux
system_u:object_r:var_t srv
system_u:object_r:sysfs_t sys
system_u:object_r:tmp_t tmp
system_u:object_r:usr_t usr
system_u:object_r:var_t var
system_u:object_r:httpd_sys_content_t www</screen>
  </example>

  <para>
   The most important line in the security context is the context type. This
   is the part of the security context that ends in _t. It tells &selnx;
   which kind of access the object is allowed. In the policy, rules are
   specified to define which type of user or which type of role has access
   to which type of context. For example, this can happen by using a rule
   like the following:
  </para>

<screen>allow user_t bin_t:file {read execute gettattr};</screen>

  <para>
   This example rule states that the user who has the context type
   <systemitem class="username">user_t</systemitem> (this user is referred
   to as the source object) is allowed to access the file with the context
   type <filename>bin_t</filename> (the target), using the permissions read,
   execute and getattr.
  </para>

  <para>
   The standard policy that you are going to use contains a huge amount of
   rules. To make it more manageable, policies are often split into modules.
   This allows administrator to switch protection on or off for different
   parts of the system.
  </para>

  <para>
   When compiling the policy for your system, you will have a choice to
   either work with a modular policy, or a monolithic policy, where one huge
   policy is used to protect everything on your system. It is strongly
   recommended to use a modular policy and not a monolithic policy. Modular
   policies are much easier to manage.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.selinux.install">
  <title>Installing &selnx; Packages and Modifying &grub;</title>

  <para>
   The easiest way to make sure that all &selnx; components are installed is
   by using &yast;. The procedure described below shows what to do on an
   installed &productname;:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log in to your server as <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>
     and start &yast;.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Software</guimenu> <guimenu>Software
     Management</guimenu> </menuchoice>
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     <menuchoice> <guimenu>Select View</guimenu> <guimenu>Patterns</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> and select the entire C<guimenu>/C++ Compiler and
     Tools</guimenu> software category for installation.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     <menuchoice> <guimenu>Select View</guimenu> <guimenu>Search</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> and make sure that <guimenu>Search in Name</guimenu>,
     <guimenu>Keywords</guimenu> and <guimenu>Summary</guimenu> are
     selected. Now enter the keyword <literal>selinux</literal> and click
     <guimenu>Search</guimenu>. You now see a list of packages.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Make sure that all the packages you have found are selected and click
     <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to install them.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <figure xml:id="fig.packages.yast">
   <title>Selecting all &selnx; Packages in &yast;</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="pdf">
     <imagedata fileref="selnx_policy_compiler.png" width="85%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="selnx_policy_compiler.png" width="95%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   After installing the &selnx; packages, you need to modify the &grub; boot
   loader. Do this from &yast;, select <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>System</guimenu> <guimenu>Boot Loader</guimenu> <guimenu>Kernel
   Parameters</guimenu></menuchoice>. Now add the following parameters to
   the <guimenu>Optional Kernel Command Line Parameters</guimenu>:
  </para>

<screen>security=selinux selinux=1 enforcing=0</screen>

  <para>
   These options are used for the following purposes:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>security=selinux</literal>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option tells the kernel to use &selnx; and not &aa;
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>selinux=1</literal>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option switches on &selnx;
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>enforcing=0</literal>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option puts &selnx; in permissive mode. In this mode, &selnx; is
      fully functional, but does not enforce any of the security settings in
      the policy. Use this mode for configuring your system. To switch on
      &selnx; protection, when the system is fully operational, change the
      option to <literal>enforcing=1</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   After installing the &selnx; packages and enabling the &selnx; &grub;
   boot options, reboot your server to activate the configuration.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.selinux.compilepolicy">
  <title>&selnx; Policy</title>

  <para>
   Policy is an essential component of &selnx;. &productname; 12 SP1
   includes the <emphasis>minimum</emphasis> &selnx; reference policy in the
   <systemitem>selinux-policy-minimum</systemitem> package. The examples in
   this chapter refer to this policy if not stated otherwise.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <para>
    To install a different policy, you need to download it from
    <link xlink:href="https://build.opensuse.org/package/binaries/security:SELinux/selinux-policy?repository=SLE_12"/>
    and install:
<screen>sudo zypper in selinux-policy-targeted-<replaceable>version_number</replaceable>.noarch.rpm</screen>
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
   After installing the policy, you are ready to start file system labeling.
   Run
  </para>

<screen>restorecon -Rv /</screen>

  <para>
   to start the <command>/sbin/setfiles</command> command to label all files
   on your system. The
   <filename>/etc/selinux/minimum/contexts/files/file_contexts</filename>
   input file is used. The <filename>file_contexts</filename> file needs to
   match your actual file system as much as possible. Otherwise, it can lead
   to a completely unbootable system. If that happens, tune the contents of
   the <filename>file_contexts</filename> file to match the structure of the
   file system your server is using. Before doing this, make sure to read
   the rest of this chapter, so you fully understand how context type is
   applied to files and directories. Do not forget to make a backup of the
   <filename>file_contexts</filename> file before starting.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>The User <systemitem class="username">nobody</systemitem></title>
   <para>
    While using <command>semanage</command>, you may get a message that
    complains about the home directory of
    <systemitem class="username">nobody</systemitem>. In this case, change
    the login shell of user <systemitem class="username">nobody</systemitem>
    to <filename>/sbin/nologin</filename>. Then the settings of
    <systemitem class="username">nobody</systemitem> match the current
    policy settings.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   After another reboot &selnx; should be operational. To verify this, use
   the command <command>sestatus -v</command>. It should give you an output
   similar to
   <xref linkend="ex.selnx.sestatus" xrefstyle="select:label quotedtitle nopage"/>.
  </para>

  <example xml:id="ex.selnx.sestatus">
   <title>Verifying that &selnx; is functional</title>
<screen>sestatus -v
SELinux status:                 enabled
SELinuxfs mount:                /selinux
Current mode:                   permissive
Mode from config file:          permissive
Policy version:                 26
Policy from config file:        minimum
                
Process contexts:
Current context:                root:staff_r:staff_t
Init context:                   system_u:system_r:init_t
/sbin/mingetty                  system_u:system_r:sysadm_t
/usr/sbin/sshd                  system_u:system_r:sshd_t
                
File contexts:
Controlling term:               root:object_r:user_devpts_t
/etc/passwd                     system_u:object_r:etc_t
/etc/shadow                     system_u:object_r:shadow_t
/bin/bash                       system_u:object_r:shell_exec_t
/bin/login                      system_u:object_r:login_exec_t
/bin/sh                         system_u:object_r:bin_t -&gt; system_u:object_r:shell_exec_t
/sbin/agetty                    system_u:object_r:getty_exec_t
/sbin/init                      system_u:object_r:init_exec_t
/sbin/mingetty                  system_u:object_r:getty_exec_t
/usr/sbin/sshd                  system_u:object_r:sshd_exec_t
/lib/libc.so.6                  system_u:object_r:lib_t -&gt; system_u:object_r:lib_t
/lib/ld-linux.so.2              system_u:object_r:lib_t -&gt; system_u:object_r:ld_so_t</screen>
  </example>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.selinux.configure">
  <title>Configuring &selnx;</title>

  <para>
   At this point you have a completely functional &selnx; system and it is
   time to further configure it. In the current status, &selnx; is
   operational but not in enforcing mode. This means that it does not limit
   you in doing anything, it logs everything that it should be doing if it
   were in enforcing mode. This is good, because based on the log files you
   can find what it is that it would prevent you from doing. As a first
   test, put &selnx; in enforcing mode and find out if you can still use
   your server after doing so: open the
   <filename>/etc/selinux/config</filename> file and make sure that the
   option <option>enforcing=1</option> is set. Reboot your server and see if
   it still comes up the way you expect it to. If it does, leave it like
   that and start modifying the server in a way that everything works as
   expected. However, you may not even be able to boot the server properly.
   In that case, switch back to the mode where &selnx; is not enforcing and
   start tuning your server.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.selinux.verify">
   <title>Verifying the Installation</title>
   <para>
    Before you start tuning your server, verify the &selnx; installation.
    You have already used the command <command>sestatus -v</command> to view
    the current mode, process, and file contexts. Next, run
   </para>
<screen>semanage boolean -l</screen>
   <para>
    which shows a list of all Boolean switches that are available, and at
    the same time verifies that you can access the policy.
    <xref linkend="ex.selnx.ls.bool"/> shows part of the output of this
    command.
   </para>
   <example xml:id="ex.selnx.ls.bool">
    <title>Getting a List of Booleans and Verifying Policy Access</title>
<screen>semanage boolean -l
SELinux boolean                          Description
ftp_home_dir                   -&gt; off   ftp_home_dir
mozilla_read_content           -&gt; off   mozilla_read_content
spamassassin_can_network       -&gt; off   spamassassin_can_network
httpd_can_network_relay        -&gt; off   httpd_can_network_relay
openvpn_enable_homedirs        -&gt; off   openvpn_enable_homedirs
gpg_agent_env_file             -&gt; off   gpg_agent_env_file
allow_httpd_awstats_script_anon_write -&gt; off   allow_httpd_awstats_script_anon_write
httpd_can_network_connect_db   -&gt; off   httpd_can_network_connect_db
allow_ftpd_full_access         -&gt; off   allow_ftpd_full_access
samba_domain_controller        -&gt; off   samba_domain_controller
httpd_enable_cgi               -&gt; off   httpd_enable_cgi
virt_use_nfs                   -&gt; off   virt_use_nfs</screen>
    <para>
     Another command that outputs useful information at this stage is
    </para>
<screen>semanage fcontext -l</screen>
    <para>
     It shows the default file context settings as provided by the policy
     (see
     <xref linkend="ex.selnx.fcon" xrefstyle="select:label quotedtitle nopage"/>
     for partial output of this command).
    </para>
   </example>
   <example xml:id="ex.selnx.fcon">
    <title>Getting File Context Information</title>
<screen>semanage fcontext -l
/var/run/usb(/.*)?                                 all files          system_u:object_r:hotplug_var_run_t
/var/run/utmp                                      regular file       system_u:object_r:initrc_var_run_t
/var/run/vbe.*                                     regular file       system_u:object_r:hald_var_run_t
/var/run/vmnat.*                                   socket             system_u:object_r:vmware_var_run_t
/var/run/vmware.*                                  all files          system_u:object_r:vmware_var_run_t
/var/run/vpnc(/.*)?                                all files          system_u:object_r:vpnc_var_run_t
/var/run/watchdog\.pid                             regular file       system_u:object_r:watchdog_var_run_t
/var/run/winbindd(/.*)?                            all files          system_u:object_r:winbind_var_run_t
/var/run/wnn-unix(/.*)                             all files          system_u:object_r:canna_var_run_t
/var/run/wpa_supplicant(/.*)?                      all files          system_u:object_r:NetworkManager_var_run_t
/var/run/wpa_supplicant-global                     socket             system_u:object_r:NetworkManager_var_run_t
/var/run/xdmctl(/.*)?                              all files          system_u:object_r:xdm_var_run_t
/var/run/yiff-[0-9]+\.pid                          regular file       system_u:object_r:soundd_var_run_t</screen>
   </example>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.selinux.manage">
  <title>Managing &selnx;</title>

  <para>
   The base &selnx; configuration is now operational and it can now be
   configured to secure your server. In &selnx;, an additional set of rules
   is used to define exactly which process or user can access which files,
   directories, or ports. To do this, &selnx; applies a context to every
   file, directory, process, and port. This context is a security label that
   defines how this file, directory, process, or port should be treated.
   These context labels are used by the &selnx; policy, which defines
   exactly what should be done with the context labels. By default, the
   policy blocks all non-default access, which means that, as an
   administrator, you need to enable all features that are non-default on
   your server.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.selinux.viewcontext">
   <title>Viewing the Security Context</title>
   <para>
    As already mentioned, files, directories, and ports can be labeled.
    Within each label, different contexts are used. To be able to perform
    your daily administration work, the type context is what you are most
    interested in. As an administrator, you will mostly work with the type
    context. Many commands allow you to use the <option>-Z</option> option
    to show a list of current context settings. In
    <xref linkend="ex.selnx.def.con" xrefstyle="select:label quotedtitle nopage"/>
    you can see what the context settings are for the directories in the
    root directory.
   </para>
   <example xml:id="ex.selnx.def.con">
    <title>The default context for directories in the root directory</title>
<screen>ls -Z
dr-xr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:bin_t:s0       bin
dr-xr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:boot_t:s0      boot
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:cgroup_t:s0    cgroup
drwxr-xr-x+ root root unconfined_u:object_r:default_t:s0 data
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:device_t:s0    dev
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:etc_t:s0       etc
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:home_root_t:s0 home
dr-xr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:lib_t:s0       lib
dr-xr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:lib_t:s0       lib64
drwx------. root root system_u:object_r:lost_found_t:s0 lost+found
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:mnt_t:s0       media
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:autofs_t:s0    misc
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:mnt_t:s0       mnt
drwxr-xr-x. root root unconfined_u:object_r:default_t:s0 mnt2
drwxr-xr-x. root root unconfined_u:object_r:default_t:s0 mounts
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:autofs_t:s0    net
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:usr_t:s0       opt
dr-xr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:proc_t:s0      proc
drwxr-xr-x. root root unconfined_u:object_r:default_t:s0 repo
dr-xr-x---. root root system_u:object_r:admin_home_t:s0 root
dr-xr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:bin_t:s0       sbin
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:security_t:s0  selinux
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:var_t:s0       srv
-rw-r--r--. root root unconfined_u:object_r:swapfile_t:s0 swapfile
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:sysfs_t:s0     sys
drwxrwxrwt. root root system_u:object_r:tmp_t:s0       tmp
-rw-r--r--. root root unconfined_u:object_r:etc_runtime_t:s0 tmp2.tar
-rw-r--r--. root root unconfined_u:object_r:etc_runtime_t:s0 tmp.tar
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:usr_t:s0       usr
drwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:var_t:s0       var</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    In the listing above, you can see the complete context for all
    directories. It consists of a user, a role, and a type. The s0 setting
    indicates the security level in Multi Level Security environments. These
    environments are not discussed here. In such an environment, make sure
    that s0 is set. The Context Type defines what kind of activity is
    permitted in the directory. Compare, for example, the
    <filename>/root</filename> directory, which has the
    <filename>admin_home_t</filename> context type, and the
    <filename>/home</filename> directory, which has the
    <filename>home_root_t</filename> context type. In the &selnx; policy,
    different kinds of access are defined for these context types.
   </para>
   <para>
    Security labels are not only associated with files, but also with other
    items, such as ports and processes. In
    <xref linkend="ex.selnx.set.proc" xrefstyle="select:label quotedtitle nopage"/>
    for example you can see the context settings for processes on your
    server.
   </para>
   <example xml:id="ex.selnx.set.proc">
    <title>Showing &selnx; settings for processes</title>
<screen>ps Zaux
LABEL                           USER       PID %CPU %MEM    VSZ   RSS TTY      STAT START   TIME COMMAND
system_u:system_r:init_t        root         1  0.0  0.0  10640   808 ?        Ss   05:31   0:00 init [5]
system_u:system_r:kernel_t      root         2  0.0  0.0      0     0 ?        S    05:31   0:00 [kthreadd]
system_u:system_r:kernel_t      root         3  0.0  0.0      0     0 ?        S    05:31   0:00 [ksoftirqd/0]
system_u:system_r:kernel_t      root         6  0.0  0.0      0     0 ?        S    05:31   0:00 [migration/0]
system_u:system_r:kernel_t      root         7  0.0  0.0      0     0 ?        S    05:31   0:00 [watchdog/0]
system_u:system_r:sysadm_t      root      2344  0.0  0.0  27640   852 ?        Ss   05:32   0:00 /usr/sbin/mcelog --daemon --config-file /etc/mcelog/mcelog.conf
system_u:system_r:sshd_t        root      3245  0.0  0.0  69300  1492 ?        Ss   05:32   0:00 /usr/sbin/sshd -o PidFile=/var/run/sshd.init.pid
system_u:system_r:cupsd_t       root      3265  0.0  0.0  68176  2852 ?        Ss   05:32   0:00 /usr/sbin/cupsd
system_u:system_r:nscd_t        root      3267  0.0  0.0 772876  1380 ?        Ssl  05:32   0:00 /usr/sbin/nscd
system_u:system_r:postfix_master_t root   3334  0.0  0.0  38320  2424 ?        Ss   05:32   0:00 /usr/lib/postfix/master
system_u:system_r:postfix_qmgr_t postfix  3358  0.0  0.0  40216  2252 ?        S    05:32   0:00 qmgr -l -t fifo -u
system_u:system_r:crond_t       root      3415  0.0  0.0  14900   800 ?        Ss   05:32   0:00 /usr/sbin/cron
system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t    root      3437  0.0  0.0  16468  1040 ?        S    05:32   0:00 /usr/sbin/smartd
system_u:system_r:sysadm_t      root      3441  0.0  0.0  66916  2152 ?        Ss   05:32   0:00 login -- root
system_u:system_r:sysadm_t      root      3442  0.0  0.0   4596   800 tty2     Ss+  05:32   0:00 /sbin/mingetty tty2</screen>
   </example>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.selinux.selectmode">
   <title>Selecting the &selnx; Mode</title>
   <para>
    In &selnx;, three different modes can be used:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Enforcing:</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This is the default mode. &selnx; protects your server according to
       the rules in the policy, and &selnx; logs all of its activity to the
       audit log.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Permissive:</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This mode is useful for troubleshooting. If set to Permissive,
       &selnx; does not protect your server, but it still logs everything
       that happens to the log files. Also, in permissive mode, the Linux
       kernel still maintains the &selnx; labels in the file system. This is
       good, because this prevents your system from relabeling everything
       after turning &selnx; on again.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Disabled:</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In this mode, &selnx; is switched off completely and no logging
       occurs. The file system labels however are not removed from the file
       system.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    You have already read how you can set the current &selnx; mode from
    &grub; while booting using the enforcing boot parameter.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.selinux.modifycontext">
   <title>Modifying &selnx; Context Types</title>
   <para>
    An important part of the work of an administrator is setting context
    types on files to ensure appropriate working of &selnx;.
   </para>
   <para>
    If a file is created within a specific directory, it inherits the
    context type of the parent directory by default. If, however, a file is
    moved from one location to another location, it retains the context type
    that it had in the old location.
   </para>
   <para>
    To set the context type for files, you can use the <command>semanage
    fcontext</command> command. With this command, you write the new context
    type to the policy, but it does not change the actual context type
    immediately! To apply the context types that are in the policy, you need
    to run the <command>restorecon</command> command afterwards.
   </para>
   <para>
    The challenge when working with <command>semanage fcontext</command> is
    to find out which context you actually need. You can use
   </para>
<screen>semanage fcontext -l</screen>
   <para>
    to show a list of all contexts in the policy, but it may be a bit hard
    to find out the actual context you need from that list as it is rather
    long (see
    <xref linkend="ex.selnx.semanage" xrefstyle="select:label quotedtitle nopage"/>).
   </para>
   <example xml:id="ex.selnx.semanage">
    <title>Viewing Default File Contexts</title>
<screen>semanage fcontext -l | less
&selnx; fcontext                                   type               Context
              
/                                                  directory          system_u:object_r:root_t:s0
/.*                                                all files          system_u:object_r:default_t:s0
/[^/]+                                             regular file       system_u:object_r:etc_runtime_t:s0
/\.autofsck                                        regular file       system_u:object_r:etc_runtime_t:s0
/\.autorelabel                                     regular file       system_u:object_r:etc_runtime_t:s0
/\.journal                                         all files          X:&gt;&gt;None&gt;&gt;
/\.suspended                                       regular file       system_u:object_r:etc_runtime_t:s0
/a?quota\.(user|group)                             regular file       system_u:object_r:quota_db_t:s0
/afs                                               directory          system_u:object_r:mnt_t:s0
/bin                                               directory          system_u:object_r:bin_t:s0
/bin/.*                                            all files          system_u:object_r:bin_t:s0</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    There are three ways to find out which context settings are available
    for your services:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Install the service and look at the default context settings that are
      used. This is the easiest and recommended option.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Consult the man page for the specific service. Some services have a
      man page that ends in <literal>_selinux</literal>, which contains all
      the information you need to find the correct context settings.
     </para>
     <para>
      When you have found the right context setting, apply it using
      <command>semanage fcontext</command>. This command takes
      <option>-t</option> context type as its first argument, followed by
      the name of the directory or file to which you want to apply the
      context settings. To apply the context to everything that already
      exists in the directory where you want to apply the context, you add
      the regular expression <literal>(/.*)?</literal> to the name of the
      directory. This means: optionally, match a slash followed by any
      character. The examples section of the <command>semanage</command> man
      page has some useful usage examples for <command>semanage</command>.
      For more information on regular expressions, see for example the
      tutorial at <link xlink:href="http://www.regular-expressions.info/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Display a list of all context types that are available on your system:
     </para>
<screen>seinfo -t</screen>
     <para>
      Since the command by itself outputs an overwhelming amount of
      information, it should be used in combination with
      <command>grep</command> or a similar command for filtering.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.selinux.applyfilecontext">
   <title>Applying File Contexts</title>
   <para>
    To help you apply the &selnx; context properly, the following procedure
    shows how to set a context using <command>semanage fcontext</command>
    and <command>restorecon</command>. You will notice that at first
    attempt, the Web server with a non-default document root does not work.
    After changing the &selnx; context, it will.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Create the <filename>/web</filename> directory and then change to it:
     </para>
<screen>sudo mkdir /web  &amp;&amp; cd /web</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use a text editor to create the file
      <filename>/web/index.html</filename> that contains the text welcome to
      my Web site.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Open the file <filename>/etc/apache2/default-server.conf</filename>
      with an editor, and change the DocumentRoot line to
      <literal>DocumentRoot /web</literal>
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the Apache Web server:
     </para>
<screen>sudo systemctl start apache2</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Open a session to your local Web server:
     </para>
<screen>w3m localhost</screen>
     <para>
      You will receive a <emphasis>Connection refused</emphasis> message.
      Press <keycap function="enter"/>, and then <command>q</command> to
      quit w3m.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Find the current context type for the default Apache
      <literal>DocumentRoot</literal>, which is
      <filename>/srv/www/htdocs</filename>. It should be set to
      <filename>httpd_sys_content_t</filename>:
     </para>
<screen>ls -Z /srv/www</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Set the new context in the policy and press
      <keycap function="enter"/>:
     </para>
<screen>semanage fcontext -a -f "" -t httpd_sys_content_t '/web(/.*) ?'</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Apply the new context type:
     </para>
<screen>restorecon /web</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Show the context of the files in the directory
      <filename>/web</filename>. You will see that the new context type has
      been set properly to the <filename>/web</filename> directory, but not
      to its contents.
     </para>
<screen>ls -Z /web</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Apply the new context recursively to the <filename>/web</filename>
      directory. The type context has now been set correctly.
     </para>
<screen>restorecon -R /web</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Restart the Web server:
     </para>
<screen>sudo systemctl restart apache2</screen>
     <para>
      You should now be able to access the contents of the
      <filename>/web</filename> directory.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.selinux.configurepolicy">
   <title>Configuring &selnx; Policies</title>
   <para>
    The easiest way to change the behavior of the policy is by working with
    Booleans. These are on-off switches that you can use to change the
    settings in the policy. To find out which Booleans are available, run
   </para>
<screen>semanage boolean -l</screen>
   <para>
    It will show you a long list of Booleans, with a short description of
    what each of these Booleans will do for you. When you have found the
    Boolean you want to set, you can use <command>setsebool -P</command>,
    followed by the name of the Boolean that you want to change. It is
    important to use the <option>-P</option> option at all times when using
    <command>setsebool</command>. This option writes the setting to the
    policy file on disk, and this is the only way to make sure that the
    Boolean is applied automatically after a reboot.
   </para>
   <para>
    The procedure below gives an example of changing Boolean settings
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      List Booleans that are related to FTP servers.
<screen>semanage boolean -l | grep ftp</screen>
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Turn the Boolean off:
     </para>
<screen>setsebool allow_ftpd_anon_write off</screen>
     <para>
      Note that it does not take much time to write the change. Then verify
      that the Boolean is indeed turned off:
<screen>semanage boolean -l|grep ftpd_anon</screen>
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Reboot your server.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Check again to see if the <literal>allow_ftpd_anon_write</literal>
      Boolean is still turned on. As it has not yet been written to the
      policy, you will notice that it is off.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Switch the Boolean and write the setting to the policy:
     </para>
<screen>setsebool -P allow_ftpd_anon_write</screen>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.selinux.module">
   <title>Working with &selnx; Modules</title>
   <para>
    By default, &selnx; is compiled as modular. This means that the policy
    that implements &selnx; features is not just one huge policy, but it
    consists of many smaller modules. Each module covers a specific part of
    the &selnx; configuration. The concept of the &selnx; module was
    introduced to make it easier for third party vendors to make their
    services compatible with &selnx;. To get an overview of the &selnx;
    modules, you can use the <command>semodule -l</command> command. This
    command shows a list of all current modules in use by &selnx; and their
    version numbers.
   </para>
   <para>
    As an administrator, you can switch modules on or off. This can be
    useful if you want to disable only a part of &selnx; and not everything
    to run a specific service without &selnx; protection. Especially in the
    case of &productname;, where there is not a completely supported &selnx;
    policy yet, it can make sense to switch off all modules that you do not
    need so that you can focus on the services that really do need &selnx;
    protection. To switch off an &selnx; module, use
   </para>
<screen>semodule -d <replaceable>modulename</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    If you want to switch it on again, you can use
   </para>
<screen>semodule -e modulename</screen>
   <para>
    It will change the current state of the module in the
    <filename>/etc/selinux/minimum/policy/modules.conf</filename> file.
    Alternatively, you could also edit this file by hand.
   </para>
   <para>
    To handle policy modules properly, it helps to understand what you are
    dealing with. In the end, a policy module is a compiled policy file that
    you can load using the <command>semodule -e</command> command. You can
    recognize these files by the extension they use:
    *<filename>.pp</filename> (which stands for Policy Package). In some
    cases it can be useful to modify modules to have them do exactly what
    you need them to do. Three different kinds of files are used as input
    files for policy modules and you can find them in subdirectories of the
    <filename>/etc/selinux/minimum/policy/modules</filename> directory:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <filename>*.te</filename> files contain transition rules. These rules
      tell the policy how to deal with specific subprocesses that are
      started. You will not often change these as an administrator.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <filename>*.if</filename> files define what exactly the policy should
      be doing. As an administrator you do not typically change the contents
      of these files.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <filename>*.fc</filename> files contain the labeling instructions that
      apply to this policy. As an administrator, you might want to change
      the contents of the <filename>.fc</filename> files to modify the
      default behavior of policies.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    In
    <xref linkend="ex.selnx.li.apachefc" xrefstyle="select:label quotedtitle nopage"/>
    below you can see the first 20 lines of the
    <filename>apache.fc</filename> file. This is the file that contains the
    default file contexts that are used for the Apache server.
   </para>
   <example xml:id="ex.selnx.li.apachefc">
    <title>The First 20 Lines of <filename>apache.fc</filename></title>
<screen>/etc/apache(2)?(/.*)? gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_config_t,s0)
/etc/apache-ssl(2)?(/.*)? gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_config_t,s0)
/etc/htdig(/.*)? gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_sys_content_t,s0)
/etc/httpd -d gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_config_t,s0) /etc/httpd/conf.*
gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_config_t,s0) /etc/httpd/logs
gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_log_t,s0) /etc/httpd/modules
gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_modules_t,s0) /etc/vhosts --
gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_config_t,s0) /srv/([^/]*/)?www(/.*)?
gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_sys_content_t,s0) /srv/gallery2(/.*)?
gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_sys_content_t,s0) /usr/bin/htsslpass --
gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_helper_exec_t,s0) /usr/lib/apache-ssl/.+ --
gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_exec_t,s0) /usr/lib/cgi-bin(/.*)?
gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_sys_script_exec_t,s0)
/usr/lib(64)?/apache(/.*)? gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_modules_t,s0)
/usr/lib(64)?/apache2/modules(/.*)?
gen_context(system_u:object_r:httpd_modules_t,s0)</screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    In the <filename>fc</filename> file, you will be able to recognize
    different elements. First is the name of the directory or file to which
    the file context will apply. As you can see, variables can be used (as
    is the case in the first line that starts with
    <varname>HOME_DIR</varname>), and typically, regular expressions will be
    used as well. Next, the gen_context command tells the policy to which
    context the files related to the policy module should be set. This is
    the same context setting that you can see when using <command>ls
    -Z</command> on the file or directory.
   </para>
   <para>
    As an administrator, you do not typically change the contents of the
    policy files that come from the &selnx; Policy RPM. You would rather use
    <command>semanage fcontext</command> to change file contexts. If you are
    using <command>audit2allow</command> to generate policies for your
    server, you might want to change the policy files after all. If you want
    to change the contents of any of the policy module files, you will need
    to compile the changes into a new policy module file. To do this, copy
    or link the &selnx; Makefile from
    <filename>/etc/selinux/minimum</filename> to the directory that contains
    the policy module input files and run the following command to compile
    the module:
   </para>
<screen>make &amp;&amp; make install &amp;&amp; make load</screen>
   <para>
    When <command>make</command> has completed, you can manually load the
    modules into the system, using <command>semodule -e</command>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.selinux.troubleshoot">
  <title>Troubleshooting</title>

  <para>
   By default, if &selnx; is the reason why something is not working, a log
   message to this effect is sent to the
   <filename>/var/log/audit/audit.log</filename> file. That is, if the
   auditd service is running. If you see an empty
   <filename>/var/log/audit</filename>, start the auditd service using
  </para>

<screen>sudo systemctl start auditd</screen>

  <para>
   and enable it in the targets of your system, using
  </para>

<screen>sudo systemctl enable auditd</screen>

  <para>
   In
   <xref linkend="ex.selnx.li.auditlog" xrefstyle="select:label quotedtitle nopage"/>
   you can see a partial example of the contents of
   <filename>/var/log/audit/audit.log</filename>
  </para>

  <example xml:id="ex.selnx.li.auditlog">
   <title>Example Lines from <filename>/etc/audit/audit.log</filename></title>
<screen>type=DAEMON_START msg=audit(1348173810.874:6248): auditd start, ver=1.7.7 format=raw kernel=3.0.13-0.27-default auid=0 pid=4235 subj=system_u:system_r:auditd_t res=success
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.081:292): avc:  denied  { write } for  pid=3426 comm="smartd" name="smartmontools" dev=sda6 ino=581743 scontext=system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:var_lib_t tclass=dir
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.081:293): avc:  denied  { remove_name } for  pid=3426 comm="smartd" name="smartd.WDC_WD2500BEKT_75PVMT0-WD_WXC1A21E0454.ata.state~" dev=sda6 ino=582390 scontext=system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:var_lib_t tclass=dir
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.081:294): avc:  denied  { unlink } for  pid=3426 comm="smartd" name="smartd.WDC_WD2500BEKT_75PVMT0-WD_WXC1A21E0454.ata.state~" dev=sda6 ino=582390 scontext=system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:var_lib_t tclass=file
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.081:295): avc:  denied  { rename } for  pid=3426 comm="smartd" name="smartd.WDC_WD2500BEKT_75PVMT0-WD_WXC1A21E0454.ata.state" dev=sda6 ino=582373 scontext=system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:var_lib_t tclass=file
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.081:296): avc:  denied  { add_name } for  pid=3426 comm="smartd" name="smartd.WDC_WD2500BEKT_75PVMT0-WD_WXC1A21E0454.ata.state~" scontext=system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:var_lib_t tclass=dir
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.081:297): avc:  denied  { create } for  pid=3426 comm="smartd" name="smartd.WDC_WD2500BEKT_75PVMT0-WD_WXC1A21E0454.ata.state" scontext=system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:var_lib_t tclass=file
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.081:298): avc:  denied  { write open } for  pid=3426 comm="smartd" name="smartd.WDC_WD2500BEKT_75PVMT0-WD_WXC1A21E0454.ata.state" dev=sda6 ino=582390 scontext=system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:var_lib_t tclass=file
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.081:299): avc:  denied  { getattr } for  pid=3426 comm="smartd" path="/var/lib/smartmontools/smartd.WDC_WD2500BEKT_75PVMT0-WD_WXC1A21E0454.ata.state" dev=sda6 ino=582390 scontext=system_u:system_r:fsdaemon_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:var_lib_t tclass=file
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.309:300): avc:  denied  { append } for  pid=1316
comm="rsyslogd" name="acpid" dev=sda6 ino=582296 scontext=system_u:system_r:syslogd_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:apmd_log_t tclass=file</screen>
  </example>

  <para>
   At first look, the lines in <filename>audit.log</filename> are a bit hard
   to read. However, on closer examination they are not that hard to
   understand. Every line can be broken down into sections. For example, the
   sections in the last line are:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>type=AVC</literal>:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      every &selnx;-related audit log line starts with the type
      identification <literal>type=AVC</literal>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>msg=audit(1348173901.309:300)</literal>: </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This is the time stamp, which unfortunately is written in epoch time,
      the number of seconds that have passed since Jan 1, 1970. You can use
      <command>date -d</command> on the part up to the dot in the epoch time
      notation to find out when the event has happened:
     </para>
<screen>date -d @1348173901
Thu Sep 20 16:45:01 EDT 2012</screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>avc: denied { append }</literal>:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      the specific action that was denied. In this case the system has
      denied the appending of data to a file. While browsing through the
      audit log file, you can see other system actions, such as write open,
      getattr and more.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>for pid=1316</literal>:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      the process ID of the command or process that initiated the action
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>comm="rsyslogd"</literal>:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      the specific command that was associated with that PID
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>name="acpid"</literal>:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      the name of the subject of the action
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>dev=sda6 ino=582296</literal>:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      the block device and inode number of the file that was involved
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>scontext=system_u:system_r:syslogd_t</literal>:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      the source context, which is the context of the initiator of the
      action
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>tclass=file</literal>:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      a class identification of the subject
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   Instead of interpreting the events in audit.log yourself, there is
   another approach. You can use the <command>audit2allow</command> command,
   which helps analyze the cryptic log messages in
   <filename>/var/log/audit/audit.log</filename>. An audit2allow
   troubleshooting session always consists of three different commands.
   First, you would use <command>audit2allow -w -a</command> to present the
   audit information in a more readable way. The <command>audit2allow -w
   -a</command> by default works on the audit.log file. If you want to
   analyze a specific message in the audit.log file, copy it to a temporary
   file and analyze that with
  </para>

<screen>audit2allow -w -i <replaceable>file_name</replaceable></screen>

  <example>
   <title>Analyzing Audit Messages</title>
<screen>audit2allow -w -i testfile
type=AVC msg=audit(1348173901.309:300): avc:  denied  { append } for  pid=1316
comm="rsyslogd" name="acpid" dev=sda6 ino=582296
scontext=system_u:system_r:syslogd_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:apmd_log_t tclass=file</screen>
  </example>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>This was caused by:</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Missing type enforcement (TE) allow rule.
     </para>
     <para>
      To generate a loadable module to allow this access, run
     </para>
<screen>audit2allow</screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   To find out which specific rule has denied access, you can use
   <command>audit2allow -a</command> to show the enforcing rules from all
   events that were logged to the <filename>audit.log </filename> file, or
   <command>audit2allow -i <replaceable>file_name</replaceable></command> to
   show it for messages that you have stored in a specific file:
  </para>

  <example>
   <title>Viewing Which Lines Deny Access</title>
<screen>audit2allow -i testfile
#============= syslogd_t ==============
allow syslogd_t apmd_log_t:file append;</screen>
  </example>

  <para>
   To create an &selnx; module with the name <literal>mymodule</literal>
   that you can load in order to allow the access that was previously
   denied, run
  </para>

<screen>audit2allow -a -M mymodule</screen>

  <para>
   If you want to do this for all events that have been logged to the
   audit.log, use the <option>-a -M</option> command arguments. To do it
   only for specific messages that are in a specific file, use <option>-i
   -M</option> as in the example below:
  </para>

  <example>
   <title>Creating a Policy Module Allowing an Action Previously Denied</title>
<screen>audit2allow -i testfile -M example
******************** IMPORTANT ***********************
To make this policy package active, execute:

semodule -i example.pp</screen>
  </example>

  <para>
   As indicated by the <command>audit2allow</command> command, you can now
   run this module by using the <command>semodule -i</command> command,
   followed by the name of the module that <command>audit2allow</command>
   has created for you (<filename>example.pp</filename> in the above
   example).
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.selinux.enforcingmode">
  <title>Switching to Enforcing Mode</title>

  <para>
   With everything you have done so far, you still cannot switch &selnx; to
   enforcing mode. This is because of a misconfiguration in the context
   types for some files. If you switch to enforcing mode now, you can see
   that many AVC denied messages are written that are related to the tmpfs,
   and following these messages your system hangs with the message
   <quote>INIT: Id "1" respawning too fast</quote>.
  </para>

  <example>
   <title>Messages That Appear Before the System Stops</title>
<screen>[ 5.595812] type=1400 audit(1361363803.588:3): avc: denied { read write }
for pid=431 comm="sh" name="console" dev=tmpfs ino=2513
scontext=system_u:system_r:sysadm_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:tmpfs_t
tclass=chr_file
[ 5.607734] type=1400 audit(1361363803.604:4): avc: denied { read write } for
pid=431 comm="sh" path="/dev/console" dev=tmpfs ino=2513
scontext=system_u:system_r:sysadm_t tcontext=system_u:object_r:tmpfs_t
tclass=chr_file</screen>
  </example>

  <para>
   As you will see, this message is repeated several times.
  </para>

  <para>
   To fix this problem, reboot your computer in permissive mode. Copy the
   <filename>/var/log/audit/audit.log</filename> file to a temporary file
   (like <filename>/var/log/audit/audit.2allow</filename>) and remove all
   lines with the exception of the lines that contain the audit log messages
   for the errors listed above. Assuming that the name of the log file that
   you have created is <filename>audit.2allow</filename>, you should now run
   the following command:
  </para>

<screen>audit2allow -i audit.2allow -M bootme</screen>

  <para>
   This creates a policy module file with the name
   <filename>bootme.pe</filename>. Make sure that this module is included in
   your &selnx; configuration by using
  </para>

<screen>semodule -i bootme.pp</screen>

  <para>
   Now reboot your computer in enforcing mode. You will be able to boot and
   log in as root in your &selnx;-protected system. If this is not the case,
   you will need to repeat this procedure until you have no more messages in
   your <filename>audit.log</filename> that refer to
   <filename>path="/dev/console" dev=tmpfs</filename>. This may involve
   several reboots.
  </para>

  <para>
   From here, the fine tuning begins. You will notice that many items on
   your system do not work yet. You will need to fix them one by one. The
   approach for fixing all of these errors is by using
   <command>audit2allow</command> as described in the above example, and by
   setting the appropriate context on files and directories on your system.
   Until a supported version of the &selnx; policy is provided with
   &productname;, you will need to follow this approach to get it to work.
   At least using this procedure does allow you to configure a computer with
   the very detailed security settings that are offered with &selnx; and
   will make your system more secure than when using other solutions.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
