<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!--

2015-12-16: suggestion from Frank
When user has SDK repo installed, it should be make sure that
the user needs to change the repo URL to the new SP version.

Check with Simona, if this is supported or needed.

-->
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha-upgrade-offline"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Upgrading offline</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    This chapter describes how to upgrade an existing &sle; installation using
    &yast; which is booted from an installation medium. The &yast; installer
    can, for example, be started from a DVD, over the network, or from the hard
    disk the system resides on.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-upgrade-offline-conceptual-overview">
  <title>Conceptual overview</title>
  <para>
   Before upgrading your system, read <xref linkend="cha-update-preparation"/>
   first.
  </para>
  <para>
   To upgrade your system, boot from an installation source, as you would
   do for a fresh installation. However, when the boot
   screen appears, you need to select <guimenu>Upgrade</guimenu> (instead of
   <guimenu>Installation</guimenu>). The upgrade can be started from:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Removable media</title>
     <para>
      This includes media such as CDs, DVDs or USB mass storage devices.
      For more information, see
      <xref linkend="sec-upgrade-offline-dvd"/>.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Network resource</title>
     <para>
      You can either boot from the local medium
      and then select the respective network installation type, or boot via PXE.
      For more information, see
      <xref linkend="sec-upgrade-offline-network"/>.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>


 <sect1 xml:id="sec-upgrade-offline-dvd">
  <title>Starting the upgrade from an installation medium</title>
  <!--
   taroth 2019-05-06: this para is the same as in sec.update.sle.manual.network.boot-from-dvd,
   TODO: consider moving it a phrases entity for next release
  -->
  <para>
   The procedure below describes booting from a DVD, but you can
   also use another local installation medium like an ISO image on a USB mass
   storage device. The medium and boot method to select depends on the system
   architecture and on whether the machine has a traditional BIOS or UEFI.
  </para>
  <procedure xml:id="pro-update-sle12-offline-dvd">
   <title>Manually upgrading to &productname; &productnumber;</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select and prepare a boot medium, see <xref linkend="part-prep"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Insert the &leanos; DVD for &productname; &productnumber; and boot your
     machine. A <guimenu>Welcome</guimenu> screen is displayed, followed by
     the boot screen.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Optional: To force the installer to only install packages from the
     DVD and not from network sources, add the boot option
     <option>media_upgrade=1</option>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start up the system by selecting <emphasis>Upgrade</emphasis>
     in the boot menu.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Proceed with the upgrade process as described in
     <xref linkend="sec-upgrade-offline-yast"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-upgrade-offline-network">
  <title>Starting the upgrade from a network source</title>
  <para>
   To start an upgrade from a network installation source, make
   sure that the following requirements are met:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <title>Requirements for upgrading from a network installation source</title>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Network installation source</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A network installation source is set up according to
      <xref linkend="cha-deployment-instserver"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Network connection and network services</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Both the installation server and the target machine must have a
      functioning network connection. Required network services are:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Domain Name Service</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>DHCP (only needed for booting via PXE, IP can be set manually during setup)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>OpenSLP (optional)</para></listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Boot medium</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A bootable &sle; DVD, ISO image or functioning PXE setup. For
      details about booting via PXE, see <xref
      linkend="sec-deployment-prep-boot-pxeprep" />. Refer to <xref
      linkend="cha-remote-installation"/> for in-depth information on
      starting the upgrade from a remote server.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-update-sle-manual-network-boot-from-dvd">
   <title>Manually upgrading via network installation source&mdash;booting from DVD</title>
  <!--
   taroth 2019-05-06: this para is the same as in sec.upgrade-offline.dvd,
   TODO: consider moving it a phrases entity for next release
  -->
   <para>
    This procedure describes booting from a DVD as an example, but you can
    also use another local installation medium like an ISO image on a USB mass
    storage device. The way to select the boot method and to start up the
    system from the medium depends on the system architecture and on whether
    the machine has a traditional BIOS or UEFI. For details, see the links
    below.
   </para>

   <procedure xml:id="pro-update-sle-manual-network-boot-from-dvd">

    <step>
     <para>
      Insert the &leanos; DVD for &productname; &productnumber; and boot your
      machine. A <guimenu>Welcome</guimenu> screen is displayed, followed by
      the boot screen.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select the type of network installation source you want to use (FTP,
      HTTP, NFS, SMB, or SLP). Usually you get this choice by pressing
      <keycap>F4</keycap>, but in case your machine is equipped with UEFI
      instead of a traditional BIOS, you may need to manually adjust boot
      parameters. For details, see <xref linkend="cha-boot-parameters"/> and
      <xref linkend="cha-install"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Proceed with the upgrade process as described in
      <xref linkend="sec-upgrade-offline-yast"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2  xml:id="sec-update-sle-manual-network-pxe-boot">
   <title>Manually upgrading via network installation source&mdash;booting via PXE</title>
   <para>
    To perform an upgrade from a network installation source using PXE boot,
    proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <procedure xml:id="pro-update-sle-manual-network-pxe-boot">
    <step>
     <para>
      Adjust the setup of your DHCP server to provide the address information
      needed for booting via PXE. For details, see
      <xref linkend="pro-deployment-dhcp-server"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Set up a TFTP server to hold the boot image needed for booting via PXE.
      Use the Installer DVD for &productname; &productnumber; for this or
      follow the instructions in <xref linkend="sec-deployment-tftp-server"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Prepare PXE Boot and Wake-on-LAN on the target machine.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Initiate the boot of the target system and use VNC to remotely connect to
      the installation routine running on this machine. For more information,
      see <xref linkend="sec-remote-installation-monitor-vnc"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Proceed with the upgrade process as described in
      <xref linkend="sec-upgrade-offline-yast"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-upgrade-offline-yast">
  <title>Upgrading &sle;</title>
  <para>
   <remark>taroth 2014-11-13: argh, the following is terminology hell regarding
     the software strings: "upgrade"/"update" are used intermittently and
     without clear differentiation...</remark>
  </para>
  <para>
   Before you upgrade your system, read <xref linkend="cha-update-preparation"/>
   first. To perform an automated migration, proceed as follows:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <note>
    <title>&scc; and Internet connection</title>
    <para>
     If the system you want to upgrade is registered with the &scc;, make sure
     to have an Internet connection during the following procedure.
    </para>
   </note>
   <step>
    <para>
     After you have booted (either from an installation medium or the network),
     select the <guimenu>Upgrade</guimenu> entry on the boot screen.
    </para>
    <warning>
     <title>Wrong choice may lead to data loss</title>
     <para>
      Make sure you select <guimenu>Upgrade</guimenu> at this point. If you
      select <guimenu>Installation</guimenu> by mistake, your data partition
      will be overwritten with a fresh installation.
     </para>
    </warning>
    <para>
     &yast; starts the installation system.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Welcome</guimenu> screen, choose
     <guimenu>Language</guimenu> and <guimenu>Keyboard</guimenu>.
     Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     &yast; checks your partitions for already installed &sle; systems.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Select for Upgrade</guimenu> screen, select the partition
     to upgrade and click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     &yast; mounts the selected partition and displays the license agreement
     for the upgraded product. To continue, accept the license.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Previously Used Repositories</guimenu> screen, adjust the
     status of the repositories. By default all repositories are removed. If you have not added
     any custom repositories, do not change the settings. The packages for the upgrade will be
     installed from DVD, and you can optionally enable the default online repositories in the next step.
 </para>
 <para>
If you have custom repositories, you have two choices:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
        <para>
    Leave the repository in state Removed. Software that was installed from this repository will be removed during the upgrade. Use this method if no version of the repository that matches the new release is available.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
    <para>
    Update and enable the repository if it matches the new release. Change its URL
    by clicking the repository in the list, and then click <guimenu>Change</guimenu>. Enable the repository
    by checking <guimenu>Toggle Status</guimenu> until it is set to <guimenu>Enable</guimenu>.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
Do not keep repositories from the previous release, as the system may be unstable or not work at all.
Then proceed by clicking <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The next step depends on whether the upgraded system is registered with the
     &scc; or not.
    </para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       If the system is not registered with the &scc;, &yast; displays a pop-up
       message suggesting using a second installation medium, the &packagemedia;
       image.
      </para>
      <para>
       If you do not have that medium, the system cannot be upgraded without
       registration.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If the system is registered with the &scc;, &yast; will show possible
       migration targets and a summary.
      </para>
      <para>
       Select one migration target from the list and proceed with
       <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the next dialog you can optionally add an additional installation medium.
     If you have additional installation media, activate the
     <guimenu>I would like to install an additional Add On Product</guimenu>
     option and specify the media type.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Review the <guimenu>Installation Settings</guimenu> for the upgrade.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If all settings are according to your wishes, start the installation and
     removal procedure by clicking <guimenu>Update</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <tip>
     <title>Upgrade failure on &smt; clients</title>
     <para>
      If the machine to upgrade is an &smt; client, and the upgrade fails,
      see <xref linkend="pro-sec-update-prep-smt-de-register"/> and restart the
      upgrade procedure afterward.
     </para>
    </tip>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After the upgrade process has finished successfully, perform the
     post-upgrade steps described in <xref linkend="cha-upgrade-finish"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-upgrade-offline-automated" os="sles">
  <title>Upgrading with &ay;</title>
  <para>
   The upgrade process can be executed automatically. For details, see
   <xref linkend="CreateProfile-upgrade"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-upgrade-offline-manager">
  <title>Upgrading with &susemgr;</title>
  <para>
   &susemgr; is a server solution for providing updates, patches, and
   security fixes for &sle; clients. It comes with a set of tools and a
   Web-based user interface for management tasks. See <link
   xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/suse-manager/"/> for more
   information about &susemgr;.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can perform a system upgrade using &susemgr;. The &ay; technology allows
   upgrades from one major version to the next.
  </para>
<!-- taroth 2019-05-02: see also https://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1133927 -->
  &upgrade-with-suma-pointer;
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-update-reg-status-after-rollback">
  <title>Updating registration status after rollback</title>

  <para>
   When performing a service pack upgrade, it is necessary to change the
   configuration on the registration server to provide access to the new
   repositories. If the upgrade process is interrupted or reverted (via
   restoring from a backup or snapshot), the information on the registration
   server is inconsistent with the status of the system. This may lead to you
   being prevented from accessing update repositories or to wrong repositories
   being used on the client.
  </para>

  <para>
   When a rollback is done via Snapper, the system notifies the
   registration server to ensure access to the correct repositories is
   set up during the boot process. If the system was restored with
   another method, or the communication with the registration server
   fails, trigger the rollback on the client manually. An example for
   manually triggering a rollback can be that the server was not
   accessible because of network issues. To do a rollback, execute:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>snapper</command> rollback</screen>

  <para>
   We suggest always checking that the correct repositories are set up on the
   system, especially after refreshing the service using:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>zypper</command> ref -s</screen>

  <para>
   This functionality is available in the
   <package>rollback-helper</package>
   package.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-update-registersystem">
<!-- was: sec.add-ons.register -->

  <title>Registering your system</title>

  <para>
   If the system was not registered before running the upgrade you can
   register your system at any time using the <guimenu>Product
   Registration</guimenu> module in &yast;.
  </para>

  <para>
   Registering your systems has these advantages:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Eligibility for support
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Availability of security updates and bug fixes
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Access to &scc;
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start &yast; and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Product Registration</guimenu> </menuchoice> to open the
     <guimenu>Registration</guimenu> dialog.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Provide the <guimenu>E-mail</guimenu> address associated with the &suse;
     account you or your organization uses to manage subscriptions. In case you
     do not have a SUSE account yet, go to the &scc; home page
     (<link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="&sccurl;"/>) to create one.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the <guimenu>Registration Code</guimenu> you received with your copy
     of &productname;.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
     <para>
      If one or more local registration servers are available on your network,
      you can choose one of them from a list.
     </para>
   </step>
   <step xml:id="st-y2-register-final">
    <para>
     To start the registration, proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     After successful registration, &yast; lists extensions, add-ons, and
     modules that are available for your system. To select and install them,
     proceed with <xref linkend="sec-register-sle-add-modules"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

</chapter>
