<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!--

2015-12-16: suggestion from Frank
When user has SDK repo installed, it should be make sure that
the user needs to change the repo URL to the new SP version.

Check with Simona, if this is supported or needed.

-->
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha.update.offline"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Upgrading Offline</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    This chapter describes how to upgrade an existing &sle; installation with
    the help of &yast; which is booted from an installation medium. The &yast;
    installer can, for example, be started from a DVD, over the network, or from
    the hard disk the system resides on.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.update.offline.conceptual-overview">
  <title>Conceptual Overview</title>
  <para>
   Before upgrading your system, read <xref linkend="sec.update.prep"/>
   first.
  </para>
  <para>
   To upgrade your system, boot from an installation source, as you would
   do for a fresh installation. However, when the boot
   screen appears, you need to select <guimenu>Upgrade</guimenu> (instead of
   <guimenu>Installation</guimenu>). The upgrade can be started from:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Removable Media</title>
     <para>
      This includes media such as CDs, DVDs or USB mass storage devices.
      For more information, see
      <xref linkend="sec.update.offline.dvd"/>.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Network Resource</title>
     <para>
      You can either boot from the local medium
      and then select the respective network installation type, or boot via PXE.
      For more information, see
      <xref linkend="sec.update.offline.network"/>.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Hard Disk</title>
     <para>
      You can copy the new kernel and initrd image from
      the ISO image to your hard disk containing the current &sle; installation
      and adjust the boot menu. For more information, see
      <xref linkend="sec.update.offline.harddisk" />
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>


 <sect1 xml:id="sec.update.offline.dvd">
  <title>Starting the Upgrade from Installation Medium</title>
  <para>
   The procedure below describes booting from a DVD as an example, but you can
   also use another local installation medium like an ISO image on a USB mass
   storage device. The medium and boot method to select depends on the system
   architecture and on whether the machine has a traditional BIOS or UEFI.
  </para>
  <procedure xml:id="pro.update.sle12.offline.dvd">
   <title>Manually Upgrading from &slea;&nbsp;11 SP4  to &slea;&nbsp;12 SP3</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select and prepare a boot medium, see <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.startup"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Insert DVD 1 of the &sle; 12 SP3 installation medium and boot your
     machine. A <guimenu>Welcome</guimenu> screen is displayed, followed by
     the boot screen.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start up the system with selecting <emphasis>Upgrade</emphasis>
     in the boot menu.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Proceed with the upgrade process as described in
     <xref linkend="sec.update.sle12.start.upgr.after.boot"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.update.offline.network">
  <title>Starting Upgrade from Network Source</title>
  <para>
   If you want to start an upgrade from a network installation source, make
   sure that the following requirements are met:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <title>Requirements for Upgrading from a Network Installation Source</title>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Network Installation Source</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A network installation source is set up according to
      <xref linkend="cha.deployment.instserver"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Network Connection and Network Services</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Both the installation server and the target machine must have a functioning
      network connection. Required network services are:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Domain Name Service</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>DHCP (only needed for booting via PXE, IP can be set manually during setup)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>OpenSLP (optional)</para></listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Boot Medium</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      You have a &productname; DVD 1 (or a local ISO image) at hand to boot the target
      system <emphasis>or</emphasis> a target system that is set up for
      booting via PXE according to
      <xref linkend="sec.deployment.prep_boot.pxeprep" xrefstyle="HeadingOnPage"/>.
      Refer to <xref linkend="cha.deployment.remoteinst"/> for in-depth
      information on starting the upgrade from a remote server.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec.update.sle.manual.network.boot-from-dvd">
   <title>Manually Upgrading via Network Installation Source&mdash;Booting from DVD</title>
   <para>
    This procedure describes booting from a DVD as an example, but you can
    also use another local installation medium like an ISO image on a USB mass
    storage device. The way to select the boot method and to start up the
    system from the medium depends on the system architecture and on whether
    the machine has a traditional BIOS or UEFI. For details, see the links
    below.
   </para>
   <procedure xml:id="pro.update.sle.manual.network.boot-from-dvd">
    
    <step>
     <para>
      Insert DVD 1 of the &sle; 12 SP2 installation media and boot your
      machine. A <guimenu>Welcome</guimenu> screen is displayed, followed by
      the boot screen.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select the type of network installation source you want to use (FTP,
      HTTP, NFS, SMB, or SLP). Usually you get this choice by pressing
      <keycap>F4</keycap>, but in case your machine is equipped with UEFI
      instead of a traditional BIOS, you may need to manually adjust boot
      parameters. For details, see <xref linkend="sec.i.yast2.source.net"/> in
      <xref linkend="cha.inst"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Proceed with the upgrade process as described in
      <xref linkend="sec.update.sle12.start.upgr.after.boot"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2  xml:id="sec.update.sle.manual.network.pxe-boot">
   <title>Manually Upgrading via Network Installation Source&mdash;Booting via PXE</title>
   <para>
    To perform an upgrade from a network installation source using PXE boot,
    proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <procedure xml:id="pro.update.sle.manual.network.pxe-boot">
    <step>
     <para>
      Adjust the setup of your DHCP server to provide the address information
      needed for booting via PXE. For details, see
      <xref linkend="sec.deployment.prep_boot.pxeprep"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Set up a TFTP server to hold the boot image needed for booting via PXE.
      Use DVD 1 of your &sle; 12 SP2 installation media for this or follow the
      instructions in <xref linkend="sec.deployment.prep_boot.tftp"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Prepare PXE Boot and Wake-on-LAN on the target machine.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Initiate the boot of the target system and use VNC to remotely connect to
      the installation routine running on this machine. For more information,
      see <xref linkend="sec.deployment.remoteinst.monitor.vnc"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Proceed with the upgrade process as described in
      <xref linkend="sec.update.sle12.start.upgr.after.boot"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.update.offline.harddisk">
  <title>Starting Upgrade from Hard Disk</title>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec.update.sle.offline.automated">
   <title>Automated Migration from &sle; 11 SP3 or SP4 to &sle; 12 SP2</title>
   <procedure xml:id="pro.update.sle.offline.automated">
    <remark>toms 2014-03-19: See FATE#315037</remark>
    <remark role="future">toms 2014-03-20: From SLE12 SP1 on, we should probably base
     this example on GRUB2, but not for GA.</remark>
    <remark>jsrain 2015-09-02: This is still the old system; at some point
        of time we should switch to GRUB2, but as long as amjority of
        customers still runs SLE11, I would stay with legacy GRUB. Anyway, we
        could include both options, that would be probably best solution</remark>
    <step>
     <para>
      Copy the installation kernel <filename>linux</filename> and the file
      <filename>initrd</filename> from <filename>/boot/x86_64/loader/</filename>
      from your first installation DVD to your system's
      <filename>/boot</filename> directory:
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>cp</command> -vi <replaceable>DVDROOT</replaceable>/boot/x86_64/loader/linux /boot/linux.upgrade
&prompt.root;<command>cp</command> -vi <replaceable>DVDROOT</replaceable>/boot/x86_64/loader/initrd /boot/initrd.upgrade</screen>
     <para>
      <replaceable>DVDROOT</replaceable> denotes the path where your system
      mounts the DVD, usually <filename>/run/media/$USER/$DVDNAME</filename>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Open the GRUB legacy configuration file
      <filename>/boot/grub/menu.lst</filename> and add another section. For
      other boot loaders, edit the respective configuration file(s). Adjust
      device names and the <parameter>root</parameter> parameter accordingly.
      For example:
     </para>
     <para>
      <remark>sseeberg 2017-04-11: this is only valid for sle11?</remark>
     </para>
<screen>title Linux Upgrade Kernel
kernel (hd0,0)/boot/linux.upgrade root=/dev/sda1 upgrade=1 autoupgrade=1
initrd (hd0,0)/boot/initrd.upgrade</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      The following steps either need the DVD in the drive or the ISO image
      has to be present on the local disk. If the computer has no DVD drive,
      either download the ISO and save it as <filename>/install.iso</filename>
      or copy it from the DVD
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>dd</command> if=/dev/cdrom of=/install.iso</screen>
     <para>
      If you copied the ISO to your hard disk, you need to add a parameter
      to the previously edited <filename>/boot/grub/menu.lst</filename>.
      To the line beginning with <literal>kernel</literal> add the option
     </para>
<screen>install=hd:/install.iso</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Reboot your machine and select the newly added section from the boot menu
      (here: <emphasis>Linux Upgrade Kernel</emphasis>). You can use
      <command>grubonce</command> to preselect the newly created GRUB entry for
      an unattended automatic reboot into the newly created entry. You can also
      use <command>reboot</command> to initiate the reboot from the command
      line.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Proceed with the upgrade process as described in
      <xref linkend="sec.update.sle12.start.upgr.after.boot"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      After the upgrade process was finished successfully, remove the
      installation Kernel and initrd files
      (<filename>/boot/linux.upgrade</filename> and
      <filename>/boot/initrd.upgrade</filename>). They are not needed anymore.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.update.offline.automated">
  <title>Enabling Automatic Upgrade</title>
  <para>
   The upgrade process can be executed automatically. To enable the automatic
   update the kernel, the kernel parameter <literal>autoupgrade = 1</literal>
   must be set. The parameter can be set on boot in the <literal>Boot Options</literal>
   field. For details, see 
   <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/documentation/sles-12/book_autoyast/data/introduction.html" />.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.update.sle12.start.upgr.after.boot">
  <title>Upgrading &sle;</title>
  <para>
   <remark>taroth 2014-11-13: argh, the following is terminology hell regarding
     the software strings: "upgrade"/"update" are used intermittently and
     without clear differentiation...</remark>
  </para>
  <para>
   Before you upgrade your system, read <xref linkend="sec.update.prep"/>
   first. To perform an automated migration, proceed as follows:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     After you have booted (either from an installation medium or the network),
     select the <guimenu>Upgrade</guimenu> entry on the boot screen. If you want
     to do the upgrade as described in the next steps manually, you need to 
     disable the automatic upgrade process. Refer to 
     <xref linkend="sec.update.offline.automated" />.
    </para>
    <warning>
     <title>Wrong Choice May Lead to Data Loss</title>
     <para>
      If you select <guimenu>Installation</guimenu> instead of
      <guimenu>Upgrade</guimenu>, data may be lost later. You need to be extra
      careful to not destroy your data partitions by doing a fresh
      installation, for example by repartitioning the disks (which can destroy
      the existing partitions) or by reformatting the data partitions (which
      erases all data on them).
     </para>
     <para>
      Make sure to select <guimenu>Upgrade</guimenu> here.
     </para>
    </warning>
    <para>
     &yast; starts the installation system.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Welcome</guimenu> screen, choose
     <guimenu>Language</guimenu> and <guimenu>Keyboard</guimenu> and accept the
     license agreement. Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     &yast; checks your partitions for already installed &sle; systems.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Select for Upgrade</guimenu> screen, select the partition
     to upgrade and click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     &yast; mounts the selected partition and displays all repositories that
     have been found on the partition that you want to upgrade.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Previously Used Repositories</guimenu> screen, adjust the
     status of the repositories: enable those you want to include in the
     upgrade process and disable any repositories that are no longer needed.
     Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Registration</guimenu> screen, select whether to register
     the upgraded system now (by entering your registration data and clicking
     <guimenu>Next</guimenu>) or if to <guimenu>Skip Registration</guimenu>.
     For details on registering your system, see
     <xref linkend="sec.update.registersystem"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Review the <guimenu>Installation Settings</guimenu> for the upgrade,
     especially the <guimenu>Update Options</guimenu>. Choose between the
     following options:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Only Update Installed Packages</guimenu>, in which case you
       might miss new features shipped with the latest &sle; version.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Update with Installation of New Software and
       Features</guimenu>. Click <guimenu>Select Patterns</guimenu> if you want
       to enable or disable patterns and packages according to your wishes.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
<!--taroth 2014-11-19: fix for bsc#904188-->
    <note>
     <title>Choice of Desktop</title>
     <para>
      If you used KDE before upgrading to &sle; 12
      (<varname>DEFAULT_WM</varname> in
      <filename>/etc/sysconfig/windowmanager</filename> was set to
      <literal>kde*</literal>), your desktop environment will automatically be
      replaced with &gnome; after the upgrade. By default, the KDM display
      manager will be replaced with GDM.
     </para>
     <para>
      To change the choice of desktop environment or window manager, adjust the
      software selection by clicking <guimenu>Select Patterns</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </note>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If all settings are according to your wishes, start the installation and
     removal procedure by clicking <guimenu>Update</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After the upgrade process was finished successfully, check for any
     <quote>orphaned packages</quote>. Orphaned packages are packages which
     belong to no active repository anymore. The following command gives you a
     list of these:
    </para>
<screen>zypper packages --orphaned</screen>
    <para>
     With this list, you can decide if a package is still needed or can be
     uninstalled safely.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.update.sle.manager">
  <title>Updating via &susemgr;</title>

  <para>
   &susemgr; is a server solution for providing updates, patches, and security
   fixes for &sle; clients. It comes with a set of tools and a Web-based user
   interface for management tasks. See
   <link
    xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/suse-manager/"/> for
   details.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.update.reg.status.after.rollback">
  <title>Updating Registration Status After Rollback</title>

  <para>
   When performing a service pack upgrade, it is necessary to change the
   configuration on the registration server to provide access to the new
   repositories. If the upgrade process is interrupted or reverted (via
   restoring from a backup or snapshot), the information on the registration
   server is inconsistent with the status of the system. This may lead to you
   being prevented from accessing update repositories or to wrong repositories
   being used on the client.
  </para>

  <para>
   When a rollback is done via Snapper, the system will notify the registration
   server to ensure access to the correct repositories is set up during the
   boot process. If the system was restored any other way or the communication
   with the registration server failed for any reason (for example, because the
   server was not accessible because of network issues), trigger the rollback
   on the client manually by calling:
  </para>

<screen><command>snapper</command> rollback</screen>

  <para>
   We suggest always checking that the correct repositories are set up on the
   system, especially after refreshing the service using:
  </para>

<screen><command>zypper</command> ref -s</screen>

  <para>
   This functionality is available in the
   <package>rollback-helper</package>
   package.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.update.registersystem">
<!-- was: sec.add-ons.register -->

  <title>Registering Your System</title>

  <para>
   If you skipped the registration step during the installation, you can
   register your system at any time using the <guimenu>Product
   Registration</guimenu> module in &yast;.
  </para>

  <para>
   Registering your systems has these advantages:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Eligibility for support
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Availability of security updates and bug fixes
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Access to &scc;
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start &yast; and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Product Registration</guimenu> </menuchoice> to open the
     <guimenu>Registration</guimenu> dialog.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Provide the <guimenu>E-mail</guimenu> address associated with the &suse;
     account you or your organization uses to manage subscriptions. In case you
     do not have a SUSE account yet, go to the &scc; home page
     (<link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="&sccurl;"/>) to create one.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the <guimenu>Registration Code</guimenu> you received with your copy
     of &productname;.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step xml:id="step.y2.register.final">
    <para>
     To start the registration, proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. If
     one or more local registration servers are available on your network, you
     can choose one of them from a list. Alternatively, to ignore the local
     registration servers and  register with the default &suse; registration server,
     choose <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     During the registration, the online update repositories will be added to
     your upgrade setup. When finished, you can choose whether to install the
     latest available package versions from the update repositories. This
     provides a clean upgrade path for all packages and ensures that
     &productname; is upgraded with the latest security updates available. If
     you choose <guimenu>No</guimenu>, all packages will be installed from the
     installation media. Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     After successful registration, &yast; lists extensions, add-ons, and
     modules that are available for your system. To select and install them,
     proceed with <xref linkend="sec.add-ons.extensions"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

</chapter>
