<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.sled_plan">
 <title>Planning for &sled;</title>
 <para>
  This chapter is addressed mainly to corporate system administrators who
  face the task of having to deploy &sledreg; at their site. Rolling out
  &sled; to an entire site should involve careful planning and consideration
  of the following questions:
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>For which purpose will the &sled; workstations be used?</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Determine the purpose for which &sled; should be used and make sure
     that hardware and software with the ability to match these requirements
     are used. Consider testing your setup on a single machine before
     rolling it out to the entire site.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>How many workstations should be installed?</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Determine the scope of your deployment of &sled;. Depending on the
     number of installations planned, consider different approaches to the
     installation or even a mass installation using &sle;s unique &ay; or
     &kiwi; technology. For more information about this subject, refer to
     <xref linkend="cha.deployment"></xref>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>How do you get software updates for your deployment?</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     All patches provided by Novell for your product are available for
     download to registered users. Register and find the patch support
     database at
     <ulink url="http://www.novell.com/linux/suse/portal/index.html"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Do you need help for your local deployment?</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Novell provides training, support, and consulting for all topics
     pertaining to &sled;. Find more information about this at
     <ulink url="http://www.novell.com/products/desktop/"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <sect1 id="sec.sled_plan.hw">
  <title>Hardware Requirements</title>

  <para>
   For a standard installation of &sled;, including the desktop environment
   and a wealth of applications, the following configuration is recommended:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Intel Pentium IV, 2.4 GHz or higher or any AMD64 or &intel64; processor
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     1&ndash;2 physical CPUs
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     512 MB physical RAM or higher
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     3 GB of available disk space or more
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     1024 x 768 display resolution (or higher)
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.sled_plan.usage">
  <title>Reasons to Use &sled;</title>

  <para>
   Let the following items guide you in your selection of &sled; and
   determining the purpose of the installed systems:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Wealth of Applications</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      &sled;'s broad offer of software makes it appeal to both professional
      users in a corporate environment and to home users or users in smaller
      networks.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Ease of Use</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      &sled; comes with two enterprise-ready desktop environments, GNOME and
      KDE. Both enable users to comfortably adjust to a Linux system while
      maintaining their efficiency and productivity.
      <phrase
       os="osuse;sled">To explore the desktops in detail,
      refer to the <xref linkend="book.kdeuser"/> and the
      <xref linkend="book.gnomeuser"/>.</phrase>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Support for Mobile Users</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      With the NetworkManager technology fully integrated into &sled; and
      its two desktop environments, mobile users will enjoy the freedom of
      easily joining and switching wired and wireless networks.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Seamless Integration into Existing Networks</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      &sled; was designed to be a versatile network citizen. It cooperates
      with various different network types:
     </para>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Pure Linux Networks</title>
      <para>
       &sled; is a complete Linux client and supports all the protocols used
       in traditional Linux and Unix* environments. It integrates well with
       networks consisting of other &suselinux; or &sle; machines. LDAP,
       NIS, and local authentication are supported.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Windows Networks</title>
      <para>
       &sled; supports Active Directory as an authentication source. It
       offers you all the advantages of a secure and stable Linux operating
       system plus convenient interaction with other Windows clients, as
       well as the means to manipulate your Windows user data from a Linux
       client. Explore this feature in detail in
       <xref linkend="cha.security.ad"></xref>.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Windows and Novell Networks</title>
<!--taroth 060621: dropped iFolder for SLED 10 according to mail from
							Elizabeth-->
      <para>
       <remark role="clarity"> 2006-03-31 - jjaeger: not sure about
        the trademarking. What a mess! </remark>
       Being backed by Novell and their networking expertise, &sled;
       naturally offers you support for Novell technologies, like GroupWise,
       Novell Client for Linux,
<!--iFolder, -->
       and iPrint, and it also offers authentication support for Novell
       eDirectory services.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Application Security with &aa;</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      &sled; enables you to secure your applications by enforcing security
      profiles tailor-made for your applications. To learn more about &aa;,
      refer to
      <ulink url="http://www.novell.com/documentation/apparmor/"></ulink>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
