<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha-upgrade-preparation-slemicro"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"> 
 <title>Preparing the upgrade</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
  <abstract>
    <para>
    Before you start the upgrade procedure of &slema;, you need to perform checks as described in this chapter.
   </para>
 </abstract>
</info>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-upgrade-background-identify-slemicro">
  <title>Identifying the &slema; version</title>

  <para>
   If you need to identify the version of an
   &slema;
   installation, check the content of the file
   <filename>/etc/os-release</filename>.
  </para>

  <para>
   A machine readable XML output is available with <command>zypper</command>:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.root;<command>zypper --no-remote --no-refresh --xmlout --non-interactive products -i</command>
&lt;?xml version='1.0'?&gt;
&lt;stream&gt;
&lt;product-list&gt;
&lt;product name="SUSE-MicroOS" version="5.1" release="1" epoch="0" arch="x86_64" vendor="SUSE" summary="SUSE Linux Enterprise Micro 5.1" repo="@System" productline="SUSE-MicroOS" registerrelease="" shortname="SUSE Linux Enterprise Micro" flavor="" isbase="true" installed="true"&gt;&lt;endoflife time_t="0" text="0"/&gt;&lt;registerflavor/&gt;&lt;description&gt;SUSE Linux Enterprise Micro 5.1&lt;/description&gt;&lt;/product&gt;
&lt;/product-list&gt;
&lt;/stream&gt;
</screen>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-update-preparation-relnotes-slemicro">
  <title>Read the release notes</title>

  <para>
   Find a list of all changes, new features, and known issues in the
   <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/">release notes</link>.
   You can also find the release notes on the installation media in the
   <filename>docu</filename> directory.
  </para>

  <para>
   The release notes usually only contain the changes between two subsequent
   releases.
  </para>

  <para>
   Check the release notes to see whether:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     your hardware needs special considerations;
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     any used software packages have changed significantly;
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     special precautions are necessary for your installation.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-upgrade-slemicro-register">
  <title>Registering and deregistering machines</title>

  <para>
   On registration, the system receives repositories from the &scc; (see
   <link xlink:href="&sccurl;"/>) or a local registration proxy like &smt;. The
   repository names map to specific URIs in the customer center. To list all
   available repositories on your system, use <command>zypper</command> as
   follows:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.root;<command>zypper</command> repos -u</screen>

  <para>
   This gives you a list of all available repositories on your system. Each
   repository is listed by its alias, name and whether it is enabled and will
   be refreshed. The option <option>-u</option> also gives you the URI from
   where it originated.
  </para>

    <para>
   To register your machine, run the <command>transactional-update</command> as
   follows:
  </para>

<screen>
&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update</command> register -r <replaceable>REGCODE</replaceable>
</screen>

  
  <para>
   To deregister your machine, you can use the
   <command>transactional-update</command> as follows:
  </para>

<screen>
&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update</command> register -d
</screen>

  <para>
   To check your locally installed products and their status, use the following
   command:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.root;<command>&suseconnect;</command> -s</screen>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-update-slemicro-update">
  <title>Make sure the current system is up-to-date</title>

  <para>
   Upgrading the system is only supported from the most recent patch level.
   Make sure the latest system updates are installed by running:
  </para>

<screen>
  &prompt.root;transactional-update patch
  </screen>
 </sect1>


<sect1 xml:id="sec-update-slemicro-packagelist">
  <title>Listing installed packages and repositories</title>

  <para>
   <remark>jufa 2021-02-08: explain importance and purposeof this list.
    Clarify if requirement or suggestion?
    Used for reverting changes or to set-up new system?</remark>
   You can save a list of installed packages, for example when doing a fresh
   install of a new major &slea; release or reverting to the old version.
  </para>

  <note>
   <para>
    <remark>jufa: check if manual editing is still relevant 2021-02-09</remark>
    Be aware that not all installed packages or used repositories are available
    in newer releases of &sle;. Some may have been renamed and others replaced.
    It is also possible that some packages are still available for legacy
    purposes while another package is used by default. Therefore some manual
    editing of the files might be necessary. This can be done with any text
    editor.
   </para>
  </note>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create a file named <filename>repositories.bak.repo</filename> containing
     a list of all used repositories:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>zypper</command> lr -e repositories.bak</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Also create a file named <filename>installed-software.bak</filename>
     containing a list of all installed packages:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>rpm</command> -qa --queryformat '%{NAME}\n' >
     installed-software.bak</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Back up both files. The repositories and installed packages can be
     restored with the following commands:
    </para>
<screen>
&prompt.root;<command>zypper</command> ar repositories.bak.repo
&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg install</command> $(cat installed-software.bak)
</screen>
    
    <note>
     <title>Number of packages increases with an update to a new release</title>
     <para>
      A system upgraded to a new (minor or major) version may contain more
      packages than the initial system. It could also contain more packages
      than a fresh installation of the new &slema; with the same pattern
      selection. Reasons for this are:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Packages were split to allow a more fine-grained package selection.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        When a package has been split, all new packages are installed in the
        upgrade case to retain the same functionality as with the previous
        version. However, the new default for a fresh installation of &slema;
        new versions may be to not install all packages.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Legacy packages from the initial &slema; may be kept for compatibility
        reasons.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Package dependencies and the scope of patterns may have changed.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </note>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-update-slemicro-backup">
  <title>Make a backup</title>

  <para>
   Before upgrading, back up your data by copying the existing configuration
   files to a separate medium (such as tape device, removable hard disk, etc.).
   This primarily applies to files stored in <filename>/etc</filename> and some
   directories and files in <filename>/var</filename> and
   <filename>/opt</filename>. You may also want to write the user data in
   <filename>/home</filename> (the <envar>HOME</envar> directories) to a backup
   medium.
  </para>

  <para>
   Back up all data as &rootuser;. Only &rootuser; has sufficient permissions
   for all local files.
  </para>  
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-update-slemicro-disk">
  <title>Disk space</title>

  <para>
   Software tends to grow from version to version. Therefore, take a look at
   the available partition space before updating. If you suspect you are
   running short of disk space, back up your data before increasing the
   available space by resizing partitions, for example. There is no general
   rule regarding how much space each partition should have. Space requirements
   depend on your particular partitioning profile and the software selected.
  </para>

  
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-update-slemicro-disk-btrfs-on-root">
   <title>Checking disk space on Btrfs root file systems</title>
      <para>
    On a Btrfs file system, the output of <command>df</command> can be
    misleading, because in addition to the space the raw data allocates, a
    Btrfs file system also allocates and uses space for metadata.
   </para>
   <para>
    Consequently a Btrfs file system may report being out of space even though
    it seems that plenty of space is still available. In that case, all space
    allocated for the metadata is used up. 
   </para>
   
   <para>
    Make sure there is enough free space as the root file system uses Btrfs and
    might consume significant amount of space. Check the available space on all
    mounted partitions. In the worst case, an upgrade needs as much disk space
    as the current root file system (without <filename>/.snapshot</filename>)
    for a new snapshot.
   </para>
   <para>
    The following recommendations have been proven:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      For all file systems, including Btrfs, you need enough free disk space to
      download and install big RPMs. The space of old RPMs is only freed after
      new RPMs are installed.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      For Btrfs with snapshots, you need as a minimum as much free space as
      your current installation takes. We recommend having twice as much free
      space as the current installation.
     </para>
     <para>
      If you do not have enough free space, you can try to delete old snapshots
      with <command>snapper</command>:
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>snapper</command> list
&prompt.root;<command>snapper</command> delete NUMBER</screen>
     <para>
      However, this may not help in all cases. Before migration, most snapshots
      occupy only little space.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-update-slemicro-vms">
  <title>Shut down virtual machine guests</title>

  <para>
   If your machine serves as a &vmhost; for &kvm;, make sure to properly shut down all running &vmguest;s prior
   to the update. Otherwise you may not be able to access the guests after the
   update.
  </para>
 </sect1>

</chapter>
