<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-snapshots" xml:lang="en">
 <title>Snapshots</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
  <warning>
   <title>Snapshots are mandatory</title>
   <para>
    As snapshots are crucial for the correct functioning of &slema;, do not
    disable the feature, and ensure that the root partition is big enough to
    store the snapshots.
   </para>
  </warning>
  <para>
   When a snapshot is created, both the snapshot and the original point to the
   same blocks in the file system. So, initially a snapshot does not occupy
   additional disk space. If data in the original file system is modified,
   changed data blocks are copied while the old data blocks are kept for the
   snapshot.
  </para>
  <para>
   Snapshots always reside on the same partition or subvolume on which the
   snapshot has been taken. It is not possible to store snapshots on a
   different partition or subvolume. As a result, partitions containing
   snapshots need to be larger than partitions which do not contain snapshots.
   The exact amount depends strongly on the number of snapshots you keep and
   the amount of data modifications. As a rule of thumb, give partitions twice
   as much space as you normally would. To prevent disks from running out of
   space, old snapshots are automatically cleaned up.
  </para>
  <para>
   Snapshots that are known to be working properly are marked as
   <emphasis>important</emphasis>.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="sec-exclude-directories">
   <title>Directories excluded from snapshots</title>
   <para>
    As some directories store user-specific or volatile data, these directories
    are excluded from snapshots:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>/home</filename></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Contains users' data. Excluded so that the data will not be included in
       snapshots and thus potentially overwritten by a rollback operation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>/root</filename></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Contains root's data. Excluded so that the data will not be included in
       snapshots and thus potentially overwritten by a rollback operation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>/opt</filename></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Third-party products usually get installed to <filename>/opt</filename>.
       Excluded so that these applications are not uninstalled during
       rollbacks.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>/srv</filename></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Contains data for Web and FTP servers. Excluded in order to avoid data
       loss on rollbacks.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>/usr/local</filename></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This directory is used when manually installing software. It is excluded
       to avoid uninstalling these installations on rollbacks.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>/var</filename></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This directory contains many variable files, including logs, temporary
       caches, third-party products in <filename>/var/opt</filename>, and is
       the default location for virtual machine images and databases.
       Therefore, a separate subvolume is created with Copy-On-Write disabled,
       so as to exclude all of this variable data from snapshots.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>/tmp</filename></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The directory contains temporary data.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>the architecture-specific <filename>/boot/grub2</filename> directory</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Rollback of the boot loader binaries is not supported.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-snapshot-size">
   <title>Showing exclusive disk space used by snapshots</title>
   <para>
    Snapshots share data, for efficient use of storage space, so using ordinary
    commands like <command>du</command> and <command>df</command> won't measure
    used disk space accurately. When you want to free up disk space on Btrfs
    with quotas enabled, you need to know how much exclusive disk space is used
    by each snapshot, rather than shared space. The <command>btrfs</command>
    command provides a view of space used by snapshots:
   </para>
<screen>
&prompt.root;btrfs qgroup show -p /
qgroupid         rfer         excl parent  
--------         ----         ---- ------  
0/5          16.00KiB     16.00KiB ---     
[...]    
0/272         3.09GiB     14.23MiB 1/0     
0/273         3.11GiB    144.00KiB 1/0     
0/274         3.11GiB    112.00KiB 1/0     
0/275         3.11GiB    128.00KiB 1/0     
0/276         3.11GiB     80.00KiB 1/0     
0/277         3.11GiB    256.00KiB 1/0     
0/278         3.11GiB    112.00KiB 1/0     
0/279         3.12GiB     64.00KiB 1/0     
0/280         3.12GiB     16.00KiB 1/0     
1/0           3.33GiB    222.95MiB --- 
</screen>
   <para>
    The <literal>qgroupid</literal> column displays the identification number
    for each subvolume, assigning a qgroup level/ID combination.
   </para>
   <para>
    The <literal>rfer</literal> column displays the total amount of data
    referred to in the subvolume.
   </para>
   <para>
    The <literal>excl</literal> column displays the exclusive data in each
    subvolume.
   </para>
   <para>
    The <literal>parent</literal> column shows the parent qgroup of the
    subvolumes.
   </para>
   <para>
    The final item, <literal>1/0</literal>, shows the totals for the parent
    qgroup. In the above example, 222.95 MiB will be freed if all subvolumes
    are removed. Run the following command to see which snapshots are
    associated with each subvolume:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;btrfs subvolume list -st /</screen>
  </section>
</chapter>