<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-health-checker" xml:lang="en">
 <title>Health checker</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
  <para>
   Health checker is a program delivered with &slema; that checks whether
   services are running properly during booting of your system.
  </para>
  <para>
   During the boot process, <literal>systemd</literal> calls Health checker,
   which in turn calls its plugins. Each plugin checks a particular service or
   condition. If each check passes, a status file
   (<filename>/var/lib/misc/health-check.state</filename>) is created. The
   status file marks the current root file system as correct.
  </para>
  <para>
   If any of the health checker plugins reports an error, the action taken
   depends on a particular condition, as described below:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><emphasis>The snapshot is booted for the first time.</emphasis></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If the current snapshot is different from the last one that worked
      properly, an automatic rollback to the last working snapshot is
      performed. This means that the last change performed to the file system
      broke the snapshot.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><emphasis>The snapshot has already booted correctly in the past.</emphasis></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      There could be just a temporary problem, and the system is rebooted
      automatically.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><emphasis>The reboot of a previously correctly booted snapshot has failed.</emphasis></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If there was already a problem during boot and automatic reboot has been
      triggered, but the problem still persists, then the system is kept
      running to enable to the administrator to fix the problem. The services
      that are tested by the health checker plugins are stopped if possible.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <section xml:id="sec-health-plugins">
   <title>Adding custom plugins</title>
   <para>
    Health checker supports the addition of your own plugins to check services
    during the boot process. Each plugin is a bash script that must fulfill the
    following requirements:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Plugins are located within a specific
      directory&mdash;<filename>/usr/libexec/health-checker</filename>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The service that will be checked by the particular plugin must be defined
      in the <literal>Unit</literal> section of the
      <filename>/usr/lib/systemd/system/health-checker.service</filename> file.
      For example, the <literal>etcd</literal> service is defined as follows:
     </para>
<screen>
[Unit]
...
After=etcd.service
...
</screen>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Each plugin must have functions called <literal>run.checks</literal> and
      <literal>stop_services</literal> defined. The
      <literal>run.checks</literal> function checks whether a particular
      service has started properly. Bear in mind that service that has not been
      enabled by systemd, should be ignored. The function
      <literal>stop_services</literal> is called to stop the particular service
      in case the service has not been started properly. You can use the plugin
      template for your reference.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>