<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="smt.reporting">
 <title>&smt; Reports</title>
 <info/>
 <para>
  This chapter introduces reports generated based on the SMT and SUSE
  Customer Center data. The reports generated contain statistics of all the
  registered machines, products used and all active, expiring or missing
  subscriptions.
 </para>
 <note>
  <title>Assignment of Reports</title>
  <para>
   If you are using more than one &smt; server in your environment,
   generated reports may not represent all of the &smt; servers or machines
   in your environment. For the complete statistics of all your registered
   machines, refer to the information in the &scc;.
  </para>
 </note>
 <sect1>
  <title>Report Schedule and Recipients</title>

  <para>
   Generated &smt; reports can be sent to a defined list of e-mail addresses
   periodically. To create or edit this list, and to set the frequency of
   the reports, use the &yast; &smt; Configuration module. How to configure
   this list is described in <xref linkend="smt.yast.reports"/>.
   Configuration of the report schedule is described in
   <xref linkend="smt.yast.scheduling"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   The list can also be edited manually in the <option>reportEmail</option>
   option of the <filename>/etc/smt.conf</filename> configuration file. For
   more information about editing the list of addresses directly, see
   <xref linkend="smt.config.smtconf.report"/>. To set the frequency of
   reports manually, you can directly edit the
   <filename>smt-gen-report</filename> lines of the crontab in
   <filename>/etc/cron.d/novell.com-smt</filename>. For more information
   about the crontab format, see <command>man 5 crontab</command>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Reports, including those created as a scheduled &smt; job, are created by
   the <command>smt-report</command> command. This command has various
   parameters. To edit parameters used with scheduled commands, edit the
   <filename>/etc/smt.d/smt-cron.conf</filename> configuration file. For
   more information, see <xref linkend="smt.config.cronconf"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Report Output Formats and Targets</title>

  <para>
   &smt; reports can be printed to the standard output, exported to one or
   multiple files (in CSV format) and be mailed to the defined list of
   e-mail addresses. Use the following options for the
   <command>smt-report</command> command:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>--quiet</option> or <option>-q</option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Suppress output to STDOUT and run <command>smt-report</command> in
      quiet mode.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>--file</option> or <option>-F</option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Export report to one or several files. By default, the report will be
      written to a single file, rendered as tables. Optionally, the file name
      or whole path may be specified after the parameter: <option>--file
      <replaceable>filename</replaceable></option>. If no file name is
      specified, a default file name containing a time stamp is used. However,
      &smt; will not check if the file or files already exist.
     </para>
     <para>
      In CSV (Comma-Separated Value) mode the report will be written to
      multiple files, therefore the specified file name will expand to
      <filename><replaceable>[path/]filename</replaceable>-<replaceable>reportname</replaceable>.<replaceable>extension</replaceable></filename>
      for every report.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>--csv</option> or <option>-c</option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para> The report will be exported to multiple files in CSV format.
            The first line of each *.csv file consists of the column
            names, then the data starts on line two. It is recommended
            to use the <option>--csv</option> parameter together with
            the <option>--file</option> parameter. If the specified file
            name contains a <literal>.csv</literal> extension, the
            report format will be CSV (as if the <option>--csv</option>
            parameter was used). </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>--mail</option> or <option>-m</option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Activate mailing of the report to the addresses configured with the
      &yast; &smt; Configuration module and written in
      <filename>/etc/smt.conf</filename>. The report will be rendered as
      tables.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>--attach</option> or <option>-a</option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Attach the report to the mails in CSV format. This option should only
      be used together with the <option>--mail</option> option.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>--pdf</option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The report will be exported to multiple files in pdf format.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>--xml</option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The report will be exported to multiple files in xml format.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <note>
   <title>Disabling Sending Attachments</title>
   <para>
    If you want to disable sending CSV attachments with report mails, edit
    the <filename>/etc/smt.d/smt-cron.conf</filename> configuration file as
    follows: remove the <option>--attach</option> option from the
    <literal>REPORT_PARAMS</literal> value. The default line reads:
    <literal>REPORT_PARAMS="--mail --attach -L
    /var/log/smt-report.log"</literal>. To disable CSV attachments, change
    it to: <literal>REPORT_PARAMS="--mail -L
    /var/log/smt-report.log"</literal>.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you have disabled CSV attachments but need them occasionally, you can
    send them manually with the <command>smt-report --mail --attach -L
    /var/log/smt-report.log</command> command.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
