<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="smt.management">
 <title>Managing Repositories with &yast; &smt; Server Management</title>
 <info/>
 <para>
  You can use the &yast; &smt; Server Management module for day-to-day
  management. &smt; Server Management enables and disables the mirroring
  of repositories, the staging flag for repositories, and performs the
  mirroring and staging.
 </para>
 <sect1 xml:id="smt.yast.staging.starting">
  <title>Starting &smt; Management Module</title>

  <para>
   &smt; Management is a &yast; module. To start the module, do one of
   the following:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Start &yast; and select <guimenu>Network Services</guimenu>, then
     <guimenu>&smt; Server Management</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Enter <command>yast2 smt</command> in the command line as
     &rootuser;.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   The &smt; Management application window opens with the
   <guimenu>Repositories</guimenu> tab active.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>List of Repositories</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="smt_repos.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="smt_repos.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="smt.yast.staging.viewing">
  <title>Viewing and Managing Repositories</title>

  <para>
   In the <guimenu>Repositories</guimenu> tab, you can see the list of all
   available package repositories for &smt;. For each repository, the
   list shows the repository's name, target product and architecture,
   mirroring and staging flag, date of last mirroring, and a short
   description. You can sort the list by clicking on the relevant column's
   header, and scroll the list items using the scroll bars on the window's
   right side.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="smt.yast.staging.viewing.filter">
   <title>Filtering Repositories</title>
   <para>
    You can also filter out groups of repositories with the
    <guimenu>Filter</guimenu> drop-down list in the upper left part of the
    window. The filter list items are collected and assembled dynamically
    from the first word of the repositories' names. If you use a filter to
    limit the number of displayed repositories, you can always go back and
    view all of them by selecting <guimenu>All</guimenu> from the
    <guimenu>Filter</guimenu> drop-down list. You can also use more than one
    filter in sequence.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="smt.yast.staging.viewing.mirror">
   <title>Mirroring Repositories</title>
   <para>
    Before you can start to offer package repositories, you need to create a
    local mirror of their packages. To do this, follow the procedure:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      From the list, select the line containing the name of the repository
      you want to mirror.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click on the selected line highlighting it.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click on the <guimenu>Toggle Mirroring</guimenu> button in the lower
      left part of the window. In the <guimenu>Mirroring</guimenu> column of
      the selected repository, a check mark appears. If the repository was
      already selected for mirroring before, the check mark will disappear,
      and the repository will not be mirrored anymore.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Hit the <guimenu>Mirror Now</guimenu> button and the repository will
      be mirrored immediately.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      A pop-up window appears with the information about mirroring status
      and result.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click OK and the original window with the list of repositories will be
      refreshed.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <figure>
    <title>Status of Mirroring Process</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="smt_mirroring-done.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="smt_mirroring-done.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="smt.yast.staging.stage">
  <title>Staging Repositories</title>

  <para>
   After the mirroring is finished, you can stage the mirrored repositories.
   In &smt;, <emphasis>staging</emphasis> is a process where you create
   either testing or production repositories based on the mirrored ones. The
   testing repository helps you examine the repository and its packages
   before you make them available in a production environment. To make
   repositories available for staging, do the following:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     From the repository list, select the line containing the name of the
     repository you want to manage.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click on the selected line, highlighting it.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click on the <guimenu>Toggle Staging</guimenu> button in the lower left
     part of the window next to the <guimenu>Toggle Mirroring</guimenu>
     button. In the <guimenu>Staging</guimenu> column of the selected
     repository, a check mark appears. If the repository was already
     selected for staging before, the check mark will disappear, and the
     repository will not be available for staging.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Repeat steps 1 to 3 for all directory whose staging flag you wish to
     change.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <important>
   <title>Toggle Staging Button Not Active</title>
   <para>
    You can only stage the repositories that were previously selected for
    mirroring. If it is not the case, the <guimenu>Toggle Staging</guimenu>
    button will not be active.
   </para>
  </important>

  <para>
   Once you mirror the repositories and make them available for staging,
   click on the <guimenu>Staging</guimenu> tab. In the upper left part of
   the window, there is a <guimenu>Repository Name</guimenu> drop-down list
   of all repositories which are available for staging. There the repository
   names have the name of the staging group attached in parentheses. Select
   the one you want to stage and a list of packages of this repository
   appears below. Information about the patch name, its version and
   category, testing and production flags, and a short summary is available
   for each patch.
  </para>

  <para>
   Next to the <guimenu>Repository Name</guimenu> drop-down list, there is a
   <guimenu>Patch Category</guimenu> filter. It helps you to list only the
   patches that belong to one of the predefined categories.
  </para>

  <para>
   If the selected repository allows for patch filtering, you can toggle the
   status flag for individual patches. Do so by clicking on the
   <guimenu>Toggle Patch Status</guimenu> button in the lower left part of
   the window.
  </para>

  <para>
   Before creating a repository of packages that are available in the
   <emphasis>production</emphasis> environment, you need to create and test
   the <emphasis>testing</emphasis> repository. Click on the <guimenu>Create
   Snapshot</guimenu> drop-down menu and select <guimenu>From Full Mirror to
   Testing</guimenu> menu item. A small pop-up window appears informing you
   about the staging process. After the testing repository snapshot is
   created, the relevant check marks in the <guimenu>Testing</guimenu>
   column will be displayed.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Testing Snapshot Created</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="smt_staging1.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="smt_staging1.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <important>
   <title>Creating a Production Snapshot</title>
   <para>
    After you enable <emphasis>staging</emphasis> for an update repository,
    you have to create its <emphasis>production</emphasis> snapshot to make
    it available to the clients. Otherwise the clients will not be able to
    find the update repository.
   </para>
  </important>

  <para>
   After you have examined the newly created testing repository, you can
   safely create a production one. Click on the <guimenu>Create
   Snapshot</guimenu> drop-down menu and select <guimenu>From Testing to
   Production</guimenu> menu item. A small pop-up window appears informing
   you about the linking the testing repository to the production one. After
   the production snapshot is created, the relevant check marks in the
   <guimenu>Production</guimenu> column will be displayed. Also, a green
   check mark appears in the <guimenu>Repository Name</guimenu> drop-down
   list.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="smt.yast.staging.client">
  <title>Checking the Client Status</title>

  <para>
   The third tab called <guimenu>Clients Status</guimenu> contains the
   status information about all the clients that use the repositories on
   your &smt; server. It is divided into two main parts: the list of the
   clients and the detailed information.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can read the client's host name, the date and time of the last
   network contact with the &smt; server, and its update status. The
   update status can be one of the following:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <title/>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Up-to-date</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The client packages are updated to their last version available in the
      production repository.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Updates available</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This status means that there are updates available for the client that
      are either <literal>optional</literal> or
      <literal>recommended</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Critical</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Either <literal>security</literal> patches or <literal>package
      manager</literal> patches are available for the client.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   In the lower part of the window, more detailed information about the
   highlighted client is available. It usually consists of extended status
   information and detailed information about the number and types of
   available updates.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Clients Status</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="smt_clients_status.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="smt_clients_status.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
