<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.snapper">
 <title>System Recovery and Snapshot Management with Snapper</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    Being able to do file system snapshots providing the ability to do
    rollbacks on Linux is a feature that was often requested in the past.
    Snapper, with the <literal>Btrfs</literal> file system or thin-provisioned
    LVM volumes now fills that gap.
   </para>

   <para>
    <literal>Btrfs</literal>, a new copy-on-write file system for Linux,
    supports file system snapshots (a copy of the state of a subvolume at a
    certain point of time) of subvolumes (one or more separately mountable file
    systems within each physical partition). Snapshots are also supported on
    thin-provisioned LVM volumes formatted with XFS, Ext4 or Ext3. Snapper lets
    you create and manage these snapshots. It comes with a command line and a
    &yast; interface. Starting with &sls; 12 it is also possible to boot from
    <literal>Btrfs</literal> snapshots&mdash;see
    <xref
    linkend="sec.snapper.snapshot-boot"/> for more information.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>
 <para>
  Using Snapper you can perform the following tasks:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Undo system changes made by <command>zypper</command> and &yast;. See
    <xref linkend="sec.snapper.auto"/> for details.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Restore files from previous snapshots. See
    <xref linkend="sec.snapper.backup"/> for details.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Do a system rollback by booting from a snapshot. See
    <xref linkend="sec.snapper.snapshot-boot"/> for details.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Manually create snapshots on the fly and manage existing snapshots. See
    <xref linkend="sec.snapper.manage"/> for details.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.snapper.setup">
  <title>Default Setup</title>

  <para>
   Snapper on &productname; is set up to serve as an <quote>undo and recovery
   tool</quote> for system changes. By default, the root partition
   (<filename>/</filename>) of &productname; is formatted with
   <literal>Btrfs</literal>. Taking snapshots is automatically enabled if the
   root partition (<filename>/</filename>) is big enough (approximately more
   than 16 GB). Taking snapshots on partitions other than
   <filename>/</filename> is not enabled by default.
  </para>

  <para>
   When a snapshot is created, both the snapshot and the original point to the
   same blocks in the file system. So, initially a snapshot does not occupy
   additional disk space. If data in the original file system is modified,
   changed data blocks are copied while the old data blocks are kept for the
   snapshot. Therefore, a snapshot occupies the same amount of space as the
   data modified. So, over time, the amount of space a snapshot allocates,
   constantly grows. As a consequence, deleting files from a
   <literal>Btrfs</literal> file system containing snapshots may
   <emphasis>not</emphasis> free disk space!
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>Snapshot Location</title>
   <para>
    Snapshots always reside on the same partition or subvolume on which the
    snapshot has been taken. It is not possible to store snapshots on a
    different partition or subvolume.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   As a result, partitions containing snapshots need to be larger than
   <quote>normal</quote> partitions. The exact amount strongly depends on the
   number of snapshots you keep and the amount of data modifications. As a rule
   of thumb you should consider using twice the size than you normally would.
   To prevent disks from running out of space, old snapshots are automatically
   cleaned up. Refer to
   <xref
   linkend="sec.snapper.setup.customize.archiving"/> for details.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="snapper.snapshot-type">
   <title>Types of Snapshots</title>
   <para>
    Although snapshots themselves do not differ in a technical sense, we
    distinguish between three types of snapshots, based on the occasion on
    which they were taken:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Timeline Snapshots</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A single snapshot is created every hour. Old snapshots are automatically
       deleted. By default, the first snapshot of the last ten days, months,
       and years are kept. Timeline snapshots are disabled by default.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Installation Snapshots</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Whenever one or more packages are installed with &yast; or Zypper, a
       pair of snapshots is created: one before the installation starts
       (<quote>Pre</quote>) and another one after the installation has finished
       (<quote>Post</quote>). In case an important system component such as the
       kernel has been installed, the snapshot pair is marked as important
       (<literal>important=yes</literal>). Old snapshots are automatically
       deleted. By default the last ten important snapshots and the last ten
       <quote>regular</quote> (including administration snapshots) snapshots
       are kept. Installation snapshots are enabled by default.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Administration Snapshots</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Whenever you administrate the system with &yast;, a pair of snapshots is
       created: one when a &yast; module is started (<quote>Pre</quote>) and
       another when the module is closed (<quote>Post</quote>). Old snapshots
       are automatically deleted. By default the last ten important snapshots
       and the last ten <quote>regular</quote> snapshots (including
       installation snapshots) are kept. Administration snapshots are enabled
       by default.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="snapper.dir-excludes">
   <title>Directories That Are Excluded from Snapshots</title>
   <para>
    Some directories need to be excluded from snapshots for different reasons.
    The following list shows all directories that are excluded:
   </para>
   <xi:include href="snapshot_excludes_i.xml"/>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.snapper.setup.customize">
   <title>Customizing the Setup</title>
   <para>
    &productname; comes with a reasonable default setup, which should be
    sufficient for most use cases. However, all aspects of taking automatic
    snapshots and snapshot keeping can be configured according to your needs.
   </para>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.snapper.setup.customize.auto_snapshots">
    <title>Disabling/Enabling Snapshots</title>
    <para>
     Each of the three snapshot types (timeline, installation, administration)
     can be enabled or disabled independently.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Disabling/Enabling Timeline Snapshots</term>
      <listitem>
       <formalpara>
        <title>Enabling</title>
        <para>
         <command>snapper-c root set-config "TIMELINE_CREATE=yes"</command>
        </para>
       </formalpara>
       <formalpara>
        <title>Disabling</title>
        <para>
         <command>snapper -c root set-config "TIMELINE_CREATE=no"</command>
        </para>
       </formalpara>
       <para>
        Timeline snapshots are enabled by default, except for the root
        partition.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Disabling/Enabling Installation Snapshots</term>
      <listitem>
       <formalpara>
        <title>Enabling:</title>
        <para>
         Install the package
         <systemitem class="resource">snapper-zypp-plugin</systemitem>
        </para>
       </formalpara>
       <formalpara>
        <title>Disabling:</title>
        <para>
         Uninstall the package
         <systemitem class="resource">snapper-zypp-plugin</systemitem>
        </para>
       </formalpara>
       <para>
        Installation snapshots are enabled by default.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Disabling/Enabling Administration Snapshots</term>
      <listitem>
       <formalpara>
        <title>Enabling:</title>
        <para>
         Set <envar>USE_SNAPPER</envar> to <literal>yes</literal> in
         <filename>/etc/sysconfig/yast2</filename>.
        </para>
       </formalpara>
       <formalpara>
        <title>Disabling:</title>
        <para>
         Set <envar>USE_SNAPPER</envar> to <literal>no</literal> in
         <filename>/etc/sysconfig/yast2</filename>.
        </para>
       </formalpara>
       <para>
        Administration snapshots are enabled by default.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.snapper.setup.customize.inst_snapshots">
    <title>Controlling Installation Snapshots</title>
    <para>
     Taking snapshot pairs upon installing packages with &yast; or Zypper is
     handled by the
     <systemitem class="resource">snapper-zypp-plugin</systemitem>. An XML
     configuration file, <filename>/etc/snapper/zypp-plugin.conf</filename>
     defines, when to make snapshots. By default the file looks like the
     following:
    </para>
<screen> 1 &lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?&gt;
 2 &lt;snapper-zypp-plugin-conf&gt;
 3  &lt;solvables&gt;
 4   &lt;solvable match="w"<co xml:id="zypp-conf.match"/> important="true"<co xml:id="zypp-conf.important"/>&gt;kernel-*<co xml:id="zypp-conf.kernel"/>&lt;/solvable&gt;
 5   &lt;solvable match="w" important="true"&gt;dracut&lt;/solvable&gt;
 6   &lt;solvable match="w" important="true"&gt;glibc&lt;/solvable&gt;
 7   &lt;solvable match="w" important="true"&gt;systemd*&lt;/solvable&gt;
 8   &lt;solvable match="w" important="true"&gt;udev&lt;/solvable&gt;
 9   &lt;solvable match="w"&gt;*&lt;/solvable&gt;<co xml:id="zypp-conf.packages"/>
10  &lt;/solvables&gt;
11 &lt;/snapper-zypp-plugin-conf&gt;</screen>
    <calloutlist>
     <callout arearefs="zypp-conf.match">
      <para>
       The match attribute defines whether the pattern is a Unix shell-style
       wild card (<literal>w</literal>) or a Python regular expression
       (<literal>re</literal>).
      </para>
     </callout>
     <callout arearefs="zypp-conf.important">
      <para>
       If the given pattern matches and the corresponding package is marked as
       important (for example Kernel packages), the snapshot will also be
       marked as important.
      </para>
     </callout>
     <callout arearefs="zypp-conf.kernel">
      <para>
       Pattern to match a package name. Based on the setting of the
       <literal>match</literal> attribute, special characters are either
       interpreted as shell wild cards or regular expressions. This pattern
       matches all package names starting with <literal>kernel-</literal>.
      </para>
     </callout>
     <callout arearefs="zypp-conf.packages">
      <para>
       This line unconditionally matches all packages.
      </para>
     </callout>
    </calloutlist>
    <para>
     With this configuration snapshot, pairs are made whenever a package is
     installed (line 9). When Kernel, dracut, glibc, systemd, or udev packages
     marked as important are installed, the snapshot pair will also be marked
     as important (lines 4 to 8). All rules are evaluated.
    </para>
    <para>
     To disable a rule, either delete it or deactivate it using XML comments.
     To prevent the system from making snapshot pairs for every package
     installation for example, comment line 9:
    </para>
<screen> 1 &lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?&gt;
 2 &lt;snapper-zypp-plugin-conf&gt;
 3  &lt;solvables&gt;
 4   &lt;solvable match="w" important="true"&gt;kernel-*&lt;/solvable&gt;
 5   &lt;solvable match="w" important="true"&gt;dracut&lt;/solvable&gt;
 6   &lt;solvable match="w" important="true"&gt;glibc&lt;/solvable&gt;
 7   &lt;solvable match="w" important="true"&gt;systemd*&lt;/solvable&gt;
 8   &lt;solvable match="w" important="true"&gt;udev&lt;/solvable&gt;
 9   &lt;!-- &lt;solvable match="w"&gt;*&lt;/solvable&gt; --&gt;
10  &lt;/solvables&gt;
11 &lt;/snapper-zypp-plugin-conf&gt;</screen>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.snapper.setup.customizing.new_subvolume">
    <title>Creating and Mounting New Subvolumes</title>
    <para>
     Creating a new subvolume underneath the <filename>/</filename>-hierarchy
     and permanently mounting it is supported. However, you need to make sure
     not to create it inside a snapshot, since you would not be able to delete
     snapshots anymore after a rollback.
    </para>
    <para>
     &productname; is configured with the <filename>/@/</filename> subvolume
     which serves as an independent root for permanent subvolumes such as
     <filename>/opt</filename>, <filename>/srv</filename>,
     <filename>/home</filename> and others. Any new subvolumes you create and
     permanently mount need to be created in this initial root file system.
    </para>
    <para>
     To do so, run the following commands. In this example, a new subvolume
     <filename>/usr/important</filename> is created from
     <filename>/dev/sda2</filename>.
    </para>
<screen>mount /dev/sda2 -o subvol=@ /mnt
btrfs subvolume create /mnt/usr/important
umount /mnt</screen>
    <para>
     The corresponding entry in <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> needs to look
     like the following:
    </para>
<screen>/dev/sda2 /usr/important btrfs subvol=@/usr/important 0 0</screen>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.snapper.setup.customize.archiving">
    <title>Controlling Snapshot Archiving</title>
    <para>
     Snapshots occupy disk space. To prevent disks from running out of space
     and thus causing system outages, old snapshots are automatically deleted.
     By default, up to ten important installation and administration snapshots
     and up to ten regular installation and administration snapshots are kept.
     If these snapshots occupy more than 50% of the root file system size,
     additional snapshots will be deleted. A minimum of four important and two
     regular snapshots are always kept.
    </para>
    <para>
     Refer to <xref linkend="sec.snapper.config.modify"/> for instructions on
     how to change these values.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.snapper.lvm">
    <title>Using Snapper on Thin-Provisioned LVM Volumes</title>
    <para>
     Apart from snapshots on <literal>Btrfs</literal> file systems, Snapper
     also supports taking snapshots on thin-provisioned LVM volumes (snapshots
     on regular LVM volumes are <emphasis>not</emphasis> supported) formatted
     with XFS, Ext4 or Ext3. For more information and setup instructions on LVM
     volumes, refer to <xref linkend="sec.yast2.system.lvm"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     To use Snapper on a thin-provisioned LVM volume you need to create a
     Snapper configuration for it. On LVM it is required to specify the file
     system with
     <option>--fstype=lvm(<replaceable>FILESYSTEM</replaceable>)</option>.
     <literal>ext3</literal>, <literal>etx4</literal> or <literal>xfs</literal>
     are valid values for <replaceable>FILESYSTEM</replaceable>. Example:
    </para>
<screen>snapper -c lvm create-config --fstype="lvm(xfs)" /thin_lvm</screen>
    <para>
     You can adjust this configuration according to your needs as described in
     <xref linkend="sec.snapper.config.modify"/>.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.snapper.auto">
  <title>Using Snapper to Undo Changes</title>

  <para>
   Snapper on &productname; is preconfigured to serve as a tool that lets you
   undo changes made by <command>zypper</command> and &yast;. For this purpose,
   Snapper is configured to create a pair of snapshots before and after each
   run of <command>zypper</command> and &yast;. Snapper also lets you restore
   system files that have been accidentally deleted or modified. Timeline
   snapshots for the root partition need to be enabled for this
   purpose&mdash;see
   <xref linkend="sec.snapper.setup.customize.auto_snapshots"/> for details.
  </para>

  <para>
   By default, automatic snapshots as described above are configured for the
   root partition and its subvolumes. To make snapshots available for other
   partitions such as <filename>/home</filename> for example, you can create
   custom configurations.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Undoing Changes Compared to Rollback</title>
   <para>
    When working with snapshots to restore data, it is important to know that
    there are two fundamentally different scenarios Snapper can handle:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Undoing Changes</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       When undoing changes as described in the following, two snapshots are
       being compared and the changes between these two snapshots are made
       undone. Using this method also allows to explicitly select the files
       that should be restored.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Rollback</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       When doing rollbacks as described in
       <xref linkend="sec.snapper.snapshot-boot"/>, the system is reset to the
       state at which the snapshot was taken.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    When undoing changes, it is also possible to compare a snapshot against the
    current system. When restoring <emphasis>all</emphasis> files from such a
    comparison, this will have the same result as doing a rollback. However,
    using the method described in <xref linkend="sec.snapper.snapshot-boot"/>
    for rollbacks should be preferred, since it is faster and allows you to
    review the system before doing the rollback.
   </para>
  </important>

  <warning>
   <title>Data Consistency</title>
   <para>
    There is no mechanism to ensure data consistency when creating a snapshot.
    Whenever a file (for example, a database) is written at the same time as
    the snapshot is being created, it will result in a broken or partly written
    file. Restoring such a file will cause problems. Furthermore, some system
    files such as <filename>/etc/mtab</filename> must never be restored.
    Therefore it is strongly recommended to <emphasis>always</emphasis> closely
    review the list of changed files and their diffs. Only restore files that
    really belong to the action you want to revert.
   </para>
  </warning>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.snapper.yast">
   <title>Undoing &yast; and Zypper Changes</title>
   <para>
    If you set up the root partition with <literal>Btrfs</literal> during the
    installation, Snapper&mdash;preconfigured for doing rollbacks of &yast; or
    Zypper changes&mdash;will automatically be installed. Every time you start
    a &yast; module or a Zypper transaction, two snapshots are created: a
    <quote>pre-snapshot</quote> capturing the state of the file system before
    the start of the module and a <quote>post-snapshot</quote> after the module
    has been finished.
   </para>
   <para>
    Using the &yast; Snapper module or the <command>snapper</command> command
    line tool, you can undo the changes made by &yast;/Zypper by restoring
    files from the <quote>pre-snapshot</quote>. Comparing two snapshots the
    tools also allow you to see which files have been changed. You can also
    display the differences between two versions of a file (diff).
   </para>
   <procedure xml:id="proc.snapper.undo.yast">
    <title>Undoing Changes Using the &yast; <guimenu>Snapper</guimenu> Module</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the <guimenu>Snapper</guimenu> module from the
      <guimenu>Miscellaneous</guimenu> section in &yast; or by entering
      <command>yast2 snapper</command>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Make sure <guimenu>Current Configuration</guimenu> is set to
      <guimenu>root</guimenu>. This is always the case unless you have manually
      added own Snapper configurations.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose a pair of pre- and post-snapshots from the list. Both, &yast; and
      Zypper snapshot pairs are of the type <guimenu>Pre &amp; Post</guimenu>.
      &yast; snapshots are labeled as <literal>zypp(y2base)</literal> in the
      <guimenu>Description column</guimenu>; Zypper snapshots are labeled
      <literal>zypp(zypper)</literal>.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="snapper_yast2_list.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="snapper_yast2_list.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Show Changes</guimenu> to open the list of files that
      differ between the two snapshots.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="snapper_yast2_changes.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="snapper_yast2_changes.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Review the list of files. To display a <quote>diff</quote> between the
      pre- and post-version of a file, select it from the list.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="snapper_yast2_diff.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="snapper_yast2_diff.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To restore one or more files, select the relevant files or directories by
      activating the respective check box. Click <guimenu>Restore
      Selected</guimenu> and confirm the action by clicking
      <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="snapper_yast2_restore.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="snapper_yast2_restore.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
     <para>
      To restore a single file, activate its diff view by clicking its name.
      Click <guimenu>Restore From First</guimenu> and confirm your choice with
      <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure xml:id="proc.snapper.yast.cmdline">
    <title>Undoing Changes Using the <command>snapper</command> Command</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Get a list of &yast; and Zypper snapshots by running <command>snapper
      list -t pre-post</command>. &yast; snapshots are labeled
      as <literal>yast <replaceable>module_name</replaceable></literal> in the
      <guimenu>Description column</guimenu>; Zypper snapshots are labeled
      <literal>zypp(zypper)</literal>.
     </para>
<screen><?dbsuse-fo font-size="0.60em"?>&prompt.root;snapper list -t pre-post
Pre # | Post # | Pre Date                      | Post Date                     | Description
------+--------+-------------------------------+-------------------------------+--------------
311   | 312    | Tue 06 May 2014 14:05:46 CEST | Tue 06 May 2014 14:05:52 CEST | zypp(y2base)
340   | 341    | Wed 07 May 2014 16:15:10 CEST | Wed 07 May 2014 16:15:16 CEST | zypp(zypper)
342   | 343    | Wed 07 May 2014 16:20:38 CEST | Wed 07 May 2014 16:20:42 CEST | zypp(y2base)
344   | 345    | Wed 07 May 2014 16:21:23 CEST | Wed 07 May 2014 16:21:24 CEST | zypp(zypper)
346   | 347    | Wed 07 May 2014 16:41:06 CEST | Wed 07 May 2014 16:41:10 CEST | zypp(y2base)
348   | 349    | Wed 07 May 2014 16:44:50 CEST | Wed 07 May 2014 16:44:53 CEST | zypp(y2base)
350   | 351    | Wed 07 May 2014 16:46:27 CEST | Wed 07 May 2014 16:46:38 CEST | zypp(y2base) </screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Get a list of changed files for a snapshot pair with <command>snapper
      status</command>
      <replaceable>PRE</replaceable>..<replaceable>POST</replaceable>. Files
      with content changes are marked with <guimenu>c</guimenu>, files that
      have been added are marked with <guimenu>+</guimenu> and deleted files
      are marked with <guimenu>-</guimenu>.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;snapper status 350..351
+..... /usr/share/doc/packages/mikachan-fonts
+..... /usr/share/doc/packages/mikachan-fonts/COPYING
+..... /usr/share/doc/packages/mikachan-fonts/dl.html
c..... /usr/share/fonts/truetype/fonts.dir
c..... /usr/share/fonts/truetype/fonts.scale
+..... /usr/share/fonts/truetype/みかちゃん-p.ttf
+..... /usr/share/fonts/truetype/みかちゃん-pb.ttf
+..... /usr/share/fonts/truetype/みかちゃん-ps.ttf
+..... /usr/share/fonts/truetype/みかちゃん.ttf
c..... /var/cache/fontconfig/7ef2298fde41cc6eeb7af42e48b7d293-x86_64.cache-4
c..... /var/lib/rpm/Basenames
c..... /var/lib/rpm/Dirnames
c..... /var/lib/rpm/Group
c..... /var/lib/rpm/Installtid
c..... /var/lib/rpm/Name
c..... /var/lib/rpm/Packages
c..... /var/lib/rpm/Providename
c..... /var/lib/rpm/Requirename
c..... /var/lib/rpm/Sha1header
c..... /var/lib/rpm/Sigmd5</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To display the diff for a certain file, run <command>snapper
      diff</command>
      <replaceable>PRE</replaceable>..<replaceable>POST</replaceable>
      <replaceable>FILENAME</replaceable>. If you do not specify
      <replaceable>FILENAME</replaceable>, a diff for all files will be
      displayed.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;snapper diff 350..351 /usr/share/fonts/truetype/fonts.scale
--- /.snapshots/350/snapshot/usr/share/fonts/truetype/fonts.scale       2014-04-23 15:58:57.000000000 +0200
+++ /.snapshots/351/snapshot/usr/share/fonts/truetype/fonts.scale       2014-05-07 16:46:31.000000000 +0200
@@ -1,4 +1,4 @@
-1174
+1486
 ds=y:ai=0.2:luximr.ttf -b&amp;h-luxi mono-bold-i-normal--0-0-0-0-c-0-iso10646-1
 ds=y:ai=0.2:luximr.ttf -b&amp;h-luxi mono-bold-i-normal--0-0-0-0-c-0-iso8859-1
[...]</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To restore one or more files run <command>snapper -v undochange</command>
      <replaceable>PRE</replaceable>..<replaceable>POST</replaceable>
      <replaceable>FILENAMES</replaceable>. If you do not specify a
      <replaceable>FILENAMES</replaceable>, all changed files will be restored.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;snapper -v undochange 350..351
     create:0 modify:13 delete:7
     undoing change...
     deleting /usr/share/doc/packages/mikachan-fonts
     deleting /usr/share/doc/packages/mikachan-fonts/COPYING
     deleting /usr/share/doc/packages/mikachan-fonts/dl.html
     deleting /usr/share/fonts/truetype/みかちゃん-p.ttf
     deleting /usr/share/fonts/truetype/みかちゃん-pb.ttf
     deleting /usr/share/fonts/truetype/みかちゃん-ps.ttf
     deleting /usr/share/fonts/truetype/みかちゃん.ttf
     modifying /usr/share/fonts/truetype/fonts.dir
     modifying /usr/share/fonts/truetype/fonts.scale
     modifying /var/cache/fontconfig/7ef2298fde41cc6eeb7af42e48b7d293-x86_64.cache-4
     modifying /var/lib/rpm/Basenames
     modifying /var/lib/rpm/Dirnames
     modifying /var/lib/rpm/Group
     modifying /var/lib/rpm/Installtid
     modifying /var/lib/rpm/Name
     modifying /var/lib/rpm/Packages
     modifying /var/lib/rpm/Providename
     modifying /var/lib/rpm/Requirename
     modifying /var/lib/rpm/Sha1header
     modifying /var/lib/rpm/Sigmd5
     undoing change done</screen>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <warning>
    <title>Reverting User Additions</title>
    <para>
     Reverting user additions via undoing changes with Snapper is not
     recommended. Since certain directories are excluded from snapshots, files
     belonging to these users will remain in the file system. If a user with
     the same user ID as a deleted user is created, this user will inherit the
     files. Therefore it is strongly recommended to use the &yast;
     <guimenu>User and Group Management</guimenu> tool to remove users.
    </para>
   </warning>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.snapper.backup">
   <title>Using Snapper to Restore Files</title>
   <para>
    Apart from the installation and administration snapshots, Snapper creates
    timeline snapshots. You can use these backup snapshots to restore files
    that have accidentally been deleted or to restore a previous version of a
    file. By using Snapper's diff feature you can also find out which
    modifications have been made at a certain point of time.
   </para>
   <para>
    Being able to restore files is especially interesting for data, which may
    reside on subvolumes or partitions for which snapshots are not taken by
    default. To be able to restore files from home directories, for example,
    create a separate Snapper configuration for <filename>/home</filename>
    doing automatic timeline snapshots. See
    <xref linkend="sec.snapper.config"/> for instructions.
   </para>
   <warning>
    <title>Restoring Files Compared to Rollback</title>
    <para>
     Snapshots taken from the root file system (defined by Snapper's root
     configuration), can be used to do a system rollback. The recommended way
     to do such a rollback is to boot from the snapshot and then perform the
     rollback. See <xref linkend="sec.snapper.snapshot-boot"/> for details.
    </para>
    <para>
     Performing a rollback would also be possible by restoring all files from a
     root file system snapshot as described below. However, this is not
     recommended. You may restore single files, for example a configuration
     file from the <systemitem>/etc</systemitem> directory, but not the
     complete list of files from the snapshot.
    </para>
    <para>
     This restriction only affects snapshots taken from the root file system!
    </para>
   </warning>
   <procedure xml:id="proc.snapper.restore.yast">
    <title>Restoring Files Using the &yast; <guimenu>Snapper</guimenu> Module</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the <guimenu>Snapper</guimenu> module from the
      <guimenu>Miscellaneous</guimenu> section in &yast; or by entering
      <command>yast2 snapper</command>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose the <guimenu>Current Configuration</guimenu> from which to choose
      a snapshot.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select a timeline snapshot from which to restore a file and choose
      <guimenu>Show Changes</guimenu>. Timeline snapshots are of the type
      <guimenu>Single</guimenu> with a description value of
      <guimenu>timeline</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select a file from the text box by clicking the file name. The difference
      between the snapshot version and the current system is shown. Activate
      the check box to select the file for restore. Do so for all files you
      want to restore.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Restore Selected</guimenu> and confirm the action by
      clicking <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure xml:id="proc.snapper.restore.cmdl">
    <title>Restoring Files Using the <command>snapper</command> Command</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Get a list of timeline snapshots for a specific configuration by running
      the following command:
     </para>
<screen>snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> list -t single | grep timeline</screen>
     <para>
      <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> needs to be replaced by an existing
      Snapper configuration. Use <command>snapper list-configs</command> to
      display a list.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Get a list of changed files for a given snapshot by running the following
      command:
     </para>
<screen>snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> status <replaceable>SNAPSHOT_ID</replaceable>..0</screen>
     <para>
      Replace <replaceable>SNAPSHOT_ID</replaceable> by the ID for the snapshot
      from which you want to restore the file(s).
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Optionally list the differences between the current file version and the
      one from the snapshot by running
     </para>
<screen>snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> diff <replaceable>SNAPSHOT_ID</replaceable>..0 <replaceable>FILE NAME</replaceable></screen>
     <para>
      If you do not specify <replaceable>&lt;FILE NAME&gt;</replaceable>, the
      difference for all files are shown.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To restore one or more files, run
     </para>
<screen>snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> -v undochange
      <replaceable>SNAPSHOT_ID</replaceable>..0 <replaceable>FILENAME1</replaceable> <replaceable>FILENAME2</replaceable></screen>
     <para>
      If you do not specify file names, all changed files will be restored.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.snapper.snapshot-boot">
  <title>System Rollback by Booting from Snapshots</title>

  <para>
   The &grub; version included on &productname; can boot from Btrfs snapshots.
   Together with Snapper's rollback feature, this allows to recover a
   misconfigured system. Only snapshots created for the default Snapper
   configuration (<literal>root</literal>) are bootable.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Supported Configuration</title>
   <para>
<!-- fs 2016-06-17: This will change with SP3 - see FATE #316347 -->
    As of &productname; &productnumber; system rollbacks are only supported if
    the default subvolume configuration of the root partition has not been
    changed.
   </para>
  </important>

  <para>
   When booting a snapshot, the parts of the file system included in the
   snapshot are mounted read-only; all other file systems and parts that are
   excluded from snapshots are mounted read-write and can be modified.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Undoing Changes Compared to Rollback</title>
   <para>
    When working with snapshots to restore data, it is important to know that
    there are two fundamentally different scenarios Snapper can handle:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Undoing Changes</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       When undoing changes as described in <xref linkend="sec.snapper.auto"/>,
       two snapshots are compared and the changes between these two snapshots
       are reverted. Using this method also allows to explicitly exclude
       selected files from being restored.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Rollback</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       When doing rollbacks as described in the following, the system is reset
       to the state at which the snapshot was taken.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </important>

  <para>
   To do a rollback from a bootable snapshot, the following requirements must
   be met. When doing a default installation, the system is set up accordingly.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <title>Requirements for a Rollback from a Bootable Snapshot</title>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The root file system needs to be Btrfs. Booting from LVM volume snapshots
     is not supported.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The root file system needs to be on a single device, a single partition
     and a single subvolume. Directories that are excluded from snapshots such
     as <filename>/srv</filename> (see <xref linkend="snapper.dir-excludes"/>
     for a full list) may reside on separate partitions.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The system needs to be bootable via the installed boot loader.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   To perform a rollback from a bootable snapshot, do as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Boot the system. In the boot menu choose <guimenu>Bootable
     snapshots</guimenu> and select the snapshot you want to boot. The list of
     snapshots is listed by date&mdash;the most recent snapshot is listed
     first.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log in to the system. Carefully check whether everything works as
     expected. Note that you cannot write to any directory that is part of the
     snapshot. Data you write to other directories will
     <emphasis>not</emphasis> get lost, regardless of what you do next.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Depending on whether you want to perform the rollback or not, choose your
     next step:
    </para>
    <substeps performance="required">
     <step>
      <para>
       If the system is in a state where you do not want to do a rollback,
       reboot to boot into the current system state, to choose a different
       snapshot, or to start the rescue system.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       If you want to perform the rollback, run
      </para>
<screen>sudo snapper rollback</screen>
      <para>
       and reboot afterward. On the boot screen, choose the default boot entry
       to reboot into the reinstated system.
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <tip>
   <title>Rolling Back to a Specific Installation State</title>
   <para>
    If snapshots are not disabled during installation, an initial bootable
    snapshot is created at the end of the initial system installation. You can
    go back to that state at any time by booting this snapshot. The snapshot
    can be identified by the description <literal>after installation</literal>.
   </para>
   <para>
    A bootable snapshot is also created when starting a system upgrade to a
    service pack or a new major release (provided snapshots are not disabled).
   </para>
  </tip>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.snapper.snapshot-boot.identify">
   <title>Accessing and Identifying Snapshot Boot Entries</title>
   <para>
    To boot from a snapshot, reboot your machine and choose <guimenu>Start
    Bootloader from a read-only snapshot</guimenu>. A screen listing all
    bootable snapshots opens. The most recent snapshot is listed first, the
    oldest last. Use the keys <keycap function="down"/> and
    <keycap function="up"/> to navigate and press <keycap function="enter"/> to
    activate the selected snapshot. Activating a snapshot from the boot menu
    does not reboot the machine immediately, but rather opens the boot loader
    of the selected snapshot.
   </para>
   <figure xml:id="fig.snapper.snapshot-boot.identify">
    <title>Boot Loader: Snapshots</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="boot_snapshots.png" width="75%" format="png"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="boot_snapshots.png" width="75%" format="png"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    Each snapshot entry in the boot loader follows a naming scheme which makes
    it possible to identify it easily:
   </para>
<screen>[*]<co xml:id="snapper.boot.important"/><replaceable>OS</replaceable><co xml:id="snapper.boot.os"/> (<replaceable>KERNEL</replaceable><co xml:id="snapper.boot.kernel"/>,<replaceable>DATE</replaceable><co xml:id="snapper.boot.date"/>T<replaceable>TIME</replaceable><co xml:id="snapper.boot.time"/>,<replaceable>DESCRIPTION</replaceable><co xml:id="snapper.boot.description"/>)</screen>
   <calloutlist>
    <callout arearefs="snapper.boot.important">
     <para>
      If the snapshot was marked <literal>important</literal>, the entry is
      marked with a <literal>*</literal>.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="snapper.boot.os">
     <para>
      Operating system label.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="snapper.boot.date">
     <para>
      Date in the format <literal>YYYY-MM-DD</literal>.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="snapper.boot.time">
     <para>
      Time in the format <literal>HH:MM</literal>.
     </para>
    </callout>
    <callout arearefs="snapper.boot.description">
     <para>
      This field contains a description of the snapshot. In case of a manually
      created snapshot this is the string created with the option
      <option>--description</option> or a custom string (see
      <xref
      linkend="tip.snapper.snapshot-boot.custom_descr"/>). In case
      of an automatically created snapshot, it is the tool that was called, for
      example <literal>zypp(zypper)</literal> or
      <literal>yast_sw_single</literal>. Long descriptions may be truncated,
      depending on the size of the boot screen.
     </para>
    </callout>
   </calloutlist>
   <tip xml:id="tip.snapper.snapshot-boot.custom_descr">
    <title>Setting a Custom Description for Boot Loader Snapshot Entries</title>
    <para>
     It is possible to replace the default string in the description field of a
     snapshot with a custom string. This is for example useful if an
     automatically created description is not sufficient, or a user-provided
     description is too long. To set a custom string
     <replaceable>STRING</replaceable> for snapshot
     <replaceable>NUMBER</replaceable>, use the following command:
    </para>
<screen>snapper modify --userdata "bootloader=<replaceable>STRING</replaceable>" <replaceable>NUMBER</replaceable></screen>
    <para>
     The description should be no longer than 25 characters&mdash;everything
     that exceeds this size will not be readable on the boot screen.
    </para>
   </tip>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.snapper.snapshot-boot.limits">
   <title>Limitations</title>
   <para>
    A <emphasis>complete</emphasis> system rollback, restoring the complete
    system to the identical state as it was in when a snapshot was taken, is
    not possible.
   </para>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.snapper.limits.snapshot-boot.excludes">
    <title>Directories Excluded from Snapshots</title>
    <para>
     Root file system snapshots do not contain all directories. See
     <xref linkend="snapper.dir-excludes"/> for details and reasons. As a
     general consequence, data from these directories is not restored,
     resulting in the following limitations.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       Add-ons and Third Party Software may be Unusable after a Rollback
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Applications and add-ons installing data in subvolumes excluded from
        the snapshot, such as <filename>/opt</filename>, may not work after a
        rollback, if others parts of the application data are also installed on
        subvolumes included in the snapshot. Re-install the application or the
        add-on to solve this problem.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>File Access Problems</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If an application had changed file permissions and/or ownership in
        between snapshot and current system, the application may not be able to
        access these files. Reset permissions and/or ownership for the affected
        files after the rollback.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Incompatible Data Formats</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If a service or an application has established a new data format in
        between snapshot and current system, the application may not be able to
        read the affected data files after a rollback.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Subvolumes with a Mixture of Code and Data</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Subvolumes like <filename>/srv</filename> may contain a mixture of code
        and data. A rollback may result in non-functional code. A downgrade of
        the PHP version, for example, may result in broken PHP scripts for the
        Web server.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>User Data</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If a rollback removes users from the system, data that is owned by
        these users in directories excluded from the snapshot, is not removed.
        If a user with the same user ID is created, this user will inherit the
        files. Use a tool like <command>find</command> to locate and remove
        orphaned files.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.snapper.limits.snapshot-boot.grub">
    <title>No Rollback of Boot Loader Data</title>
    <para>
     A rollback of the boot loader is not possible, since all
     <quote>stages</quote> of the boot loader must fit together. This cannot be
     guaranteed when doing rollbacks of <filename>/boot</filename>.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.snapper.config">
  <title>Creating and Modifying Snapper Configurations</title>

  <para>
   The way Snapper behaves is defined in a configuration file that is specific
   for each partition or <literal>Btrfs</literal> subvolume. These
   configuration files reside under <filename>/etc/snapper/configs/</filename>.
  </para>

  <para>
   In case the root file system is big enough (approximately 16 GB), snapshots
   are automatically enabled for the root file system
   <filename>/</filename> upon the installation. The corresponding default
   configuration is named <filename>root</filename>. It creates and manages the
   &yast; and Zypper snapshot. See
   <xref
   linkend="sec.snapper.config.modify.values"/> for a list of the
   default values.
  </para>

  <para>
   You may create your own configurations for other partitions formatted with
   <literal>Btrfs</literal> or existing subvolumes on a
   <literal>Btrfs</literal> partition. In the following example we will set up
   a Snapper configuration for backing up the Web server data residing on a
   separate, <literal>Btrfs</literal>-formatted partition mounted at
   <filename>/srv/www</filename>.
  </para>

  <para>
   After a configuration has been created, you can either use
   <command>snapper</command> itself or the &yast; <guimenu>Snapper</guimenu>
   module to restore files from these snapshots. In &yast; you need to select
   your <guimenu>Current Configuration</guimenu>, while you need to specify
   your configuration for <command>snapper</command> with the global switch
   <option>-c</option> (for example, <command>snapper -c myconfig
   list</command>).
  </para>

  <para>
   To create a new Snapper configuration, run <command>snapper
   create-config</command>:
  </para>

<screen>snapper -c www-data<co xml:id="snapper.create.name"/> create-config /srv/www<co xml:id="snapper.create.volume"/></screen>

  <calloutlist>
   <callout arearefs="snapper.create.name">
    <para>
     Name of configuration file.
    </para>
   </callout>
   <callout arearefs="snapper.create.volume">
    <para>
     Mount point of the partition or <literal>Btrfs</literal> subvolume on
     which to take snapshots.
    </para>
   </callout>
  </calloutlist>

  <para>
   This command will create a new configuration file
   <filename>/etc/snapper/configs/www-data</filename> with reasonable default
   values (taken from
   <filename>/etc/snapper/config-templates/default</filename>). Refer to
   <xref linkend="sec.snapper.config.modify"/> for instructions on how to
   adjust these defaults.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <title>Configuration Defaults</title>
   <para>
    Default values for a new configuration are taken from
    <filename>/etc/snapper/config-templates/default</filename>. To use your own
    set of defaults, create a copy of this file in the same directory and
    adjust it to your needs. To use it, specify the <option>-t</option> option
    with the create-config command:
   </para>
<screen>snapper -c www-data create-config -t <replaceable>my_defaults</replaceable> /srv/www</screen>
  </tip>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.snapper.config.modify">
   <title>Managing Existing Configurations</title>
   <para>
    The <command>snapper</command> offers several subcommands for managing
    existing configurations. You can list, show, delete and modify them:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>List Configurations</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use the command <command>snapper list-configs</command> to get all
       existing configurations:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;snapper list-configs
Config | Subvolume
-------+----------
root   | /
usr    | /usr
local  | /local</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Show a Configuration</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use the subcommand <command>snapper -c
       <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> get-config</command> to display the
       specified configuration. <replaceable>Config</replaceable> needs to be
       replaced by a configuration name shown by <command>snapper
       list-configs</command>. See
       <xref linkend="sec.snapper.config.modify.values"/> for more information
       on the configuration options.
      </para>
      <para>
       To display the default configuration run
      </para>
<screen>snapper -c root get-config</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Modify a Configuration</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use the subcommand <command>snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable>
       set-config
       <replaceable>OPTION</replaceable>=<replaceable>VALUE</replaceable></command>
       to modify an option in the specified configuration.
       <replaceable>Config</replaceable> needs to be replaced by a
       configuration name shown by <command>snapper list-configs</command>.
       Possible values for <replaceable>OPTION</replaceable> and
       <replaceable>VALUE</replaceable> are listed in <xref
       linkend="sec.snapper.config.modify.values"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Delete a Configuration</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use the subcommand <command>snapper -c
       <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> delete-config</command> to delete a
       configuration. <replaceable>Config</replaceable> needs to be replaced by
       a configuration name shown by <command>snapper list-configs</command>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.snapper.config.modify.values">
    <title>Configuration Data</title>
    <para>
     Each configuration contains a list of options that can be modified from
     the command line. The following list provides details for each option. To
     change a value, run <command>snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable>
     set-config
     "<replaceable>KEY</replaceable>=<replaceable>VALUE</replaceable>"</command>.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>ALLOW_GROUPS</literal>,
      <literal>ALLOW_USERS</literal>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Granting permissions to use snapshots to regular users. See
        <xref linkend="sec.snapper.config.user"/> for more information.
       </para>
       <para>
        The default value is <literal>""</literal>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>BACKGROUND_COMPARISON</literal>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Defines whether pre and post snapshots should be compared in the
        background after creation.
       </para>
       <para>
        The default value is <literal>"yes"</literal>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>EMPTY_*</literal>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Defines the clean-up algorithm for snapshots pairs with identical pre
        and post snapshots. See <xref linkend="sec.snapper.clean-up.empty"/>
        for details.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>FSTYPE</literal>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        File system type of the partition. Do not change.
       </para>
       <para>
        The default value is <literal>"btrfs"</literal>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>NUMBER_*</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Defines the clean-up algorithm for installation and admin snapshots.
        See <xref linkend="sec.snapper.clean-up.number"/> for details.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>QGROUP</literal> / <literal>SPACE_LIMIT</literal>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Adds quota support to the clean-up algorithms. See
        <xref
        linkend="sec.snapper.clean-up.quota"/> for details.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>SUBVOLUME</literal>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Mount point of the partition or subvolume to snapshot. Do not change.
       </para>
       <para>
        The default value is <literal>"/"</literal>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>SYNC_ACL</literal>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If Snapper is to be used by regular users (see
        <xref linkend="sec.snapper.config.user"/>) the users must be able to
        access the <filename>.snapshot</filename> directories and to read files
        within them. If SYNC_ACL is set to <literal>yes</literal>, Snapper
        automatically makes them accessible using ACLs for users and groups
        from the ALLOW_USERS or ALLOW_GROUPS entries.
       </para>
       <para>
        The default value is <literal>"no"</literal>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>TIMELINE_CREATE</literal>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If set to <literal>yes</literal>, hourly snapshots are created. Valid
        values: <literal>yes</literal>, <literal>no</literal>.
       </para>
       <para>
        The default value is <literal>"no"</literal>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>TIMELINE_CLEANUP</literal> /
       <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_*</literal>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Defines the clean-up algorithm for timeline snapshots. See
        <xref
        linkend="sec.snapper.clean-up.timeline"/> for details.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.snapper.config.user">
    <title>Using Snapper as Regular User</title>
    <para>
     By default Snapper can only be used by &rootuser;. However, there are
     cases in which certain groups or users need to be able to create snapshots
     or undo changes by reverting to a snapshot:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Web site administrators who want to take snapshots of
       <filename>/srv/www</filename>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Users who want to take a snapshot of their home directory
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     For these purposes Snapper configurations that grant permissions to users
     or/and groups can be created. The corresponding
     <filename>.snapshots</filename> directory needs to be readable and
     accessible by the specified users. The easiest way to achieve this is to
     set the SYNC_ACL option to <literal>yes</literal>.
    </para>
    <procedure>
     <title>Enabling Regular Users to Use Snapper</title>
     <para>
      Note that all steps in this procedure need to be run by &rootuser;.
     </para>
     <step>
      <para>
       If not existing, create a Snapper configuration for the partition or
       subvolume on which the user should be able to use Snapper. Refer to
       <xref linkend="sec.snapper.config"/> for instructions. Example:
      </para>
<screen>snapper --config web_data create /srv/www</screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       The configuration file is created under
       <filename>/etc/snapper/configs/<replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable></filename>,
       where CONFIG is the value you specified with
       <option>-c/--config</option> in the previous step (for example
       <filename>/etc/snapper/configs/web_data</filename>). Adjust it according
       to your needs; see <xref linkend="sec.snapper.config.modify"/> for
       details.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Set values for <envar>ALLOW_USERS</envar> and/or
       <envar>ALLOW_GROUPS</envar> to grant permissions to users and/or groups,
       respectively. Multiple entries need to be separated by
       <keycap function="space"/>. To grant permissions to the user
       <systemitem class="username">www_admin</systemitem> for example, run:
      </para>
<screen>snapper -c web_data set-config "ALLOW_USERS=www_admin" SYNC_ACL="yes"</screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       The given Snapper configuration can now be used by the specified user(s)
       and/or group(s). You can test it with the <literal>list</literal>
       command, for example:
      </para>
<screen>www_admin:~ &gt; snapper -c web_data list</screen>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.snapper.manage">
  <title>Manually Creating and Managing Snapshots</title>

  <para>
   Snapper is not restricted to creating and managing snapshots automatically
   by configuration; you can also create snapshot pairs (<quote>before and
   after</quote>) or single snapshots manually using either the command line
   tool or the &yast; module.
  </para>

  <para>
   All Snapper operations are carried out for an existing configuration (see
   <xref linkend="sec.snapper.config"/> for details). You can only take
   snapshots of partitions or volumes for which a configuration exists. By
   default the system configuration (<literal>root</literal>) is used. If you
   want to create or manage snapshots for your own configuration you need to
   explicitly choose it. Use the <guimenu>Current Configuration</guimenu>
   drop-down box in &yast; or specify the <option>-c</option> on the command
   line (<command>snapper -c <replaceable>MYCONFIG</replaceable>
   <replaceable>COMMAND</replaceable></command>).
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.snapper.manage.metadata">
   <title>Snapshot Metadata</title>
   <para>
    Each snapshot consists of the snapshot itself and some metadata. When
    creating a snapshot you also need to specify the metadata. Modifying a
    snapshot means changing its metadata&mdash;you cannot modify its content.
    Use <command>snapper list</command> to show existing snapshots and their
    metadata:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper --config home list</command>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Lists snapshots for the configuration <literal>home</literal>. To list
       snapshots for the default configuration (root), use <command>snapper -c
       root list</command> or <command>snapper list</command>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper list -a</command>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Lists snapshots for all existing configurations.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper list -t pre-post</command>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Lists all pre and post snapshot pairs for the default
       (<literal>root</literal>) configuration.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper list -t single</command>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Lists all snapshots of the type <literal>single</literal> for the
       default (<literal>root</literal>) configuration.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    The following metadata is available for each snapshot:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Type</emphasis>: Snapshot type, see
      <xref linkend="sec.snapper.manage.metadata.type"/> for details. This data
      cannot be changed.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Number</emphasis>: Unique number of the snapshot.
      This data cannot be changed.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Pre Number</emphasis>: Specifies the number of the
      corresponding pre snapshot. For snapshots of type post only. This data
      cannot be changed.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: A description of the
      snapshot.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Userdata</emphasis>: An extended description where
      you can specify custom data in the form of a comma-separated key=value
      list: <literal>reason=testing, project=foo</literal>. This field is also
      used to mark a snapshot as important (<literal>important=yes</literal>)
      and to list the user that created the snapshot
      (user=&exampleuser_plain;).
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Cleanup-Algorithm</emphasis>: Cleanup-algorithm for
      the snapshot, see <xref linkend="sec.snapper.clean-up"/> for details.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.snapper.manage.metadata.type">
    <title>Snapshot Types</title>
    <para>
     Snapper knows three different types of snapshots: pre, post, and single.
     Physically they do not differ, but Snapper handles them differently.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>pre</literal>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Snapshot of a file system <emphasis>before</emphasis> a modification.
        Each <literal>pre</literal> snapshot has got a corresponding
        <literal>post</literal> snapshot. Used for the automatic &yast;/Zypper
        snapshots, for example.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>post</literal>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Snapshot of a file system <emphasis>after</emphasis> a modification.
        Each <literal>post</literal> snapshot has got a corresponding
        <literal>pre</literal> snapshot. Used for the automatic &yast;/Zypper
        snapshots, for example.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>single</literal>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Stand-alone snapshot. Used for the automatic hourly snapshots, for
        example. This is the default type when creating snapshots.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec.snapper.manage.metadata.cleanup">
    <title>Cleanup-algorithms</title>
    <para>
     Snapper provides three algorithms to clean up old snapshots. The
     algorithms are executed in a daily cron-job. It is possible to define the
     number of different types of snapshots to keep in the Snapper
     configuration (see <xref linkend="sec.snapper.config.modify"/> for
     details).
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>number</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Deletes old snapshots when a certain snapshot count is reached.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>timeline</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Deletes old snapshots having passed a certain age, but keeps several
        hourly, daily, monthly, and yearly snapshots.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>empty-pre-post</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Deletes pre/post snapshot pairs with empty diffs.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.snapper.manage.create">
   <title>Creating Snapshots</title>
   <para>
    Creating a snapshot is done by running <command>snapper create</command> or
    by clicking <guimenu>Create</guimenu> in the &yast; module
    <guimenu>Snapper</guimenu>. The following examples explain how to create
    snapshots from the command line. It should be easy to adopt them when using
    the &yast; interface.
   </para>
   <tip>
    <title>Snapshot Description</title>
    <para>
     You should always specify a meaningful description to later be able to
     identify its purpose. Even more information can be specified via the user
     data option.
    </para>
   </tip>
   <para/>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper create --description "Snapshot for week 2
      2014"</command>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Creates a stand-alone snapshot (type single) for the default
       (<literal>root</literal>) configuration with a description. Because no
       cleanup-algorithm is specified, the snapshot will never be deleted
       automatically.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper --config home create --description "Cleanup in
     ~&exampleuser_plain;"</command>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Creates a stand-alone snapshot (type single) for a custom configuration
       named <literal>home</literal> with a description. Because no
       cleanup-algorithm is specified, the snapshot will never be deleted
       automatically.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper --config home create --description "Daily data
     backup" --cleanup-algorithm timeline</command>>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Creates a stand-alone snapshot (type single) for a custom configuration
       named <literal>home</literal> with a description. The file will
       automatically be deleted when it meets the criteria specified for the
       timeline cleanup-algorithm in the configuration.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper create --type pre --print-number --description
     "Before the Apache config cleanup" --userdata "important=yes"</command>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Creates a snapshot of the type <literal>pre</literal> and prints the
       snapshot number. First command needed to create a pair of snapshots used
       to save a <quote>before</quote> and <quote>after</quote> state. The
       snapshot is marked as important.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper create --type post --pre-number 30 --description
     "After the Apache config cleanup" --userdata "important=yes"</command>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Creates a snapshot of the type <literal>post</literal> paired with the
       <literal>pre</literal> snapshot number <literal>30</literal>. Second
       command needed to create a pair of snapshots used to save a
       <quote>before</quote> and <quote>after</quote> state. The snapshot is
       marked as important.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper create --command <replaceable>COMMAND</replaceable>
     --description "Before and after COMMAND"</command>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Automatically creates a snapshot pair before and after running
       <replaceable>COMMAND</replaceable>. This option is only available when
       using snapper on the command line.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.snapper.manage.modify">
   <title>Modifying Snapshot Metadata</title>
   <para>
    Snapper allows you to modify the description, the cleanup algorithm, and
    the user data of a snapshot. All other metadata cannot be changed. The
    following examples explain how to modify snapshots from the command line.
    It should be easy to adopt them when using the &yast; interface.
   </para>
   <para>
    To modify a snapshot on the command line, you need to know its number. Use
    <command>snapper list</command> to display all snapshots
    and their numbers.
   </para>
   <para>
    The &yast; <guimenu>Snapper</guimenu> module already lists all snapshots.
    Choose one from the list and click <guimenu>Modify</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper modify --cleanup-algorithm "timeline"</command>
      10
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Modifies the metadata of snapshot 10 for the default
       (<literal>root</literal>) configuration. The cleanup algorithm is set to
       <literal>timeline</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper --config home modify --description "daily backup"
     -cleanup-algorithm "timeline" 120</command>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Modifies the metadata of snapshot 120 for a custom configuration named
       <literal>home</literal>. A new description is set and the cleanup
       algorithm is unset.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.snapper.manage.delete">
   <title>Deleting Snapshots</title>
   <para>
    To delete a snapshot with the &yast; <guimenu>Snapper</guimenu> module,
    choose a snapshot from the list and click <guimenu>Delete</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    To delete a snapshot with the command line tool, you need to know its
    number. Get it by running <command>snapper list</command>. To delete a
    snapshot, run <command>snapper delete</command>
    <replaceable>NUMBER</replaceable>.
   </para>
   <para>
    When deleting snapshots with Snapper, the freed space will be claimed by a
    Btrfs process running in the background. Thus the visibility and the
    availability of free space is delayed. In case you need space freed by
    deleting a snapshot to be available immediately, use the option
    <option>--sync</option> with the delete command.
   </para>
   <tip>
    <title>Deleting Snapshot Pairs</title>
    <para>
     When deleting a <literal>pre</literal> snapshot, you should always delete
     its corresponding <literal>post</literal> snapshot (and vice versa).
    </para>
   </tip>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper delete 65</command>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Deletes snapshot 65 for the default (<literal>root</literal>)
       configuration.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper -c home delete 89 90</command>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Deletes snapshots 89 and 90 for a custom configuration named
       <literal>home</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper delete --sync 23</command></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Deletes snapshot 23 for the default (<literal>root</literal>)
       configuration and makes the freed space available immediately.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <tip>
    <title>Delete Unreferenced Snapshots</title>
    <para>
     Sometimes the Btrfs snapshot is present but the XML file containing the
     metadata for Snapper is missing. In this case the snapshot is not visible
     for Snapper and needs to be deleted manually:
    </para>
<screen>btrfs subvolume delete /.snapshots/<replaceable>SNAPSHOTNUMBER</replaceable>/snapshot
rm -rf /.snapshots/SNAPSHOTNUMBER</screen>
   </tip>
   <tip>
    <title>Old Snapshots Occupy More Disk Space</title>
    <para>
     If you delete snapshots to free space on your hard disk, make sure to
     delete old snapshots first. The older a snapshot is, the more disk space
     it occupies.
    </para>
   </tip>
   <para>
    Snapshots are also automatically deleted by a daily cron-job. Refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.snapper.manage.metadata.cleanup"/> for details.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.snapper.clean-up">
  <title>Automatic Snapshot Clean-Up</title>

  <para>
   Snapshots occupy disk space and over time the amount of disk space occupied
   by the snapshots may become large. To prevent disks from running out of
   space, Snapper offers algorithms to automatically delete old snapshots.
   These algorithms differentiate between timeline snapshots and numbered
   snapshots (administration plus installation snapshot pairs). You can specify
   the number of snapshots to keep for each type.
  </para>

  <para>
   In addition to that, you can optionally specify a disk space quota, defining
   the maximum amount of disk space the snapshots may occupy. It is also
   possible to automatically delete pre and post snapshots pairs that do not
   differ.
  </para>

  <para>
   A clean-up algorithm is always bound to a single Snapper configuration, so
   you need to configure algorithms for each configuration. In case you want to
   prevent certain snapshots from being automatically deleted, refer to
   <xref linkend="faq.snapper.permanent"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   The default setup (<literal>root</literal>) is configured to do clean-up
   for numbered snapshots and empty pre and post snapshot pairs. Quota support
   is enabled&mdash;snapshots may not occupy more than 50% of the available
   disk space of the root partition. Timeline snapshots are disabled by
   default, therefore the timeline clean-up algorithm is also disabled.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.snapper.clean-up.number">
   <title>Cleaning Up Numbered Snapshots</title>
   <para>
    Cleaning up for numbered snapshots&mdash;administration plus installation
    snapshot pairs&mdash;is controlled by the following parameters of a Snapper
    configuration.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>NUMBER_CLEANUP</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Enables or disables clean-up of installation and admin snapshot pairs.
       If enabled, snapshot pairs are deleted when the total snapshot count
       exceeds a number specified with <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT</literal> and/or
       <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT</literal> <emphasis>and</emphasis> an
       age specified with <literal>NUMBER_MIN_AGE</literal>. Valid values:
       <literal>yes</literal> (enable), <literal>no</literal> (disable).
      </para>
      <para>
       The default value is <literal>"yes"</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
       Example command to change or set:
      </para>
<screen>snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> set-config "NUMBER_CLEANUP=no"</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>NUMBER_LIMIT</literal> /
      <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Defines how many regular and/or important installation and
       administration snapshot pairs to keep. Only the youngest snapshots will
       be kept. Ignored if <literal>NUMBER_CLEANUP</literal> is set to
       <literal>"no"</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
       The default value is <literal>"2-10"</literal> for
       <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT</literal> and <literal>"4-10"</literal> for
       <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
       Example command to change or set:
      </para>
<screen>snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> set-config "NUMBER_LIMIT=10"</screen>
      <important>
       <title>Ranged Compared to Constant Values</title>
       <para>
        In case quota support is enabled (see
        <xref
        linkend="sec.snapper.clean-up.quota"/>) the limit needs
        to be specified as a minimum-maximum range, for example
        <literal>2-10</literal>. If quota support is disabled, a constant
        value, for example <literal>10</literal>, needs to be provided,
        otherwise cleaning-up will fail with an error.
       </para>
      </important>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>NUMBER_MIN_AGE</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Defines the minimum age in seconds a snapshot must have before it can
       automatically be deleted. Snapshots younger than the value specified
       here will not be deleted, regardless of how many exist.
      </para>
      <para>
       The default value is <literal>"1800"</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
       Example command to change or set:
      </para>
<screen>snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> set-config "NUMBER_MIN_AGE=864000"</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <note>
    <title>Limit and Age</title>
    <para>
     <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT</literal>, <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT</literal>
     and <literal>NUMBER_MIN_AGE</literal> are always evaluated. Snapshots are
     only deleted when <emphasis>all</emphasis> conditions are met.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you always want to keep the number of snapshots defined with
     <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT*</literal> regardless of their age, set
     <literal>NUMBER_MIN_AGE</literal> to <literal>0</literal>.
    </para>
    <example>
     <title>Keep the Last 10 Important and Regular Snapshots Regardless of Age</title>
<screen>NUMBER_CLEANUP=yes
NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT=10
NUMBER_LIMIT=10
NUMBER_MIN_AGE=0</screen>
    </example>
    <para>
     On the other hand, if you do not want to keep snapshots beyond a certain
     age, set <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT*</literal> to <literal>0</literal> and
     provide the age with <literal>NUMBER_MIN_AGE</literal>.
    </para>
    <example>
     <title>Only Keep Snapshots Younger Than Ten Days</title>
<screen>NUMBER_CLEANUP=yes
NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT=0
NUMBER_LIMIT=0
NUMBER_MIN_AGE=864000</screen>
    </example>
   </note>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.snapper.clean-up.timeline">
   <title>Cleaning Up Timeline Screenshots</title>
   <para>
    Cleaning up for timeline snapshots is controlled by the following
    parameters of a Snapper configuration.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>TIMELINE_CLEANUP</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Enables or disables clean-up of timeline snapshots. If enabled,
       snapshots are deleted when the total snapshot count exceeds a number
       specified with <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_*</literal>
       <emphasis>and</emphasis> an age specified with
       <literal>TIMELINE_MIN_AGE</literal>. Valid values:
       <literal>yes</literal>, <literal>no</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
       The default value is <literal>"yes"</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
       Example command to change or set:
      </para>
<screen>snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> set-config "TIMELINE_CLEANUP=yes"</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_DAILY</literal>,
      <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_HOURLY</literal>,
      <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_MONTHLY</literal>,
      <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_WEEKLY</literal>,
      <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_YEARLY</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Number of snapshots to keep for hour, day, month, week, and year.
      </para>
      <para>
       The default value for each entry is <literal>"10"</literal>, except for
       <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_WEEKLY</literal>, which is set to
       <literal>"0"</literal> by default.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>TIMELINE_MIN_AGE</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Defines the minimum age in seconds a snapshot must have before it can
       automatically be deleted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The default value is <literal>"1800"</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <example xml:id="ex.snapper.config.timeline">
    <title>Example timeline configuration</title>
<screen>TIMELINE_CLEANUP="yes"
TIMELINE_CREATE="yes"
TIMELINE_LIMIT_DAILY="7"
TIMELINE_LIMIT_HOURLY="24"
TIMELINE_LIMIT_MONTHLY="12"
TIMELINE_LIMIT_WEEKLY="4"
TIMELINE_LIMIT_YEARLY="2"
TIMELINE_MIN_AGE="1800"</screen>
    <para>
     This example configuration enables hourly snapshots which are
     automatically cleaned up. <literal>TIMELINE_MIN_AGE</literal> and
     <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_*</literal> are always both evaluated. In this
     example, the minimum age of a snapshot before it can be deleted is set to
     30 minutes (1800 seconds). Since we create hourly snapshots, this ensures
     that only the latest snapshots are kept. If
     <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_DAILY</literal> is set to not zero, this means
     that the first snapshot of the day is kept, too.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
     <title>Snapshots to be Kept</title>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Hourly: The last 24 snapshots that have been made.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Daily: The first daily snapshot that has been made is kept from the last
       seven days.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Monthly: The first snapshot made on the last day of the month is kept
       for the last twelve months.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Weekly: The first snapshot made on the last day of the week is kept from
       the last four weeks.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Yearly: The first snapshot made on the last day of the year is kept for
       the last two years.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </example>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.snapper.clean-up.empty">
   <title>Cleaning Up Snapshot Pairs That Do Not Differ</title>
   <para>
    As explained in <xref linkend="snapper.snapshot-type"/>, whenever you run a
    &yast; module or execute Zypper, a pre snapshot is created on start-up and
    a post snapshot is created when exiting. In case you have not made any
    changes there will be no difference between the pre and post snapshots.
    Such <quote>empty</quote> snapshot pairs can be automatically be deleted by
    setting the following parameters in a Snapper configuration:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>EMPTY_PRE_POST_CLEANUP</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If set to <literal>yes</literal>, pre and post snapshot pairs that do
       not differ will be deleted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The default value is <literal>"yes"</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>EMPTY_PRE_POST_MIN_AGE</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Defines the minimum age in seconds a pre and post snapshot pair that
       does not differ must have before it can automatically be deleted.
      </para>
      <para>
       The default value is <literal>"1800"</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.snapper.clean-up.manual">
   <title>Cleaning Up Manually Created Snapshots</title>
   <para>
    Snapper does not offer custom clean-up algorithms for manually created
    snapshots. However, you can assign the number or timeline clean-up
    algorithm to a manually created snapshot. If you do so, the snapshot will
    join the <quote>clean-up queue</quote> for the algorithm you specified.
    You can specify a clean-up algorithm when creating a snapshot, or by
    modifying an existing snapshot:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper create --description "Test" --cleanup-algorithm number</command>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Creates a stand-alone snapshot (type single) for the default (root)
       configuration and assigns the <literal>number</literal> clean-up
       algorithm.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><command>snapper modify --cleanup-algorithm "timeline" 25</command>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Modifies the snapshot with the number 25 and assigns the clean-up
       algorithm <literal>timeline</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.snapper.clean-up.quota">
   <title>Adding Disk Quota Support</title>
   <para>
    In addition to the number and/or timeline clean-up algorithms described
    above, Snapper supports quotas. You can define what percentage of the
    available space snapshots are allowed to occupy. This percentage value
    always applies to the Btrfs subvolume defined in the respective Snapper
    configuration.
   </para>
   <para>
    If Snapper was enabled during the installation, quota support is
    automatically enabled. In case you manually enable Snapper at a later point
    in time, you can enable quota support by running <command>snapper
    setup-quota</command>. This requires a valid configuration (see
    <xref
    linkend="sec.snapper.config"/> for more information).
   </para>
   <para>
    Quota support is controlled by the following parameters of a Snapper
    configuration.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>QGROUP</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The Btrfs quota group used by Snapper. If not set, run <command>snapper
       setup-quota</command>. If already set, only change if you are familiar
       with <command>man 8 btrfs-qgroup</command>. This value is set with
       <command>snapper setup-quota</command> and should not be changed.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>SPACE_LIMIT</literal>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Limit of space snapshots are allowed to use in fractions of 1 (100%).
       Valid values range from 0 to 1 (0.1 = 10%, 0.2 = 20%, ...).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    The following limitations and guidelines apply:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Quotas are only activated in <emphasis>addition</emphasis> to an existing
      number and/or timeline clean-up algorithm. If no clean-up algorithm is
      active, quota restrictions are not applied.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      With quota support enabled, Snapper will perform two clean-up runs if
      required. The first run will apply the rules specified for number and
      timeline snapshots. Only if the quota is exceeded after this run, the
      quota-specific rules will be applied in a second run.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Even if quota support is enabled, Snapper will always keep the number of
      snapshots specified with the <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT*</literal> and
      <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT*</literal> values, even if the quota will be
      exceeded. It is therefore recommended to specify ranged values
      (<literal><replaceable>min</replaceable>-<replaceable>max</replaceable></literal>)
      for <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT*</literal> and
      <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT*</literal> to ensure the quota can be applied.
     </para>
     <para>
      If, for example, <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT=5-20</literal> is set, Snapper
      will perform a first clean up run and reduce the number of regular
      numbered snapshots to 20. In case these 20 snapshots exceed the
      quota, Snapper will delete the oldest ones in a second run until the
      quota is met. A minimum of five snapshots will always be kept, regardless
      of the amount of space they occupy.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.snapper.faqs">
  <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>

  <qandaset defaultlabel="qanda">
   <qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
      Why does Snapper Never Show Changes in <filename>/var/log</filename>,
      <filename>/tmp</filename> and Other Directories?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
      For some directories we decided to exclude them from snapshots. See
      <xref linkend="snapper.dir-excludes"/> for a list and reasons. To exclude
      a path from snapshots we create a subvolume for that path.
     </para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry>
   <qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
      How much disk space is used by snapshots? How to free disk space?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
      Displaying the amount of disk space a snapshot allocates is currently not
      supported by the <literal>Btrfs</literal> tools. However, if you have
      quota enabled, it is possible to determine how much space would be freed
      if <emphasis>all</emphasis> snapshots would be deleted:
     </para>
     <procedure>
      <step>
       <para>
        Get the quota group ID (<literal>1/0</literal> in the following
        example):
       </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;snapper -c root get-config | grep QGROUP
QGROUP                 | 1/0</screen>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Rescan the subvolume quotas:
       </para>
<screen>btrfs quota rescan -w /</screen>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Show the data of the quota group (<literal>1/0</literal> in the
        following example):
       </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;btrfs qgroup show / | grep "1/0"
1/0           4.80GiB    108.82MiB</screen>
       <para>
        The third column shows the amount of space that would be freed when
        deleting all snapshots (<literal>108.82MiB</literal>).
       </para>
      </step>
     </procedure>
     <para>
      To free space on a <literal>Btrfs</literal> partition containing
      snapshots you need to delete unneeded snapshots rather than files. Older
      snapshots occupy more space than recent ones. See
      <xref linkend="sec.snapper.setup.customize.archiving"/> for details.
     </para>
     <para>
      Doing an upgrade from one service pack to another results in snapshots
      occupying a lot of disk space on the system subvolumes, because a lot of
      data gets changed (package updates). Manually deleting these snapshots
      after they are no longer needed is recommended. See
      <xref linkend="sec.snapper.manage.delete"/> for details.
     </para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry>
   <qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
      Can I Boot a Snapshot from the Boot Loader?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
      Yes&mdash;refer to <xref linkend="sec.snapper.snapshot-boot"/> for
      details.
     </para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry>
   <qandaentry xml:id="faq.snapper.permanent">
    <question>
     <para>
      How to make a snapshot permanent?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
      Currently Snapper does not offer means to prevent a snapshot from being
      deleted manually. However, you can prevent snapshots from being
      automatically deleted by clean-up algorithms. Manually created snapshots
      (see <xref linkend="sec.snapper.manage.create"/>) have no clean-up
      algorithm assigned unless you specify one with
      <option>--cleanup-algorithm</option>. Automatically created snapshots
      always either have the <literal>number</literal> or
      <literal>timeline</literal> algorithm assigned. To remove such an
      assignment from one or more snapshots, proceed as follows:
     </para>
     <procedure>
      <step>
       <para>
        List all available snapshots:
       </para>
<screen>snapper list -a</screen>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Memorize the number of the snapshot(s) you want to prevent from being
        deleted.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Run the following command and replace the number placeholders with the
        number(s) you memorized:
       </para>
<screen>snapper modify --cleanup-algorithm "" <replaceable>#1</replaceable> <replaceable>#2</replaceable> <replaceable>#n</replaceable></screen>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Check the result by running <command>snapper list -a</command> again.
        The entry in the column <literal>Cleanup</literal> should now be empty
        for the snapshots you modified.
       </para>
      </step>
     </procedure>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry>
   <qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
      Where can I get more information on Snapper?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
      See the Snapper home page at <link xlink:href="http://snapper.io/"/>.
     </para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry>
  </qandaset>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
