<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="nfsv4acls" lang="en">
  <title>Managing Access Control Lists over NFSv4</title>
  <para>
   There is no single standard for Access Control Lists (ACLs) in Linux
   beyond the simple user-group-others read, write, and execute
   (<literal>rwx</literal>) flags. One option for finer control are the
   <citetitle>Draft POSIX ACLs</citetitle>, which were never formally
   standardised by POSIX. Another is the NFSv4 ACLs, which were designed to
   be part of the NFSv4 network file system with the goal of making
   something that provided reasonable compatibility between POSIX systems on
   Linux and WIN32 systems on Microsoft Windows.
  </para>
  <para>
   NFSv4 ACLs are not sufficient to correctly implement Draft POSIX ACLs so
   no attempt has been made to map ACL accesses on an NFSv4 client (such as
   using <command>setfacl</command>).
  </para>
  <para>
   When using NFSv4, Draft POSIX ACLs cannot be used even in emulation and
   NFSv4 ACLs need to be used directly; i.e., while
   <command>setfacl</command> can work on NFSv3, it cannot work on NFSv4.+To
   allow NFSv4 ACLs to be used on an NFSv4 file system, SUSE Linux
   Enterprise Server provides the <filename>nfs4-acl-tools</filename>
   package which contains the following:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <filename>nfs4-getfacl</filename>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <filename>nfs4-setfacl</filename>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <filename>nfs4-editacl</filename>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   These operate in a generally similar way to <command>getfacl</command>
   and <command>setfacl</command> for examining and modifying NFSv4
   ACLs.These commands are effective only if the file system on the NFS
   server provides full support for NFSv4 ACLs. Any limitation imposed by
   the server will affect programs running on the client in that some
   particular combinations of Access Control Entries (ACEs) might not be
   possible.
  </para>
  <para>
   It is not supported to mount NFS volumes locally on the exporting NFS
   server.
  </para>
  <bridgehead id="bxut1i2">Additional Information</bridgehead>
  <para>
   For information, see
   <ulink url="http://wiki.linux-nfs.org/wiki/index.php/ACLs#Introduction_to_NFSv4_ACLs"><quote>Introduction
   to NFSv4 ACLs</quote> on the Linux-nfs.org Web site</ulink>.
  </para>
 </chapter>
