<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.fcoe" xml:lang="en">
 <title>Fibre Channel Storage over Ethernet Networks: FCoE</title>
 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
          </dm:bugtracker>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <para>
  Many enterprise data centers rely on Ethernet for their LAN and data
  traffic, and on Fibre Channel networks for their storage infrastructure.
  Open Fibre Channel over Ethernet (FCoE) Initiator software allows servers
  with Ethernet adapters to connect to a Fibre Channel storage subsystem
  over an Ethernet network. This connectivity was previously reserved
  exclusively for systems with Fibre Channel adapters over a Fibre Channel
  fabric. The FCoE technology reduces complexity in the data center by
  aiding network convergence. This helps to preserve your existing
  investments in a Fibre Channel storage infrastructure and to simplify
  network management.
 </para>
 <figure>
  <title>Open Fibre Channel over Ethernet SAN</title>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="fcoe_san_a.svg" width="80%" format="SVG"/>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="fcoe_san_a.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>
 <para>
  Open-FCoE allows you to run the Fibre Channel protocols on the host,
  instead of on proprietary hardware on the host bus adapter. It is targeted
  for 10 Gbps (gigabit per second) Ethernet adapters, but can work on any
  Ethernet adapter that supports pause frames. The initiator software
  provides a Fibre Channel protocol processing module as well as an
  Ethernet-based transport module. The Open-FCoE module acts as a low-level
  driver for SCSI. The Open-FCoE transport uses
  <command>net_device</command> to send and receive packets. Data Center
  Bridging (DCB) drivers provide the quality of service for FCoE.
 </para>
 <para>
  FCoE is an encapsulation protocol that moves the Fibre Channel protocol
  traffic over Ethernet connections without changing the Fibre Channel
  frame. This allows your network security and traffic management
  infrastructure to work the same with FCoE as it does with Fibre Channel.
 </para>
 <para>
  You might choose to deploy FCoE in your enterprise if the following
  conditions exist:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Your enterprise already has a Fibre Channel storage subsystem and
    administrators with Fibre Channel skills and knowledge.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You are deploying 10 Gbps Ethernet in the network.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  This section describes how to set up FCoE in your network.
 </para>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.fcoe.installation">
  <title>Configuring FCoE Interfaces during the Installation</title>

  <para>
   The &yast; installation for &productname; allows you to configure
   FCoE disks during the operating system installation if FCoE is enabled at
   the switch for the connections between the server and the Fibre Channel
   storage infrastructure. Some system BIOS types can automatically detect
   the FCoE disks, and report the disks to the &yast; Installation
   software. However, automatic detection of FCoE disks is not supported by
   all BIOS types. To enable automatic detection in this case, you can add
   the <command>withfcoe</command> option to the kernel command line when
   you begin the installation:
  </para>

<screen>withfcoe=1</screen>

  <para>
   When the FCoE disks are detected, the &yast; installation offers the
   option to configure FCoE instances at that time. On the Disk Activation
   page, select <guimenu>Configure FCoE Interfaces</guimenu> to access the
   FCoE configuration. For information about configuring the FCoE
   interfaces, see
   <xref linkend="sec.fcoe.yast" xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage"/>.
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="fcoe_inst_disk_activation_a.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="fcoe_inst_disk_activation_a.png" width="10%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.fcoe.install">
  <title>Installing FCoE and the &yast; FCoE Client</title>

  <para>
   You can set up FCoE disks in your storage infrastructure by enabling FCoE
   at the switch for the connections to a server. If FCoE disks are
   available when the &productname; operating system is installed, the
   FCoE Initiator software is automatically installed at that time.
  </para>

  <para>
   If the FCoE Initiator software and the &yast; FCoE Client software are
   not installed, use the following procedure to manually install them with
   the following command:
  </para>

<screen>sudo zypper in yast2-fcoe-client fcoe-utils</screen>

  <para>
   Alternatively, use the &yast; Software Manager to install the packages
   listed above.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.fcoe.yast">
  <title>Managing FCoE Services with &yast;</title>

  <para>
   You can use the &yast; FCoE Client Configuration option to create,
   configure, and remove FCoE interfaces for the FCoE disks in your Fibre
   Channel storage infrastructure. To use this option, the FCoE Initiator
   service (the <systemitem class="daemon">fcoemon</systemitem> daemon) and
   the Link Layer Discovery Protocol agent daemon
   (<systemitem class="daemon">llpad</systemitem>) must be installed and
   running, and the FCoE connections must be enabled at the FCoE-capable
   switch.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Launch &yast; and select <menuchoice><guimenu>Network
     Services</guimenu><guimenu>FCoE Client
     Configuration</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="fcoe_services_a.png" width="201pt" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="fcoe_services_a.png" width="201pt" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Services</guimenu> tab, view or modify the FCoE service
     and Lldpad (Link Layer Discovery Protocol agent daemon) service start
     time as necessary.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
     <listitem>
      <formalpara>
       <title>FCoE Service Start:</title>
       <para>
        Specifies whether to start the Fibre Channel over Ethernet service
        <command>fcoemon</command> daemon at the server boot time or
        manually. The daemon controls the FCoE interfaces and establishes a
        connection with the <systemitem class="daemon">llpad</systemitem>
        daemon. The values are <guimenu>When Booting</guimenu> (default) or
        <guimenu>Manually</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Lldpad Service Start:</title>
       <para>
        Specifies whether to start the Link Layer Discovery Protocol agent
        <systemitem class="daemon">llpad</systemitem> daemon at the server
        boot time or manually. The
        <systemitem class="daemon">llpad</systemitem> daemon informs the
        <command>fcoemon</command> daemon about the Data Center Bridging
        features and the configuration of the FCoE interfaces. The values
        are <guimenu>When Booting</guimenu> (default) or
        <guimenu>Manually</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     If you modify a setting, click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to save and apply
     the change.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Interfaces</guimenu> tab, view information about all of
     the detected network adapters on the server, including information
     about VLAN and FCoE configuration. You can also create an FCoE VLAN
     interface, change settings for an existing FCoE interface, or remove an
     FCoE interface.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="fcoe_notconfig_interface_a.png" width="201pt" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="fcoe_notconfig_interface_a.png" width="201pt" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
     Use the <guimenu>FCoE VLAN Interface</guimenu> column to determine
     whether FCoE is available or not:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><replaceable>Interface Name</replaceable>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If a name is assigned to the interface, such as
        <filename>eth4.200</filename>, FCoE is available on the switch, and
        the FCoE interface is activated for the adapter.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Not Configured:</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If the status is <guimenu>not configured</guimenu>, FCoE is enabled
        on the switch, but an FCoE interface has not been activated for the
        adapter. Select the adapter, then click <guimenu>Create FCoE VLAN
        Interface</guimenu> to activate the interface on the adapter.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Not Available:</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If the status is <guimenu>not available</guimenu>, FCoE is not
        possible for the adapter because FCoE has not been enabled for that
        connection on the switch.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To set up an FCoE-enabled adapter that has not yet been configured,
     select it and click <guimenu>Create FCoE VLAN Interface</guimenu>.
     Confirm the query with <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The adapter is now listed with an interface name in the <guimenu>FCoE
     VLAN Interface</guimenu> column.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To change the settings for an adapter that is already configured,
     select it from the list, then click <guimenu>Change Settings</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The following options can be configured:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>FCoE Enable</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Enable or disable the creation of FCoE instances for the adapter.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>DCB Required</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Specifies whether Data Center Bridging is required for the adapter
        (usually this is the case).
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term><guimenu>Auto VLAN</guimenu>
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Specifies whether the
        <systemitem class="daemon">fcoemon</systemitem> daemon creates the
        VLAN interfaces automatically.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
     If you modify a setting, click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to save and
     apply the change. The settings are written to the
     <filename>/etc/fcoe/eth<replaceable>X</replaceable></filename> file.
     The <systemitem class="daemon">fcoemon</systemitem> daemon reads the
     configuration files for each FCoE interface when it is initialized.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To remove an interface that is already configured, select it from the
     list. Click <guimenu>Remove Interface</guimenu> and
     <guimenu>Continue</guimenu> to confirm. The FCoE Interface value
     changes to <guimenu>not configured</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Configuration</guimenu> tab, view or modify the general
     settings for the FCoE system service. You can enable or disable
     debugging messages from the FCoE service script and the
     <systemitem class="daemon">fcoemon</systemitem> daemon and specify
     whether messages are sent to the system log.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="fcoe_configtab_a.png" width="201pt" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="fcoe_configtab_a.png" width="201pt" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to save and apply changes.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.fcoe.cli">
  <title>Configuring FCoE with Commands</title>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open a terminal console.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Use &yast; to configure the Ethernet network interface card, such as
     <filename>eth2</filename>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the Link Layer Discovery Protocol agent daemon
     (<systemitem class="daemon">llpad</systemitem>).
    </para>
<screen>sudo systemctl start lldpad,service</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para role="intro">
     Enable Data Center Bridging on your Ethernet adapter.
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;dcbtool sc eth2 dcb on
  Version:       2
  Command:       Set Config
  Feature:       DCB State
  Port:          eth2
  Status:        Successful</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enable and set the Priority Flow Control (PFC) settings for Data Center
     Bridging.
    </para>
<screen>sudo dcbtool sc eth&lt;x&gt; pfc e:1 a:1 w:1</screen>
    <para>
     Argument setting values are:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry xml:id="bynkj1s">
      <term>e:&lt;0|1&gt;</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Controls feature enablement.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry xml:id="bynkjej">
      <term>a:&lt;0|1&gt;</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Controls whether the feature is advertised via Data Center Bridging
        Exchange protocol to the peer.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry xml:id="bynkjy8">
      <term>w:&lt;0|1&gt;</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Controls whether the feature is willing to change its operational
        configuration based on what is received from the peer.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enable the Data Center Bridging to accept the switch’s priority
     setting for FCoE.
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;sudo dcbtool sc eth2 app:fcoe e:1
  Version:       2
  Command:       Set Config
  Feature:       Application FCoE
  Port:          eth2
  Status:        Successful</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Copy the default FCoE configuration file to
     <filename>/etc/fcoe/cfg-eth2</filename>.
    </para>
<screen>sudo cp /etc/fcoe/cfg-ethx /etc/fcoe/cfg-eth2</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the FCoE Initiator service.
    </para>
<screen>systemctl start fcoe.status</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Set up the Link Layer Discovery Protocol agent daemon
     (<systemitem class="daemon">llpad</systemitem>) and the FCoE Initiator
     service to start when booting.
    </para>
<screen>systemctl enable llpad.service fcoe.service</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.fcoe.admin">
  <title>Managing FCoE Instances with the FCoE Administration Tool</title>

  <para>
   The <command>fcoeadm</command> utility is the Fibre Channel over Ethernet
   (FCoE) management tool. It can be used to create, destroy, and reset an
   FCoE instance on a given network interface. The
   <command>fcoeadm</command> utility sends commands to a running
   <systemitem class="daemon">fcoemon</systemitem> process via a socket
   interface. For information about <command>fcoemon</command>, see the
   <command>man 8 fcoemon</command>.
  </para>

  <para>
   The <command>fcoeadm</command> utility allows you to query the FCoE
   instances about the following:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Interfaces
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Target LUNs
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Port statistics
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   The <command>fcoeadm</command> utility is part of the
   <filename>fcoe-utils</filename> package. The general syntax for the
   command looks like the following:
  </para>

<screen>fcoeadm
  [-c|--create] [&lt;ethX&gt;]
  [-d|--destroy] [&lt;ethX&gt;]
  [-r|--reset] [&lt;ethX&gt;]
  [-S|--Scan] [&lt;ethX&gt;]
  [-i|--interface] [&lt;ethX&gt;]
  [-t|--target] [&lt;ethX&gt;]
  [-l|--lun] [&lt;ethX&gt;]
  [-s|--stats &lt;ethX&gt;] [&lt;interval&gt;]
  [-v|--version]
  [-h|--help]
</screen>

  <para>
   Refer to <command>man 8 fcoeadm</command> for details.
  </para>

  <bridgehead>Examples</bridgehead>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>fcoeadm -c eth2.101</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Create an FCoE instance on eth2.101.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>fcoeadm -d eth2.101</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Destroy an FCoE instance on eth2.101.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>fcoeadm -i eth3</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Show information about all of the FCoE instances on interface
      <literal>eth3</literal>. If no interface is specified, information for
      all interfaces that have FCoE instances created will be shown. The
      following example shows information on connection eth0.201:
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;sudo fcoeadm -i eth0.201
  Description:      82599EB 10-Gigabit SFI/SFP+ Network Connection 
  Revision:         01
  Manufacturer:     Intel Corporation 
  Serial Number:    001B219B258C 
  Driver:           ixgbe 3.3.8-k2 
  Number of Ports:  1      

      Symbolic Name:     fcoe v0.1 over eth0.201     
      OS Device Name:    host8     
      Node Name:         0x1000001B219B258E     
      Port Name:         0x2000001B219B258E     
      FabricName:        0x2001000573D38141     
      Speed:             10 Gbit     
      Supported Speed:   10 Gbit     
      MaxFrameSize:      2112     
      FC-ID (Port ID):   0x790003     
      State:             Online
</screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>fcoeadm -l eth3.101</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Show detailed information about all of the LUNs discovered on
      connection eth3.101. If no connection is specified, information about
      all of the LUNs discovered on all FCoE connections will be shown.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>fcoeadm -r eth2.101</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Reset the FCoE instance on eth2.101.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>fcoeadm -s eth3 3</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Show statistical information about a specific eth3 port that has FCoE
      instances, at an interval of three seconds. The statistics are
      displayed one line per time interval. If no interval is given, the
      default of one second is used.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>fcoeadm -t eth3</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Show information about all of the discovered targets from a given eth3
      port having FCoE instances. After each discovered target, any
      associated LUNs are listed. If no instance is specified, targets from
      all of the ports that have FCoE instances are shown. The following
      example shows information of targets from the eth0.201 connection:
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;sudo fcoeadm -t eth0.201  
  Interface:        eth0.201 
  Roles:            FCP Target 
  Node Name:        0x200000D0231B5C72 
  Port Name:        0x210000D0231B5C72 
  Target ID:        0 
  MaxFrameSize:     2048 
  OS Device Name:   rport-8:0-7 
  FC-ID (Port ID):  0x79000C 
  State:            Online  

LUN ID  Device Name   Capacity   Block Size  Description 
------  -----------  ----------  ----------  ----------------------------     
    40  /dev/sdqi     792.84 GB      512     IFT DS S24F-R2840-4 (rev 386C)
    72  /dev/sdpk     650.00 GB      512     IFT DS S24F-R2840-4 (rev 386C)
   168  /dev/sdgy       1.30 TB      512     IFT DS S24F-R2840-4 (rev 386C)
</screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.fcoe.info">
  <title>Additional Information</title>

  <para>
   For information, see the follow documentation:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For information about the Open-FCoE service daemon, see the
     <command>fcoemon(8)</command> man page.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For information about the Open-FCoE Administration tool, see the
     <command>fcoeadm(8)</command> man page.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For information about the Data Center Bridging Configuration tool, see
     the <command>dcbtool(8)</command> man page.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For information about the Link Layer Discovery Protocol agent daemon,
     see the <filename>lldpad(8)</filename> man page.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <citetitle>Open Fibre Channel over Ethernet Quick Start</citetitle>
     <link xlink:href="http://www.open-fcoe.org/open-fcoe/wiki/quickstart"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>