<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.raid_degraded" lang="en">
 <title>Creating a Degraded RAID Array</title>
 <abstract>
 <para>
    A degraded array is one in which some devices are missing. Degraded
    arrays are supported only for RAID 1, RAID 4, RAID 5, and RAID 6. These
    RAID types are designed to withstand some missing devices as part of
    their fault-tolerance features. Typically, degraded arrays occur when a
    device fails. It is possible to create a degraded array on purpose.
   </para>
 </abstract>
 <informaltable>
  <tgroup cols="3">
   <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="33*"/>
   <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="33*"/>
   <colspec colnum="3" colname="3" colwidth="33*"/>
   <thead>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       RAID Type
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Allowable Number of Slots Missing
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry/>
    </row>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       RAID 1
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       All but one device
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry/>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       RAID 4
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       One slot
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry/>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       RAID 5
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       One slot
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry/>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       RAID 6
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       One or two slots
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry/>
    </row>
   </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </informaltable>

 <para>
  To create a degraded array in which some devices are missing, simply
  give the word <literal>missing</literal> in place of a device name. This
  causes <command>mdadm</command> to leave the corresponding slot in the
  array empty.
 </para>

 <para>
  When creating a RAID 5 array, <command>mdadm</command> automatically
  creates a degraded array with an extra spare drive. This is because
  building the spare into a degraded array is generally faster than
  resynchronizing the parity on a non-degraded, but not clean, array. You
  can override this feature with the <literal>--force</literal> option.
 </para>
 
 <para>
  Creating a degraded array might be useful if you want create a RAID, but
  one of the devices you want to use already has data on it. In that case,
  you create a degraded array with other devices, copy data from the
  in-use device to the RAID that is running in degraded mode, add the
  device into the RAID, then wait while the RAID is rebuilt so that the
  data is now across all devices. An example of this process is given in
  the following procedure:
 </para>

 <procedure>
  <step>
   <para>
    Create a degraded RAID 1 device <filename>/dev/md0</filename>, using
    one single drive <filename>/dev/sd1</filename>, enter the following at
    the command prompt:
   </para>
<screen>mdadm --create /dev/md0 -l 1 -n 2 /dev/sda1 missing</screen>
   <para>
    The device should be the same size or larger than the device you plan to
    add to it.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    If the device you want to add to the mirror contains data that you
    want to move to the RAID array, copy it now to the RAID array while it
    is running in degraded mode.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Add the device you copied the data from to the mirror. For example, to add
    <filename>/dev/sdb1</filename> to the RAID, enter the following at the
    command prompt:
   </para>
<screen>mdadm /dev/md0 -a /dev/sdb1</screen>
     <para>
      You can add only one device at a time. You must wait for the kernel to
      build the mirror and bring it fully online before you add another
      mirror.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Monitor the build progress by entering the following at the command
      prompt:
     </para>
<screen>cat /proc/mdstat</screen>
     <para>
      To see the rebuild progress while being refreshed every second, enter
     </para>
<screen>watch -n 1 cat /proc/mdstat </screen>
    </step>
 </procedure>
</chapter>
