<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.nfs4_acls" xml:lang="en">
 <title>Managing Access Control Lists over NFSv4</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  There is no single standard for Access Control Lists (ACLs) in Linux beyond
  the simple read, write, and execute (<literal>rwx</literal>) flags for user,
  group, and others (<literal>ugo</literal>). One option for finer control is
  the <citetitle>Draft POSIX ACLs</citetitle>, which were never formally
  standardized by POSIX. Another is the NFSv4 ACLs, which were designed to be
  part of the NFSv4 network file system with the goal of making something that
  provided reasonable compatibility between POSIX systems on Linux and WIN32
  systems on Microsoft Windows.
 </para>
 <para>
  NFSv4 ACLs are not sufficient to correctly implement Draft POSIX ACLs so no
  attempt has been made to map ACL accesses on an NFSv4 client (such as using
  <command>setfacl</command>).
 </para>
 <para>
  When using NFSv4, Draft POSIX ACLs cannot be used even in emulation and NFSv4
  ACLs need to be used directly; that means while <command>setfacl</command>
  can work on NFSv3, it cannot work on NFSv4. To allow NFSv4 ACLs to be used on
  an NFSv4 file system, SUSE Linux Enterprise Server provides the
  <filename>nfs4-acl-tools</filename> package, which contains the following:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <command>nfs4-getfacl</command>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <command>nfs4-setfacl</command>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <command>nfs4-editacl</command>
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  These operate in a generally similar way to <command>getfacl</command> and
  <command>setfacl</command> for examining and modifying NFSv4 ACLs. These
  commands are effective only if the file system on the NFS server provides
  full support for NFSv4 ACLs. Any limitation imposed by the server will affect
  programs running on the client in that some particular combinations of Access
  Control Entries (ACEs) might not be possible.
 </para>
 <para>
  It is not supported to mount NFS volumes locally on the exporting NFS server.
 </para>
 <bridgehead>Additional Information</bridgehead>
 <para>
  For information, see <citetitle>Introduction to NFSv4 ACLs</citetitle> at
  <link xlink:href="http://wiki.linux-nfs.org/wiki/index.php/ACLs#Introduction_to_NFSv4_ACLs"/>.
 </para>
</chapter>
