<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.lvm_snapshots" lang="en">
  <title>LVM Volume Snapshots</title>
  <para>
   A Logical Volume Manager (LVM) logical volume snapshot is a copy-on-write
   technology that monitors changes to an existing volume’s data blocks so
   that when a write is made to one of the blocks, the block’s value at
   the snapshot time is copied to a snapshot volume. In this way, a
   point-in-time copy of the data is preserved until the snapshot volume is
   deleted.
  </para>
  <sect1 id="sec.lvm_snapshots.intro">
   <title>Understanding Volume Snapshots</title>

   <para>
    A file system snapshot contains metadata about and data blocks from a
    source logical volume that have changed since the snapshot was taken.
    When you access data via the snapshot, you see a point-in-time copy of
    the source logical volume. There is no need to restore data from backup
    media or to overwrite the changed data.
   </para>

   <important>
    <title>Mounting Volumes with Snapshots</title>
    <para>
     During the snapshot’s lifetime, the snapshot must be mounted before
     its source logical volume can be mounted.
    </para>
   </important>

   <para>
    LVM volume snapshots allow you to create a backup from a point-in-time
    view of the file system. The snapshot is created instantly and persists
    until you delete it. You can backup the file system from the snapshot
    while the volume itself continues to be available for users. The
    snapshot initially contains some metadata about the snapshot, but no
    actual data from the source logical volume. Snapshot uses copy-on-write
    technology to detect when data changes in an original data block. It
    copies the value it held when the snapshot was taken to a block in the
    snapshot volume, then allows the new data to be stored in the source
    block. As more blocks change from their original value on the source
    logical volume, the snapshot size grows.
   </para>

   <para>
    When you are sizing the snapshot, consider how much data is expected to
    change on the source logical volume and how long you plan to keep the
    snapshot. The amount of space that you allocate for a snapshot volume
    can vary, depending on the size of the source logical volume, how long
    you plan to keep the snapshot, and the number of data blocks that are
    expected to change during the snapshot’s lifetime. The snapshot volume
    cannot be resized after it is created. As a guide, create a snapshot
    volume that is about 10% of the size of the original logical volume. If
    you anticipate that every block in the source logical volume will change
    at least one time before you delete the snapshot, then the snapshot
    volume should be at least as large as the source logical volume plus
    some additional space for metadata about the snapshot volume. Less space
    is required if the data changes infrequently or if the expected lifetime
    is sufficiently brief.
   </para>

   <para>
    In LVM2, snapshots are read/write by default. When you write data
    directly to the snapshot, that block is marked in the exception table as
    used, and never gets copied from the source logical volume. You can
    mount the snapshot volume, and test application changes by writing data
    directly to the snapshot volume. You can easily discard the changes by
    dismounting the snapshot, removing the snapshot, and then re-mounting
    the source logical volume.
   </para>

   <para>
    In a virtual guest environment, you can use the snapshot function for
    LVM logical volumes you create on the server’s disks, as you would on
    a physical server.
   </para>

   <para>
    In a virtual host environment, you can use the snapshot function to back
    up the virtual machine’s storage back-end, or to test changes to a
    virtual machine image, such as for patches or upgrades, without
    modifying the source logical volume. The virtual machine must be using
    an LVM logical volume as its storage back-end, as opposed to using a
    virtual disk file. You can mount the LVM logical volume and use it to
    store the virtual machine image as a file-backed disk, or you can assign
    the LVM logical volume as a physical disk to write to it as a block
    device.
   </para>

   <para>
    Beginning in SLES 11 SP3, an LVM logical volume snapshots can be thinly
    provisioned. Thin provisioning is assumed if you to create a snapshot
    without a specified size. The snapshot is created as a thin volume that
    uses space as needed from a thin pool. A thin snapshot volume has the
    same characteristics as any other thin volume. You can independently
    activate the volume, extend the volume, rename the volume, remove the
    volume, and even snapshot the volume.
   </para>

   <important>
    <title>Thinly Provisioned Volumes in a Cluster</title>
    <para>
     To use thinly provisioned snapshots in a cluster, the source logical
     volume and its snapshots must be managed in a single cluster resource.
     This allows the volume and its snapshots to always be mounted
     exclusively on the same node.
    </para>
   </important>

   <para>
    When you are done with the snapshot, it is important to remove it from
    the system. A snapshot eventually fills up completely as data blocks
    change on the source logical volume. When the snapshot is full, it is
    disabled, which prevents you from remounting the source logical volume.
   </para>

   <para>
    If you create multiple snapshots for a source logical volume, remove the
    snapshots in a last created, first deleted order.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="sec.lvm_snapshots.create">
   <title>Creating Linux Snapshots with LVM</title>

   <para>
    The Logical Volume Manager (LVM) can be used for creating snapshots of
    your file system.
   </para>

   <para>
    Open a terminal console and enter
   </para>
   <screen>sudo lvcreate -s [-L <replaceable>&lt;size</replaceable>&gt;] -n <replaceable>snap_volume</replaceable> <replaceable>source_volume_path</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    If no size is specified, the snapshot is created as a thin snapshot.
   </para>
   <para>
    For example:
   </para>
   <screen>sudo lvcreate -s -L 1G -n linux01-snap /dev/lvm/linux01</screen>
   <para>
    The snapshot is created as the
    <filename>/dev/lvm/linux01-snap</filename> volume.
   </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec.lvm_snapshots.monitor">
   <title>Monitoring a Snapshot</title>

   <para>
    Open a terminal console and enter
   </para>
   <screen>sudo lvdisplay <replaceable>snap_volume</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    For example:
   </para>
   <screen>&prompt.user;sudo lvdisplay /dev/vg01/linux01-snap

--- Logical volume ---
  LV Name                /dev/lvm/linux01
  VG Name                vg01
  LV UUID                QHVJYh-PR3s-A4SG-s4Aa-MyWN-Ra7a-HL47KL
  LV Write Access        read/write
  LV snapshot status     active destination for /dev/lvm/linux01
  LV Status              available
  # open                 0
  LV Size                80.00 GB
  Current LE             1024
  COW-table size         8.00 GB
  COW-table LE           512
  Allocated to snapshot  30%
  Snapshot chunk size    8.00 KB
  Segments               1
  Allocation             inherit
  Read ahead sectors     0
  Block device           254:5</screen>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec.lvm_snapshots.delete">
   <title>Deleting Linux Snapshots</title>

   <para>
    Open a terminal console and enter
   </para>
   <screen>sudo lvremove <replaceable>snap_volume_path</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    For example:
   </para>
   <screen>sudo lvremove /dev/lvmvg/linux01-snap</screen>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec.lvm_snapshots.xen_host">
   <title>Using Snapshots for Virtual Machines on a Virtual Host</title>

   <para>
    Using an LVM logical volume for a virtual machine’s back-end storage
    allows flexibility in administering the underlying device, such as
    making it easier to move storage objects, create snapshots, and back up
    data. You can mount the LVM logical volume and use it to store the
    virtual machine image as a file-backed disk, or you can assign the LVM
    logical volume as a physical disk to write to it as a block device. You
    can create a virtual disk image on the LVM logical volume, then snapshot
    the LVM.
   </para>

   <para>
    You can leverage the read/write capability of the snapshot to create
    different instances of a virtual machine, where the changes are made to
    the snapshot for a particular virtual machine instance. You can create a
    virtual disk image on an LVM logical volume, snapshot the source logical
    volume, and modify the snapshot for a particular virtual machine
    instance. You can create another snapshot of the source logical volume,
    and modify it for a different virtual machine instance. The majority of
    the data for the different virtual machine instances resides with the
    image on the source logical volume.
   </para>

   <para>
    You can also leverage the read/write capability of the snapshot to
    preserve the virtual disk image while testing patches or upgrades in the
    guest environment. You create a snapshot of the LVM volume that contains
    the image, and then run the virtual machine on the snapshot location.
    The source logical volume is unchanged, and all changes for that machine
    are written to the snapshot. To return to the source logical volume of
    the virtual machine image, you power off the virtual machine, then
    remove the snapshot from the source logical volume. To start over, you
    re-create the snapshot, mount the snapshot, and restart the virtual
    machine on the snapshot image.
   </para>
   
   <para>
    The following procedure uses a file-backed virtual disk image and the
    &xen; hypervisor. You can adapt the procedure in this section for other
    hypervisors that run on the SUSE Linux platform, such as &kvm;.
    To run a file-backed virtual machine image from the snapshot volume:
   </para>

   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Ensure that the source logical volume that contains the file-backed
      virtual machine image is mounted, such as at mount point
      <filename>/var/lib/xen/images/&lt;<replaceable>image_name</replaceable>&gt;</filename>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Create a snapshot of the LVM logical volume with enough space to store
      the differences that you expect.
     </para>
     <screen>sudo lvcreate -s -L 20G -n myvm-snap /dev/lvmvg/myvm</screen>
     <para>
      If no size is specified, the snapshot is created as a thin snapshot.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Create a mount point where you will mount the snapshot volume.
     </para>
     <screen>sudo mkdir -p /mnt/xen/vm/myvm-snap</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Mount the snapshot volume at the mount point you created.
     </para>
     <screen>sudo mount -t auto /dev/lvmvg/myvm-snap /mnt/xen/vm/myvm-snap</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In a text editor, copy the configuration file for the source virtual
      machine, modify the paths to point to the file-backed image file on
      the mounted snapshot volume, and save the file such as
      <filename>/etc/xen/myvm-snap.cfg</filename>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the virtual machine using the mounted snapshot volume of the
      virtual machine.
     </para>
<screen>sudo xm create -c /etc/xen/myvm-snap.cfg</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      (Optional) Remove the snapshot, and use the unchanged virtual machine
      image on the source logical volume.
     </para>
<screen>sudo unmount /mnt/xenvms/myvm-snap
sudo lvremove -f /dev/lvmvg/mylvm-snap</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      (Optional) Repeat this process as desired.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec.lvm_snapshots.rollback">
   <title>
    Merging a Snapshot with the Source Logical Volume to Revert Changes or
    Roll Back to a Previous State
   </title>

   <para>
    Snapshots can be useful if you need to roll back or restore data on a
    volume to a previous state. For example, you might need to revert data
    changes that resulted from an administrator error or a failed or
    undesirable package installation or upgrade.
   </para>

   <para>
    You can use the <command>lvconvert --merge</command> command to revert
    the changes made to an LVM logical volume. The merging begins as
    follows:
   </para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If both the source logical volume and snapshot volume are not open,
      the merge begins immediately.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If the source logical volume or snapshot volume are open, the merge
      starts the first time either the source logical volume or snapshot
      volume are activated and both are closed.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If the source logical volume cannot be closed, such as the
      root file system, the merge is deferred until
      the next time the server reboots and the source logical volume is
      activated.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If the source logical volume contains a virtual machine image, you
      must shut down the virtual machine, deactivate the source logical
      volume and snapshot volume (by dismounting them in that order), and
      then issue the merge command. Because the source logical volume is
      automatically remounted and the snapshot volume is deleted when the
      merge is complete, you should not restart the virtual machine until
      after the merge is complete. After the merge is complete, you use the
      resulting logical volume for the virtual machine.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

   <para>
    After a merge begins, the merge continues automatically after server
    restarts until it is complete. A new snapshot cannot be created for the
    source logical volume while a merge is in progress.
   </para>

   <para>
    While the merge is in progress, reads or writes to the source logical
    volume are transparently redirected to the snapshot that is being
    merged. This allows users to immediately view and access the data as it
    was when the snapshot was created. They do not need to wait for the
    merge to complete.
   </para>

   <para>
    When the merge is complete, the source logical volume contains the same
    data as it did when the snapshot was taken, plus any data changes made
    after the merge began. The resulting logical volume has the source
    logical volume’s name, minor number, and UUID. The source logical
    volume is automatically remounted, and the snapshot volume is removed.
   </para>

   <procedure>
    <step id="b15cjobm">
     <para>
      Open a terminal console and enter
     </para>
<screen>sudo lvconvert --merge  [-b] [-i <replaceable>seconds</replaceable>] [<replaceable>snap_volume_path</replaceable>[...<replaceable>snapN</replaceable>]|@<replaceable>volume_tag</replaceable>]</screen>
     <para>
      You can specify one or multiple snapshots on the command line. You can
      alternatively tag multiple source logical volumes with the same volume
      tag then specify
      <literal>@&lt;<replaceable>volume_tag</replaceable>&gt;</literal> on
      the command line. The snapshots for the tagged volumes are merged to
      their respective source logical volumes. For information about tagging
      logical volumes, see
      <xref linkend="sec.lvm.tagging" xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage"/>.
     </para>
     <para>
      The options include:
     </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>-b</term>
       <term>--background</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Run the daemon in the background. This allows multiple specified
         snapshots to be merged concurrently in parallel.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>-i</term>
       <term>--interval &lt;<replaceable>seconds</replaceable>&gt;</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Report progress as a percentage at regular intervals. Specify the
         interval in seconds.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
     <para>
      For more information about this command, see the
      <command>lvconvert(8)</command> man page.
     </para>
     <para>
      For example:
     </para>
<screen>sudo lvconvert --merge /dev/lvmvg/linux01-snap</screen>
     <para>
      This command merges <filename>/dev/lvmvg/linux01-snap</filename> into
      its source logical volume.
     </para>
<screen>sudo lvconvert --merge @mytag</screen>
     <para>
      If <filename>lvol1</filename>, <filename>lvol2</filename>, and
      <filename>lvol3</filename> are all tagged with
      <literal>mytag</literal>, each snapshot volume is merged serially with
      its respective source logical volume; that is:
      <filename>lvol1</filename>, then <filename>lvol2</filename>, then
      <filename>lvol3</filename>. If the <literal>--background</literal>
      option is specified, the snapshots for the respective tagged logical
      volume are merged concurrently in parallel.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      (Optional) If both the source logical volume and snapshot volume are
      open and they can be closed, you can manually deactivate and activate
      the source logical volume to get the merge to start immediately.
     </para>
     <screen>sudo umount <replaceable>original_volume</replaceable>
sudo lvchange -an <replaceable>original_volume</replaceable>
sudo lvchange -ay <replaceable>original_volume</replaceable>
sudo mount <replaceable>original_volume</replaceable> <replaceable>mount_point</replaceable></screen>
     <para>
      For example:
     </para>
<screen>sudo umount /dev/lvmvg/lvol01
sudo lvchange -an /dev/lvmvg/lvol01
sudo lvchange -ay /dev/lvmvg/lvol01
sudo mount /dev/lvmvg/lvol01 /mnt/lvol01</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      (Optional) If both the source logical volume and snapshot volume are
      open and the source logical volume cannot be closed, such as the
      &rootuser; file system, you can restart the server
      and mount the source logical volume to get the merge to start
      immediately after the restart.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect1>
 </chapter>
