<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<sect2 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="sec.trouble.data.recover.rescue">
 <title>Using the Rescue System</title><info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
        </dm:bugtracker>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <indexterm>
 <primary>rescue system</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>system</primary>
 <secondary>rescuing</secondary></indexterm>
 <para>
  There are several reasons why a system could fail to come up and run
  properly. A corrupted file system following a system crash, corrupted
  configuration files, or a corrupted boot loader configuration are the most
  common ones.
 </para>
 <para>
  To help you to resolve these situations, &productname; contains a
  rescue system that you can boot. The rescue system is a small Linux system
  that can be loaded into a RAM disk and mounted as root file system,
  allowing you to access your Linux partitions from the outside. Using the
  rescue system, you can recover or modify any important aspect of your
  system.
 </para>
 <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Manipulate any type of configuration file.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Check the file system for defects and start automatic repair processes.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Access the installed system in a <quote>change root</quote> environment.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Check, modify, and re-install the boot loader configuration.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Recover from a badly installed device driver or unusable kernel.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Resize partitions using the parted command. Find more information about
    this tool at the GNU Parted Web site
    <link xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/software/parted/parted.html"/>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  The rescue system can be loaded from various sources and locations. The
  simplest option is to boot the rescue system from the original
  installation medium.
 </para>
 <note os="sles" arch="zseries">
  <title>IBM &zseries; Starting the Rescue System</title>
  <para>
   On IBM &zseries; the installation system can be used for rescue
   purposes. To start the rescue system follow the instructions in
   <xref linkend="sec.zseries.rescue"/>.
  </para>
 </note>
 <procedure><indexterm>
  <primary>rescue system</primary>
  <secondary>starting from medium</secondary></indexterm>
  <step>
   <para>
    Insert the installation medium into your DVD drive.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Reboot the system.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    At the boot screen, press <keycap>F4</keycap> and choose
    <guimenu>DVD-ROM</guimenu>. Then choose <guimenu>Rescue System</guimenu>
    from the main menu.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Enter <literal>root</literal> at the <literal>Rescue:</literal> prompt.
    A password is not required.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
 <procedure xml:id="proc.trouble.data.recover.rescue.network"><indexterm>
  <primary>rescue system</primary>
  <secondary>starting from network source</secondary></indexterm>
  <para>
   If your hardware setup does not include a DVD drive, you can boot the
   rescue system from a network source. The following example applies to a
   remote boot scenario&mdash;if using another boot medium, such as a
   DVD, modify the <filename>info</filename> file accordingly and boot as
   you would for a normal installation.
  </para>
  <step>
   <para>
    Enter the configuration of your PXE boot setup and add the lines
    <literal>install=<replaceable>protocol</replaceable>://<replaceable>instsource</replaceable></literal>
    and <literal>rescue=1</literal>. If you need to start the repair system,
    use <literal>repair=1</literal> instead. As with a normal installation,
    <replaceable>protocol</replaceable> stands for any of the supported
    network protocols (NFS, HTTP, FTP, etc.) and
    <replaceable>instsource</replaceable> for the path to your network
    installation source.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Boot the system using <quote>Wake on LAN</quote>, as described in
    <xref linkend="sec.deployment.remoteinst.boot.wol"/>.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Enter <literal>root</literal> at the <literal>Rescue:</literal> prompt.
    A password is not required.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
 <para>
  Once you have entered the rescue system, you can make use of the virtual
  consoles that can be reached with
  <keycombo><keycap function="alt"/><keycap>F1</keycap></keycombo> to
  <keycombo><keycap function="alt"/><keycap>F6</keycap></keycombo>.
 </para>
 <para>
  A shell and many other useful utilities, such as the mount program, are
  available in the <filename>/bin</filename> directory. The
  <filename>/sbin</filename> directory contains important file and network
  utilities for reviewing and repairing the file system. This directory also
  contains the most important binaries for system maintenance, such as
  <command>fdisk</command>, <command>mkfs</command>,
  <command>mkswap</command>, <command>mount</command>, and
  <command>shutdown</command>, as well as <command>ip</command> and
  <command>ss</command> for maintaining the network. The directory
  <filename>/usr/bin</filename> contains the vi editor, find, less, and SSH.
 </para>
 <para>
  To see the system messages, either use the command
  <command>dmesg</command> or view the system log with
  <command>journalctl</command>.
 </para>
 <sect3 xml:id="sec.trouble.data.recover.rescue.file">
  <title>Checking and Manipulating Configuration Files</title>
  <para>
   As an example for a configuration that might be fixed using the rescue
   system, imagine you have a broken configuration file that prevents the
   system from booting properly. You can fix this using the rescue system.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <para>
    To manipulate a configuration file, proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the rescue system using one of the methods described above.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To mount a root file system located under
     <filename>/dev/sda6</filename> to the rescue system, use the following
     command:
    </para>
<screen>mount /dev/sda6 /mnt</screen>
    <para>
     All directories of the system are now located under
     <filename>/mnt</filename>
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Change the directory to the mounted root file system:
    </para>
<screen>cd /mnt</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open the problematic configuration file in the vi editor. Adjust and
     save the configuration.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Unmount the root file system from the rescue system:
    </para>
<screen>umount /mnt</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Reboot the machine.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect3>
 <sect3 xml:id="sec.trouble.data.recover.rescue.filesystem">
  <title>Repairing and Checking File Systems</title><indexterm>
  <primary>file systems</primary>
  <secondary>repairing</secondary></indexterm>
  <para>
   Generally, file systems cannot be repaired on a running system. If you
   encounter serious problems, you may not even be able to mount your root
   file system and the system boot may end with a <quote>kernel
   panic</quote>. In this case, the only way is to repair the system from
   the outside. The system contains the utilities to check and repair the
   <literal>btrfs</literal>, <literal>ext2</literal>,
   <literal>ext3</literal>, <literal>ext4</literal>,
   <literal>reiserfs</literal>, <literal>xfs</literal>,
   <literal>dosfs</literal>, and <literal>vfat</literal> file systems. Look
   for the command <command>fsck.</command>
   <replaceable>FILESYSTEM</replaceable>, for example, if you need a file
   system check for <literal>btrfs</literal>, use
   <command>fsck.btrfs</command>.
  </para>
<!-- TODO: Add FATE#315126 -->
 </sect3>
 <sect3 xml:id="sec.trouble.data.recover.rescue.access">
  <title>Accessing the Installed System</title>
  <para>
   If you need to access the installed system from the rescue system, you
   need to do this in a <emphasis>change root</emphasis> environment. For
   example, to modify the boot loader configuration, or to execute a
   hardware configuration utility.
  </para>
  <para>
   To set up a change root environment based on the installed system,
   proceed as follows:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     First mount the root partition from the installed system and the device
     file system (change the device name to your current settings):
    </para>
<screen>mount /dev/sda6 /mnt
mount --bind /dev /mnt/dev</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Now you can <quote>change root</quote> into the new environment:
    </para>
<screen>chroot /mnt</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Then mount <filename>/proc</filename> and <filename>/sys</filename>:
    </para>
<screen>mount /proc
mount /sys</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Finally, mount the remaining partitions from the installed system:
    </para>
<screen>mount -a</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Now you have access to the installed system. Before rebooting the
     system, unmount the partitions with <command>umount</command>
     <option>-a</option> and leave the <quote>change root</quote>
     environment with <command>exit</command>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <warning>
   <title>Limitations</title>
   <para>
    Although you have full access to the files and applications of the
    installed system, there are some limitations. The kernel that is running
    is the one that was booted with the rescue system, not with the change
    root environment. It only supports essential hardware and it is not
    possible to add kernel modules from the installed system unless the
    kernel versions are exactly the same. Always check the version of the
    currently running (rescue) kernel with <command>uname -r</command> and
    then find out if a matching subdirectory exists in the
    <filename>/lib/modules</filename> directory in the change root
    environment. If yes, you can use the installed modules, otherwise you
    need to supply their correct versions on other media, such as a flash
    disk. Most often the rescue kernel version differs from the installed
    one &mdash; then you cannot simply access a sound card, for example.
    It is also not possible to start a graphical user interface.
   </para>
   <para>
    Also note that you leave the <quote>change root</quote> environment when
    you switch the console with
    <keycombo><keycap function="alt"/><keycap>F1</keycap></keycombo> to
    <keycombo><keycap function="alt"/><keycap>F6</keycap></keycombo>.
   </para>
  </warning>
 </sect3>
 <sect3 xml:id="sec.trouble.data.recover.rescue.grub">
  <title>Modifying and Re-installing the Boot Loader</title>
  <para>
   Sometimes a system cannot boot because the boot loader configuration is
   corrupted. The start-up routines cannot, for example, translate physical
   drives to the actual locations in the Linux file system without a working
   boot loader.
  </para>
  <para>
   To check the boot loader configuration and re-install the boot loader,
   proceed as follows:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Perform the necessary steps to access the installed system as described
     in <xref linkend="sec.trouble.data.recover.rescue.access"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Check whether the following files are correctly configured according to
     the &grub; configuration principles outlined in
     <xref linkend="cha.grub2"/> and apply fixes if necessary.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <filename>/etc/default/grub</filename>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <filename>/boot/grub2/device.map</filename> (optional file, only
       present if created manually)
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <filename>/boot/grub2/grub.cfg</filename> (this file is generated, do
       not edit)
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <filename>/etc/sysconfig/bootloader</filename>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Re-install the boot loader using the following command sequence:
    </para>
<screen>grub2-mkconfig -o /boot/grub2/grub.cfg</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Unmount the partitions, log out from the <quote>change root</quote>
     environment, and reboot the system:
    </para>
<screen>umount -a
exit
reboot</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect3>
 <sect3 xml:id="sec.trouble.data.recover.rescue.dud">
  <title>Fixing Kernel Installation</title>
  <para>
   A kernel update may introduce a new bug which can impact the operation of
   your system. For example a driver for a piece of hardware in your system
   may be faulty, which prevents you from accessing and using it. In this
   case, revert to the last working kernel (if available on the system) or
   install the original kernel from the installation media.
  </para>
  <tip>
   <title>How to Keep Last Kernels after Update</title>
   <para>
    To prevent failures to boot after a faulty kernel update, use the kernel
    multiversion feature and tell <systemitem>libzypp</systemitem> which
    kernels you want to keep after the update.
   </para>
   <para>
    For example to always keep the last two kernels and the currently
    running one, add
   </para>
<screen>multiversion.kernels = latest,latest-1,running</screen>
   <para>
    to the <filename>/etc/zypp/zypp.conf</filename> file. See
    <xref linkend="cha.tuning.multikernel"/> for more information.
   </para>
  </tip>
  <para>
   A similar case is when you need to re-install or update a broken driver
   for a device not supported by &productname;. For example when a
   hardware vendor uses a specific device, such as a hardware RAID
   controller, which needs a binary driver to be recognized by the operating
   system. The vendor typically releases a Driver Update Disk (DUD) with the
   fixed or updated version of the required driver.
  </para>
  <para>
   In both cases you need to access the installed system in the rescue mode
   and fix the kernel related problem, otherwise the system may fail to boot
   correctly:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Boot from the &productname; installation media.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If you are recovering after a faulty kernel update, skip this step. If
     you need to use a driver update disk (DUD), press <keycap>F6</keycap>
     to load the driver update after the boot menu appears, and choose the
     path or URL to the driver update and confirm with
     <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Choose <guimenu>Rescue System</guimenu> from the boot menu and press
     <keycap function="enter"/>. If you chose to use DUD, you will be asked
     to specify where the driver update is stored.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter <literal>root</literal> at the <literal>Rescue:</literal> prompt.
     A password is not required.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Manually mount the target system and <quote>change root</quote> into
     the new environment. For more information, see
     <xref linkend="sec.trouble.data.recover.rescue.access"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If using DUD, install/re-install/update the faulty device driver
     package. Always make sure the installed kernel version exactly matches
     the version of the driver you are installing.
    </para>
    <para>
     If fixing faulty kernel update installation, you can install the
     original kernel from the installation media with the following
     procedure.
    </para>
    <substeps performance="required">
     <step>
      <para>
       Identify your DVD device with <command>hwinfo --cdrom</command> and
       mount it with <command>mount /dev/sr0 /mnt</command>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Navigate to the directory where your kernel files are stored on the
       DVD, for example <command>cd /mnt/suse/x86_64/</command>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Install required <systemitem>kernel-*</systemitem>,
       <systemitem>kernel-*-base</systemitem>, and
       <systemitem>kernel-*-extra</systemitem> packages of your flavor with
       the <command>rpm -i</command> command.
      </para>
     </step>
<!-- fs 2014-02-19:
     Commenting, since there is currently no convenient way to check this with
     GRUB 2 (rather than manually checking grub.cfg or looking into the YaST
     grub module

      <step>
       <para>
        After the installation finishes, check that a new menu entry
        relevant for the newly installed kernel was added to the boot loader
        configuration file. (<filename>/boot/grub/menu.lst</filename> for
        <systemitem>grub</systemitem>).
       </para>
      </step>
-->
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Update configuration files and reinitialize the boot loader if needed.
     For more information, see
     <xref linkend="sec.trouble.data.recover.rescue.grub"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Remove any bootable media from the system drive and reboot.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect3>
</sect2>
