<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter  PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.tablet">
 <title>Using Tablet PCs</title><indexterm id="idx.tablet" class="startofrange">
 <primary>Tablet PCs</primary></indexterm>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   &productnamereg; comes with support for Tablet PCs. In the following,
   learn how to install and configure your Tablet PC and discover some
   useful Linux* applications which accept input from digital pens.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <para>
  The following Tablet PCs are supported:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Tablet PCs with serial and USB <phrase role="productname">Wacom</phrase>
    tablet (pen based), touch-screen or multi-touch devices.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Tablet PCs with <phrase role="productname">FinePoint</phrase> devices,
    such as <phrase role="productname">Gateway C210X/M280E/CX2724</phrase>
    or <phrase role="productname">HP Compaq TC1000</phrase>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Tablet PCs with touch screen devices, such as
    <phrase role="productname">Asus R2H</phrase>,
    <phrase role="productname">Clevo TN120R</phrase>,
    <phrase role="productname">Fujitsu Siemens Computers P-Series</phrase>,
    <phrase role="productname">LG C1</phrase>,
    <phrase role="productname">Samsung Q1/Q1-Ultra</phrase>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  After you have installed the Tablet PC packages and configured your
  digitizer correctly, input with the pen (also called a stylus) can be used
  for the following actions and applications:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Logging in to GDM
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Unlocking your screen on the GNOME desktops
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Actions that can also be triggered by other pointing devices (such as
    mouse or touch pad), for example, moving the cursor on the screen,
    starting applications, closing, resizing and moving windows, shifting
    window focus and dragging and dropping objects
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Using gesture recognition in applications of the X Window System
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Drawing with GIMP
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Taking notes or sketching with applications like Jarnal or Xournal or
    editing larger amounts of text with Dasher
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <sect1 id="sec.tablet.install">
  <title>Installing Tablet PC Packages</title>

  <para>
   <indexterm>
   <primary>Tablet PCs</primary>
   <secondary>installing</secondary>
   </indexterm> The packages needed for Tablet PCs are included in the
   <literal>TabletPC</literal> installation pattern&mdash;if this is
   selected during installation, the following packages should already be
   installed on your system:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <systemitem class="resource">cellwriter</systemitem>: a character-based
     hardwriting input panel
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <systemitem class="resource">jarnal</systemitem>: a Java-based note
     taking application
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <systemitem class="resource">xournal</systemitem>: an application for
     note taking and sketching
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <systemitem class="resource">xstroke</systemitem>: a gesture
     recognition program for the X Window System
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <systemitem class="resource">xvkbd</systemitem>: a virtual keyboard for
     the X Window System
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <systemitem class="resource">x11-input-fujitsu</systemitem>: the X
     input module for <phrase role="productname">Fujitsu P-Series</phrase>
     tablets
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <systemitem class="resource">x11-input-evtouch</systemitem>: the X
     input module for some Tablet PCs with touch screens
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <systemitem class="resource">xorg-x11-driver-input</systemitem>: the X
     input module for input devices, including the module for Wacom devices.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   If these packages are not installed, manually install the packages you
   need from command line or select the <systemitem>TabletPC</systemitem>
   pattern for installation in &yast;.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.tablet.conf">
  <title>Configuring Your Tablet Device</title>

  <para>
   During installation, your tablet or touch device is configured by
   default. If you have trouble with the configuration of your Wacom device,
   you use <command>xsetwacom</command> on the command line to change the
   settings.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.tablet.use.login">
  <title>Using the Virtual Keyboard</title>

  <para>
   <indexterm>
   <primary>Tablet PCs</primary>
   <secondary>xvkbd</secondary>
   </indexterm> To log in to the GNOME desktop or to unlock the screen, you
   can either enter your username and password as usual or via the virtual
   keyboard (xvkbd) displayed below the login field. To configure the
   keyboard or to access the integrated help, click the
   <guimenu>xvkbd</guimenu> field at the left lower corner and open the
   xvkbd main menu.
  </para>

  <para>
   If your input is not visible (or is not transferred to the window where
   you need it), redirect the focus by clicking the <guimenu>Focus</guimenu>
   key in xvkbd and then clicking into the window that should get the
   keyboard events.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.tablet.xvkbd">
   <title>xvkbd Virtual Keyboard</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="xvkbd.png" width="95%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="xvkbd.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   If you want to use xvkbd after login, start it from the main menu or with
   <command>xvkbd</command> from a shell.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.tablet.use.rotate">
  <title>Rotating Your Display</title>

  <para>
   <indexterm>
   <primary>Tablet PCs</primary>
   <secondary>KRandRTray</secondary>
   </indexterm> <indexterm>
   <primary>Tablet PCs</primary>
   <secondary>gnome-display-properties</secondary>
   </indexterm> Use gnome-display-properties (GNOME) to rotate or resize
   your display manually on the fly. gnome-display-properties is an applet
   for the RANDR extension of the X server.
  </para>

  <para>
   gnome-display-properties from the main menu, or enter
   <command>gnome-display-properties</command> to start the applet from a
   shell. After you have started the applet, the applet icon is usually
   added to your system tray. If the gnome-display-properties icon does not
   automatically appear in the system tray, make sure <guimenu>Show Displays
   in Panel</guimenu> is activated in the <guimenu>Monitor Resolution
   Settings</guimenu> dialog.
  </para>

  <para>
   To rotate your display with KRandRTray, right-click the icon and select
   <guimenu>Configure Display</guimenu>. Select the desired orientation from
   the configuration dialog.
  </para>

  <para>
   To rotate your display with gnome-display-properties, right-click the
   icon and select the desired orientation. Your display is immediately
   tilted to the new direction. The orientation of the graphics tablet
   changes also, so it can still interpret the movement of the pen
   correctly.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you have problems changing the orientation of your desktop, refer to
   <xref linkend="sec.tablet.trouble"/> for more information.
  </para>

  <para os="sled">
   For more information about the desktop-specific applets for the RANDR
   extension refer to
   <xref
    linkend="sec.gnome.settings.hardware.screen"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.tablet.use.gesture">
  <title>Using Gesture Recognition</title>

  <para>
   &productname; includes both CellWriter and xstroke for gesture
   recognition. Both applications accept gestures executed with the pen or
   other pointing devices as input for applications on the X Window System.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.tablet.use.gesture.cellwriter">
   <title>Using CellWriter</title>
   <para>
    <indexterm>
    <primary>Tablet PCs</primary>
    <secondary>CellWriter</secondary>
    </indexterm> With CellWriter, you can write characters into a grid of
    cells&mdash;the writing is instantly recognized on a character basis.
    After you have finished writing, you can send the input to the currently
    focused application. Before you can use CellWriter for gesture
    recognition, the application needs to be trained to recognize your
    handwriting: You need to train each character of a certain map of keys
    (untrained characters are not activated and thus cannot be used).
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Training CellWriter</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start CellWriter from the main menu or with
      <command>cellwriter</command> from the command line. On the first
      start, CellWriter automatically starts in the training mode. In
      training mode it shows a set of characters of the currently chosen key
      map.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Enter the gesture you would like to use for a character into the
      respective character's cell. With the first input, the background
      changes its color to white, whereas the character itself is shown in
      light gray. Repeat the gesture multiple times until the character
      changes its color to black. Untrained characters are shown on a light
      gray or brown background (depending on the desktop's color scheme).
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Repeat this step until you have trained CellWriter for all characters
      you need.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      If you want to train CellWriter for another language, click the
      <guimenu> Setup</guimenu> button and select a language from the
      <guimenu>Languages</guimenu> tab. <guimenu>Close</guimenu> the
      configuration dialog. Click the <guimenu>Train</guimenu> button and
      select the key map from the drop-down box at the bottom right corner
      of the <guimenu>CellWriter</guimenu> window. Now repeat your training
      for the new map of keys.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      After having finished the training for the map of keys, click the
      <guimenu>Train</guimenu> button to switch to the normal mode.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    In the normal mode, the CellWriter windows shows a couple of empty cells
    in which to enter the gestures. The characters are not sent to another
    application until you click the <guimenu>Enter</guimenu> button, so you
    can correct or delete characters before you use them as input.
    Characters that have been recognized with a low degree of confidence
    will appear highlighted. To correct your input, use the context menu
    that appears on right-clicking a cell. To delete a character, either use
    your pen's eraser, or middle-click with the mouse to clear the cell.
    After finishing your input in CellWriter, define which application
    should receive the input by clicking into the application's window. Then
    send the input to the application by clicking <guimenu>Enter</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <figure id="fig.tablet.cellwriter">
    <title>Gesture Recognition with CellWriter</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="cellwriter.png" width="95%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="cellwriter.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    If you click the <guimenu>Keys</guimenu> button in CellWriter, you get a
    virtual keyboard that can be used instead of the handwriting
    recognition.
   </para>
   <para>
    To hide CellWriter, close the CellWriter window. The application now
    appears as icon in your system tray. To show the input window again,
    click the icon in the system tray.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.tablet.use.gesture.xstroke">
   <title>Using Xstroke</title>
   <para>
    <indexterm>
    <primary>Tablet PCs</primary>
    <secondary>xstroke</secondary>
    </indexterm> With xstroke, you can use gestures with your pen or other
    pointing devices as input for applications on the X Window System. The
    xstroke alphabet is a unistroke alphabet that resembles the Graffiti*
    alphabet. When activated, xstroke sends the input to the currently
    focused window.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start xstroke from the main menu or with <command>xstroke</command>
      from a shell. This adds a pencil icon to your system tray.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the application for which you want to create text input with the
      pen (for example, a terminal window, a text editor or an &ooo;
      Writer).
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To activate the gesture recognition mode, click the pencil icon once.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Perform some gestures on the graphics tablet with the pen or another
      pointing device. xstroke captures the gestures and transfers them to
      text that appears in the application window that has the focus.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To switch focus to a different window, click the desired window with
      the pen and hold for a moment (or use the keyboard shortcut defined in
      your desktop's control center).
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To deactivate the gesture recognition mode, click the pencil icon
      again.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.tablet.use.journal">
  <title>Taking Notes and Sketching with the Pen</title>

  <para>
   <indexterm>
   <primary>Tablet PCs</primary>
   <secondary>Xournal</secondary>
   </indexterm> <indexterm>
   <primary>Tablet PCs</primary>
   <secondary>Jarnal</secondary>
   </indexterm> To create drawings with the pen, you can use a professional
   graphics editor like GIMP or try one of the note-taking applications,
   Xournal or Jarnal. With both Xournal and Jarnal, you can take notes,
   create drawings or comment PDF files with the pen. As a Java-based
   application available for several platforms, Jarnal also offers basic
   collaboration features. For more information, refer to
   <ulink
    url="http://www.dklevine.com/general/software/tc1000/jarnal-net.htm"/>.
   When saving your contents, Jarnal stores the data in an archive format
   (*.jaj) that also contains a file in SVG format.
  </para>

  <para>
   Start Jarnal or Xournal from the main menu or by entering
   <command>jarnal</command> or <command>xournal</command> in a shell. To
   comment a PDF file in Xournal, for example, select <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Annotate PDF</guimenu> </menuchoice> and
   open the PDF file from your file system. Use the pen or another pointing
   device to annotate the PDF and save your changes with <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenu>Export to PDF</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.tablet.xournal">
   <title>Annotating a PDF with Xournal</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="xournal.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="xournal.png" width="50%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   <indexterm>
   <primary>Tablet PCs</primary>
   <secondary>Dasher</secondary>
   </indexterm> Dasher is another useful application. It was designed for
   situations where keyboard input is impractical or unavailable. With a bit
   of training, you can rapidly enter larger amounts of text using only the
   pen (or other input devices&mdash;it can even be driven with an eye
   tracker).
  </para>

  <para>
   Start Dasher from the main menu or with <command>dasher</command> from a
   shell. Move your pen in one direction and the application starts to zoom
   into the letters on the right side. From the letters passing the cross
   hairs in the middle, the text is created or predicted and is printed to
   the upper part of the window. To stop or start writing, click the display
   once with the pen. Modify the zooming speed at the bottom of the window.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.tablet.dasher">
   <title>Editing Texts with Dasher</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="dasher.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="dasher.png" width="50%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   The Dasher concept works for many languages. For more information, refer
   to the Dasher Web site, which offers comprehensive documentation,
   demonstrations and training texts. Find it at
   <ulink
    url="http://www.inference.phy.cam.ac.uk/dasher/"/>
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.tablet.trouble">
  <title>Troubleshooting</title>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Virtual Keyboard Does Not Appear on Login Screen</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Occasionally, the virtual keyboard is not displayed on the login
      screen. To solve this, restart the X server by pressing <keycombo>
      <keycap function="control"/> <keycap function="alt"/>
      <keycap function="backspace"/> </keycombo> or press the appropriate
      key on your Tablet PC (if you use a slate model without integrated
      keyboard). If the virtual keyboard still does not show, connect an
      external keyboard to your slate model and log in using the hardware
      keyboard.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Orientation of the Wacom Graphics Tablets Does Not Change</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      With the <command>xrandr</command> command, you can change the
      orientation of your display from within a shell. Enter <command>xrandr
      <option>--help</option></command> to view the options available. To
      simultaneously change the orientation of your graphics tablet, the
      command needs to be modified as described below:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        For normal orientation (0째 rotation):
       </para>
<screen>xrandr -o normal &amp;&amp; xsetwacom --set "Serial Wacom Tablet" Rotate NONE</screen>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        For 90째 rotation (clockwise, portrait):
       </para>
<screen>xrandr -o right &amp;&amp; xsetwacom --set "Serial Wacom Tablet" Rotate CW</screen>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        For 180째 rotation (landscape):
       </para>
<screen> xrandr -o inverted &amp;&amp; xsetwacom --set "Serial Wacom Tablet" Rotate HALF</screen>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        For 270째 rotation (counterclockwise, portrait):
       </para>
<screen> xrandr -o left &amp;&amp; xsetwacom set --"Serial Wacom Tablet" Rotate CCW</screen>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
     <para>
      Note that the commands above depend on the output of the
      <command>xsetwacom list</command> command. Replace <option>"Serial
      Wacom Tablet"</option> with the output for the stylus or the touch
      device. If you have a Wacom device with touch support (you can use
      your fingers on the tablet to move the cursor), you need to rotate
      also the touch device.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   Some of the applications mentioned here do not offer integrated online
   help, but you can find some useful information about usage and
   configuration in your installed system in <filename>
   /usr/share/doc/package/<replaceable>packagename</replaceable></filename>
   or on the Web:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For the Xournal manual, refer to
     <ulink
      url="http://xournal.sourceforge.net/manual.html"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The Jarnal documentation is located at
     <ulink url="http://jarnal.wikispaces.com/"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Find the xstroke man page at
     <ulink
      url="http://davesource.com/Projects/xstroke/xstroke.txt"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Find a HOWTO for configuring X on the Linux Wacom Web site:
     <ulink
      url="http://sourceforge.net/apps/mediawiki/linuxwacom/index.php?title=Configuring_X"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Find a very informative Web site about the Dasher project at
     <ulink
      url="http://www.inference.phy.cam.ac.uk/dasher/"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Find more information and documentation about CellWriter at
     <ulink
      url="http://risujin.org/cellwriter/"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Information on gnome-display-properties can be found at
     <ulink url="http://old-en.opensuse.org/GNOME/Multiscreen"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist><indexterm class="endofrange" startref="idx.tablet"/>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
