<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xml:id="cha-transactional-updates" xml:lang="en">
 <title>Transactional updates</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    Transactional updates are available in &productname; as a technology
    preview, for updating &slsa; when the root file system is read-only. 
    Transactional updates are atomic (all updates are applied only if all 
    updates succeed) and support rollbacks. It does not affect a running system 
    as no changes are activated until after the system is rebooted. As reboots
    are disruptive, the admin must decide if a reboot is more expensive than
    disturbing running services. If reboots are too expensive then do not use
    transactional updates.
   </para>

   <para>
    Transactional updates are run daily by the
    <command>transactional-update</command> script. The script checks for
    available updates. If there are any updates, it creates a new snapshot of
    the root file system in the background, and then fetches updates from the
    release channels. After the new snapshot is completely updated, it is
    marked as active and will be the new default root file system after the next 
    reboot of the system. When <command>transactional-update</command> is set to run
    automatically (which is the default behavior) it also reboots the system.
    Both the time that the update runs and the reboot maintenance window are 
    configurable.
   </para>

   <para>
    Only packages that are part of the snapshot of the root file system can be
    updated. If packages contain files that are not part of the snapshot, the
    update could fail or break the system.
   </para>

   <para>
    RPMs that require a license to be accepted cannot be updated.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>
 
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-tu-limitations">
  <title>Limitations of technology preview</title>

  <para>
   As a technology preview, there are certain limitations in functionality. The
   following packages will not work with <command>transactional-update</command>:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The <package>nginx</package> default index.html page may not be available
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>tomcat-webapps</package> and
     <package>tomcat-admin-webapps</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>phpMyAdmin</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>sca-appliance-*</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>mpi-selector</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>emacs</package> works except for Emacs games
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>bind</package> and <package>bind-chrootenv</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>docbook*</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>sblim-sfcb*</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>texlive*</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>iso_ent</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>openjade</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>opensp</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>pcp</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>plymouth</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>postgresql-server-10</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>pulseaudio-gdm-hooks</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>smartmontools</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   The updater component of the system installer does not work with a read-only
   file system as it has no support for transactional updates.
  </para>

  <para>
   Further considerations:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In general it is a good idea to minimize the time between updating the
     system and rebooting the machine.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Only one update can be applied at a time. Be sure to reboot after an
     update, and before the next update is applied.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <command>update-alternatives</command> should not be run after a
     transactional update until the machine has been rebooted.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Do not create new system users or system groups after a transactional
     update until after reboot. It is acceptable to create normal users and
     groups (UID > 1000, GID > 1000).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &yast; is not yet aware of transactional updates. If a YaST module needs
     to install additional packages, this will not work. Normal system
     operations only modifying configuration files in <filename>/etc</filename>
     will work.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For <package>php7-fastcgi</package>, you must manually create a symbolic link,
     <filename>/srv/www/cgi-bin/php</filename>, that points to
     <filename>/usr/bin/php-cgi</filename>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>ntp</package>is part of the Legacy Module for migration from
     older SLES versions. It is not supported on a new &productname;
     installation, and has been replaced by <package>chrony</package>. If you
     continue to use <package>ntp</package>, a fresh installation is required
     to work correctly with transactional updates.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>sblim-sfcb</package>: The whole sblim ecosystem is incompatible
     with transactional update.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <command>btrfs-defrag</command> from the
     <package>btrfsmaintenance</package> package does not work with a read-only
     root file system.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For <command>btrfs-balance</command>, the variable
     <literal>BTRFS_BALANCE_MOUNTPOINTS</literal> in
     <filename>/etc/sysconfig/btrfsmaintenance</filename> must be changed from
     <literal>/</literal> to <literal>/.snapshots</literal>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For <command>btrfs-scrub</command>, the variable
     <literal>BTRFS_SCRUB_MOUNTPOINTS</literal> in
     <filename>/etc/sysconfig/btrfsmaintenance</filename> must be changed from
     <literal>/</literal> to <literal>/.snapshots</literal>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-install-tu">
  <title>Enabling <package>transactional-update</package></title>
  <para>
   You must enable the Transactional Server Module during system installation,
   and then select the Transactional Server System Role. Installing any package 
   from the Transactional Server Module later in a running system is NOT 
   supported and may break the system.
  </para>
  <para>
      Note that changing the subvolume layout of the root partition, or putting 
      sub-directories or subvolumes of the root partition on their own partitions 
      (except <filename>/home</filename>, <filename>/var</filename>, 
      <filename>/srv</filename>, and <filename>/opt</filename>) is not supported, 
      and will most likely break the system.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 
  <sect1 xml:id="sec-tu-disable">
  <title>Managing automatic updates</title>
  <para>
      Automatic updates are controlled by a <command>systemd.timer</command> 
      that runs once per day. This applies all updates, and informs 
      <command>rebootmgrd</command> that the machine should be rebooted. You may
      adjust the time when the update runs, see systemd.timer(5). To adjust the
      maintenance window, which is when <command>rebootmgrd</command> reboots the
      system, see rebootmgrd(8).
  </para>
  <para>
   You can disable automatic transactional updates with this command:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.root;<command>systemctl --now disable transactional-update.timer</command></screen>
</sect1>
 
 <sect1>
  <title>The <command>transactional-update</command> command</title>
  <para>
   The <command>transactional-update</command> command enables atomic installation 
   or removal of updates; updates are applied only
   if all of them can be successfully installed.
   <command>transactional-update</command> creates a snapshot of your system
   before the update is applied, and you can restore this snapshot. All changes become 
   active only after reboot.
  </para>

<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><literal>--continue</literal></term>
   <listitem>
     <para>
         The <command>--continue</command> option is for making multiple changes to an
         existing snapshot without rebooting.
     </para>
     <para>
         The default <command>transactional-update</command> behavior 
         is to create a new snapshot from the current root file system. If you
         forget something, such as installing a new package, you have to reboot
         to apply your previous changes, run <command>transactional-update</command>
         again to install the forgotten package, and reboot again. You cannot run the
         <command>transactional-update</command> command multiple times without rebooting
         to add more changes to the snapshot, because that creates separate 
         independent snapshots that do not include changes from the previous snapshots.
     </para>
     <para>
         Use the <command>--continue</command> option to make as many changes as you
         want without rebooting. A separate snapshot is made each time, and each
         snapshot contains all the changes you made in the previous snapshots, plus your 
         new changes. Repeat this process as many times as you want, and when the final
         snapshot includes everything you want reboot the system, and your final snapshot
         becomes the new root file system.
     </para>
     <para>
         Another useful feature of the <command>--continue</command> option is you may
         select any existing snapshot as the base for your new snapshot. The following example
         demonstrates running <command>transactional-update</command> to install a new
         package in a snapshot based on snapshot 13, and then running it again to install 
         another package:
     </para>
     <screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg install <replaceable>package_1</replaceable></command></screen>
    <screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update --continue 13 pkg install <replaceable>package_2</replaceable></command></screen>
    <para>
        The <command>--continue [num]</command> option calls <command>snapper create --from</command>,
        see <xref linkend="sec-snapper-manage-create"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><literal>cleanup</literal></term>
   <listitem>
  <para>
    If the current root file system is identical to the active root
    file system (after a reboot, before <command>transactional-update</command>
    creates a new snapshot with updates), all old snapshots without a
    cleanup algorithm get a cleanup algorithm set. This ensures that old 
    snapshots will be deleted by Snapper. (See the section about cleanup 
    algorithms in snapper(8).) This also removes all unreferenced (and thus 
    unused) <filename>/etc</filename> overlay directories in 
    <filename>/var/lib/overlay</filename>:
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update cleanup</command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>  
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>pkg in/install</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Installs individual packages from the available channels using the
      <command>zypper install</command> command. This command can also be used
      to install Program Temporary Fix (PTF) RPM files.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg install <replaceable>package_name</replaceable></command></screen>
     <para>
      or
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg install <replaceable>rpm1 rpm2</replaceable></command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>pkg rm/remove</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Removes individual packages from the active snapshot using the
      <command>zypper remove</command> command. This command can also be used
      to remove PTF RPM files.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg remove <replaceable>package_name</replaceable></command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>pkg up/update</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Updates individual packages from the active snapshot using the
      <command>zypper update</command> command. Only packages that are part of
      the snapshot of the base file system can be updated.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg remove <replaceable>package_name</replaceable></command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>up/update</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If there are new updates available, a new snapshot is created and
      <command>zypper up/update</command> updates the snapshot.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update up</command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>dup</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If there are new updates available, a new snapshot is created and
      <command>zypper dup –no-allow-vendor-change</command> updates the
      snapshot. The snapshot is activated afterwards and becomes the new root
      file system after reboot.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update dup</command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>patch</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If there are new updates available, a new snapshot is created and
      <command>zypper patch</command> updates the snapshot.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update patch</command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>rollback</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This sets the default subvolume. On systems with a read-write file system
      <command>snapper rollback</command> is called. On a read-only file system
      and without any argument, the current system is set to a new default root
      file system. If you specify a number, that snapshot is used as the
      default root file system. On a read-only file system, it does not create
      any additional snapshots.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update rollback <replaceable>snapshot_number</replaceable></command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>grub.cfg</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This creates a new GRUB2 configuration. Sometimes it is necessary to
      adjust the boot configuration, for example adding additional kernel
      parameters. Edit <replaceable>/etc/default/grub</replaceable>, run
      <command>transactional-update grub.cfg</command>, and then reboot to
      activate the change. You must immediately reboot, or the new GRUB2
      configuration will be overwritten with the default by the next
      transactional-update.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update grub.cfg</command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>reboot</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This parameter triggers a reboot after the action is completed.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update <replaceable>dup</replaceable> reboot</command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>--help</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This prints a help screen with options and subcommands.
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update --help</command></screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-tu-troubleshooting">
  <title>Troubleshooting</title>

  <para>
   If the upgrade fails, run <command>supportconfig</command> to collect log
   data. Provide the resulting files, including
   <filename>/var/log/transactional-update.log</filename> to &suse; Support.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
