<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!-- fs 2010-04-26:
     First draft. There is possibly room for improvement e.g. by being more
     verbose ...
-->
<chapter id="cha.tuning.basics">
<!-- fs 2010-04-26: Better title? -->
 <title>General Notes on System Tuning</title>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   This manual discusses how to find the reasons for performance problems and
   provides means to solve these problems. Before you start tuning your
   system, you should make sure you have ruled out common problems and have
   found the cause for the problem. You should also have a detailed plan on
   how to tune the system, because applying random tuning tips often will not
   help and could make things worse.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <procedure>
  <title>General Approach When Tuning a System</title>
  <step>
   <para>
    Specify the problem that needs to be solved.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    In case the degradation is new, identify any recent changes to the system.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step id="st.tuning.basics.whyproblem">
   <para>
    Identify why the issue is considered a performance problem.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Specify a metric that can be used to analyze performance. This metric could
    for example be latency, throughput, the maximum number of simultaneously
    logged-in users, or the maximum number of active users.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Measure current performance using the metric from the previous step.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Identify the subsystem(s) where the application is spending the most time.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para/>
   <substeps>
    <step>
     <para>
      Monitor the system and/or the application.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Analyze the data, categorize where time is being spent.
     </para>
    </step>
   </substeps>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Tune the subsystem identified in the previous step.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Remeasure the current performance without monitoring using the same
    metric as before.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    If performance is still not acceptable, start over with
    <xref linkend="st.tuning.basics.whyproblem"/>.
   </para>
  </step>
</procedure>

 <sect1 id="sec.tuning.basics.what">
  <title>Be Sure What Problem to Solve</title>

  <para>
   Before starting to tuning a system, try to describe the problem as exact
   as possible. A statement like <quote>The system is slow!</quote> is not a
   helpful problem description. For example, it could make a difference
   whether the system speed needs to be improved in general or only at peak
   times.
  </para>

  <para>
   Furthermore, make sure you can apply a measurement to your problem,
   otherwise you will not be able to verify if the tuning was a success or
   not. You should always be able to compare <quote>before</quote> and
   <quote>after</quote>. Which metrics to use depends on the scenario or
   application you are looking into.  Relevant Web server metrics, for
   example, could be expressed in terms of
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Latency</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The time to deliver a page throughput, measured in pages per second or
      megabytes per second
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Active Users</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The maximum number of users that can be downloading pages while still
      receive pages within an acceptable latency
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.tuning.basics.common">
  <title>Rule Out Common Problems</title>

  <para>
   A performance problem often is caused by network or hardware problems,
   bugs, or configuration issues. Make sure to rule out problems such as the
   ones listed below before attempting to tune your system:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check the output of the &systemd; journal (see <xref
     linkend="cha.journalctl"/> for unusual entries.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check (using <command>top</command> or <command>ps</command>) whether a
     certain process misbehaves by eating up unusual amounts of CPU time or
     memory.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check for network problems by inspecting
     <filename>/proc/net/dev</filename>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In case of I/O problems with physical disks, make sure it is not caused
     by hardware problems (check the disk with the
     <systemitem>smartmontools</systemitem>) or by a full disk.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Ensure that background jobs are scheduled to be carried out in times
     the server load is low. Those jobs should also run with low priority
     (set via <command>nice</command>).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If the machine runs several services using the same resources, consider
     moving services to another server.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Last, make sure your software is up-to-date.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.tuning.basics.bottleneck">
  <title>Finding the Bottleneck</title>

  <para>
   Finding the bottleneck very often is the hardest part when tuning a
   system. &productname; offers many tools to help you with this task.
   See <xref linkend="part.tuning.monitoring"/> for detailed information on
   general system monitoring applications and log file analysis. If the
   problem requires a long-time in-depth analysis, the Linux kernel offers
   means to perform such analysis. See
   <xref linkend="part.tuning.kerneltrace"/> for coverage.
  </para>

  <para>
   Once you have collected the data, it needs to be analyzed. First, inspect
   if the server's hardware (memory, CPU, bus) and its I/O capacities (disk,
   network) are sufficient. If these basic conditions are met, the system
   might benefit from tuning.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.tuning.basics.tuning">
  <title>Step-by-step Tuning</title>

  <para>
   Make sure to carefully plan the tuning itself. It is of vital importance
   to only do one step at a time. Only by doing so you will be able to
   measure if the change provided an improvement or even had a negative
   impact. Each tuning activity should be measured over a sufficient time
   period in order to ensure you can do an analysis based on significant
   data. If you cannot measure a positive effect, do not make the change
   permanent. Chances are, that it might have a negative effect in the
   future.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
