<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.uefi">
 <title>UEFI (Unified Extensible Firmware Interface)</title>
 <para>
  UEFI (Unified Extensible Firmware Interface) is the interface between the
  firmware that comes with the system hardware, all the hardware components
  of the system, and the operating system.
 </para>
 <para>
  UEFI is becoming more and more available on PC systems and thus is
  replacing the traditional PC-BIOS. UEFI, for example, properly supports
  64-bit systems and offers secure booting (<quote>Secure Boot</quote>,
  firmware version 2.3.1c or better required), which is one of its most
  important features. Lastly, with UEFI a standard firmware will
  become available on all x86 platforms.
 </para>
 <para>
  UEFI additionally offers the following advantages:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Booting from large disks (over 2 TiB) with a GUID Partition Table (GPT).
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    CPU-independent architecture and drivers.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Flexible pre-OS environment with network capabilities.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    CSM (Compatibility Support Module) to support booting legacy operating
    systems via a PC-BIOS-like emulation.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  For more information, see
  <ulink
url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unified_Extensible_Firmware_Interface"/>.
  The following sections are not meant as a general UEFI overview; these are
  just hints about how some features are implemented in &sle;.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.uefi.secboot">
  <title>Secure Boot</title>

<!-- # http://www.suse.com/blogs/uefi-secure-boot-overview/ -->

  <para>
   In the world of UEFI, securing the bootstrapping process means
   establishing a chain of trust. The <quote>platform</quote> is the root of
   this chain of trust; in the context of &sle;, the motherboard and the
   on-board firmware could be considered the <quote>platform</quote>. Or,
   put slightly differently, it is the hardware vendor, and the chain of
   trust flows from that hardware vendor to the component manufacturers, the
   OS vendors, etc.
  </para>

  <para>
   The trust is expressed via public key cryptography. The hardware vendor
   puts a so-called Platform Key (PK) into the firmware, representing the
   root of trust. The trust relationship with operating system vendors and
   others is documented by signing their keys with the Platform Key.
  </para>

  <para>
   Finally, security is established by requiring that no code will be
   executed by the firmware unless it has been signed by one of these
   <quote>trusted</quote> keys&mdash;be it an OS boot loader, some driver
   located in the flash memory of some PCI Express card or on disk, or be it
   an update of the firmware itself.
  </para>

  <para>
   Essentially, if you want to use Secure Boot, you need to have your OS
   loader signed with a key trusted by the firmware, and you need the OS
   loader to verify that the kernel it loads can be trusted.
  </para>

  <para>
<!-- WP, re-phrased -->
   Key Exchange Keys (KEK) can be added to the UEFI key database. This way,
   you can use other certificates, as long as they are signed with the
   private part of the PK.
<!-- but they must still
have a connection to the private portion of the Platform key.-->
  </para>

  <sect2>
   <title>Implementation on SUSE Linux Enterprise</title>
   <para>
    Microsoft’s Key Exchange Key (KEK) is installed by default.
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>GUID Partitioning Table (GPT) Required</title>
    <para>
     The Secure Boot feature requires that a GUID Partitioning Table (GPT)
     replaces the old partitioning with a Master Boot Record (MBR).
    </para>
    <para>
     If &yast; detects EFI mode during the installation, it will try to create
     a GPT partition. UEFI expects to find the EFI programs on a FAT-formatted
     EFI System Partition (ESP).
    </para>
   </note>
<!-- http://www.suse.com/blogs/uefi-secure-boot-plan/ -->
   <para>
    Supporting UEFI Secure Boot essentially requires having a boot loader
    with a digital signature that the firmware recognizes as a trusted key.
    In order to be useful to &sle; customers, that key is trusted by the
    firmware a priori, without requiring any manual intervention.
   </para>
   <para>
    There are two ways of getting there. One is to work with hardware
    vendors to have them endorse a SUSE key, which SUSE then signs the boot
    loader with. The other way is to go through Microsoft’s Windows Logo
    Certification program to have the boot loader certified and have
    Microsoft recognize the SUSE signing key (that is, have it signed with
    their KEK). By now, SUSE got the loader signed by UEFI Signing Service
    (that is Microsoft in this case).
   </para>
<!-- We are currently evaluating both approaches, and may eventually
even pursue both in parallel. -->
   <figure id="fig.uefi.secure.boot.mok2">
    <title>UEFI: Secure Boot Process</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="uefi-secure-boot-mok2.png" width="50%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="uefi-secure-boot-mok2.png" width="80%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    At the implementation layer, SUSE uses the <systemitem>shim</systemitem>
    loader&mdash;it is a smart solution that avoids legal issues, and
    simplifies the certification and signing step considerably. The
    <systemitem>shim</systemitem> loader’s job is to load a boot loader
    such as &elilo; or &grub; and verify it; this boot loader in turn will
    load kernels signed by a SUSE key only. SUSE provides this functionality
    since SLE11 SP3 on fresh installations with UEFI Secure Boot enabled.
   </para>
<!-- 2013-03-28 rw does not want to talk about this -->
<!--
   <note>
    <title>The &grub; UEFI Module</title>
    <para>
     In SP3 a &grub; UEFI module is in place, which is actually used
     via an &elilo; compatibility layer.  In the following this is meant,
     if the term <quote>&grub;</quote> is used for short.
    </para>
   </note>
   -->
<!--
http://www.suse.com/blogs/uefi-secure-boot-details/
   -->
   <para>
    There are two types of trusted users:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      First, those who hold the keys. The Platform Key (PK) allows almost
      everything. The Key Exchange Key (KEK) allows all a PK can except
      changing the PK.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Second, anyone with physical access to the machine. A user with
      physical access can reboot the machine, and configure UEFI.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    UEFI offers two types of variables to fulfill the needs of those users:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The first is the so-called <quote>Authenticated Variables</quote>,
      which can be updated from both within the boot process (the so-called
      Boot Services Environment) and the running OS, but only when the new
      value of the variable is signed with the same key that the old value
      of the variable was signed with. And they can only be appended to or
      changed to a value with a higher serial number.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The second is the so-called <quote>Boot Services Only
      Variables</quote>. These variables are accessible to any code that
      runs during the boot process. After the boot process ends and before
      the OS starts, the boot loader must call the
      <literal>ExitBootServices</literal> call. After that, these variables
      are no longer accessible, and the OS cannot touch them.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    The various UEFI key lists are of the first type, as this allows online
    updating, adding, and blacklisting of keys, drivers, and firmware
    fingerprints. It is the second type of variable, the <quote>Boot
    Services Only Variable</quote>, that helps to implement Secure Boot, in
    a matter that is both secure and open source friendly, and thus
    compatible with GPLv3.
   </para>
   <para>
    SUSE starts with <systemitem>shim</systemitem>&mdash;a small and simple
    EFI boot loader&mdash;which was originally developed by Fedora. It is
    signed by a certificate signed by the SUSE KEK and a Microsoft-issued
    certificate, based on which KEKs are available in the UEFI key database
    on the system.
   </para>
   <para>
    This allows <systemitem>shim</systemitem> to load and execute.
   </para>
   <para>
    <systemitem>shim</systemitem> then goes on to verify that the boot
    loader it wants to load is trusted.
<!-- ??? It will not use the SUSE KEK nor the
Microsoft certificate for this. -->
    In a default situation <systemitem>shim</systemitem> will use an
    independent SUSE certificate embedded in its body. In addition,
    <systemitem>shim</systemitem> will allow to <quote>enroll</quote>
    additional keys, overriding the default SUSE key. In the following, we
    call them <quote>Machine Owner Keys</quote> or MOKs for short.
   </para>
   <para>
    Next the boot loader will verify and then boot the kernel, and the
    kernel will do the same on the modules.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>MOK (Machine Owner Key)</title>
<!-- <para>
Enroll key from the OS (with a password for MOK list), using mokutils tool.
Rebooted is required, where <systemitem>shim</systemitem> will check password: ensure physical user is present. 
This key is added to MOK list, saved into in an UEFI Boot Service Only Variable and will be used for future boots to ensure key is not modified.
MOK list can only be modified in Secure Boot phase (before kernel is started).
Enroll can also be done at boot time if key is available on EFI System
Partition.
</para>
-->
   <para>
    If the user (<quote>machine owner</quote>) wants to replace any
    components of the boot process, Machine Owner Keys (MOKs) are to be
    used. The <systemitem>mokutils</systemitem> tool will help with signing
    components and managing MOKs.
   </para>
   <para>
    The enrollment process begins with rebooting the machine and
    interrupting the boot process (for example, pressing a key) when
    <systemitem>shim</systemitem> loads. <systemitem>shim</systemitem> will
    then go into enrollment mode, allowing the user to replace the default
    SUSE key with keys from a file on the boot partition. If the user
    chooses to do so, <systemitem>shim</systemitem> will then calculate a
    hash of that file and put the result in a <quote>Boot Services
    Only</quote> variable. This allows <systemitem>shim</systemitem> to
    detect any change of the file made outside of Boot Services and thus
    avoid tampering with the list of user-approved MOKs.
   </para>
   <para>
    All of this happens during boot time&mdash;only verified code is
    executing now. Therefore, only a user present at the console can use the
    machine owner's set of keys. It cannot be malware or a hacker with
    remote access to the OS because hackers or malware can only change the
    file, but not the hash stored in the <quote>Boot Services Only</quote>
    variable.
   </para>
   <para>
    The boot loader, once loaded and verified by
    <systemitem>shim</systemitem>, will call back to
    <systemitem>shim</systemitem> when it wants to verify the
    kernel&mdash;to avoid duplication of the verification code.
    <systemitem>Shim</systemitem> will use the same list of MOKs for this
    and tell the boot loader whether it can load the kernel.
   </para>
   <para>
    This way, you can install your own kernel or boot loader. It is only
    necessary to install a new set of keys and authorize them by being
    physically present during the first reboot. Because MOKs are a list and
    not just a single MOK, you can make <systemitem>shim</systemitem> trust
    keys from several different vendors, allowing dual- and multi-boot from
    the boot loader.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Booting a Custom Kernel</title>
   <para>
    The following is based on
    <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/openSUSE:UEFI#Booting_a_custom_kernel"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Secure Boot does not prevent you from using a self-compiled kernel. You
    just must sign it with your own certificate and make that certificate
    known to the firmware or MOK.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Create a custom X.509 key and certificate used for signing:
     </para>
<screen>openssl req -new -x509 -newkey rsa:2048 -keyout key.asc \
  -out cert.pem -nodes -days 666 -subj "/CN=$USER/"</screen>
     <para>
<!-- bnc#811869 -->
      For more information about creating certificates, see
      <ulink
     url="http://en.opensuse.org/openSUSE:UEFI_Image_File_Sign_Tools#Create_Your_Own_Certificate"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Package the key and the certificate as a PKCS#12 structure:
     </para>
<screen>openssl pkcs12 -export -inkey key.asc -in cert.pem \
  -name kernel_cert -out cert.p12</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Generate an NSS database for use with <command>pesign</command>:
     </para>
<screen>certutil -d . -N</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Import the key and the certificate contained in PKCS#12 into the NSS
      database:
     </para>
<screen>pk12util -d . -i cert.p12</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      <quote>Bless</quote> the kernel with the new signature using
      <command>pesign</command>:
     </para>
<screen>pesign -n . -c kernel_cert -i arch/x86/boot/bzImage \
  -o vmlinuz.signed -s</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      List the signatures on the kernel image:
     </para>
<screen>pesign -n . -S -i vmlinuz.signed</screen>
     <para>
      At that point, you can install the kernel in
      <filename>/boot</filename> as usual. Because the kernel now has a
      custom signature the certificate used for signing needs to be imported
      into the UEFI firmware or MOK.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Convert the certificate to the DER format for import into the firmware
      or MOK:
     </para>
<screen>openssl x509 -in cert.pem -outform der -out cert.der</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Copy the certificate to the ESP for easier access:
     </para>
<screen>sudo cp cert.der /boot/efi/</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use <command>mokutil</command> to launch the MOK list automatically.
     </para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>
        Import the certificate to MOK:
       </para>
<screen>mokutil --root-pw --import cert.der</screen>
       <para>
        The <option>--root-pw</option> option enables usage of the
        &rootuser; user directly.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Check the list of certificates that are prepared to be enrolled:
       </para>
<screen>mokutil --list-new</screen>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Reboot the system; <systemitem>shim</systemitem> should launch
        MokManager. You need to enter the &rootuser; password to confirm the
        import of the certificate to the MOK list.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Check if the newly imported key was enrolled:
       </para>
<screen>mokutil --list-enrolled</screen>
      </step>
     </substeps>
     <substeps>
      <step>
     <para>
      Alternatively, this is the procedure if you want to launch MOK
      manually:
     </para>
       <para>
        Reboot
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        In the &grub; menu press the '<literal>c</literal>' key.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Type:
       </para>
<screen>chainloader $efibootdir/MokManager.efi
boot</screen>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Select <guimenu>Enroll key from disk</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Navigate to the <filename>cert.der</filename> file and press
        <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Follow the instructions to enroll the key. Normally this should be
        pressing '<literal>0</literal>' and then '<literal>y</literal>' to
        confirm.
       </para>
       <para>
        Alternatively, the firmware menu may provide ways to add a new key
        to the Signature Database.
       </para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
   </procedure>
<!--
Booting the Machine without vendor provided Keys

If the firmware menu offers options to reset the keys used for secure boot you may install new PK, KEK and db without Microsoft keys. Import /usr/lib64/efi/shim-opensuse.der into db to make openSUSE kernels boot in that case. The default shim is signed by both Microsoft and openSUSE. Some firmware versions don't support double signing though. In that case install /usr/lib64/efi/shim-opensuse.efi which only has the openSUSE signature as as /boot/efi/EFI/opensuse/shim.efi
-->
<!--
Glossary

PK
    The "Platform Key" typically refers to a certificate installed by the hardware vendor on the machine. To be able to modify the KEK a valid signature of the PK is required. 

KEK
    A valid signature of the "Key Exchange Key" is required to update the signature database. 

db
    The Signature Database contains well known certificates, signatures or hashes of binaries. Only binaries that can be verified using that database are executed by the firmware. A valid signature of the KEK is required to update the Signature Database. 

dbx
    The Forbidden Signatures Database is the opposite of 'db', a blacklist of certificates, signatures and hashes. If a binary matches any of the entries there it cannot be executed. A valid signature of the KEK is required to update the Forbidden Signature Database. 

MOK
    Machine Owner Keys. An extra database of certificates or hashes used by MokManager. MokManager can be used interactively by the user during boot to update MOKs. 
-->
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <!-- 2014-06-03, ke: according to fate#317500 -->
   <title>Features and Limitations</title>
   <para>When booting in Secure Boot mode, the following features apply:</para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Installation to UEFI default boot-loader location,  a mechanism to
      keep or restore the EFI boot entry.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Reboot via UEFI.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Xen hypervisor will boot with UEFI when there is no legacy BIOS to
      fall back to.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      UEFI IPv6 PXE boot support.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      UEFI get videomode support, the kernel is able to retrieve video
      mode from UEFI to configure KMS mode with the same parameters.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      UEFI booting from USB devices is supported.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    When booting in Secure Boot mode, the following limitations apply:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To ensure that Secure Boot cannot be easily circumvented, some kernel
      features are disabled when running under Secure Boot.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <!-- the rest is taken from fate#317500 -->
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Bootloader, kernel, and kernel modules must be signed.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      kexec and kdump are disabled.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Hibernation (suspend on disk) is disabled.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Access to <filename>/dev/kmem</filename> and
      <filename>/dev/mem</filename> is not possible, not even as root user.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Access to the I/O port is not possible, not even as root user. All X11
      graphical drivers must use a kernel driver.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      PCI BAR access through sysfs is not possible.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>custom_method</literal> in ACPI is not available.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      debugfs for asus-wmi module is not available.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      the <literal>acpi_rsdp</literal> parameter does not have any effect on the
      kernel.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
<!--
*** statements
making it harder for attackers to hide a rootkit in the boot chain.


UEFI Specification:

UEFI supports booting from media that contain an UEFI OS loader or an
UEFI-defined System Partition. An UEFI-defined System Partition is
required by UEFI to boot from a block device. UEFI does not require any
change to the first sector of a partition, so it is possible to build
media that will boot on both legacy architectures and UEFI platforms.
-->
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.uefi.moreinfo">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://www.uefi.org"/> &mdash;UEFI home page where you can
     find the current UEFI specifications.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Blog posts by Olaf Kirch and Vojtěch Pavlík (the chapter above is
     heavily based on these posts):
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/blogs/uefi-secure-boot-plan/"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/blogs/uefi-secure-boot-overview/"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/blogs/uefi-secure-boot-details/"/>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/openSUSE:UEFI"/> &mdash;UEFI with
     openSUSE.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
<!--
* Fates
** #313527: [META] [UEFI] Secure Boot for UEFI 2.3.1
   Enthält Verweise auf alle anderen UEFI Features

** #314578: [DOCU] Document current limitations in a UEFI Secure Boot
   Context
   Release Notes
** #314528: [DOCU] update documentation for Secure Boot


osc -A https://api.suse.de sr -m"Update text and image files" home:keichwa:branches:Devel:WebYaST:1.3 webyast-user_en Devel:WebYaST:1.3
-->
</chapter>
