<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-virt-help">
 <title>Integrated help and package documentation</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  The various virtualization packages provide commands for managing many aspects
  of a virtualization host. It is not possible or expected to remember all
  options supported by these commands. A base installation of a &xen; or &kvm;
  host includes man pages and integrated help for shell commands. The
  documentation sub-packages provide additional content beyond what is provided
  by the base installation.
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Man pages for shell commands</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Most commands include a man page that provides detailed information about
     the command, describes any options, and in some cases gives example command
     usage. For example, to see the manual for the <command>virt-install</command>
     command type
    </para>
<screen>man virt-install</screen>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Integrated help for shell commands</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Commands also include integrated help, providing more compact and topic-driven
     documentation. For example to see a brief description of the
     <command>virt-install</command> command type
    </para>
    <screen>virt-install --help</screen>
    <para>
     Integrated help can also be used to see the details of a specific option. For
     example, to see the sub-options supported by the disk option type
    </para>
<screen>virt-install --disk help</screen>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Documentation sub-packages</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Many of the virtualization packages provide additional content in their
     documentation sub-package. As an example, the libvirt-doc package contains
     all of the documentation available at libvirt.org, plus sample code
     demonstrating use of the libvirt C API. <command>rpm</command> can be used
     to view the contents of a documentation sub-package. For example to see the
     contents of libvirt-doc
    </para>
<screen>rpm -ql libvirt-doc</screen>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
</chapter>
