<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-virt-logs">
 <title>Gathering system information and logs</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  When a virtualization host encounters a problem, it is often necessary to
  collect a detailed system report, which can be done with the help of the
  <command>supportconfig</command> tool. See <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/&product-dsc-url-substring;/html/SLES-all/cha-adm-support.html"/>
  for more information about <command>supportconfig</command>.
 </para>
 <para>
  In some cases, the information gathered by <command>supportconfig</command>
  is insufficient, and logs generated from a custom logging or debugging
  configuration might be required to determine the cause of a problem.
 </para>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-logs-libvirt">
  <title>&libvirt; log controls</title>

  <para>
   &libvirt; provides logging facilities for both the library and the daemon.
   The behavior of the logging facility is controlled by adjusting the log level,
   filter, and output settings.
  </para>
  
<variablelist>
 <varlistentry>
  <term>Log level</term>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    &libvirt; log messages are classified into four priority levels: DEBUG,
    INFO, WARNING, and ERROR. The DEBUG level is very verbose and capable of
    generating gigabytes of information in a short time. The volume of log
    messages progressively decreases with the INFO, WARNING, and ERROR log
    levels. ERROR is the default log level.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 <varlistentry>
  <term>Log filters</term>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Log filters provide a way to log only messages matching a specific
    component and log level. Log filters allow collecting the verbose DEBUG
    log messages of specific components, but only ERROR level log messages from
    the rest of the system. By default, no log filters are defined.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 <varlistentry>
  <term>Log outputs</term>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Log outputs allow specifying where the filtered log messages are sent.
    Messages can be sent to a file, the standard error stream of the process,
    or journald. By default, filtered log messages are sent to journald.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
  <para>
   See <link xlink:href="https://libvirt.org/logging.html"/> for more details
   on &libvirt;'s log controls.
  </para>

  <para>
   A default &libvirt; installation has the log level set to ERROR, no log filters
   defined, and log outputs set to journald. Log messages from the &libvirt;
   daemon can be viewed with the <command>journalctl</command> command:
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;journalctl --unit libvirtd</screen>
  <para>
   The default log facility settings are fine for normal operations and
   provide useful messages for applications and users of &libvirt;, but
   internal issues often require DEBUG level messages. As an example,
   consider a potential bug in the interaction between &libvirt; and the
   &qemu; monitor. In this case, we only need to see the debug messages of
   the communication between &libvirt; and &qemu;. The following example
   creates a log filter to select debug messages from the &qemu; driver
   and send them to a file named <filename>/tmp/libvirtd.log</filename>
  </para>
<screen>
   log_filters="1:qemu.qemu_monitor_json"
   log_outputs="1:file:/tmp/libvirtd.log"
</screen>
  <para>
   Log controls for the &libvirt; daemon can be found in
   <filename>/etc/libvirt/libvirtd.conf</filename>. The daemon must be
   restarted after making any changes to the configuration file.
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;systemctl restart libvirtd.service</screen>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
