<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="app.vmdp.driver">
 <title>Virtual Machine Drivers</title>
 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
        </dm:bugtracker>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <para>
  Virtualization allows the consolidation of workloads on newer, more
  powerful, energy-efficient hardware. Paravirtualized operating systems
  such as &productnamereg; and other Linux distributions are aware of the
  underlying virtualization platform, and can therefore interact efficiently
  with it. Unmodified operating systems such as Microsoft Windows* are
  unaware of the virtualization platform and expect to interact directly
  with the hardware. Because this is not possible when consolidating
  servers, the hardware must be emulated for the operating system. Emulation
  can be slow, but it is especially troubling for high-throughput disk and
  network subsystems. Most performance loss occurs in this area.
 </para>
 <para>
  The &sle; Virtual Machine Driver Pack (VMDP) contains 32-bit and 64-bit
  paravirtualized network, bus and block drivers for several Microsoft
  Windows operating systems. These drivers bring many of the performance
  advantages of paravirtualized operating systems to unmodified operating
  systems: Only the paravirtualized device driver (not the rest of
  the operating system) is aware of the virtualization platform. For
  example, a paravirtualized disk device driver appears as a normal,
  physical disk to the operating system. However, the device driver
  interacts directly with the virtualization platform (with no emulation). This
  helps to efficiently deliver disk access, allowing the disk and network subsystems
  to operate at near native speeds in a virtualized environment, without
  requiring changes to existing operating systems.
 </para>
 <para>
  The &slereg; Virtual Machine Driver Pack is available as an add-on
  product for &productname;. For detailed information refer to
  <link xlink:href="http://www.suse.com/products/vmdriverpack/"/>.
 </para>
 <para>
  Refer to the Official VMDP Installation Guide at
  <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/documentation/sle-vmdp-22/"/> for
  more information.
 </para>
</appendix>
