<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.vnc">
 <title>Remote Access with VNC</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker/>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    Virtual Network Computing (VNC) enables you to control a remote computer
    via a graphical desktop (as opposed to a remote shell access). VNC is
    platform-independent and lets you access the remote machine from any
    operating system.
   </para>
   <para>
    &productname; supports two different kinds of VNC sessions: One-time
    sessions that <quote>live</quote> as long as the VNC connection from the
    client is kept up, and persistent sessions that <quote>live</quote>
    until they are explicitly terminated.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>
 <note>
  <title>Session Types</title>
  <para>
   A machine can offer both kinds of sessions simultaneously on different
   ports, but an open session cannot be converted from one type to the
   other.
  </para>
 </note>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.vnc.one-time">
  <title>One-time VNC Sessions</title>

  <para>
   A one-time session is initiated by the remote client. It starts a
   graphical login screen on the server. This way you can choose the user
   which starts the session and, if supported by the login manager, the
   desktop environment. When you terminate the client connection to such a
   VNC session, all applications started within that session will be
   terminated, too. One-time VNC sessions cannot be shared, but it is
   possible to have multiple sessions on a single host at the same time.
  </para>

  <procedure xml:id="pro.vnc.one-time.activate">
   <title>Enabling One-time VNC Sessions</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start <menuchoice> <guimenu>&yast;</guimenu> <guimenu>Network
     Services</guimenu> <guimenu>Remote Administration (VNC)</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Check <guimenu>Allow Remote Administration</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If necessary, also check <guimenu>Open Port in Firewall</guimenu> (for
     example, when your network interface is configured to be in the
     External Zone). If you have more than one network interface, restrict
     opening the firewall ports to a specific interface via
     <guimenu>Firewall Details</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Confirm your settings with <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In case not all needed packages are available yet, you need to approve
     the installation of missing packages.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.vnc.one-time.configs">
   <title>Available Configurations</title>
   <para>
    The default configuration on &productname; serves sessions with a
    resolution of 1024x768 pixels at a color depth of 16-bit. The sessions
    are available on ports <systemitem class="resource">5901</systemitem>
    for <quote>regular</quote> VNC viewers (equivalent to VNC display
    <literal>1</literal>) and on port
    <systemitem class="resource">5801</systemitem> for Web browsers.
   </para>
   <para>
    Other configurations can be made available on different
    ports<phrase os="sles;osuse">, see
    <xref linkend="sec.vnc.one-time.config"/></phrase>.<phrase os="sled">
    Ask your system administrator for details if you need to modify the
    configuration.</phrase>
   </para>
   <para>
    VNC display numbers and X display numbers are independent in one-time
    sessions. A VNC display number is manually assigned to every
    configuration that the server supports (:1 in the example above).
    Whenever a VNC session is initiated with one of the configurations, it
    automatically gets a free X display number.
   </para>
   <para>
    By default, both the VNC client and server try to communicate securely
    via a self-signed SSL certificate, which is generated after
    installation. You can either use the default one, or replace it with your
    own. When using the self-signed certificate, you need to confirm its
    signature before the first connection&mdash;both in the VNC viewer and
    the Web browser. The Java client is served over HTTPS, using the same
    certificate as VNC.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.vnc.one-time.connect">
   <title>Initiating a One-time VNC Session</title>
   <para>
    To initiate a one-time VNC session, a VNC viewer must be installed on
    the client machine. The standard viewer on &suse; Linux products is
    <command>vncviewer</command>, provided by the package
    <systemitem class="resource">tigervnc</systemitem>. You may also view a
    VNC session using your Web browser and a Java applet.
   </para>
   <para>
    To start your VNC viewer and initiate a session with the server's
    default configuration, use the command:
   </para>
<screen>vncviewer &wsIname;:1</screen>
   <para>
    Instead of the VNC display number you can also specify the port number
    with two colons:
   </para>
<screen>vncviewer &wsIname;::5901</screen>
   <para>
    Alternatively use a Java-capable Web browser to view the VNC session by
    entering the following URL: <literal>http://&wsIname;:5801</literal>
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.vnc.one-time.config">
   <title>Configuring One-time VNC Sessions</title>
   <para>
    You can skip this section, if you do not need or want to modify the
    default configuration.
   </para>
   <para>
    One-time VNC sessions are started via the
    <systemitem class="daemon">xinetd</systemitem> daemon. A configuration
    file is located at <filename>/etc/xinetd.d/vnc</filename>. By default it
    offers six configuration blocks: three for VNC viewers
    (<literal>vnc1</literal> to <literal>vnc3</literal>), and three serving
    a Java applet (<literal>vnchttpd1</literal> to
    <literal>vnchttpd3</literal>). By default only <literal>vnc1</literal>
    and <literal>vnchttpd1</literal> are active.
   </para>
   <para>
    To activate a configuration, comment the line <literal>disable =
    yes</literal> with a <literal>#</literal> character in the first column,
    or remove that line completely. To deactivate a configuration uncomment
    or add that line.
   </para>
   <para>
    The <command>Xvnc</command> server can be configured via the
    <literal>server_args</literal> option&mdash;see <command>Xnvc
    --help</command> for a list of options.
   </para>
   <para>
    When adding custom configurations, make sure they are not using ports
    that are already in use by other configurations, other services, or
    existing persistent VNC sessions on the same host.
   </para>
   <para>
    Activate configuration changes by entering the following command:
   </para>
<screen>sudo rcxinetd reload</screen>
<!--taroth 2014-03-19: systemd - according to fcrozat, xinetd is *not* managed by
    systemd, so let's keep this rc* command for now...
<screen>sudo systemctl reload xinetd</screen>-->
   <important>
    <title>Firewall and VNC Ports</title>
    <para>
     When activating Remote Administration as described in
     <xref linkend="pro.vnc.one-time.activate"/>, the ports
     <systemitem class="resource">5801</systemitem> and
     <systemitem class="resource">5901</systemitem> are opened in the
     firewall. If the network interface serving the VNC sessions is
     protected by a firewall, you need to manually open the respective ports
     when activating additional ports for VNC sessions. See
     <xref linkend="cha.security.firewall"/> for instructions.
    </para>
   </important>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.vnc.persistent">
  <title>Persistent VNC Sessions</title>

  <!-- fs 2015-09-10: Commenting all view-only related documentation, since
       this feature does not work on SLE 12 GA/SP1. According to bsc#941307 it
       will be added with SLE 12 SP2.
  -->

  <para>
   A persistent VNC session is initiated on the server. The session and all
   applications started in this session run regardless of client connections
   until the session is terminated.
  </para>

  <para>
   A persistent session can be accessed from multiple clients
   simultaneously. This is ideal for demonstration purposes
   <!-- where one client has full access and all other clients have view-only
        access. Another use case are
   -->
   or for trainings where the trainer might need access to the trainee's
   desktop. However, most of the times you probably do not want to share
   your VNC session.
  </para>

  <para>
   In contrast to one-time sessions that start a display manager, a
   persistent session starts a ready-to-operate desktop that runs as the
   user that started the VNC session. Access to persistent sessions is
   protected by a password.
  </para>
<!--
  <para>
   Access to persistent sessions is protected by two possible types of
   passwords:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     a regular password that grants full access or
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     an optional view-only password that grants a non-interactive
     (view-only) access.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   A session can have multiple client connections of both kinds at once.
  </para>
-->

  <procedure xml:id="pro.vnc.persistent.activate">
   <title>Starting a Persistent VNC Session</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open a shell and make sure you are logged in as the user that should
     own the VNC session.
<!-- max: should we add some more
     words here to explain that the shell session could either be a
     local one or a ssh session, or can we assume this to be known by
     the customer? -->
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If the network interface serving the VNC sessions is protected by a
     firewall, you need to manually open the port used by your session in
     the firewall. If starting multiple sessions you may alternatively open
     a range of ports. See <xref linkend="cha.security.firewall"/> for
     details on how to configure the firewall.
    </para>
    <para>
     <command>vncserver</command> uses the ports
     <systemitem class="resource">5901</systemitem> for display
     <literal>:1</literal>, <systemitem class="resource">5902</systemitem>
     for display <literal>:2</literal>, and so on. For persistent sessions,
     the VNC display and the X display usually have the same number.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To start a session with a resolution of 1024x769 pixel and with a color
     depth of 16-bit, enter the following command:
    </para>
<screen>vncserver -geometry 1024x768 -depth 16</screen>
    <para>
     The <command>vncserver</command> command picks an unused display number
     when none is given and prints its choice. See <command>man 1
     vncserver</command> for more options.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   When running <command>vncviewer</command> for the first time, it asks for
   a password for full access to the session.
   <!--
   If needed, you can also
   provide a password for view-only access to the session.
   -->
  </para>

  <para>
   The password you are providing here is also used for future sessions
   started by the same user. It can be changed with the
   <command>vncpasswd</command> command.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>Security Considerations</title>
   <para>
    Make sure to use strong passwords of significant length (eight or more
    characters). Do not share these passwords.
   </para>
   <para>
    VNC connections are unencrypted, so people who can sniff the network(s)
    between the two machines can read the password when it gets transferred
    at the beginning of a session.
   </para>
  </important>

  <para>
   To terminate the session shut down the desktop environment that runs
   inside the VNC session from the VNC viewer as you would shut it down if
   it was a regular local X session.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you prefer to manually terminate a session, open a shell on the VNC
   server and make sure you are logged in as the user that owns the VNC
   session you want to terminate. Run the following command to terminate the
   session that runs on display <literal>:1</literal>: <command>vncserver
   -kill :1</command>
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.vnc.persistent.connect">
   <title>Connecting to a Persistent VNC Session</title>
   <para>
    To connect to a persistent VNC session, a VNC viewer must be installed.
    The standard viewer on &suse; Linux products is
    <command>vncviewer</command>, provided by the package <systemitem class="resource">tigervnc</systemitem> (default). You may also view a VNC
    session using your Web browser and a Java applet.
   </para>
   <para>
    To start your VNC viewer and connect to display <literal>:1</literal> of
    the VNC server, use the command
   </para>
<screen>vncviewer &wsIname;:1</screen>
   <para>
    Instead of the VNC display number you can also specify the port number
    with two colons:
   </para>
<screen>vncviewer &wsIname;::5901</screen>
   <para>
    Alternatively use a Java-capable Web browser to view the VNC session by
    entering the following URL: <literal>http://&wsIname;:5801</literal>
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.vnc.persistent.configure">
   <title>Configuring Persistent VNC Sessions</title>
   <para>
    Persistent VNC sessions can be configured by editing
    <filename>$HOME/.vnc/xstartup</filename>. By default this shell script
    starts the same GUI/window manager it was started from. In &productname;
    this will either be &gnome; or IceWM. If you want to start your session
    with a window manager of your choice, set the variable
    <envar>WINDOWMANAGER</envar>:
   </para>
<screen>WINDOWMANAGER=gnome vncserver -geometry 1024x768
WINDOWMANAGER=icewm vncserver -geometry 1024x768</screen>
   <note>
    <title>One Configuration for Each User</title>
    <para>
     Persistent VNC sessions are configured in a single per-user
     configuration. Multiple sessions started by the same user will all use
     the same start-up and password files.
    </para>
   </note>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
