<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>

<chapter id="chap.guestfs" lang="en">
 <title>libguestfs</title>
 <para>
  <xref linkend="gloss.vt.vm"/>s consist of disk images and definition
  files. Manually accessing and manipulating these guest components (outside
  of normal hypervisor processes) is possible, but inherently dangerous and
  risks compromising data integrity.  libguestfs is a C library and
  corresponding set of tools designed for safely accessing and modifying <xref
  linkend="gloss.vt.vm"/> disk images - outside of normal hypervisor
  processes, but without the risk normally associated with manual editing.
 </para>
 
 <sect1 id="sec.guestfs.intro">
  <title>&vmguest; Manipulation Overview</title>
  <para></para>
  <sect2 id="sec.guestfs.intro.risk">
   <title>&vmguest; Manipulation Risk</title>
   <para>
    As disk images and definition files are simply another type of file in a
    Linux environment, it is possible to use many different tools to access,
    edit and write to these files. When used correctly, such tools can be an
    important part of guest adminitration. However, even correct usage of
    these tools is not without risk. Some of the risks that should be
    considered when manually manipulating guest disk images include:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Data Corruption</emphasis>: Concurrently accessing images, by
      the host machine or another node in a cluster, can cause changes to be
      lost or data corruption to occur if virtualization protection layers are
      bypassed.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Security</emphasis>:
      Mounting disk images as loop devices requires root access. While an image is loop mounted,
      other users and processes can potentially access the disk contents.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Administrator Error</emphasis>:
      Bypassing virtualization layers correctly requires advanced understanding of virtual
      components and tools. Failing to isolate the images or failing to clean up properly after
      changes have been made can lead to further problems once back in virtualization control.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.guestfs.intro.design">
   <title>libguestfs Design</title>
   <para>
     libguestfs C library has been designed to safely and securely create,
     access and modify virtual machine (&vmguest;) disk images. It also
     provides additional language bindings: for <ulink
     url="http://libguestfs.org/guestfs-perl.3.html">Perl</ulink>, <ulink
     url="http://libguestfs.org/guestfs-python.3.html">Python</ulink>, PHP
     (only for 64-bit machines), and <ulink
     url="http://libguestfs.org/guestfs-ruby.3.html"> Ruby</ulink>.
     libguestfs can access &vmguest; disk images without needing root and with
     multiple layers of defense against rogue disk images.
   </para>
   <para>
    libguestfs provides many different tools designed for accessing and
    modifying &vmguest; disk images and contents. These tools provide such
    capabilities as: viewing and editing files inside guests, scripting
    changes to &vmguest;s, monitoring disk used/free statistics, creating
    guests, doing V2V migrations, performing backups, cloning &vmguest;s,
    formatting disks, and resizing disks.
   </para>
  <warning>
   <title>Best Practices</title>
   <para>
    You must not use libguestfs tools on live virtual machines. Doing so will
    probably result in disk corruption in the &vmguest;. libguestfs tools try to stop
    you from doing this, but cannot catch all cases.
   </para>
   <para>
    However most command have the <option>--ro</option> (read only) option. With this option,
    you can attach a command to a live virtual machine. The results might be strange or
    inconsistent at times but you will not risk disk corruption.
   </para>
  </warning>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.guestfs.package">
  <title>Package Installation</title>
  <para>
   libguestfs is shipped through 3 packages:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     libguestfs0: which provides the main C library
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     guestfs-data: which contains the kernel and initrd used when launching images
     (stored in <filename>/usr/lib64/guestfs</filename>)
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     guestfs-tools: the core guestfs tools, man pages, and the
     <filename>/etc/libguestfs-tools.conf</filename> configuration file.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   To install guestfs tools on your system run:
  </para>
  <screen>zypper in guestfs-tools</screen>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 id="sec.guestfs.tools">
  <title>Guestfs Tools</title>
  <para>
  </para>  
  <sect2 id="sec.guestfs.tools.intro">
   <title>Modifying Virtual Machines</title>
   <para>
    The set of tools found within the guestfs-tools package is used for accessing and modifying
    virtual machine disk images. This functionality is provided through a familiar shell
    interface with built-in safeguards which ensure image integrity. Guestfs tools shells expose
    all capabilities of the guestfs API, and use the kernel and initrd found
    in <filename>/usr/lib4/guestfs</filename>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.guestfs.tools.supportedfs">
   <title>Supported File Systems and Disk Images</title>
   <para>
    Guestfs tools support various file systems including:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Ext2, Ext3, Ext4
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Xfs
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Brtfs
     </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     Multiple disk image formats are also supported:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       raw
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       qcow2
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <warning>
     <title>Unsupported File System</title>
     <para>
      Guestfs may also support Windows* file systems (VFAT, NTFS), BSD* and
      Apple* file systems, and other disk image formats (VMDK,
      VHDX...). However, these file systems and disk image formats are
      unsupported on &sle;.
     </para>
    </warning>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.guestfs.tools.virt-rescue">
   <title><command>virt-rescue</command></title>
   <para>
    <command>virt-rescue</command> is similar to a rescue CD, but for virtual
    machines, and without the need for a CD. virt-rescue presents users with a
    rescue shell and some simple recovery tools which can be used to examine
    and correct problems within a virtual machine or disk image.
   </para>
   <screen>&prompt.user; virt-rescue -a sles.qcow2 
Welcome to virt-rescue, the libguestfs rescue shell.

Note: The contents of / are the rescue appliance.
You have to mount the guest's partitions under /sysroot
before you can examine them. A helper script for that exists:
mount-rootfs-and-do-chroot.sh /dev/sda2

&gt;&lt;rescue&gt; 
[   67.194384] EXT4-fs (sda1): mounting ext3 file system
using the ext4 subsystem
[   67.199292] EXT4-fs (sda1): mounted filesystem with ordered data
mode. Opts: (null)
mount: /dev/sda1 mounted on /sysroot.
mount: /dev bound on /sysroot/dev.
mount: /dev/pts bound on /sysroot/dev/pts.
mount: /proc bound on /sysroot/proc.
mount: /sys bound on /sysroot/sys.
Directory: /root
Thu Jun  5 13:20:51 UTC 2014
(none):~ #
   </screen>
   <para>You are now running the &vmguest; in rescue mode:</para>
   <screen>(none):~ # cat /etc/fstab 
devpts  /dev/pts          devpts  mode=0620,gid=5 0 0
proc    /proc             proc    defaults        0 0
sysfs   /sys              sysfs   noauto          0 0
debugfs /sys/kernel/debug debugfs noauto          0 0
usbfs   /proc/bus/usb     usbfs   noauto          0 0
tmpfs   /run              tmpfs   noauto          0 0
/dev/disk/by-id/ata-QEMU_HARDDISK_QM00001-part1 / ext3 defaults 1 1</screen>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.guestfs.tools.virt-resize">
   <title><command>virt-resize</command></title>
   <para>
    <command>virt-resize</command> is used to resize a virtual machine disk, making it larger
    or smaller overall, and resizing or deleting any partitions contained within.
   </para>
   <procedure id="pro.guestfs.tools.virt-resize">
    <title>Expanding a Disk</title>
    <para>Full step-by-step example: How to expand a virtual machine
    disk</para>
    <step>
     <para>First, with virtual machine powered off, determine the size of the partitions
     available on this virtual machine:
     </para>
     <screen>&prompt.user; virt-filesystems --long --parts --blkdevs -h -a sles.qcow2
Name       Type       MBR  Size  Parent
/dev/sda1  partition  83   16G   /dev/sda
/dev/sda   device     -    16G   -</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      <command>virt-resize</command> cannot do in-place disk
      modifications&mdash;there must be sufficient space to store the resized
      output disk. Use the <command>truncate</command> command to create a
      file of suitable size:
     </para>
     <screen>&prompt.user; truncate -s 32G outdisk.img</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Use <command>virt-resize</command> to resize the disk image.
     <command>virt-resize</command> requires two mandatory parameters for the
     input and output images:
     </para>
     <screen>&prompt.user; virt-resize --expand /dev/sda1 sles.qcow2 outdisk.img
Examining sles.qcow2 ...
**********
Summary of changes:

/dev/sda1: This partition will be resized from 16,0G to 32,0G.  The 
    filesystem ext3 on /dev/sda1 will be expanded using the 'resize2fs' 
    method.

**********
Setting up initial partition table on outdisk.img ...
Copying /dev/sda1 ...
◐ 84%
⟦▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒▒════════⟧ 00:03
Expanding /dev/sda1 using the 'resize2fs' method ...

Resize operation completed with no errors.  Before deleting the old 
disk, carefully check that the resized disk boots and works correctly.</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Confirm the image was resized properly:</para>
     <screen>&prompt.user; virt-filesystems --long --parts --blkdevs -h -a outdisk.img
Name       Type       MBR  Size  Parent
/dev/sda1  partition  83   32G   /dev/sda
/dev/sda   device     -    32G   -</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Bring up the &vmguest; using the new disk image and confirm correct operation before deleting
      the old image.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.guestfs.tools.others">
   <title>Other virt-* Tools</title>
   <para>
    Various other guestfs tools exist to ease administrative tasks&mdash;such as viewing and
    editing files, or obtaining information on the virtual machine.
   </para>
   <sect3 id="sec.guestfs.tools.others.filesystem">
    <title><command>virt-filesystems</command></title>
    <para>
     This tool is used to report information regarding file systems, partitions, and
     logical volumes in a disk image or virtual machine.
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.user; virt-filesystems -l -a sles.qcow2 
Name       Type        VFS   Label  Size         Parent
/dev/sda1  filesystem  ext3  -      17178820608  -</screen>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.guestfs.tools.others.ls">
    <title><command>virt-ls</command></title>
    <para>
     <command>virt-ls</command> lists file names, file sizes, checksums,
     extended attributes and more from a virtual machine or disk image.
     Multiple directory names can be given, in which case the output from each
     is concatenated.  To list directories from a libvirt guest, use the
     <option>-d</option> option to specify the name of the guest. For a disk
     image, use the <option>-a</option> option.
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.user; virt-ls -h -lR -a sles.qcow2 /var/log/ 
d 0755       4,0K /var/log/
d 0700       4,0K /var/log//YaST2
- 0644       1,9K /var/log//YaST2/mkinitrd.log
- 0644        496 /var/log//YaST2/perl-BL-standalone-log
- 0600       3,2K /var/log//faillog
d 0700       4,0K /var/log//krb5
- 0644        29K /var/log//lastlog
- 0644        496 /var/log//pbl.log
- 0664          0 /var/log//wtmp
d 0755       4,0K /var/log//zypp</screen>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.guestfs.tools.others.cat">
    <title><command>virt-cat</command></title>
    <para>
     <command>virt-cat</command> is a command line tool to display the contents of a file
     that exists in the named virtual machine (or disk image).
     Multiple file names can be given, in which case they are concatenated
     together. Each file name must be a full path, starting at the root
     directory (starting with '/').
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.user; virt-cat -a sles.qcow2 /etc/fstab
devpts /dev/pts devpts mode=0620,gid=5 0 0 
proc   /proc    proc   defaults        0 0</screen>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.guestfs.tools.others.df">
    <title><command>virt-df</command></title>
    <para>
     <command>virt-df</command> is a command line tool to display free space on virtual machine
     file systems. Unlike other tools, it doesn't just display the size of disk
     allocated to a virtual machine, but can look inside disk images to show
     how much space is actually being used.
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.user; virt-df -a sles.qcow2 
Filesystem                           1K-blocks       Used  Available  Use%
sles.qcow2:/dev/sda1                  16381864     520564   15022492  4%</screen>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.guestfs.tools.others.edit">
    <title><command>virt-edit</command></title>
    <para>
     <command>virt-edit</command> is a command line tool capable of editing files that reside in
     the named virtual machine (or disk image).
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.guestfs.tools.others.tar">
    <title><command>virt-tar-in/out</command></title>
    <para>
     <command>virt-tar-in</command> unpacks an uncompressed tarball into a virtual machine disk
     image or named libvirt domain.
     <command>virt-tar-out</command> packs a virtual machine disk image directory into a tarball.
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.user; virt-tar-out -a sles.qcow2 /home homes.tar</screen>
   </sect3>   
   <sect3 id="sec.guestfs.tools.others.copy">
    <title><command>virt-copy-in/out</command></title>
    <para>
     <command>virt-copy-in</command> copies files and directories from the local disk into a
     virtual machine disk image or named libvirt domain.
     <command>virt-copy-out</command> copies files and directories out of a virtual
     machine disk image or named libvirt domain.
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.user; virt-copy-in -a sles.qcow2 data.tar /tmp/
virt-ls -a sles.qcow2 /tmp/
.ICE-unix
.X11-unix
data.tar</screen>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.guestfs.guestfish">
   <title><command>guestfish</command></title>
   <para>
    <command>guestfish</command> is a shell and command line tool for examining and modifying
    virtual machine file systems. It uses libguestfs and exposes all of the
    functionality of the guestfs API.
   </para>
   <para>Examples of usage:</para>
   <screen>&prompt.user; guestfish -a disk.img &lt;&lt;EOF
run
list-filesystems
EOF</screen>
<screen>guestfish 

Welcome to guestfish, the guest filesystem shell for
editing virtual machine filesystems and disk images.

Type: 'help' for help on commands
      'man' to read the manual
      'quit' to quit the shell

&gt;&lt;fs&gt; add sles.qcow2
&gt;&lt;fs&gt; run
&gt;&lt;fs&gt; list-filesystems 
/dev/sda1: ext3
&gt;&lt;fs&gt; mount /dev/sda1 /
 cat /etc/fstab 
devpts  /dev/pts          devpts  mode=0620,gid=5 0 0
proc    /proc             proc    defaults        0 0
sysfs   /sys              sysfs   noauto          0 0
debugfs /sys/kernel/debug debugfs noauto          0 0
usbfs   /proc/bus/usb     usbfs   noauto          0 0
tmpfs   /run              tmpfs   noauto          0 0
/dev/disk/by-id/ata-QEMU_HARDDISK_QM00001-part1 / ext3 defaults 1 1</screen>
  </sect2>
  
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.guestfs.trouble">
  <title>Troubleshooting</title>
  <para>
  </para>
  <sect2 id="sec.guestfs.trouble.env">
   <title>Environment</title>
   <para>
    When troubleshooting problems within a libguestfs appliance, the environment variable
    <emphasis>LIBGUESTFS_DEBUG=1</emphasis> can be used to enable debug messages. To output
    each command/API call in a format that is similar to guestfish commands, use the
    environment variable <emphasis>LIBGUESTFS_TRACE=1</emphasis>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.guestfs.trouble.tools">
   <title><command>libguestfs-test-tool</command></title>
   <para>
    <command>libguestfs-test-tool</command> is a test program that checks if basic libguestfs
    functionality is working. It will print a large amount of diagnostic messages and details
    of the guestfs environment, then create a test image and try to start it. If it runs to
    completion successfully, the following message should be seen near the end:
   </para>
   <screen>===== TEST FINISHED OK =====</screen>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.guestfs.external.doc">
  <title>External References</title>
  <para></para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://libguestfs.org">libguestfs.org</ulink>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://libguestfs.org/guestfs-faq.1.html">libguestfs FAQ</ulink>
    </para>
   </listitem>
<!--   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://libguestfs.org/guestfs-release-notes.1.html">guestfs
     release notes</ulink>
    </para>
   </listitem> -->
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
