<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossary PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>

<glossary id="gloss.vt.glossary">
 <title>Glossary</title>
 <glossdiv id="gloss.vt.general">
  <title>General</title>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.vmm">
   <glossterm>Virtual Machine Manager</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     Virtual Machine Manager: A software program included in &yast; that
     provides a graphical user interface for creating and managing virtual
     machines.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.virtualized">
   <glossterm>Virtualized</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A guest operating system or application running on a virtual machine.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.xen">
   <glossterm>&xen;</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     See <xref linkend="cha.xen.basics" xrefstyle="ChapTitleOnPage"/>
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.kvm">
   <glossterm>&kvm;</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     See <xref linkend="cha.kvm.intro" xrefstyle="ChapTitleOnPage"/>
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.xl">
   <glossterm>xl</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A set of commands for &xen; that lets administrators manage virtual
     machines from a command prompt on the host computer.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.domain">
   <glossterm>Domain</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     Domain: A virtual machine. The host operating system is actually a virtual
     machine running in a privileged domain and can be referred to as domain
     0. All other virtual machines on the host run in unprivileged domains and
     can be referred to as domain U's.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.createvm">
   <glossterm>Create Virtual Machine Wizard</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A software program available in &yast; and
     Virtual Machine Manager that provides a graphical interface to guide you
     through the steps to create virtual machines. It can also be run in text
     mode by entering <command>virt-install</command> at a command prompt in the
     host environment.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.hostenv">
   <glossterm>Host Environment</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     The desktop or command line environment that allows
     interaction with the host computer's environment. It provides a command
     line environment and can also include a graphical desktop, such as GNOME
     or IceWM. The host environment runs as a special type of virtual machine
     that has privileges to control and manage other virtual machines. Other
     commonly used terms include domain 0, privileged domain, and host
     operating system.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.hypervisor">
   <glossterm>Hypervisor</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     The software that coordinates the low-level interaction
     between virtual machines and the underlying physical computer
     hardware.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.parafb">
   <glossterm>Paravirtualized Frame Buffer</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     The video output device that drives a video
     display from a memory buffer containing a complete frame of data for
     virtual machine displays running in paravirtual mode.   
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
 </glossdiv>
 <glossdiv id="gloss.vt.network">
  <title>Network</title>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.network.bridgenet">
   <glossterm>Bridged Networking</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A type of network connection that lets a virtual machine be identified on
     an external network as a unique identity that is separate from and
     unrelated to its host computer.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.network.emptybridge">
   <glossterm>Empty Bridge</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A type of network bridge that has no physical network device or virtual
     network device provided by the host. This lets virtual machines
     communicate with other virtual machines on the same host but not with the
     host or on an external network.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.network.externalnet">
   <glossterm>External Network</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     The network outside a host's internal network environment.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.network.internalnetwork">
   <glossterm>Internal Network</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A type of network configuration that restricts virtual
     machines to their host environment.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.network.localbridge">
   <glossterm>Local Bridge</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A type of network bridge that has a virtual network device
     but no physical network device provided by the host. This lets virtual
     machines communicate with the host and other virtual machines on the
     host. Virtual machines can communicate on an external network through the
     host.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.network.nat">
   <glossterm>Network Address Translation (NAT)</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A type of network connection that lets
     a virtual machine use the IP address and MAC address of the host.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.network.nohostbridge">
   <glossterm>No Host Bridge</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A type of network bridge that has a physical network
     device but no virtual network device provided by the host. This lets
     virtual machines communicate on an external network but not with the
     host. This lets you separate virtual machine network communications from
     the host environment.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.network.traditionalbridge">
   <glossterm>Traditional Bridge</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A type of network bridge that has both a physical network device and a
     virtual network device provided by the host
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
 </glossdiv>
 
 <glossdiv id="gloss.vt.storage">
  <title>Storage</title>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.storage.bd">
   <glossterm>Block Device</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     Data storage devices, such as CD-ROM drives or disk drives,
     that move data in the form of blocks. Partitions and volumes are also
     considered block devices.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.storage.fbvd">
   <glossterm>File-Backed Virtual Disk</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A virtual disk based on a file, also called a disk image file.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.storage.rawdisk">
   <glossterm>Raw Disk</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A method of accessing data on a disk at the individual byte
     level instead of through its file system.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.storage.sparse">
   <glossterm>Sparse Image File</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A disk image file that does not reserve its entire
     amount of disk space but expands as data is written to it
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss.vt.storage.xvda">
   <glossterm>xvda</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
    The drive designation given to the first virtual disk on a paravirtual machine
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
 </glossdiv>
 
<glossdiv id="gloss.vt.acronym">
 <title>Virtualization Acronyms</title>
 <glossentry id="gloss.vt.acronym.vmx">
  <glossterm>VMX</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>
    Virtual Machine eXtensions
   </para>
   <para>
    Virtual Machine eXtensions instructions on processors with x86 virtualization
   </para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>
 </glossdiv>
</glossary>

