<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>

<chapter id="chap.virtualization.introduction" lang="en">
 <title>Virtualization Technology</title>
 <para>
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.virtualization.introduction.basics">
  <title>Virtualization Basics</title>
  <para>
   Virtualization is a technology which provides a way for a machine (Host) to
   run another operating system (guest virtual machines) on top of the host
   operating system.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem><para>
    Virtual Machine: A virtualized PC environment capable of hosting a guest
    operating system and associated applications.
   </para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>
    Virtual Machine Host: The physical computer running a &suse;
    virtualization platform software. The virtualization environment consists
    of the hypervisor, the host environment, virtual machines, and associated
    tools, commands, and configuration files. Other commonly used terms
    include host, host computer, host machine, virtual server, and
    virtualization host server.
   </para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>
    Guest Operating System: The operating system that runs on a virtual machine.
   </para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.virtualization.introduction.capabilities">
  <title>Virtualization Capabilities</title>
  <para></para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem><para>
    Server Consolidation: Many server can be replaced by one big physical
    server, so hardware is consolidated, and Guest Operating System are
    converted to virtual machine.
   </para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>
    Isolation: Guest Operating System can be fully isolated from the Host
    running it. So if the virtual machine is corrupted, the Host system is not harmed.
   </para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>
    Migration: A process to move a running virtual machine to another
    physical machines. Live migration is the extended features which allow
    this move without disconnection of the client or the application.
   </para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>
    Disaster recovery: virtualized Guest are less dependent on the
    hardware, and the Host server provides snapshot features to be able 
    to restore a know running system without any corruption.
   </para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>
    Dynamic load balancing: migration feature brings a simple way to load
    balance your service across your infrastructure.
   </para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.virtualization.introduction.benefits">
  <title>Virtualization Benefits</title>
  <para>
   Virtualization brings a lot of advantages while providing the same service
   as Hardware server.
  </para>
  <para>
   First it reduces the cost of your infrastructure. Server are mainly used to
   provide a service to customer, a virtualized operating system can provide
   the same service, with:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem><para>
    less Hardware: You can run several Operating System on one Host, so all
    hardware maintenance will be reduced.
   </para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>
    Less power/cooling: less hardware means you don't need to invest more in
    electric power, backup power, and cooling if you need more service.
   </para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>
    Save space: your data center space will be saved because you don't need
    more hardware server (less server than service running).
   </para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>
    Less management: Using virtualized Guest simplify the administration
    of your infrastructure.
   </para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>
    Agility and productivity: virtualization provides
    <emphasis>migration</emphasis> capabilities, and <emphasis>live
    migration</emphasis>, <emphasis>snapshots</emphasis>, this will reduce
    downtime, and will bring an easy way to move your service from one place
    to another one without any interruption.
   </para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.virtualization.introduction.fvpv">
  <title>Understanding Virtualization Modes</title>
  <para>
   Guest operating systems are hosted on virtual machines in either full
   virtualization mode or paravirtual mode. Each virtualization mode has
   advantages and disadvantages.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Full virtualization mode lets virtual machines run unmodified operating
     systems, such as Windows* Server 2003, but requires the
     computer running as the &vmhost; to support hardware-assisted
     virtualization technology, such as AMD* Virtualization or Intel*
     Virtualization Technology.
    </para>
    <para>
     Some guest operating systems hosted in full virtualization mode, can be
     configured to run the Novell* Virtual Machine Drivers instead of
     drivers originating from the operating system. Running virtual machine
     drivers improves performance dramatically on guest operating systems,
     such as Windows Server 2003. For more information, see
     <xref linkend="app.vmdp.driver" xrefstyle="ChapTitleOnPage"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Paravirtual mode does not require the host computer to support
     hardware-assisted virtualization technology, but does require the guest
     operating system to be modified for the virtualization environment.
     Typically, operating systems running in paravirtual mode enjoy better
     performance than those requiring full virtualization mode.
    </para>
    <para>
     Operating systems currently modified to run in paravirtual mode are
     referred to as <emphasis>paravirtualized operating systems</emphasis>
     and include &productname; 11 and NetWare® 6.5 SP8.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
