<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>

<chapter id="chap.virtualization.introduction" lang="en">
 <title>Virtualization Technology</title>
 <para>
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.virtualization.introduction.basics">
  <title>Virtualization Basics</title>
  <para>
   Virtualization is a technology which provides a way for a machine (Host) to
   run another operating system (guest virtual machines) on top of the host
   operating system.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem><para>
    Virtual Machine: A virtualized PC environment capable of hosting a guest
    operating system and associated applications.
   </para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>
    Virtual Machine Host: The physical computer running a &suse;
    virtualization platform software. The virtualization environment consists
    of the hypervisor, the host environment, virtual machines, and associated
    tools, commands, and configuration files. Other commonly used terms
    include host, host computer, host machine, virtual server, and
    virtualization host server.
   </para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>
    Guest Operating System: The operating system that runs on a virtual machine.
   </para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 id="sec.virtualization.introduction.fvpv">
  <title>Understanding Virtualization Modes</title>
  <para>
   Guest operating systems are hosted on virtual machines in either full
   virtualization mode or paravirtual mode. Each virtualization mode has
   advantages and disadvantages.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Full virtualization mode lets virtual machines run unmodified operating
     systems, such as Windows* Server 2003, but requires the
     computer running as the &vmhost; to support hardware-assisted
     virtualization technology, such as AMD* Virtualization or Intel*
     Virtualization Technology.
    </para>
    <para>
     Some guest operating systems hosted in full virtualization mode, can be
     configured to run the Novell* Virtual Machine Drivers instead of
     drivers originating from the operating system. Running virtual machine
     drivers improves performance dramatically on guest operating systems,
     such as Windows Server 2003. For more information, see
     <xref linkend="cha.xen.driver" xrefstyle="ChapTitleOnPage"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Paravirtual mode does not require the host computer to support
     hardware-assisted virtualization technology, but does require the guest
     operating system to be modified for the virtualization environment.
     Typically, operating systems running in paravirtual mode enjoy better
     performance than those requiring full virtualization mode.
    </para>
    <para>
     Operating systems currently modified to run in paravirtual mode are
     referred to as <emphasis>paravirtualized operating systems</emphasis>
     and include &productname; 11 and NetWare® 6.5 SP8.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 id="sec.virtualization.introduction.terminology">
  <title>Terminology</title>
  <para>
  </para>
  
  <sect2 id="sec.virtualization.introduction.terminology.general">
   <title>General</title>
   <para>
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>
     Virtual Machine Manager: A software program included in &yast; that
     provides a graphical user interface for creating and managing virtual
     machines.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     Virtualized: A guest operating system or application running on a virtual machine.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     &xen;: See <xref linkend="cha.xen.basics" xrefstyle="ChapTitleOnPage"/>
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     &kvm;: See <xref linkend="cha.kvm.intro" xrefstyle="ChapTitleOnPage"/>
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     xl: A set of commands for &xen; that lets administrators manage virtual
     machines from a command prompt on the host computer.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     Domain: A virtual machine. The host operating system is actually a virtual
     machine running in a privileged domain and can be referred to as domain
     0. All other virtual machines on the host run in unprivileged domains and
     can be referred to as domain U's.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     Create Virtual Machine Wizard: A software program available in &yast; and
     Virtual Machine Manager that provides a graphical interface to guide you
     through the steps to create virtual machines. It can also be run in text
     mode by entering <command>virt-install</command> at a command prompt in the
     host environment.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     Host Environment: The desktop or command line environment that allows
     interaction with the host computer's environment. It provides a command
     line environment and can also include a graphical desktop, such as GNOME
     or IceWM. The host environment runs as a special type of virtual machine
     that has privileges to control and manage other virtual machines. Other
     commonly used terms include domain 0, privileged domain, and host
     operating system.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     Hypervisor: The software that coordinates the low-level interaction
     between virtual machines and the underlying physical computer
     hardware.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     Paravirtualized Frame Buffer: The video output device that drives a video
     display from a memory buffer containing a complete frame of data for
     virtual machine displays running in paravirtual mode.
    </para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.virtualization.introduction.terminology.network">
   <title>Network</title>
   <para>   
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>
     Bridged Networking: A type of network connection that lets a virtual
     machine be identified on an external network as a unique identity that is
     separate from and unrelated to its host computer.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     Empty Bridge: A type of network bridge that has no physical network device
     or virtual network device provided by the host. This lets virtual machines
     communicate with other virtual machines on the same host but not with the
     host or on an external network.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     External Network: The network outside a host's internal network environment.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     Internal Network: A type of network configuration that restricts virtual
     machines to their host environment.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     Local Bridge: A type of network bridge that has a virtual network device
     but no physical network device provided by the host. This lets virtual
     machines communicate with the host and other virtual machines on the
     host. Virtual machines can communicate on an external network through the
     host.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     Network Address Translation (NAT): A type of network connection that lets
     a virtual machine use the IP address and MAC address of the host.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     No Host Bridge: A type of network bridge that has a physical network
     device but no virtual network device provided by the host. This lets
     virtual machines communicate on an external network but not with the
     host. This lets you separate virtual machine network communications from
     the host environment.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     Traditional Bridge: A type of network bridge that has both a physical network device and a virtual network device provided by the host.
    </para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.virtualization.introduction.terminology.storage">
   <title>Storage</title>
   <para>
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>
     Block Device: Data storage devices, such as CD-ROM drives or disk drives,
     that move data in the form of blocks. Partitions and volumes are also
     considered block devices.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     File-Backed Virtual Disk: A virtual disk based on a file, also called a disk image file.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     Raw Disk: A method of accessing data on a disk at the individual byte
     level instead of through its file system.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     Sparse Image File: A disk image file that does not reserve its entire
     amount of disk space but expands as data is written to it.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
     xvda: The drive designation given to the first virtual disk on a paravirtual machine.
    </para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

</chapter>
