<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="chap-virtualization-introduction">
<!-- I/O virtualization -->
 <title>Virtualization technology</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
   </dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    Virtualization is a technology that provides a way for a machine (Host) to
    run another operating system (guest virtual machines) on top of the host
    operating system.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-virtualization-introduction-overview">
  <title>Overview</title>

<!-- import from White papers -->

  <para>
   &productname; includes the latest open source virtualization technologies,
   &xen; and &kvm;. With these hypervisors, &productname; can be used to
   provision, de-provision, install, monitor and manage multiple virtual
   machines (&vmguest;s) on a single physical system (for more information see
   <xref linkend="gloss-vt-hypervisor"/>).  &productname; can create virtual
   machines running both modified, highly tuned, paravirtualized operating
   systems and fully virtualized unmodified operating systems.
  </para>

  <para>
   The primary component of the operating system that enables virtualization
   is a hypervisor (or virtual machine manager), which is a layer of software
   that runs directly on server hardware. It controls platform resources,
   sharing them among multiple &vmguest;s and their operating systems by
   presenting virtualized hardware interfaces to each &vmguest;.
  </para>

  <para>
   <phrase os="sles;sled">&sle; is an enterprise-class</phrase><phrase
   os="osuse">&opensuse; is a</phrase> Linux server operating system that
   offers two types of hypervisors: &xen; and &kvm;.
  </para>
  <para>
    &productname; with &xen; or &kvm; acts as a virtualization host server
   (<xref linkend="gloss-vt-vhs"/>) that supports &vmguest;s with its own guest
   operating systems. The &suse; &vmguest; architecture consists of a
   hypervisor and management components that constitute the VHS, which runs
   many application-hosting &vmguest;s.
  </para>

  <para>
   In &xen;, the management components run in a privileged &vmguest; often
   called <xref linkend="gloss-vt-dom0"/>. In &kvm;, where the Linux kernel
   acts as the hypervisor, the management components run directly on the VHS.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-virtualization-introduction-benefits">
  <title>Virtualization benefits</title>

  <para>
   Virtualization brings a lot of advantages while providing the same
   service as a hardware server.
  </para>

  <para>
   First, it reduces the cost of your infrastructure. Servers are mainly
   used to provide a service to a customer, and a virtualized operating
   system can provide the same service, with:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Less hardware: You can run several operating system on one host, so all
     hardware maintenance will be reduced.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Less power/cooling: Less hardware means you do not need to invest more
     in electric power, backup power, and cooling if you need more service.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Save space: Your data center space will be saved because you do not need
     more hardware servers (less servers than service running).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Less management: Using a &vmguest; simplifies the administration of
     your infrastructure.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Agility and productivity: Virtualization provides
     <emphasis>migration</emphasis> capabilities, <emphasis>live
     migration</emphasis> and <emphasis>snapshots</emphasis>. These features
     reduce downtime, and bring an easy way to move your service from one
     place to another without any service interruption.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-virtualization-introduction-fvpv">
  <title>Virtualization modes</title>

  <para>
   Guest operating systems are hosted on virtual machines in either full
   virtualization (FV) mode or paravirtual (PV) mode. Each virtualization
   mode has advantages and disadvantages.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Full virtualization mode lets virtual machines run unmodified operating
     systems, such as Windows* Server 2003. It can use either Binary
     Translation or <xref linkend="gloss-vt-hwassisted"/> virtualization
     technology, such as AMD* Virtualization or Intel* Virtualization
     Technology. Using hardware assistance allows for better performance on
     processors that support it.
    </para>
    <para os="sles;sled">
     Some guest operating systems hosted in full virtualization mode can be
     configured to use drivers from the SUSE Virtual Machine Drivers Pack
     (VMDP) instead of
     drivers originating from the operating system. Running virtual machine
     drivers improves performance dramatically on guest operating systems,
     such as Windows Server 2003. For more information, see
     <xref linkend="app-vmdp-driver" xrefstyle="ChapTitleOnPage"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To be able to run under paravirtual mode, guest operating systems
     usually need to be modified for the virtualization environment. However,
     operating systems running in paravirtual mode have better performance
     than those running under full virtualization.
    </para>
    <para>
     Operating systems currently modified to run in paravirtual mode are
     called <emphasis>paravirtualized operating systems</emphasis>
     and include &productname;.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
<!-- I/O virtualization -->
 <xi:include href="vt_io.xml"/>
</chapter>
