<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>

<chapter id="chap.virtualization.introduction" lang="en">
 <title>Virtualization Technology</title>
 <para>
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.virtualization.introduction.basics">
  <title>Virtualization Basics</title>
  <para>
   Virtualization is a technology which provides a way for a machine (Host) to
   run another operating system (guest virtual machines) on top of the host
   operating system.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem><para>
    Virtual Machine: A virtualized PC environment capable of hosting a guest
    operating system and associated applications.
   </para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>
    Virtual Machine Host: The physical computer running a &suse;
    virtualization platform software. The virtualization environment consists
    of the hypervisor, the host environment, virtual machines, and associated
    tools, commands, and configuration files. Other commonly used terms
    include host, host computer, host machine, virtual server, and
    virtualization host server.
   </para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>
    Guest Operating System: The operating system that runs on a virtual machine.
   </para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 id="sec.virtualization.introduction.fvpv">
  <title>Understanding Virtualization Modes</title>
  <para>
   Guest operating systems are hosted on virtual machines in either full
   virtualization mode or paravirtual mode. Each virtualization mode has
   advantages and disadvantages.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Full virtualization mode lets virtual machines run unmodified operating
     systems, such as Windows* Server 2003, but requires the
     computer running as the &vmhost; to support hardware-assisted
     virtualization technology, such as AMD* Virtualization or Intel*
     Virtualization Technology.
    </para>
    <para>
     Some guest operating systems hosted in full virtualization mode, can be
     configured to run the Novell* Virtual Machine Drivers instead of
     drivers originating from the operating system. Running virtual machine
     drivers improves performance dramatically on guest operating systems,
     such as Windows Server 2003. For more information, see
     <xref linkend="cha.xen.driver" xrefstyle="ChapTitleOnPage"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Paravirtual mode does not require the host computer to support
     hardware-assisted virtualization technology, but does require the guest
     operating system to be modified for the virtualization environment.
     Typically, operating systems running in paravirtual mode enjoy better
     performance than those requiring full virtualization mode.
    </para>
    <para>
     Operating systems currently modified to run in paravirtual mode are
     referred to as <emphasis>paravirtualized operating systems</emphasis>
     and include &productname; 11 and NetWare® 6.5 SP8.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
