<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.x11">
 <title>The X Window System</title><indexterm>
 <primary>X Window System</primary>
 <see>X</see></indexterm>
 <para>
  The X Window System (X11) is the de facto standard for graphical user
  interfaces in Unix. X is network-based, enabling applications started on
  one host to be displayed on another host connected over any kind of
  network (LAN or Internet). This chapter provides basic information on the
  X configuration, as well as background information about the use of fonts
  in &productnamereg;.
 </para>
 <para>
  In most cases, the X Window System needs no configuration at all. The hardware
  is dynamically detected during X start-up. The use of
  <filename>xorg.conf</filename> is therefore deprecated.
 If you still need to specify custom options to change the way X behaves, you
 can still do so by modifying configuration files under
 <filename>/etc/X11/xorg.conf.d/</filename>.
 </para>
 <tip arch="zseries" os="sles">
  <title>IBM &zseries;: Configuring the Graphical User Interface</title>
  <para>
   IBM &zseries; does not have any input or output devices supported by
   &xvendor;. Therefore, none of the configuration procedures described in
   this section apply. More relevant information for IBM &zseries; can be
   found in <xref linkend="cha.zseries"/>.
  </para>
 </tip>
<!--
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="x11_optimierung.xml"/>
-->
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="x11_fonts.xml"/>
 <sect1 id="sec.x11.moreinfo">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   Install the packages <systemitem class="resource">xorg-docs</systemitem>
   to get more in-depth information about X11. <command>man 5
    xorg.conf</command> tells you more about the format of the manual
   configuration (if needed). More information on the X11
   development can be found on the project's home page at
   <ulink url="http://www.x.org"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Drivers are found in <systemitem>xf86-video-*</systemitem> packages, for
   example <systemitem>xf86-video-nv</systemitem>. Many of the drivers
   delivered with these packages are described in detail in the related
   manual page. For example, if you use the <literal>nv</literal> driver,
   find more information about this driver in <command>man 4 nv</command>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Information about third-party drivers should be available in
   <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/&lt;package_name&gt;</filename>. For
   example, the documentation of
   <systemitem
    class="resource">x11-video-nvidiaG03</systemitem> is
   available in
   <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/x11-video-nvidiaG03</filename> after
   the package was installed.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
