<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entities;
]>
<sect1 id="sec.x11.fontsys">
 <title>Installing and Configuring Fonts</title><indexterm>

 <primary>X</primary>

 <secondary>TrueType fonts</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

 <primary>fonts</primary>

 <secondary>TrueType</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

 <primary>X</primary>

 <secondary>fonts</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

 <primary>X</primary>

 <secondary>xft</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

 <primary>X</primary>

 <secondary>character sets</secondary></indexterm>

 <para>
  Fonts in Linux can be categorized into two parts:
 </para>

 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Outline or Vector Fonts</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Contains a mathematical description as drawing instructions about the
     shape of a glyph. As such, each glyph can be scaled to arbitrary sizes
     without loss of quality. Before such a font (or glyph) can be used, the
     mathematical descriptions need to be transformed into a raster (grid).
     This process is called <emphasis>font rasterization</emphasis>.
     <emphasis>Font hinting</emphasis> (embedded inside the font) improves
     and optimizes the rendering result for a particular size. Rasterization
     and hinting is done with the FreeType library.
    </para>
    <para>
     Common formats under Linux are PostScript Type 1 and Type 2, TrueType,
     and OpenType.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Bitmap or Raster Fonts</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Consists of an array of pixels designed for a specific font size.
     Bitmap fonts are extremely fast and simple to render. However, compared
     to vector fonts, bitmap fonts cannot be scaled without losing quality.
     As such, these fonts are usually distributed in different sizes. These
     days, bitmap fonts are still used in the Linux console and sometimes in
     terminals.
    </para>
    <para>
     Under Linux, Portable Compiled Format (PCF) or Glyph Bitmap
     Distribution Format (BDF) are the most common formats.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>

 <para>
  The appearance of these fonts can be influenced by two main aspects:
 </para>

 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    choosing a suitable font family,
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    rendering the font with an algorithm that achieves results comfortable
    for the receiver's eyes.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>

 <para>
  The last point is only relevant to vector fonts. Although the above two
  points are highly subjective, some defaults need to be created.
 </para>

 <para>
  Linux font rendering systems consist of several libraries with different
  relations. The basic font rendering library is
  <ulink
  url="http://www.freetype.org/">FreeType</ulink>, which converts
  font glyphs of supported formats into optimized bitmap glyphs. The
  rendering process is controled by an algorithm and its parameters (which
  may be subject to patent issues).
 </para>

 <para>
  Every program or library which uses FreeType should consult the
  <ulink
  url="http://www.fontconfig.org/">Fontconfig</ulink> library. This
  library gathers font configuration from users and from the system. When a
  user amends his Fontconfig setting, this change will result in
  Fontconfig-aware applications.
 </para>

 <para>
  More sophisticated OpenType shaping needed for scripts such as Arabic, Han
  or Phags-Pa and other higher level text processing lies on the shoulders
  of <ulink url="http://www.harfbuzz.org/">Harfbuzz</ulink> or
  <ulink url="http://www.pango.org/">Pango</ulink>, to mention some
  examples.
 </para>

 <sect2 id="sec.x11.fontsys.showing.fonts">
  <title>Showing Installed Fonts</title>
  <para>
   To get an overview about which fonts are installed on your system, ask
   the commands <command>rpm</command> or <command>fc-list</command>. Both
   will give you a good answer, but may return a different list depending on
   system and user configuration:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>rpm</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Invoke <command>rpm</command> to see which software packages
      containing fonts are installed on your system:
     </para>
<screen>$ rpm -qa '*fonts*'</screen>
     <para>
      Every font package should satisfy this expression. However, the
      command may return some false positives like
      <literal>fonts-config</literal> (which is neither a font nor does it
      contain fonts).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><command>fc-list</command>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Invoke <command>fc-list</command> to get an overview about what font
      families can be accessed, whether they are installed on the system or
      in your home:
     </para>
<screen>$ fc-list ':' family</screen>
     <note>
      <title>Command <command>fc-list</command></title>
      <para>
       The command <command>fc-list</command> is a wrapper to the Fontconfig
       library. It is possible to query a lot of interesting information
       from Fontconfig&mdash;or, to be more precise, from its cache. See
       <command>man 1 fc-list</command> for more details.
      </para>
     </note>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.x11.fontsys.viewing">
  <title>Viewing Fonts</title><indexterm>
  <primary>font</primary>
  <secondary>information, see fontinfo.opensuse.org</secondary></indexterm>
  <para>
   If you want to know what an installed font family looks like, either use
   the command <command>ftview</command> (package
   <systemitem>ft2demos</systemitem>) or visit
   <ulink
   url="http://fontinfo.opensuse.org/"/>. For example, to display
   the FreeMono font in 14 point, use <command>ftview</command> like this:
  </para>
<screen>$ ftview 14 /usr/share/fonts/truetype/FreeMono.ttf</screen>
  <para>
   If you need further information, go to
   <ulink
  url="http://fontinfo.opensuse.org/"/> to find out which styles
   (regular, bold, italic, etc.) and languages are supported.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.x11.fontsys.querying">
  <title>Querying Fonts</title>
  <para>
   To query which font is used when a pattern is given, use the
   <command>fc-match</command> command.
  </para>
  <para>
   For example, if your pattern contains an already installed font,
   <command>fc-match</command> returns the file name, font family, and the
   style:
  </para>
<screen>$ fc-match 'Liberation Serif'
LiberationSerif-Regular.ttf: "Liberation Serif" "Regular"</screen>
  <para>
   If the desired font does not exist on your system, Fontconfig's matching
   rules take place and try to find the most similar fonts available. This
   means, your request is substituted:
  </para>
<screen>$ fc-match 'Foo Family'
DejaVuSans.ttf: "DejaVu Sans" "Book"</screen>
  <para>
   Fontconfig supports <emphasis>aliases</emphasis>: a name is substituted
   with another family name. A typical example are the generic names such as
   <quote>sans-serif</quote>, <quote>serif</quote>, and
   <quote>monospace</quote>. These alias names can be substituted by real
   family names or even a preference list of family names:
  </para>
<screen>$ for font in serif sans mono; do fc-match "$font" ; done
DejaVuSerif.ttf: "DejaVu Serif" "Book"
DejaVuSans.ttf: "DejaVu Sans" "Book"
DejaVuSansMono.ttf: "DejaVu Sans Mono" "Book"</screen>
  <para>
   The result may vary on your system, depending on which fonts are
   currently installed.
  </para>
  <note>
   <title>Similarity Rules according to Fontconfig</title>
   <para>
    Fontconfig <emphasis>always</emphasis> returns a real family (if at
    least one is installed) according to the given request, as similar as
    possible. <quote>Similarity</quote> depends on Fontconfig's internal
    metrics and on the user's or administrator's Fontconfig settings.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.x11.fontsys.install">
  <title>Installing Fonts</title><indexterm>
  <primary>X</primary>
  <secondary>install fonts</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
  <primary>fonts</primary>
  <secondary>install</secondary></indexterm>
  <para>
   To install a new font there are these major methods:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Manually install the font files such as <filename>*.ttf</filename> or
     <filename>*.otf</filename> to a known font directory. If it needs to be
     system-wide, use the standard directory
     <filename>/usr/share/fonts</filename>. For installation in your home
     directory, use <filename>~/.config/fonts</filename>.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you want to deviate from the standard directories, Fontconfig allows
     you to choose another one. Let Fontconfig know by using the
     <literal>&lt;dir&gt;</literal> element, see
     <xref 
    linkend="sec.x11.fontsys.config.fontconfig"/> for details.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Install fonts using <command>zypper</command>. Lots of fonts are
     already available as a package, be it on your &suse; distribution or in
     the
     <ulink 
    url="http://download.opensuse.org/repositories/M17N:/fonts/">M17N:fonts</ulink>
     repository. Add the repository to your list using the following
     command, for example <phrase 
    os="osuse">&opensuse;
     13.1</phrase><phrase os="sles;sled">&slea;11</phrase>:
    </para>
<screen os="osuse">$ sudo zypper ar http://download.opensuse.org/repositories/M17N:/fonts/openSUSE_13.1/M17N:fonts.repo</screen>
<screen os="sles;sled">$ sudo zypper ar http://download.opensuse.org/repositories/M17N:/fonts/SLE_11_SP3/M17N:fonts.repo</screen>
    <para>
     To search for your <replaceable>FONT_FAMILY_NAME</replaceable> use this
     command:
    </para>
<screen>$ sudo zypper se '<replaceable>FONT_FAMILY_NAME</replaceable>*fonts'</screen>
   </listitem>
<!-- Currently disabled -->
<!--<listitem>
       <para>Install fonts using the 1-click process, available at <ulink url="http://fontinfo.opensuse.org/"/>, 
       section <quote>Software Package Information</quote>. It contains a font card (specimen). See also
       <xref linkend="sec.x11.fontsys.viewing"/>.</para>
       </listitem>-->
  </orderedlist>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.x11.fontsys.config">
  <title>Configuring the Appearance of Fonts</title><indexterm>
  <primary>font</primary>
  <secondary>configuration</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
  <primary>font family</primary>
  <secondary>substitutions</secondary></indexterm>
  <para>
   Depending on the rendering medium, and font size, the result may be
   unsatisfactory. For example, an average monitor these days has a resolution
   of 100dpi which makes pixels too big and glyphs look clunky.
  </para>
  <para>
   There are several algorithms available to deal with low resolutions, such as
   anti-aliasing (grayscale smoothing), hinting (fitting to the grid), or
   subpixel rendering (tripling resolution in one direction). These
   algorithms can also differ from one font format to another.
  </para>
  <important>
   <title>Patent Issues with Subpixel Rendering</title>
   <para>
    <indexterm>
    <primary>font</primary>
    <secondary>subpixel patent</secondary>
    </indexterm> Subpixel rendering is not used in &suse; distributions.
    Although FreeType2 has support for this algorithm, it is covered by
    several patents expiring at the end of the year 2019. Therefore, setting
    subpixel rendering options in Fontconfig has no effect unless the system
    has a FreeType2 library with subpixel rendering compiled in.
   </para>
  </important>
  <para>
   Via Fontconfig, it is possible to select a rendering algorithms for every
   font individually or for a set of fonts.
  </para>
  <sect3 id="sec.x11.fontsys.config.sysconfig">
   <title>Configuring Fonts via <literal>sysconfig</literal></title>
   <para>
    &productname; comes with a <literal>sysconfig</literal> layer above
    Fontconfig. This is a good starting point for experimenting with font
    configuration. To change the default settings, edit the configuration file
    <filename>/etc/sysconfig/fonts-config</filename>. (or use the &yast;
    sysconfig module). After you have edited the file, run
    <command>fonts-config</command>:
   </para>
<screen>$ sudo /usr/sbin/fonts-config</screen>
   <para>
    Restart the application to make the effect visible. Keep in mind the
    following issues:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A few applications do need not to be restarted. For example, Firefox
      re-reads Fontconfig configuration from time to time. Newly created or
      reloaded tabs get new font configurations later.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The <command>fonts-config</command> script is called automatically
      after every package installation or removal (if not, it is a bug of
      the font software package).
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Every sysconfig variable can be temporarily overriden by the
      <command>fonts-config</command> command line option. See
      <command>fonts-config --help</command> for details.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    There are several sysconfig variables which can be altered. See
    <command>man 1 fonts-config</command> or the help page of the &yast;
    sysconfig module. The following variables are examples:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Usage of Rendering Algorithms</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Consider <varname>FORCE_HINTSTYLE</varname>,
       <varname>FORCE_AUTOHINT</varname>, <varname>FORCE_BW</varname>,
       <varname>FORCE_BW_MONOSPACE</varname>,
       <varname>USE_EMBEDDED_BITMAPS</varname> and
       <varname>EMBEDDED_BITMAP_LANGAGES</varname>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Preference Lists of Generic Aliases</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use <varname>PREFER_SANS_FAMILIES</varname>,
       <varname>PREFER_SERIF_FAMILIES</varname>,
       <varname>PREFER_MONO_FAMILIES</varname> and
       <varname>SEARCH_METRIC_COMPATIBLE</varname>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    The following list provides some configuration examples, sorted from the
    <quote>most readable</quote> fonts (more contrast) to <quote>most
    beautiful</quote> (more smoothed).
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry id="vle.x11.fontsys.sysconfig.bitmap">
     <term>Bitmap Fonts</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Prefer bitmap fonts via the <varname>PREFER_*_FAMILIES</varname>
       variables. Follow the example in the help section for these variables.
       Be aware that these fonts are rendered black and white, not smoothed
       and that bitmap fonts are available in several sizes only. Consider
       using
      </para>
<screen>SEARCH_METRIC_COMPATIBLE="no"</screen>
      <para>
       to disable metric compatibility-driven family name substitutions.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry id="vle.x11.fontsys.sysconfig.bw">
     <term>Scalable Fonts Rendered Black and White</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Scalable fonts rendered without antialiasing can result in a similar
       outcome to bitmap fonts, while maintaining font scalability. Use
       well hinted fonts like the Liberation families. Unfortunately, there
       is a lack of well hinted fonts though. Set the following variable to
       force this method:
      </para>
<screen>FORCE_BW="yes"</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry id="vle.x11.fontsys.sysconfig.bw_monospace">
     <term>Monospaced Fonts Rendered Black and White</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Render monospaced fonts without antialiasing only, otherwise use
       default settings:
      </para>
<screen>FORCE_BW_MONOSPACE="yes"</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry id="vle.x11.fontsys.sysconfig.default">
     <term>Default Settings</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       All fonts are rendered with antialiasing. Well hinted fonts will be
       rendered with the <emphasis>byte code interpreter</emphasis> (BCI)
       and the rest with autohinter
       (<literal>hintstyle=hintslight</literal>). Leave all relevant
       sysconfig variables to the default setting.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry id="vle.x11.fontsys.sysconfig.cff">
     <term>CFF Fonts</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Use fonts in CFF format. They can be considered also more readable
       than the default TrueType fonts given the current improvements in
       FreeType2. Try them out by following the example of
       <literal>PREFER_*_FAMILIES</literal>. Possibly make them more dark
       and bold with:
      </para>
<screen>SEARCH_METRIC_COMPATIBLE="no"</screen>
      <para>
       as they are rendered by <literal>hintstyle=hintslight</literal> by
       default. Also consider using:
      </para>
<screen>SEARCH_METRIC_COMPATIBLE="no"</screen>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry id="ex.x11.fontsys.sysconfig.autohint">
     <term>Autohinter Exclusively</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Even for a well hinted font, use FreeType2's autohinter. That can lead
       to more thicker with lower contrast and sometimes fuzzier
       results. Set the following variable to activate this:
      </para>
<screen>FORCE_AUTOHINTER="yes"</screen>
      <para>
       Use <literal>FORCE_HINTSTYLE</literal> to control the level of hinting.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect3>
  <sect3 id="sec.x11.fontsys.config.fontconfig">
   <title>Diving into Fontconfig XML</title>
   <para>
    Fontconfig's configuration format is the <emphasis>eXtensible Markup
    Language</emphasis> (XML). These few examples are not a complete
    reference, but a brief overview. Details and other inspiration can be
    found in <command>man 5 fonts-conf</command> or in
    <filename>/etc/fonts/conf.d/</filename>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The central Fontconfig configuration file is
    <filename>/etc/fonts/fonts.conf</filename>, which&mdash;along other
    work&mdash;includes the whole <filename>/etc/fonts/conf.d/</filename>
    directory. To customize Fontconfig, there are two places where you can
    insert your changes:
   </para>
   <orderedlist id="ol.x11.fontsys.configfiles">
    <title>Fontconfig Configuration Files</title>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>System-wide changes</title>
      <para>
       Edit the file <filename>/etc/fonts/local.conf</filename> (by default,
       it contains an empty <literal>fontconfig</literal> element).
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>User-specific changes</title>
      <para>
       Edit the file <filename>~/.config/fontconfig/fonts.conf</filename>.
       Place Fontconfig configuration files in the
       <filename>~/.config/fontconfig/conf.d/</filename> directory.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
   <para>
    User-specific changes overwrite any system-wide settings.
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>Deprecated User Configuration File</title>
    <para>
     The file <filename>~/.fonts.conf</filename> is marked as deprecated and
     should not be used anymore. Use
     <filename>~/.config/fontconfig/fonts.conf</filename> instead.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    Every configuration file needs to have a <literal>fontconfig</literal>
    element. As such, the minimal file looks like this:
   </para>
<screen>&lt;?xml version="1.0"?>
   &lt;!DOCTYPE fontconfig SYSTEM "fonts.dtd">
   &lt;fontconfig>
   &lt;!-- Insert your changes here -->
   &lt;/fontconfig></screen>
   <para>
    If the default directories are not enough, insert the
    <literal>dir</literal> element with the respective directory:
   </para>
<screen>&lt;dir>/usr/share/fonts2&lt;/dir></screen>
   <para>
    Fontconfig searches <emphasis>recursively</emphasis> for fonts.
   </para>
   <para>
    Font-rendering algorithms can be chosen with following Fontconfig
    snippet (see
    <xref linkend="ex.x11.fontsys.fontconfig.rendering_algorithms"/>):
   </para>
   <example id="ex.x11.fontsys.fontconfig.rendering_algorithms">
    <title>Specifying Rendering Algorithms</title>
<screen>&lt;match target="font">
 &lt;test name="family">
  &lt;string><replaceable>FAMILY_NAME</replaceable>&lt;/string>
 &lt;/test>
 &lt;edit name="antialias" mode="assign">
  &lt;bool>true&lt;/bool>
 &lt;/edit>
 &lt;edit name="hinting" mode="assign">
  &lt;bool>true&lt;/bool>
 &lt;/edit>
 &lt;edit name="autohint" mode="assign">
  &lt;bool>false&lt;/bool>
 &lt;/edit>
 &lt;edit name="hintstyle" mode="assign">
  &lt;const>hintfull&lt;/const>
 &lt;/edit>
&lt;/match></screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    Various properties of fonts can be tested. For example, the
    <literal>&lt;test></literal> element can test for the font family (as shown in
    the example), size interval, spacing, font format, and others. When
    abandoning <literal>&lt;test></literal> completely, all
    <literal>&lt;edit></literal> elements will be applied to every font
    (global change).
   </para>
   <example id="ex.x11.fontsys.fontconfig.aliases1">
    <title>Aliases and Family Name Substitutions</title>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry id="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.default">
      <term>Rule 1</term>
      <listitem>
<screen>&lt;alias>
 &lt;family>Alegreya SC&lt;/family>
 &lt;default>
  &lt;family>serif&lt;/family>
 &lt;/default>
&lt;/alias></screen>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry id="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.prefer">
      <term>Rule 2</term>
      <listitem>
<screen>&lt;alias>
 &lt;family>serif&lt;/family>
 &lt;prefer>
  &lt;family>Droid Serif&lt;/family>
 &lt;/prefer>
&lt;/alias></screen>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry id="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.accept">
      <term>Rule 3</term>
      <listitem>
<screen>&lt;alias>
 &lt;family>serif&lt;/family>
 &lt;accept>
  &lt;family>STIXGeneral&lt;/family>
 &lt;/accept>
&lt;/alias></screen>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </example>
   <para>
    The rules from <xref linkend="ex.x11.fontsys.fontconfig.aliases1"/>
    create a <emphasis>prioritized family list</emphasis> (PFL). Depending
    on the element, different actions are performed:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>&lt;default></literal> from 
     <xref linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.default"/>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This rule adds a <literal>serif</literal> family name <emphasis>at
       the end</emphasis> of the PFL.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>&lt;prefer></literal> from 
     <xref linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.prefer"/>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This rule adds <quote>Droid Serif</quote> <emphasis>just
       before</emphasis> the first occurence of <literal>serif</literal> in
       the PFL, whenever <literal>Alegreya SC</literal> is present in PFL.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><literal>&lt;accept></literal> from <xref linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.accept"/>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This rule adds a <quote>STIXGeneral</quote> family name <emphasis>just
       after</emphasis> the first occurence of the <literal>serif</literal>
       family name in the PFL.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    Putting this together, when snippets occur in the order
    <xref
   linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.default"/> -
    <xref
   linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.prefer"/> -
    <xref
   linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.accept"/> and the user
    requests <quote>Alegreya SC</quote>, then the PFL is created as depicted
    in <xref
   linkend="tab.x11.fontsys.example.alias"/>.
   </para>
   <table id="tab.x11.fontsys.example.alias">
    <title>Generating PFL from Fontconfig rules</title>
    <tgroup cols="2">
     <colspec colwidth="1*"/>
     <colspec colwidth="3*"/>
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Order
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Current PFL
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Request
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>Alegreya SC</literal>
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <xref linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.default"/>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>Alegreya SC</literal>, <literal>serif</literal>
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <xref linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.prefer"/>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>Alegreya SC</literal>, <literal>Droid Serif</literal>,
         <literal>serif</literal>
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <xref linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.accept"/>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>Alegreya SC</literal>, <literal>Droid Serif</literal>,
         <literal>serif</literal>, <literal>STIXGeneral</literal>
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </table>
   <para>
    In Fontconfig's metrics, the family name has the highest priority over other
    patterns, like style, size, etc. Fontconfig checks which family is
    currently installed on the system. If <quote>Alegreya SC</quote> is
    installed, then Fontconfig returns it. If not, it asks for <quote>Droid
    Serif</quote>, etc.
   </para>
   <para>
    Be careful. When the order of Fontconfig snippets is changed, Fontconfig
    can return different results, as depicted in
    <xref linkend="tab.x11.fontsys.example.alias2"/>.
   </para>
   <table id="tab.x11.fontsys.example.alias2">
    <title>Results from Generating PFL from Fontconfig Rules with Changed Order</title>
    <tgroup cols="3">
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Order
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Current PFL
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Note
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Request
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>Alegreya SC</literal>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Same request performed.
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <xref linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.prefer"/>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>Alegreya SC</literal>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>serif</literal> not in FPL, nothing is substituted
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <xref linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.accept"/>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>Alegreya SC</literal>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>serif</literal> not in FPL, nothing is substituted
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <xref linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.default"/>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>Alegreya SC</literal>, <literal>serif</literal>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>Alegreya SC</literal> present in FPL, substitution is
         performed
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </table>
   <note>
    <title>Implication.</title>
    <para>
     Think of the <literal>&lt;default></literal> alias as a classification or
     inclusion of this group (if not installed). As the example shows,
     <literal>&lt;default></literal> should always precede the
     <literal>&lt;prefer></literal> and <literal>&lt;accept></literal>
     aliases of that group.
    </para>
    <para>
     <literal>&lt;default></literal> classification is not limited to the
     generic aliases serif, sans-serif and monospace. See
     <filename>/usr/share/fontconfig/conf.avail/30-metric-aliases.conf</filename>
     for a complex example.
    </para>
<!-- Commented out as this  -->
<!--<para>
	We can also think about Fontconfig alias system as of oriented graph.
	<literal>&lt;default></literal> alias creates edges from specific
	families (here <literal>Alegreya SC</literal>) to generic names
	(here <literal>serif</literal>), whereas 
	<literal>&lt;prefer></literal> and <literal>&lt;accept></literal>
	aliases create edges from generics (here <literal>serif</literal>)
	to specifics (here <literal>Droid Serif</literal> and 
	<literal>STIXGeneral</literal>).
	</para>-->
   </note>
   <para>
    The following Fontconfig snippet in
    <xref linkend="ex.x11.fontsys.fontconfig.aliases2"/> creates a
    <literal>serif</literal> group. Every family in this group could
    substitute others when a former font is not installed.
   </para>
   <example id="ex.x11.fontsys.fontconfig.aliases2">
    <title>Aliases and Family Name Substitutions</title>
<screen>&lt;alias>
 &lt;family>Alegreya SC&lt;/family>
 &lt;default>
  &lt;family>serif&lt;/family>
 &lt;/default>
&lt;/alias>
&lt;alias>
 &lt;family>Droid Serif&lt;/family>
 &lt;default>
  &lt;family>serif&lt;/family>
 &lt;/default>
&lt;/alias>
&lt;alias>
 &lt;family>STIXGeneral&lt;/family>
 &lt;default>
  &lt;family>serif&lt;/family>
 &lt;/default>
&lt;/alias>
&lt;alias>
 &lt;family>serif&lt;/family>
 &lt;accept>
  &lt;family>Droid Serif&lt;/family>
  &lt;family>STIXGeneral&lt;/family>
  &lt;family>Alegreya SC&lt;/family>
 &lt;/accept>
&lt;/alias></screen>
   </example>
   <para>
    Priority is given by the order in the <literal>&lt;accept></literal>
    alias. Similarly, stronger <literal>&lt;prefer></literal> aliases can be
    used.
   </para>
   <para>
    <xref linkend="ex.x11.fontsys.fontconfig.aliases1"/> is expanded by
    <xref linkend="ex.x11.fontsys.fontconfig.aliases3"/>.
   </para>
   <example id="ex.x11.fontsys.fontconfig.aliases3">
    <title>Aliases and Family Names Substitutions</title>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry id="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.accept2">
      <term>Rule 4</term>
      <listitem>
<screen>&lt;alias>
 &lt;family>serif&lt;/family>
 &lt;accept>
  &lt;family>Liberation Serif&lt;/family>
 &lt;/accept>
&lt;/alias></screen>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry id="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.prefer2">
      <term>Rule 5</term>
      <listitem>
<screen>&lt;alias>
 &lt;family>serif&lt;/family>
 &lt;prefer>
  &lt;family>DejaVu Serif&lt;/family>
 &lt;/prefer>
&lt;/alias></screen>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </example>
   <para>
    The expanded configuration from
    <xref linkend="ex.x11.fontsys.fontconfig.aliases3"/> would lead to the
    following PFL evolution:
   </para>
   <table id="tab.x11.fontsys.example.alias3">
    <title>Results from Generating PFL from Fontconfig Rules</title>
    <tgroup cols="2">
     <colspec colwidth="1*"/>
     <colspec colwidth="3*"/>
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Order
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Current PFL
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         Request
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>Alegreya SC</literal>
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <xref linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.default"/>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>Alegreya SC</literal>, <literal>serif</literal>
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <xref linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.prefer"/>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>Alegreya SC</literal>, <literal>Droid Serif</literal>,
         <literal>serif</literal>
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <xref linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.accept"/>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>Alegreya SC</literal>, <literal>Droid Serif</literal>,
         <literal>serif</literal>, <literal>STIXGeneral</literal>
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <xref linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.accept2"/>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>Alegreya SC</literal>, <literal>Droid Serif</literal>,
         <literal>serif</literal>, <literal>Liberation Serif</literal>,
         <literal>STIXGeneral</literal>
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <xref linkend="vle.x11.fontsys.example.alias.prefer2"/>
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>
         <literal>Alegreya SC</literal>, <literal>Droid Serif</literal>,
         <literal>DejaVu Serif</literal>, <literal>serif</literal>,
         <literal>Liberation Serif</literal>, <literal>STIXGeneral</literal>
        </para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </table>
   <note>
    <title>Implications.</title>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In case multiple <literal>&lt;accept></literal> declarations for the
       same generic name exist, the declaration that is parsed last
       <quote>wins</quote>. If possible, do not use
       <literal>&lt;accept></literal> <emphasis role="bold">after</emphasis>
       user (<filename>/etc/fonts/conf.d/*-user.conf</filename>) when creating
       a system-wide configuration.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       In case multiple <literal>&lt;prefer</literal> declarations for the
       same generic name exist, the declaration that is parsed last
       <quote>wins</quote>. If possible, do not use
       <literal>&lt;prefer></literal> <emphasis role="bold">before</emphasis>
       user in the system-wide configuration.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Every <literal>&lt;prefer></literal> declaration overwrites
       <literal>&lt;accept></literal> declarations for the same generic name.  If
       the administrator wants to give the user free rein to use use even
       <literal>&lt;accept></literal> and not only
       <literal>&lt;prefer></literal>,the administrator should not use
       <literal>&lt;prefer></literal> in the system-wide configuration. On the
       other hand, users mostly use <literal>&lt;prefer></literal>,, so that
       should not be detrimental and we see the use of
       <literal>&lt;prefer></literal> also in system wide configurations.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </note>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
