<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="sec.prep.boot">
 <title>Controlling the Installation</title><info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
          </dm:bugtracker>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <indexterm>

 <primary>installation</primary>

 <secondary>controlling</secondary></indexterm>

 <para>
  Control the installation in one of several ways. The method most
  frequently used is to install &productnamereg; from the computer
  console. Other options are available for different situations. Find more
  information about the available installation methods in
  <xref linkend="cha.deployment"/>.
 </para>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.prep.boot.terminal">
  <title>Installation on the Computer Console</title><indexterm>
  <primary>installation</primary>
  <secondary>controlling</secondary>
  <tertiary>console</tertiary></indexterm>
  <para>
   The simplest way to install &productname; is using the computer
   console. With this method, a graphical installation program guides you
   through the installation. This installation method is discussed in detail
   in <xref linkend="cha.inst"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can still perform the installation on the console without a working
   graphics mode. The text-based installation program offers the same
   functionality as the graphical version. Find some hints about navigation
   in this mode in <xref linkend="sec.yast.navi.ncurses_modul"/>.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.prep.boot.serial">
  <title>Installation Using a Serial Console</title><indexterm>
  <primary>installation</primary>
  <secondary>checking</secondary>
  <tertiary>serial console</tertiary></indexterm>
  <para>
   For this installation method, you need a second computer that is
   connected by a <emphasis>null modem</emphasis> cable to the computer on
   which to install &productname;. Depending on the hardware, even the
   firmware or BIOS of the computer may already be accessible to the serial
   console. If this is possible, you can carry out the entire installation
   using this method. To activate the serial console installation,
   additionally specify the parameter <option>console=ttyS0</option> at the
   boot prompt after the boot process has completed and before the
   installation system starts.
  </para>
  <para>
   On most computers, there are two serial interfaces,
   <emphasis>ttyS0</emphasis> and <emphasis>ttyS1</emphasis>. For the
   installation, you need a terminal program like minicom or screen. To
   initiate the serial connection, launch the screen program in a local
   console by entering the following command:
  </para>
<screen>
screen /dev/ttyS0 9600
</screen>
  <para>
   This means that screen listens to the first serial port with a baud rate
   of 9600. From this point on, the installation proceeds similarly to the
   text-based installation over this terminal.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.prep.boot.ssh">
  <title>Installation with SSH</title><indexterm>
  <primary>installation</primary>
  <secondary>controlling</secondary>
  <tertiary>SSH</tertiary></indexterm>
  <para>
   If you do not have direct access to the computer hardware and, for
   example, the installation should be launched from a management console,
   control the entire installation process over the network. To do this,
   enter the parameters <option>UseSSH=1</option> and
   <option>SSHPassword=&lt;secret&gt;</option> at the boot prompt. An
   SSH daemon is then launched in the system and you can log in to the
   system as user <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> with the
   password <quote>secret</quote>. To connect, use the command
   <command>ssh</command>&nbsp;<option>-X
   root@&lt;ipaddr&gt;</option>.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you do not have a DHCP server available in your local network,
   manually assign an IP address to the installation system. Do this by
   entering the option <option>HostIP=&lt;ipaddr&gt;</option> at the
   boot prompt.
  </para>
  <para>
   As soon as you are logged in to the installation system, launch the
   actual installation with the command <command>yast</command>. The
   installation will start in the graphical mode if
   <systemitem>DISPLAY</systemitem> is set. This then guides you through the
   installation. This procedure is described in detail in
   <xref linkend="sec.deployment.remoteinst.scenario.sshdyn"/>.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.prep.boot.vnc">
  <title>Installation over VNC</title><indexterm>
  <primary>installation</primary>
  <secondary>controlling</secondary>
  <tertiary>VNC</tertiary></indexterm>
  <para>
   If you do not have direct access to the system, but want a graphical
   installation, install &productname; over VNC. This method is described
   in detail in <xref linkend="sec.deployment.remoteinst.monitor.vnc"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   As suitable VNC clients are also available for other operating systems,
   such as Microsoft Windows and MacOS, the installation can also be
   controlled from computers running those operating systems.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.prep.boot.autoyast">
  <title>Installation with AutoYaST</title><indexterm>
  <primary>installation</primary>
  <secondary>controlling</secondary>
  <tertiary>autoyast</tertiary></indexterm>
  <para>
   If you need to install &productname; on a number of computers with
   similar hardware, it is recommended you perform the installations with
   the aid of AutoYaST. In this case, start by installing one
   &productname; and use this to create the necessary AutoYaST
   configuration files.
  </para>
  <para>
   AutoYaST is extensively documented in
   <xref linkend="cha.deployment.autoinst"/>.
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>