<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="sec.instserver">
 <title>Boot and Installation Media</title><indexterm>

 <primary>installation</primary>

 <secondary>media</secondary></indexterm>

 <para>
  When installing the system, the media for booting and for installing the
  system may be different. All combinations of supported media for booting
  and installing may be used.
 </para>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.instserver.boot_media">
  <title>Boot Media</title>
  <para>
   Booting a computer depends on the capabilities of the hardware used and
   the availability of media for the respective boot option.
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Booting from DVD</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This is the most common possibility of booting a system. It is
      straightforward for most computer users, but requires a lot of
      interaction for every installation process.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Booting from a USB Hard Disk</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Depending on the hardware used, it is possible to boot from a USB hard
      disk. The respective media must be created as described in
      <xref linkend="tab.boot.opt"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Booting from the Network</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      You can only boot a computer directly from the network if this is
      supported by the computer's firmware or BIOS. This booting method
      requires a boot server that provides the needed boot images over the
      network. The exact protocol depends on your hardware. Commonly you
      need several services, such as TFTP and DHCP or PXE boot. If you need
      a boot server, also read
      <xref linkend="sec.deployment.remoteinst.scenario.vncpxe"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.instserver.installation_media">
  <title>Installation Media</title><indexterm>
  <primary>installation</primary>
  <secondary>server</secondary></indexterm>
  <para>
   The installation media contain all the necessary packages and meta
   information that is necessary to install a &productname;. These must
   be available to the installation system after booting for installation.
   Several possibilities for providing the installation media to the system
   are available with &productname;.
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Installation from DVD</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      All necessary data is delivered on the boot media. Depending on the
      selected installation, a network connection or add-on media may be
      necessary.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
<!-- bg: this should be easily possible, but i am not sure if it is
         still supported.
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Installation from Hard Disk</term>
    <para>
     Sometimes, especially for very fast installations, it may be
     useful to have the installation media available on a local
     hard drive. 
    </para>
   </varlistentry> -->
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Networked Installation</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you plan to install several systems, providing the installation
      media over the network makes things a lot easier. It is possible to
      install from many common protocols, such as NFS, HTTP, FTP, or SMB.
      For more information on how to run such an installation, refer to
      <xref linkend="cha.deployment.remoteinst"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
