<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<sect1 id="sec.bootproblem">
 <title>Dealing with Boot and Installation Problems</title><indexterm>

 <primary>problem solution</primary></indexterm>

 <para>
  Prior to delivery, &productnamereg; is subjected to an extensive test
  program. Despite this, problems occasionally occur during boot or
  installation.
 </para>

 <sect2>
  <title>Problems Booting</title>
  <para>
   Boot problems may prevent the &yast; installer from starting on your
   system. Another symptom is when your system does not boot after the
   installation has been completed.
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Installed System Boots, Not Media</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Change your computer's firmware or BIOS so that the boot sequence is
      correct. To do this, consult the manual for your hardware.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>The Computer Hangs</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Change the console on your computer so that the kernel outputs are
      visible. Be sure to check the last outputs. This is normally done by
      pressing
      <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>.
      If you are unable to resolve the problem, consult the &productname;
      support staff. To log all system messages at boot time, use a serial
      connection as described in <xref linkend="sec.prep.boot"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>The &ipf; Boot Loader</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you have manually altered the kernel or initrd on your system, run
      <command>/sbin/elilo</command> before shutting down the computer. If
      you leave out this step, your system may not be bootable.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Boot Disk</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The boot disk is a useful interim solution if you have difficulties
      setting the other configurations or if you want to postpone the
      decision regarding the final boot mechanism. A boot disk may also be a
      suitable solution in connection with OS/2 or Windows&nbsp;NT. For
      more details on creating boot disks, see
      <xref linkend="grub2.bootcd"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Virus Warning after Installation</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      There are BIOS variants that check the structure of the boot sector
      (MBR) and erroneously display a virus warning after the installation
      of &grub; or &elilo;. Solve this problem by entering the BIOS and
      looking for corresponding adjustable settings. For example, switch off
      <guimenu>virus protection</guimenu>. You can switch this option back
      on again later. It is unnecessary, however, if Linux is the only
      operating system you use.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect2>

 <sect2>
  <title>Problems Installing</title>
  <para>
   If an unexpected problem occurs during installation, information is
   needed to determine the cause of the problem. Use the following
   directions to help with troubleshooting:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check the outputs on the various consoles. You can switch consoles with
     the key combination <keycombo>
     <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Fn</keycap></keycombo>.
     For example, obtain a shell in which to execute various commands by
     pressing <keycombo>
     <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Try launching the installation in failsafe mode. If the installation
     works without problems in this case, there is an incompatibility that
     causes either <systemitem>ACPI</systemitem> or
     <systemitem>APIC</systemitem> to fail. In some cases, a BIOS or
     firmware update fixes this problem.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check the system messages on a console in the installation system by
     entering the command <command>dmesg -T</command>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect2>

 <sect2>
  <title>Redirecting the Boot Source to the Boot DVD</title>
  <para>
   To facilitate the installation process and avoid accidental
   installations, the default setting on the installation DVD for
   &productname; is that your system is booted from the first hard disk. At
   this point, an installed boot loader normally takes over control of the
   system. This means that the boot DVD can stay in the drive during an
   installation. To start the installation, choose one of the installation
   possibilities in the boot menu of the media.
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
