<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="sec.x86.prep.choose">
 <title>Installation Considerations</title>

 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
          </dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <para>
  This section encompasses many factors that need to be considered before
  installing &productname; on &amd64; and &intel64; hardware.
 </para>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.x86.prep.choose.type">
  <title>Installation Type</title>
  <para>
   &productname; is normally installed as an independent operating
   system. With the introduction of Virtualization, it is also possible to
   run multiple instances of &sls; on the same hardware. However, the
   installation of the &vmhost; is performed like a typical installation
   with some additional packages. The installation of virtual guests is
   described in <xref linkend="cha.kvm.inst"/>.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.x86.prep.choose.iplopt">
  <title>Boot Methods</title>
  <para>
   Depending on the hardware used, the following boot methods are available
   for the first boot procedure (prior to the installation of &sls;).
  </para>
  <table xml:id="tab.x86.prep.boot">
   <title>Boot Options</title>
   <tgroup cols="2">
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Boot Option
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Use
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        CD or DVD drive
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        The simplest booting method. The system requires a locally-available
        CD-ROM or DVD-ROM drive for this.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Flash disks
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Find the images required for creating boot disks on the first CD or
        DVD in the <filename>/boot</filename> directory. See also the
        <filename>README</filename> in the same directory. Booting from a
        USB memory stick is only possible if the BIOS of the machine
        supports this method.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        PXE or bootp
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Must be supported by the BIOS or by the firmware of the system used.
        This option requires a boot server in the network. This task can be
        handled by a separate &sls;.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Hard disk
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        &productname; can also be booted from hard disk. For this, copy
        the kernel (<systemitem>linux</systemitem>) and the installation
        system (<systemitem>initrd</systemitem>) from the
        <filename>/boot/loader</filename> directory of the first CD or DVD
        onto the hard disk and add an appropriate entry to the boot loader.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.x86.prep.choose.src">
  <title>Installation Source</title>
  <para>
   When installing &productname;, the actual installation data must be
   available in the network, on a hard disk partition, or on a local DVD. To
   install from the network, you need an installation server. To make the
   installation data available, set up any computer in a Unix or Linux
   environment as an NFS, HTTP, SMB, or FTP server. To make the installation
   data available from a Windows computer, release the data with SMB.
  </para>
  <para>
   The installation source is particularly easy to select if you configure
   an <emphasis>SLP server</emphasis> in the local network. For more
   information, see <xref linkend="sec.deployment.remoteinst.instserver"/>.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.x86.prep.choose.target">
  <title>Installation Target</title>
  <para>
   Most installations are to a local hard disk. Therefore, it is necessary
   for the hard disk controllers to be available to the installation system.
   If a special controller (like a RAID controller) needs an extra kernel
   module, provide a kernel module update disk to the installation system.
  </para>
  <para>
   Other installation targets may be various types of block devices that
   provide sufficient disk space and speed to run an operating system. This
   includes network block devices like <systemitem>iSCSI</systemitem> or
   <systemitem>SAN</systemitem>. It is also possible to install on network
   file systems that offer the standard Unix permissions. However, it may be
   problematic to boot these, because they must be supported by the
   <systemitem>initramfs</systemitem> before the actual system can start.
   Such installations are useful if there is a need to start the same system
   in different locations or if you intend to use &xen; features like domain
   migration.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.x86.prep.choose.how">
  <title>Different Installation Methods</title>
  <para>
   &productname; offers several different methods for controlling
   installation:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Installation on the console
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Installation via serial console
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Installation with &ay;
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Installation with KIWI images
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Installation via SSH
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Installation with VNC
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   By default, the graphical console is used. If you have a large number of
   similar computers to install, it is advisable to create an &ay;
   configuration file or a KIWI preload image and make this available to the
   installation process. See also the documentation for
   <systemitem class="resource">autoyast2</systemitem> in
   <xref linkend="cha.deployment.autoinst"/> and
   <systemitem class="resource">KIWI</systemitem> at
   <link xlink:href="http://doc.opensuse.org/projects/kiwi/doc/"/>.
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>