<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.xen.guests.suse">
 <title>SUSE Linux Virtual Machines</title>
 <para>
  On current &sle; systems, &xen; is fully integrated into the product. It
  may be used as &vmhost; or &vmguest;.
 </para>
 <para>
  To change the size of the VNC display, an extra option must be supplied to
  the &xen; boot options.
 </para>

 <remark condition="clarity">
  2014-02-10 - fs: Check whether this really works with GRUB 2
 </remark>
 
 <para>
  To change the VNC resolution to 1024x768 using 8MB of memory in &slsa; 12,
  edit the file <filename>/etc/default/grub</filename> and append
  <literal>xenfb.video=8,1024,768</literal> to the value of
  <envar>GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX_DEFAULT</envar>. Save your changes and run the
  following command afterwards:
 </para>
 <screen>grub2-mkconfig -o /boot/grub2/grub.cfg</screen>
 <para>
  In &slsa; 11 you to append <literal>xenfb.video=8,1024,768</literal> to the
  <literal>kernel</literal> line of the respective boot entry in
  <filename>/boot/grub/menu.lst</filename>. For SLES10, the same parameter is
  needed. However it must be added to the extra boot parameters of the
  configuration.
 </para>

<!--
In the virtuel machine (DomU), edit the GRUB configuration file
(boot/grub/menu.lst) and add the following to the end of the kernel line:

xenfb.video=8,1024,768

That will force the xen frame buffer video driver to load with a 8MB frame
buffer at 1024x768.

This works for SLE11 only (because we use pygrub to bootstrap the VM in
SLE11).  For SLE10 you edit the extra="" line in the VM's configuration
file with the same as above.
 -->
 <tip>
  <title>Mouse Synchronization in VNC</title>
  <para>
   During the installation of &sle;, it may happen that the mouse in VNC is
   not in sync with the mouse of your controlling X Server. To get both in
   sync, it is advisable to let &sax; create an X configuration before the
   installation starts.
  </para>
  <para>
   This can be done by adding the parameter <systemitem>sax2=1</systemitem>
   to the <guimenu>Additional Arguments</guimenu> in the <guimenu>Create
   Virtual Machine</guimenu> wizard.
  </para>
 </tip>
 <sect1 id="sec.xen.guests.suse.addon">
  <title>Using the Add-On Products Program</title>

  <para>
   The Add-On Products program is available during the SLE operating system
   installation and after installation at <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>&yast;</guimenu> <guimenu>Software</guimenu> <guimenu>Add-On
   Products</guimenu> </menuchoice>. It allows you to install additional
   products that may reside on a separate CD, ISO image file, or
   installation source.
  </para>

  <para>
   Because paravirtual machines present removable media, such as a CD
   inserted in the CD reader, as a non-removable disk device, the Add-On
   Product program does not recognize inserted CD as valid add-on product
   media.
  </para>

  <para>
   To use the Add-On Products program on a paravirtual machine, you must set
   up the add-on product media as a network installation source or copy the
   ISO image file to the virtual machine’s file system.
  </para>

  <para>
   On fully virtual machines, you can use the Add-On Products program to
   specify add-on product media as a network installation source, an ISO
   image file, or as a CD inserted in the host’s CD reader.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.xen.guests.suse.time">
  <title>Virtual Machine Clock Settings</title>

  <para>
   When booting, virtual machines get their initial clock time from their
   host. After getting their initial clock time, fully virtual machines
   manage their time independently from the host. Paravirtual machines
   manage clock time according to their independent wallclock setting. If
   the independent wallclock is enabled, the virtual machine manages its
   time independently and does not synchronize with the host. If the
   independent wallclock is disabled, the virtual machine periodically
   synchronizes its time with the host clock.
  </para>

  <note>
   <para>
    OES 2 NetWare virtual machines manage clock time independently after
    booting. They do not synchronize with the host clock time.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   If a guest operating system is configured for NTP and the virtual
   machine's independent wallclock setting is disabled, it will still
   periodically synchronize its time with the host time. This dual type of
   configuration can result in time drift between virtual machines that need
   to be synchronized. To effectively use an external time source, such as
   NTP, for time synchronization on a virtual machine, the virtual machine's
   independent wallclock setting must be enabled (set to
   <command>1</command>). Otherwise, it will continue to synchronize its
   time with its host.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Viewing the Independent Wallclock Setting</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log in to the virtual machine’s operating system as
     <systemitem>root</systemitem>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the virtual machine environment, enter
    </para>
<screen><command>cat /proc/sys/xen/independent_wallclock</command></screen>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <command>0</command> means that the virtual machine is getting its
       time from the host and is not using independent wallclock.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <command>1</command> means that the virtual machine is using
       independent wallclock and managing its time independently from the
       host.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure>
   <title>Permanently Changing the Independent Wallclock Setting</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log in to the virtual machine environment as
     <systemitem>root</systemitem>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Edit the virtual machine’s <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename>
     file.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Add or change the following entry:
    </para>
<screen>
xen.independent_wallclock=1
</screen>
    <para>
     Enter <command>1</command> to enable or <command>0</command> to disable
     the wallclock setting.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Save the file and reboot the virtual machine operating system.
    </para>
    <para>
     While booting, a virtual machine gets its initial clock time from the
     host. Then, if the wallclock setting is set to 1 in the
     <filename>sysctl.conf</filename> file, it manages its clock time
     independently and does not synchronize with the host clock time.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure>
   <title>Temporarily Changing the Independent Wallclock Setting</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log in to the virtual machine environment as
     <systemitem>root</systemitem>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the following command:
    </para>
<screen>
echo "1" &gt; /proc/sys/xen/independent_wallclock
</screen>
    <para>
     Enter <command>1</command> to enable or <command>0</command> to disable
     the wallclock setting.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Add or change the following entry:
    </para>
<screen>
xen.independent_wallclock=1
</screen>
    <para>
     Enter <command>1</command> to enable or <command>0</command> to disable
     the wallclock setting.
    </para>
    <para>
     Although the current status of the independent wallclock changes
     immediately, its clock time might not be immediately synchronized. The
     setting persists until the virtual machine reboots. Then, it gets its
     initial clock time from the host and uses the independent wallclock
     according to setting specified in the <filename>sysctl.conf</filename>
     file.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.xen.guests.suse.netupdate">
  <title>Updating a Network Installation Source</title>

  <para>
   The installation of &productname; 9 is only supported from a network
   installation source. To have the right device names supported in &xen;,
   you must update the <literal>kernel</literal> and
   <literal>initrd</literal> that are used to install the system.
   Furthermore, the updated kernel must be available in the installation
   source. In the following example, the network installation source is
   found at <filename>/srv/ftp</filename>. Create this directory manually,
   if it does not exist already.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Get the latest kernel package for your system from the &ncc;.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create a directory for executables in your home directory:
     <command>mkdir -p $HOME/bin</command>
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
<!-- FIXME: use new factory location instead of ~ug [tbd] -->
     Copy the script <command>create_update_source.sh</command> from
     <filename>http://www.suse.de/~ug/tools/create_update_source.sh</filename>
     to the <filename>bin/</filename> directory and make it executable.
    </para>
<!-- FIXME: use new factory location instead of ~ug [tbd] -->
<screen>cd $HOME/bin
wget http://www.suse.de/~ug/tools/create_update_source.sh
chmod 755 create_update_source.sh</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Install the package <literal>inst-source-utils</literal>. Then, change
     your working directory to your network installation source.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run the command <command>$HOME/bin/create_update_source.sh
     /srv/ftp</command>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Copy all updated packages to the directory
     <filename>/srv/ftp/updates/suse/&lt;arch&gt;/</filename>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run the following commands to make all the new packages known to the
     installation source:
    </para>
<screen>cd /srv/ftp/updates/suse;
perl /usr/bin/create_package_descr -x setup/descr/EXTRA_PROV</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create the checksums needed for the installation process with the
     commands:
    </para>
<screen>cd /srv/ftp/updates/suse/setup/descr
for i in *; do echo -n "META SHA1 "; \
sha1sum $i|awk '{ORS=""; print $1}'; \
echo -n " "; basename $i; done >> /srv/ftp/updates/content
     </screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   After this procedure, the packages that are copied to the updates
   directory are available during the installation. However, they will only
   be used if they are newer than the packages provided by the installation
   itself.
  </para>

  <para>
   Note, that in order to use a new kernel during the installation, you must
   also create an appropriate <literal>installation initrd</literal> as it
   is found in <filename>/srv/ftp/boot/</filename>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
