<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<!-- TODO: to trouble shooting section: how to mount partitions of image files:
losetup /dev/loopX /path/to/image
kpartx -av /dev/loopX
mount /dev/mapper/<loop_partition> <mnt point>
-->
<!--
  TODO: sharing disks for vmguest systems
  disk=[ 'phy:/dev/sdc,hda,w!', ]

NOTE: if you are using multipath, you can use the regular device name
like I did (/dev/sdc) but if you don't have multipath, you will have to
use the whole device name like
/dev/disk/by-id/scsi-36001c230ce31e9000eb0fb0c1829f4f4
-->
<!-- TODO: PXE boot for installation
http://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=471093
-->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.xen.vm">
<!-- which CPUs? -->
<!-- fs 2014-02-14:
     The boot parameter part of this section needs to be re-written for
     GRUB 2, which does not allow adding commands at boot time - one would
     have to edit the boot line using GRUB's built-in editor

     However, I strongly doubt that images created on SLE 10 GM are supported
     under SLE 12, so commenting this section for now...


 <sect1 id="sec.xen.vm.reuse">
  <title>Using an Existing &productname; Virtual Machine</title>

  <para>
   In &productname; 10 SP1 and later, the device naming is different than
   the device naming of &productname; 10. Therefore, a &productname; 10
   &vmguest; will not be able to find its root file system when running on a
   &productname; &productnumber; &vmhost;.
  </para>

  <para>
   To be able to still boot the system, you must know which device is used
   for the root partition of your virtual system. For example,
   <literal>hda</literal><replaceable>xx</replaceable> will be changed to
   <literal>xvda</literal><replaceable>xx</replaceable> where
   <replaceable>xx</replaceable> is the partition number.
  </para>

  <para>
   When booting the system, append an extra root option to the kernel
   command line, that tells the system about its root file system. If your
   &vmguest; used to live on <filename>/dev/hda2</filename>, append the
   string <literal>root=/dev/xvda2</literal> to the kernel command line.
   This option should enable you to boot the system, although additional
   file systems still will not be available to the system.
  </para>

  <para>
   To make all the needed file systems available to the &vmguest;, do the
   following:
  </para>

  <para>
   In order to have a valid initial RAM disk that knows about the new
   location of the root file system, run the command
   <command>mkinitrd</command>.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the &vmguest; with the extra <literal>root=</literal> command
     line as explained above.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log into the system as user &rootuser;.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Edit the file <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> and correct all device
     entries.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Edit the virtual machine’s <filename>/boot/grub/menu.lst</filename>
     file. At the kernel line, fix the <literal>root=</literal> and the
     <literal>resume=</literal> parameters according the new naming schema.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Reboot the virtual machine.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

-->
 <title>Setting Up Virtual Machines</title>
 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
          </dm:bugtracker>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <para>
  A virtual machine is comprised of data and operating system files that
  define the virtual environment. Virtual machines are hosted and controlled
  by the &vmhost;. This section provides generalized instructions for
  installing virtual machines.
 </para>
 <para>
  Virtual machines have few if any requirements above those required to run
  the operating system. If the operating system has not been optimized for
  the virtual machine host environment, the unmodified OS can run only on
  <xref linkend="gloss.vt.hwassisted"/> virtualization computer hardware, in
  full virtualization mode, and requires specific device drivers to be
  loaded. The hardware that is presented to the &vmguest; depends on the
  configuration of the host.
 </para>
 <para>
  You should be aware of any licensing issues related to running a single
  licensed copy of an operating system on multiple virtual machines. Consult
  the operating system license agreement for more information.
 </para>
 <note>
  <title>Virtual Machine Architectures</title>
  <para>
   The virtual machine host runs only on &amd64; and &intel64;
   hardware. It does not run on other system architectures such as &ppc;.
   A 64-bit virtual machine host can, however, run both 32-bit and 64-bit
   operating system.
<!-- 2011-09-15 toba: the following is not true since SP2:
   , while a 32-bit host cannot run a 64-bit client. This holds true
   for both, the controlling domain and all further guests. -->
  </para>
 </note>
<!-- which CPUs? -->
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.xen.vm.create">
  <title>Creating a Virtual Machine</title>

  <para>
   Before creating a virtual machine, you need the following:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Install a host server as described in <xref linkend="cha.xen.vhost"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If you want to use an automated installation file (&ay;, NetWare®
     Response File, or RedHat Kickstart), you should create and download it
     to a directory on the host machine server or make it available on the
     network.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For NetWare and OES Linux virtual machines, you need a static IP
     address for each virtual machine you create.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If you are installing Open Enterprise Server (OES) 2 Linux, you need a
     network installation source for OES 2 Linux software. For procedures to
     create the installation sources, see the &productname; Deployment
     Guide.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   For further prerequisites, consult the manuals of the respective
   operating system to install.
  </para>

  <para>
   The Create Virtual Machine Wizard
   (<menuchoice><guimenu>&yast;</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Virtualization</guimenu> <guimenu>Create Virtual
   Machines</guimenu></menuchoice>) helps you through the steps required to
   create a virtual machine and install its operating system. The
   information that follows is generalized for installing any operating
   system.
<!-- In addition to these instructions, you should consult
   <xref linkend="cha.xen.guests"/> for information specific to the
   operating system you are installing. -->
  </para>

  <para>
   The actual configuration file for the &xen; guests that is used for
   the installation is stored at <filename>/etc/xen/vm/</filename>. The
   default location for image files is
   <filename>/var/lib/xen/images</filename>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Launch the <guimenu>Create Virtual Machine Wizard</guimenu> by using one
   of the following methods:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     From the virtualization host server desktop, click <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>&yast;</guimenu> <guimenu>Virtualization</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Create Virtual Machines</guimenu> </menuchoice>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     From within Virtual Machine Manager, click <guimenu>New</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     At the command line, enter <command>vm-install</command>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Another possibility is to use the <command>virt-install</command>
     command to ease or automate the creation process. See
     <xref linkend="sec.libvirt.inst.virt-install"/> for more information.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   If the wizard does not appear or the <command>vm-install</command>
   command does not work, review the process of installing and starting the
   virtualization host server. The virtualization software might not be
   installed properly.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.xen.vm.install">
  <title>Installing an Operating System</title>

  <para>
   You can choose to run an installation program or choose a disk or disk
   image that already has an installed and bootable operating system.
  </para>

  <figure xml:id="fig.xen.vm.install">
   <title>Installing an Operating System</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="vm-install-select.png" width="55%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="vm-install-select.png" width="55%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   If you choose to run an installation program, you are presented with a
   list of operating systems. Select the one you want to install.
  </para>

  <para>
   The Summary page shows you a summary of the virtual machine you are
   creating. You can click on any of the headings to edit the information.
  </para>

  <figure xml:id="fig.xen.vm.summ">
   <title>Summary</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="03_createsummary.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="03_createsummary.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

<!--
  Removed, because I did not get any information from PM about those:

  <para>
   Information about the following operating systems is included:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     OES NetWare Virtual Machines, see
     <xref linkend="sec.xen.guests.netware"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     OES Linux Virtual Machines, see <xref linkend="sec.xen.guests.oes"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     SUSE Linux Virtual Machines, see <xref linkend="sec.xen.guests.suse"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Windows Virtual Machines, see <xref linkend="sec.xen.guests.windows"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <quote>
      Red Hat Virtual Machines, see <xref linkend="sec.xen.guests.rh"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist> -->

  <para>
   When running through the creation of a &vmguest;, the following steps
   have to be accomplished:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select if the &vmguest; should run as full or paravirtualized guest.
    </para>
    <para>
     If your computer supports hardware-assisted virtualization, you can
     create a virtual machine that runs in fully virtual mode. If you are
     installing an operating system that is modified for virtualization, you
     can create a virtual machine that runs in paravirtual mode. For more
     information about virtualization modes, see
     <xref linkend="sec.virtualization.introduction.fvpv" xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Each virtual machine must have a unique name. The name entered on this
     page is used to create and name the virtual machine’s configuration
     file. The configuration file contains parameters that define the
     virtual machine and is saved to the <filename>/etc/xen/vm/</filename>
     directory.
    </para>
    <para>
     The user interface to the name of the virtual machine also offers the
     possibility to add a description to the newly generated guest.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The Hardware page allows you to specify the amount of memory and number
     of virtual processors for your virtual machine.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Initial Memory</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The amount of memory initially allocated to the virtual machine
        (specified in megabytes).
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Maximum Memory</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The largest amount of memory the virtual machine will ever need.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Virtual Processors</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If desired, you can specify that the virtual machine has more
        virtual CPUs than the number of physical CPUs. You can specify up to
        32 virtual CPUs: however, for best performance, the number of
        virtual processors should be less than or equal to the number of
        physical processors.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In <guimenu>Peripheral Devices</guimenu>, select the keymap layout and
     graphics mode to use:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>No Graphics Support</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The virtual machine operates like a server without a monitor. You
        can access the operating system through operating system supported
        services, such as SSH or VNC.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Paravirtualized Graphics Adapter</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Requires that an appropriate graphics driver is installed in the
        operating system.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     A virtual machine must have at least one virtual disk. Virtual disks
     can be:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       File backed, which means that the virtual disk is a single image file
       on a larger physical disk.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A sparse image file, which means that the virtual disk is a single
       image file, but the space is not preallocated.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Configured from a block device, such as an entire disk, partition, or
       volume. For more information about available physical storage, see
       <xref linkend="sec.xen.config.disk"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     For best performance, create each virtual disk from an entire disk or a
     partition. For the next best performance, create an image file but do
     not create it as a sparse image file. A virtual disk based on a sparse
     image file delivers the most disk-space flexibility but slows
     installation and disk access speeds.
    </para>
    <para>
     By default, a single, file-backed virtual disk is created as a sparse
     image file in
     <filename>/var/lib/xen/images/<replaceable>vm_name</replaceable></filename>
     where <replaceable>vm_name</replaceable> is the name of the virtual
     machine. You can change this configuration to meet your specific
     requirements.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If you want to install from DVD or CD-ROM, add the drive to the list of
     available hard disks. To learn about device names of the available
     optical drives, run <command>hwinfo --cdrom</command> and search for
     the line starting with <literal>Device File:</literal>. Add this device
     file to the available hard disks of the &vmguest;. The device type
     that should be used for DVD or CD-ROMs is
     <systemitem>tap:cdrom</systemitem>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Instead of the real DVD or CD-ROM drive, you can also add the ISO image
     of an installation medium. For more details, see
     <xref linkend="sec.xen.config.vcd.para"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Note, that each CD-Rom drive or ISO image can only be used by one
     &vmguest; at the same time. When installing many &vmguest;
     systems, it may be better to use a network installation source.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     By default, a single virtual network card is created for the virtual
     machine. It has a randomly generated MAC address that you can change to
     fit your desired configuration. The virtual network card will be
     attached to a default bridge configured in the host. You can also
     create additional virtual network cards in the Network Adapters page of
     vm-install. For more details about virtual networking, see
     <xref linkend="cha.xen.network"/>.
    </para>
    <note>
     <title>Using Arbitrary Bridge Names</title>
     <para>
      If installing a fully virtualized guest and you are using a bridge
      name that is different than the default names, explicitly specify the
      bridge by selecting the bridge name from the <guimenu>Source</guimenu>
      menu on the Virtual Network Adapter page. Paravirtual guests by
      definition are aware they are running on a virtualization platform and
      therefore, do not need to have the bridge explicitly specified, thus
      leaving <guimenu>Source</guimenu> as <guimenu>Default</guimenu> will
      suffice.
     </para>
    </note>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The operating system can be installed from a CD/DVD device or an ISO
     image file. In addition, if you are installing a SUSE Linux operating
     system, you can install the operating system from a network
     installation source.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you are installing a paravirtual machine's operating system from CD
     or DVD, you probably should remove the virtual CD reader from the
     virtual machine after completing the installation. Otherwise it would
     not be available for other installations.
    </para>
<!-- changing CD-Roms works in the meantime.
    <para>
     If you are installing a paravirtual machine's operating system from CD,
     you should remove the virtual CD reader from the virtual machine after
     completing the installation, because the virtual machine assumes that
     the original CD is still in the CD reader, even if it is ejected. If it
     is ejected, the virtual machine cannot access the CD (or any other
     newly inserted CD) and receives I/O errors.
    </para>
    <warning>
     <title>Changing CD-Roms</title>
     <para>
      On paravirtual guests, it is currently not possible to go on with the
      installation of a system after changing the CD-Rom. Instead, you
      should use a DVD or a network based installation. For a workaround to
      this problem, see <xref linkend="sec.xen.config.vcd.para"/>.
     </para>
    </warning> -->
    <para>
     If the installation program is capable of recognizing an installation
     profile, response file, or script, you can automate the installation
     settings by specifying the location of the profile, response file, or
     script you want to use. For example, SUSE Linux uses an &ay;
     profile, NetWare uses a NetWare Response File, and Red Hat uses a
     Kickstart file to move through the installation screens with no
     interaction.
    </para>
    <para>
     You can also pass instructions to the kernel at install time by
     entering parameters for the <guimenu>Additional Arguments</guimenu>
     field. These arguments may either be kernel options, or options for
     <literal>linuxrc</literal>. More information about
     <literal>linuxrc</literal> can be found in the <emphasis>Deployment
     Guide</emphasis>.
<!-- <xref linkend="sec.deployment.remoteinst.bootinst"/>. -->
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   If all the information on the <guimenu>Summary</guimenu> screen is
   correct, click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to create the virtual machine. A
   Virt Viewer screen appears and at this point you begin the installation
   of your OS. From this point on, follow the regular installation
   instructions for installing your OS.
<!-- More information for any instructions that might
   be different for installing your OS in a virtualized environment may be
   found in <xref linkend="cha.xen.guests"/>. -->
  </para>

<!-- this works with SP1
  <tip>
   <title>TightVNC and Mouse Movement</title>
   <para>
    In some situations, the mouse pointer inside TightVNC and the mouse pointer
    of your X Window System are out of sync due to different mouse
    acceleration values. To still be able to use the &yast; installation system,
    the mouse pointer should be locked into TightVNC with the key combination
    <keycombo><keycap function="control"/><keycap function="alt"/></keycombo>.
   </para>
  </tip> -->
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.xen.vm.addon">
  <title>Including Add-On Products in the Installation</title>

  <para>
   In order to include an Add-On product in the installation process of a
   &vmguest;, it is necessary to provide the installation system with
   both, the standard installation images and the image for the Add-On
   product.
  </para>

  <para>
   First, add the system disk, the &productname; &productnumber;
   installation image and the physical CD-ROM or Add-On image as disks to
   the &vmguest;. For example, you may have:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>xvda</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Main system disk.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>xvdb</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      ISO image of the installation medium.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>xvdc</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      ISO image of the Add-On product.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   During the installation, add the Add-On product to the installation by
   entering the device path. Commonly, this path looks like
   <systemitem>hd:///?device=/dev/xvd&lt;letter&gt;</systemitem>. In
   the special example with <quote>xvdc</quote> as Add-On product, this
   would look like:
  </para>

<screen>hd:///?device=/dev/xvdc</screen>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.xen.vm.manualcreate">
  <title>Using the Command Line to Create Virtual Machines</title>

  <para>
   From the command line, you can enter <command>vm-install</command> to run
   a text version of the Create Virtual Machine Wizard. The text version of
   the wizard is helpful in environments without a graphical user interface.
   This command defaults to using a graphical user interface if available
   and if no options were given on the command line.
  </para>

  <para>
   For information on scripting a virtual machine installation, see the man
   pages of <command>vm-install</command> and
   <command>vm-install-jobs</command>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.xen.vm.delete">
  <title>Deleting Virtual Machines</title>

  <para>
   When you use Virtual Machine Manager or the <command>xl</command> command
   to delete a virtual machine, it no longer appears as a virtual machine,
   but its initial start-up file and virtual disks are not automatically
   deleted.
  </para>

  <para>
   To delete all components of a virtual machine configured with a
   file-backed virtual disk, you must manually delete its virtual disk image
   file (<filename>/var/lib/xen/images/</filename>) and its initial start-up
   file (<filename>/etc/xen/vm</filename>).
  </para>
 </sect1>
<!-- fs 2014-02-14:
     The boot parameter part of this section needs to be re-written for
     GRUB 2, which does not allow adding commands at boot time - one would
     have to edit the boot line using GRUB's built-in editor

     However, I strongly doubt that images created on SLE 10 GM are supported
     under SLE 12, so commenting this section for now...


 <sect1 id="sec.xen.vm.reuse">
  <title>Using an Existing &productname; Virtual Machine</title>

  <para>
   In &productname; 10 SP1 and later, the device naming is different than
   the device naming of &productname; 10. Therefore, a &productname; 10
   &vmguest; will not be able to find its root file system when running on a
   &productname; &productnumber; &vmhost;.
  </para>

  <para>
   To be able to still boot the system, you must know which device is used
   for the root partition of your virtual system. For example,
   <literal>hda</literal><replaceable>xx</replaceable> will be changed to
   <literal>xvda</literal><replaceable>xx</replaceable> where
   <replaceable>xx</replaceable> is the partition number.
  </para>

  <para>
   When booting the system, append an extra root option to the kernel
   command line, that tells the system about its root file system. If your
   &vmguest; used to live on <filename>/dev/hda2</filename>, append the
   string <literal>root=/dev/xvda2</literal> to the kernel command line.
   This option should enable you to boot the system, although additional
   file systems still will not be available to the system.
  </para>

  <para>
   To make all the needed file systems available to the &vmguest;, do the
   following:
  </para>

  <para>
   In order to have a valid initial RAM disk that knows about the new
   location of the root file system, run the command
   <command>mkinitrd</command>.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the &vmguest; with the extra <literal>root=</literal> command
     line as explained above.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log into the system as user &rootuser;.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Edit the file <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> and correct all device
     entries.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Edit the virtual machine’s <filename>/boot/grub/menu.lst</filename>
     file. At the kernel line, fix the <literal>root=</literal> and the
     <literal>resume=</literal> parameters according the new naming schema.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Reboot the virtual machine.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

-->
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.xen.vm.known">
  <title>Troubleshooting</title>

  <para>
   In some circumstances, problems may occur during the installation of the
   &vmguest;. This section describes some known problems and their
   solutions.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>During boot, the system hangs</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The software I/O translation buffer allocates a large chunk of low
      memory early in the bootstrap process. If the requests for memory
      exceed the size of the buffer it usually results in a hung boot
      process. To check if this is the case, switch to console 10 and check
      the output there for a message similar to
     </para>
<screen>kernel: PCI-DMA: Out of SW-IOMMU space for 32768 bytes at device 000:01:02.0</screen>
     <para>
      In this case you need to increase the size of the
      <literal>swiotlb</literal>. Enter <quote>swiotlb=128</quote> on the
      &dom0; command line. Note that the number can be adjusted up or
      down to find the optimal size for the machine.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>