<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha.add-ons"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Installing Modules, Extensions, and Third Party Add-On Products</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    Modules and extensions add parts or functionality to the system.
    Modules are fully supported parts of &productname; with a different life
    cycle and update timeline. They are a set of packages, have a clearly
    defined scope and are delivered via online channel only.
   </para>
   <para>
    Extensions, such as the Workstation Extension or the High Availability
    Extension, add extra functionality to the system and require an own
    registration key that is liable for costs. Extensions are delivered via
    online channel or physical media. Registering at the &scc; or a local
    registration server is a prerequisite for subscribing to the
    online channels. The Package Hub (<xref linkend="sec.add-ons.package-hub" />)
    and &sdk; (<xref linkend="sec.add-ons.sdk" />) extensions are exceptions which
    do not require a registration key and are not covered by SUSE support agreements.
   </para>

   <para>
    A list of modules and extensions for your product is available
    after having registered your system at &scc; or a local registration
    server. If you skipped the registration step during the installation, you
    can register your system at any time using the <guimenu>&scc;
    Configuration</guimenu> module in &yast;. <phrase os="sles;sled">For
    details, refer to <xref linkend="sec.update.registersystem"/>.</phrase>
   </para>

   <para>
    Some add-on products are also provided by third parties, for example,
    binary-only drivers that are needed by certain hardware to function
    properly. If you have such hardware, refer to the release notes for more
    information about availability of binary drivers for your system. The
    release notes are available from
    <phrase os="sles;sled"><link
    xlink:href="http://www.suse.com/releasenotes/"/></phrase><phrase
    os="osuse"><link
    xlink:href="https://doc.opensuse.org/release-notes/"/></phrase>,
    from &yast; or from <filename>/usr/share/doc/release-notes/</filename> in
    your installed system.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info><indexterm>
 <primary>&yast;</primary>
 <secondary>add-on</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>add-on products</primary></indexterm>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.add-ons.extensions">
  <title>Installing Modules and Extensions from Online Channels</title>

  <tip os="sled">
   <title>&sled;</title>
   <para>
    As of &sle; 12, &sled; is not only available as a separate product, but
    also as a Workstation Extension for &sls;. If you register at the &scc;,
    the Workstation Extension can be selected for installation. Note that
    installing it requires a valid registration key.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para os="sles;sled">
   The following procedure requires that you have registered your system with
   &scc;, or a local registration server. When
   registering your system, you will see a list of extensions and modules
   immediately after having completed <xref linkend="step.y2.register.final"/>
   of <xref linkend="sec.update.registersystem"/>. In that case, skip the next
   steps and proceed with <xref linkend="step.y2.extensions.list"/>.
  </para>
   <note>
    <title>Viewing Already Installed Add-Ons</title>
    <para>
     To view already installed add-ons, start &yast; and select
     <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Add-Ons</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>
    </para>
   </note>
  <procedure xml:id="pro.add-ons.extensions">
   <title>Installing Add-ons and Extensions from Online Channels with &yast;</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start &yast; and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Add System Extensions or Modules</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para>
     &yast; connects to the registration server and displays a list of
     <guimenu>Available Extensions and Modules</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <note>
     <title>Available Extensions and Modules</title>
     <para>
      The amount of available extensions and modules depends on the
      registration server. A local registration server may only offer update
      repositories and no additional extensions.
     </para>
    </note>
    <note>
     <title>Module Life Cycles</title>
     <para>
      Life cycle end dates of modules are available at
      <link xlink:href="https://scc.suse.com/docs/lifecycle/sle/12/modules"/>.
     </para>
    </note>
   </step>
   <step xml:id="step.y2.extensions.list">
    <para>
     Click an entry to see its description.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select one or multiple entries for installation by activating their check
     marks.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Installation of System Extensions</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_extension_list.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_extension_list.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step xml:id="step.y2.extensions.final">
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Depending on the repositories to be added for the extension or module, you
     may be prompted to import the repository's &gpg; key or asked to agree to a license.
    </para>
    <para>
     After confirming these messages, &yast; will download and parse the
     metadata. The repositories for the selected extensions will be added to
     your system&mdash;no additional installation sources are required.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If needed, adjust the repository <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> as
     described in <xref linkend="sec.yast2.sw.instsource.manage"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <note>
   <title>For More Information</title>
   <para>
    White paper
    <link
   xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/docrep/documents/huz0a6bf9a/suse_linux_enterprise_server_12_modules_white_paper.pdf">
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 Modules</link>.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.add-ons.install">
  <title>Installing Extensions and Third Party Add-On Products from Media</title>

  <para>
   When installing an extension or add-on product from media, you can select
   various types of product media, like DVD/CD, removable mass storage devices
   (such as flash disks), or a local directory or ISO image. The media can also
   be provided by a network server, for example, via HTTP, FTP, NFS, or Samba.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start &yast; and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Add-On Products</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Alternatively, start the
     &yast; <guimenu>Add-On Products</guimenu> module from the command line
     with <command>sudo yast2 add-on</command>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The dialog will show an overview of already installed add-on products,
     modules and extensions.
    </para>
    <figure xml:id="fig.y2.sw.addon.installed">
     <title>List of Installed Add-on Products, Modules and Extensions</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_addon_installed.png" width="90%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_addon_installed.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Choose <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to install a new add-on product.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step xml:id="step.y2.add-ons.type">
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Add-On Product</guimenu> dialog, select the option that
     matches the type of medium from which you want to install:
    </para>
    <figure xml:id="fig.y2.sw.addon.new">
     <title>Installation of an Add-on Product or an Extension</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_addon_new.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_addon_new.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To scan your network for installation servers announcing their services
       via SLP, select <guimenu>Scan Using SLP</guimenu> and click
       <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To add a repository from a removable medium, choose the relevant option
       and insert the medium or connect the USB device to the machine,
       respectively. Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to start the installation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For most media types, you will prompted to specify the path
       (or URL) to the media after selecting the respective option and clicking
       <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. Specifying a <guimenu>Repository Name</guimenu>
       is optional. If none is specified, &yast; will use the product name or
       the URL as the repository name.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     The option <guimenu>Download Repository Description Files</guimenu> is
     activated by default. If you deactivate the option, &yast; will
     automatically download the files later, if needed.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Depending on the repository you have added, you may be prompted
     to import the repository's &gpg; key or asked to agree to a
     license.
    </para>
    <para>
     After confirming these messages, &yast; will download and parse the
     metadata. It will add the repository to the list of <guimenu>Configured
     Repositories</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If needed, adjust the repository <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> as
     described in <xref linkend="sec.yast2.sw.instsource.manage"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Confirm your changes with <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to close the configuration
     dialog.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After having successfully added the repository for the add-on media, the
     software manager starts and you can install packages. For details, refer
     to <xref linkend="cha.yast2.sw"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.add-ons.sdk">
  <title>&sdk; (SDK) &productnumber;</title><indexterm>

  <primary>software</primary>

  <secondary>development</secondary>

  <tertiary>SUSE SDK</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>SUSE SDK</primary></indexterm>

  <para>
   &sdk; &productnumber; is a module for &sle; &productnumber;. It is a
   complete tool kit for application development. In fact, to provide a
   comprehensive build system, &sdk; &productnumber; includes all the open
   source tools that were used to build the &sls; product. It provides you as a
   developer, independent software vendor (ISV), or independent hardware vendor
   (IHV) with all the tools needed to port applications to all the platforms
   supported by &sled; and &sls;.
  </para>

  <para>
   The &sdk; does not require a registration key and is not covered
   by SUSE support agreements.
  </para>

  <para>
   &sdk; also contains integrated development environments (IDEs), debuggers,
   code editors, and other related tools. It supports most major programming
   languages, including C, C++, Java, and most scripting languages. For your
   convenience, &sdk; includes multiple Perl packages that are not included in
   &sle;.
  </para>

  <para>
   The SDK is a module for &sle; and is available via an online channel from
   the &scc;. Alternatively, go to
   <link
   xlink:href="http://download.suse.com/"/>, search for <literal>&sle;
   Software Development Kit</literal> and download it from there. Refer to
   <xref linkend="cha.add-ons"/> for details.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.add-ons.package-hub">
  <title>&suse; Package Hub</title>
  <para>
   In the list of <emphasis>Available Extensions and Modules</emphasis>
   you find the &suse; Package Hub. It is available without any additional
   fee. It provides a large set of additional community packages for &sle;
   that can  easily be installed but are <emphasis>not</emphasis>
   supported by &suse;.
  </para>
  <para>
   More information about &suse; Package Hub and how to contribute is
   available at <link xlink:href="https://packagehub.suse.com/"/>
  </para>
  <important>
   <title>&suse; Package Hub is Not Supported</title>
   <para>
    Be aware that packages provided in the &suse; Package Hub are not
    officially supported by &suse;. &suse; only provides support for
    enabling the Package Hub repository and help with
    installation or deployment of the RPM packages.
   </para>
  </important>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
