<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha.add-ons"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Installing Add-On Products</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
   </dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    Add-on products are system extensions. You can install a third party
    add-on product or a special system extension of &productnamereg; (for
    example, a CD with support for additional languages or a CD with binary
    drivers). To install a new add-on, start &yast; and select <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Software</guimenu> <guimenu>Add-On Products</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>. You can select various types of product media, like CD,
    FTP, USB mass storage devices (such as USB flash drives or disks) or a
    local directory. You can also work directly with ISO files. To add an
    add-on as ISO file media, select <guimenu>Local ISO Image</guimenu> then
    enter the <guimenu>Path to ISO Image</guimenu>. The <guimenu>Repository
    Name</guimenu> is arbitrary.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.add-ons.addon">
  <title>Add-Ons</title>

  <para>
   To install a new add-on, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     In &yast; select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Add-On Products</guimenu> </menuchoice> to see an overview of
     already installed add-on products.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To install a new add-on product, click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     From the list of available <guimenu>Media Types</guimenu> specify the
     type matching your repository.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To add a repository from a removable medium, choose the relevant option
     and insert the medium or connect the USB device to the machine,
     respectively.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     You can choose to <guimenu>Download Repository Description
     Files</guimenu> now. If the option is unchecked, &yast; will
     automatically download the files later, if needed. Click
     <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     When adding a repository from the network, enter the data you are
     prompted for. Continue with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Depending on the repository you have added, you may be asked if you
     want to import the &gpg; key with which it is signed or asked to agree to
     a license.
    </para>
    <para>
     After confirming these messages, &yast; will download and parse the
     metadata and add the repository to the list of <guimenu>Configured
     Repositories.</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If needed, adjust the repository <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> as
     described in <xref linkend="sec.yast2.sw.instsource.manage"/> or confirm
     your changes with <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to close the configuration
     dialog.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After having successfully added the repository for the add-on media,
     the software manager starts and you can install packages. Refer to
     <xref
      linkend="cha.yast2.sw"/> for details.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.add-ons.drivers">
  <title>Binary Drivers</title>  <para>
   Some hardware needs binary-only drivers to function properly. If you have
   such hardware, refer to the release notes for more information about
   availability of binary drivers for your system. To read the release
   notes, open &yast; and select <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Miscellaneous</guimenu> <guimenu>Release Notes</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
