<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="sec-yast-hw-print"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Setting up a printer</title>

 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>

 <para>
  &yast; can be used to configure local and network printers. Further
  information about printing (general information, technical details, and
  troubleshooting) is available in <xref linkend="cha-print"/>.
 </para>

 <para>
  In &yast;, click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu>
  <guimenu>Printer</guimenu> </menuchoice> to start the printer module. By
  default it opens in the <guimenu>Printer Configurations</guimenu> view,
  displaying a list of all printers that are available and configured. This is
  especially useful when having access to a lot of printers via the network.
  From here you can also <guimenu>Print a Test Page</guimenu> and configure
  printers.
 </para>

 <note>
  <title>Starting CUPS</title>
  <para>
   To use the printer connected to your machine you must have CUPS installed and
   running on your system. If CUPS is not running, you are prompted to start it.
   In case CUPS is not started at boot time, you are also prompted to enable
   it (recommended).
  </para>
 </note>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-hw-print-local">
  <title>Configuring printers</title>
  <para>
   Normally USB printers are detected automatically. If that does not happen,
   check whether the printer is switched on and connected to the machine.
  </para>
  <para>
   Configuring a printer is a three-step process: specify the connection type,
   choose a driver, and name the print queue for this setup.
  </para>
  <para>
   Many printer models may have several available drivers. When configuring the
   printer, &yast; defaults to those marked <literal>recommended</literal>.
   Normally, it is not necessary to change the driver. However, if you want a
   color printer to print only in black and white, you can use a driver that
   does not support color printing. If you experience performance problems with
   a PostScript printer when printing graphics, try switching from a PostScript
   to a PCL driver (provided your printer understands PCL).
  </para>
  <para>
   If no driver for your printer is listed, try selecting a generic driver with
   an appropriate standard language from the list. Refer to your printer's
   documentation to find out what language (the set of commands controlling
   the printer) your printer supports. If this does not work, refer to
   <xref linkend="sec-yast-hw-print-local-get-ppd"/> for an alternative
   solution.
  </para>
  <para>
   A printer is always used through a print queue. This ensures that
   simultaneous jobs can be queued and processed one by one. Each print queue is
   assigned to a specific driver, and a printer can have multiple queues. As an
   example, this makes it possible to set up a second queue on a color printer
   that prints black and white only. Refer to
   <xref linkend="sec-print-workflow"/> for more information about print queues.
  </para>
  <procedure xml:id="pro-y2-hw-print-local-config">
   <title>Adding a new printer</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the &yast; printer module with <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu> <guimenu>Printer</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Printer Configurations</guimenu> screen click
     <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If the printer is already listed under <literal>Specify the
     Connection</literal>, proceed with the next step. Otherwise, try
     <guimenu>Detect More</guimenu> or start the <guimenu>Connection
     Wizard</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the text box under <literal>Find and Assign a Driver</literal> enter
     the vendor name and the model name and click <guimenu>Search
     for</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Choose a driver that matches your printer. It is recommended to choose the
     driver listed first. If no suitable driver is displayed, try the following.
    </para>
    <substeps performance="required">
     <step>
      <para>
       Check the search term.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Expand the search by clicking <guimenu>Find More</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Add a driver as described in
       <xref linkend="sec-yast-hw-print-local-get-ppd"/>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Specify the <literal>Default paper size</literal>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Set Arbitrary Name</guimenu> field, enter a unique name
     for the print queue.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The printer is now configured with the default settings and ready to use.
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to return to the <guimenu>Printer
     Configurations</guimenu> view. The newly configured printer is now visible
     in the list of printers.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-hw-print-local-get-ppd">
   <title>Adding drivers with &yast;</title>
   <para>
    Not all printer drivers available for &productname; are installed by
    default. When adding a printer no suitable driver is available in the
    <guimenu>Find and Assign a Driver</guimenu> dialog, install a driver package
    containing drivers for the printer:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Installing additional driver packages</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the &yast; printer module with <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu> <guimenu>Printer</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the <guimenu>Printer Configurations</guimenu> screen, click
      <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the <literal>Find and Assign a Driver</literal> section, click
      <guimenu>Driver Packages</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose one or more suitable driver packages from the list. Do
      <emphasis>not</emphasis> specify the path to a printer description file.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose <guimenu>OK</guimenu> and confirm the package installation.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To directly use these drivers, proceed as described in
      <xref linkend="pro-y2-hw-print-local-config"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    PostScript printers do not need printer driver software. PostScript
    printers need only a PostScript Printer Description (PPD) file which
    matches the particular model. PPD files are provided by the printer
    manufacturer.
   </para>
   <para>
    If no suitable PPD file is available in the <guimenu>Find and Assign a
    Driver</guimenu> dialog when adding a PostScript printer, install a PPD file
    for your printer:
   </para>
   <para>
    There are several sources of PPD files. It is recommended to first try
    additional driver packages that are shipped with &productname; but not
    installed by default (see below for installation instructions). If these
    packages do not contain suitable drivers for your printer, get PPD files
    directly from your printer vendor or from the driver CD of a PostScript
    printer. For details, see <xref linkend="sec-print-prob-ppd"/>.
    Alternatively, find PPD files at
    <link
    xlink:href="http://www.linuxfoundation.org/collaborate/workgroups/openprinting/database/databaseintro"/>,
    the <quote>OpenPrinting.org printer database</quote>. When using PPD files
    from OpenPrinting, keep in mind that they may not be supported by
    &productname;.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Adding a PPD file for PostScript printers</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the &yast; printer module with <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu> <guimenu>Printer</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the <guimenu>Printer Configurations</guimenu> screen, click
      <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the <literal>Find and Assign a Driver</literal> section, click
      <guimenu>Driver Packages</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Enter the full path to the PPD file into the text box under <literal>Make
      a Printer Description File Available</literal>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to return to the <literal>Add New Printer
      Configuration</literal> screen.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To directly use this PPD file, proceed as described in
      <xref linkend="pro-y2-hw-print-local-config"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-hw-print-local-tune">
   <title>Editing a local printer configuration</title>
   <para>
    By editing an existing configuration for a printer you can change basic
    settings such as connection type and driver. It is also possible to adjust
    the default settings for paper size, resolution, media source, etc. You can
    change identifiers of the printer by altering the printer description or
    location.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the &yast; printer module with <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu> <guimenu>Printer</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the <guimenu>Printer Configurations</guimenu> screen, choose a local
      printer configuration from the list and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Change the connection type or the driver as described in
      <xref linkend="pro-y2-hw-print-local-config"/>. This should only be
      necessary in case you have problems with the current configuration.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Optionally, make this printer the default by checking <guimenu>Default
      Printer</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Adjust default settings by clicking <guimenu>All Options for the
      Current Driver</guimenu>. To change a setting, expand the list of options
      by clicking the <literal>+</literal> sign. Change the default by
      clicking an option. Apply your changes with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-hw-print-network">
  <title>Configuring printing via the network with &yast;</title>
  <para>
   Network printers are not detected automatically. They must be configured
   manually using the &yast; printer module. Depending on your network setup,
   you can print to a print server (CUPS, LPD, SMB, or IPX) or directly to a
   network printer (preferably via TCP). Access the configuration view for
   network printing by choosing <guimenu>Printing via Network</guimenu> from
   the left pane in the &yast; printer module.
  </para>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-hw-print-network-cups">
   <title>Using CUPS</title>
   <para>
    In a Linux environment CUPS is usually used to print via the network. The
    simplest setup is to only print via a single CUPS server which can directly
    be accessed by all clients. Printing via more than one CUPS server requires
    a running local CUPS daemon that communicates with the remote CUPS servers.
   </para>
   <important>
    <title>Browsing network print queues</title>
    <para>
     CUPS servers announce their print queues over the network either via the
     traditional CUPS browsing protocol or via Bonjour/DNS-SD. Clients need
     to browse these lists so users can select specific printers to
     send their print jobs to. To browse network print queues, the
     service <systemitem class="daemon">cups-browsed</systemitem> provided by
     the package
     <systemitem class="resource">cups-filters-cups-browsed</systemitem> must run on all clients that print via CUPS
     servers. <systemitem class="daemon">cups-browsed</systemitem> is started
     automatically when configuring network printing with &yast;.
    </para>
    <para>
     If browsing does not work after starting
     <systemitem class="daemon">cups-browsed</systemitem>, the CUPS server(s)
     probably announce the network print queues via Bonjour/DNS-SD. In this
     case you need to additionally install the package
     <systemitem class="resource">avahi</systemitem> and start the associated
     service with <command>sudo systemctl start avahi-daemon</command> on all
     clients.
    </para>
   </important>
   <procedure>
    <title>Printing via a single CUPS server</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the &yast; printer module with <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu> <guimenu>Printer</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      From the left pane, select <guimenu>Print via Network</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Check <guimenu>Do All Your Printing Directly via One Single CUPS
      Server</guimenu> and specify the name or IP address of the server.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Test Server</guimenu> to make sure you have chosen the
      correct name or IP address.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to return to the <guimenu>Printer Configurations</guimenu>
      screen. All printers available via the CUPS server are now listed.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure>
    <title>Printing via multiple CUPS servers</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the &yast; printer module with <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu> <guimenu>Printer</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      From the left pane, select <guimenu>Print via Network</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Check <guimenu>Accept Printer Announcements from CUPS Servers</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Under <literal>General Settings</literal> specify which servers to use.
      You may accept connections from all networks available or from specific
      hosts. If you choose the latter option, you need to specify the host
      names or IP addresses.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> and then <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>
      when prompted to start a local CUPS server. After the server has started
      &yast; will return to the <guimenu>Printer Configurations</guimenu>
      screen. Click <guimenu>Refresh list</guimenu> to see the printers
      detected so far.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec-yast-hw-print-network-other">
   <title>Using print servers other than CUPS</title>
   <para>
    If your network offers print services via print servers other than CUPS,
    start the &yast; printer module with <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu><guimenu>Printer</guimenu></menuchoice> and
    select <guimenu>Print via Network</guimenu> from the left pane.
    Start the <guimenu>Connection Wizard</guimenu> and choose the appropriate
    <guimenu>Connection Type</guimenu>. Ask your network administrator for
    details on configuring a network printer in your environment.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-yast-hw-print-share">
  <title>Sharing printers over the network</title>
  <para>
   Printers managed by a local CUPS daemon can be shared over the network,
   effectively turning your machine into a CUPS server. Usually you share a
   printer by enabling so-called <quote>browsing mode</quote> in CUPS. If
   browsing is enabled, the local print queues are made available on the network
   for listening to remote CUPS daemons. It is also possible to set up a
   dedicated CUPS server that manages all print queues and can be accessed by
   remote clients directly. In this case, enabling browsing is not required.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <title>Sharing printers</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the &yast; printer module with <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu> <guimenu>Printer</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Share Printers</guimenu> from the left pane.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Allow Remote Access</guimenu>. Also check <guimenu>For
     computers within the local network</guimenu> and enable browsing mode by
     also checking <guimenu>Publish printers by default within the local
     network</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to restart the CUPS server and to return to
     the <guimenu>Printer Configurations</guimenu> screen.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Regarding CUPS and firewall settings, see
     <link xlink:href="https://en.opensuse.org/SDB:CUPS_and_SANE_Firewall_settings"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
