<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.add-ons">
 <title>Installing Add-On Products</title><indexterm>
 <primary>&yast;</primary>
 <secondary>add-on</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>add-on products</primary></indexterm>
 <abstract>
  <para>Add-on products are system extensions. They can either be free extensions based on
   &productname; (such as <xref linkend="sec.add-ons.sdk" xrefstyle="select:title no page"/>, or
   additional products requiring a registration key that is liable to costs (such as the &sle;
   &hasi;). Extensions and add-ons can be available on physical media or as repositories only
   that are available for you after registering your system at &scc; or a local registration
   server.</para>
  <para>Some add-on products are also provided by third parties, for example, binary-only drivers
   that are needed by certain hardware to function properly. If you have such hardware, refer to the
   release notes for more information about availability of binary drivers for your system. The
   release notes are available from <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/"/>, from
   &yast; or from <filename>/usr/share/doc/release-notes/</filename> in your installed
   system.</para>
  <para>A list of available add-on products and extensions for your product is available after
   having registered your system at &scc; or a local registration server. If you skipped the
   registration step during the installation, you can register your system at any time using the
   <guimenu>&scc; Configuration</guimenu> module in &yast;. For details, refer to <xref
    linkend="sec.add-ons.register"/>.</para>
</abstract>
 
 <sect1 id="sec.add-ons.sdk">
  <title>&sdk; (SDK) &productnumber;</title><indexterm>
      <primary>software</primary>
      <secondary>development</secondary>
      <tertiary>SUSE SDK</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm>
       <primary>SUSE SDK</primary></indexterm> <para>&sdk; &productnumber; is
       an add-on for &sle; &productnumber;. It is a complete tool kit for
       application development. In fact, to provide a comprehensive build
       system, &sdk; &productnumber; includes all the open source tools that
       were used to build the &sls; product. It provides you - as a developer,
       independent software vendor (ISV), or independent hardware vendor (IHV)
       - with all the tools needed to port applications to all the platforms
       supported by &sled; and &sls;. </para>
  
  <para>
   &sdk; also contains integrated development environments (IDEs),
   debuggers, code editors, and other related tools. It supports most major
   programming languages, including C, C++, Java, and most scripting
   languages. For your convenience, &sdk; includes multiple Perl packages
   that are not included in &sle;.
  </para>
  
  <para>
   The SDK is available for download from <ulink
   url="https://download.suse.com/"/>. Search for <literal>&sle; Software
   Development Kit</literal>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.add-ons.register">
  <title>Registering Your System</title>
  <para>If you skipped the
   registration step during the installation, you can register your system at any time using the
   <guimenu>&scc; Configuration</guimenu> module in &yast;.</para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>Start &yast; and select <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Support</guimenu>
      <guimenu>&scc; Configuration</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> to open the <guimenu>Registration</guimenu> dialog.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Provide the <guimenu>E-mail</guimenu> address associated with the &suse; account you
     or your organization uses to manage subscriptions. In case you do not have a SUSE account yet,
     go to the &scc; home page (<ulink url="&sccurl;"/>) to create one. </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Enter the <guimenu>Registration Code</guimenu> you received with your copy of
     &productname;.</para>
   </step>
   <step id="step.y2.register.final">
    <para>Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to start the registration process. If one or more
     local registration servers are available on your network, you will be able to choose one of
     them from a list. Alternatively, choose <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu> to ignore the local
     registration servers and register with the default &suse; registration server.</para>
    <para>During the registration the online update channels will be added to your installation
     setup. </para>
    <para>After successful registration, &yast; shows a list of extensions, add-ons, and modules
     that are available for your system. To select and install them, proceed with <xref
      linkend="sec.add-ons.extensions"/>.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 

 <sect1 id="sec.add-ons.extensions">
  <title>Installing Add-ons and Extensions (Without Physical Media)</title>
  <tip os="sled">
   <title>&sled;</title>
   <para> As of &sle; 12, &sled; is not only available as a separate product, but also as an
    extension for &sls;. If you register at the &scc;, the &sled; extension can be
    selected for installation. Note that installing it requires a valid registration key. </para>
  </tip>

  <para>The following procedure requires that you have registered your system with &scc;, or a
   local registration server. If you are in the process of registering your system, you will see a
   list of extensions, add-ons, and modules immediately after having completed <xref
    linkend="step.y2.register.final"/> of <xref linkend="sec.add-ons.register"/>. In that case, skip
   the next steps and proceed with <xref linkend="step.y2.extensions.list"/>.</para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>If you have registered earlier, start &yast; and select <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Support</guimenu>
      <guimenu>&scc; Configuration</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> to open the registration dialog.</para>
    <para>It will inform you that the system is already registered.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>To display a list of extensions, add-ons, and modules that are available for your product,
     click <guimenu>Select Extensions</guimenu>.</para>
    <note>
     <title>Available Extensions and Modules</title>
     <para> The amount of available extensions and modules depends on the registration server. A
      local registration server may only offer update repositories and no additional extensions at
      all. </para>
    </note>
   </step>
   <step id="step.y2.extensions.list">
    <para>Click an entry to see its description.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Select one or multiple entries for installation by activating their check marks.</para>
    <figure>
     <title>Installation of System Extensions</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_extension_list.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_extension_list.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step id="step.y2.extensions.final">
    <para>Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed.</para>
    <para>The repositories for the selected extensions will be added to your system&mdash;no
     additional installation sources are required.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>After the successful installation of extensions, &yast; offers you a dialog in which you
   can install further add-ons (that are available on media). To select and install them, proceed
   with <xref linkend="sec.add-ons.install"/>.</para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.add-ons.install">
  <title>Installing Add-ons and Extensions (from Media)</title>
  
  <para>When installing an add-on from media, you can select various types of product media, like
   DVD/CD, USB mass storage devices (such as USB flash drives or disks), or a local directory or ISO
   image. The media can also be provided by a network server, for example, via HTTP, FTP,
   NFS, or Samba. </para>
 
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>If you are in the process of registering your system or installing extensions, you will
     see the &yast; <guimenu>Add-On Products</guimenu> dialog immediately after having completed
      <xref linkend="step.y2.extensions.final"/> of <xref linkend="sec.add-ons.extensions"/>. In
     that case, skip the next steps and proceed with <xref linkend="step.y2.add-ons.type"/>.</para>
    <para>Otherwise start &yast; and select <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Add-On Products</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> to open the &yast; <guimenu>Add-On Products</guimenu> module. Alternatively,
     start it from the command line with <command>sudo yast2 add-on</command>. </para>
   <para>If you started the module from scratch, it will show an overview of already installed
     add-on products. </para>
    <figure id="fig.y2.sw.addon.installed">
     <title>List of Installed Add-on Products</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_addon_installed.png" width="90%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_addon_installed.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To install a new add-on product from there, click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step id="step.y2.add-ons.type">
    <para> In the <guimenu>Add-On Product</guimenu> dialog, select the option that matches your type
     of medium from which you want to install the add-on product:</para>
    <figure id="fig.y2.sw.addon.new">
     <title>Installation of an Add-on Product</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_addon_new.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_addon_new.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>To scan your network for installation servers announcing their services via SLP, select
        <guimenu>Scan Using SLP</guimenu> and click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.</para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>To add a repository from a removable medium, choose the relevant option and insert the
       medium or connect the USB device to the machine, respectively. Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>
       to start the installation. </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>For the majority of media types, you will be asked to specify the path (or URL) to the
       media after selecting the respective option and clicking <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. Specifying
       a <guimenu>Repository Name</guimenu> is optional. If none is specified, &yast; will use
       the product name or the URL as repository name.</para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para> The option <guimenu>Download Repository Description Files</guimenu> is activated by
     default. If you deactivate the option, &yast; will automatically download the files later,
     if needed. </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Depending on the repository you have added, you may be asked if you
     want to import the &gpg; key with which it is signed or asked to agree
     to a license.
    </para>
    <para>
     After confirming these messages, &yast; will download and parse the
     metadata. It will add the repository to the list of <guimenu>Configured
     Repositories</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If needed, adjust the repository <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> as
     described in <xref linkend="sec.y2.sw.instsource.manage"/>. 
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Confirm your changes with <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to close the 
    configuration dialog. </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After having successfully added the repository for the add-on media,
     the software manager starts and you can install packages. Refer to
     <xref
      linkend="cha.y2.sw"/> for details.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 </chapter>
