<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.ftp">
 <title>Setting up an FTP Server with &yast;</title><indexterm>
 <primary>FTP server</primary>
 <secondary>configuring</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>configuring</primary>
 <secondary>FTP server</secondary></indexterm>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   Using the &yast; <guimenu>FTP Server</guimenu> module, you can configure
   your machine to function as an FTP (File Transfer Protocol) server.
   Anonymous and/or authenticated users can connect to your machine and
   download files using the FTP protocol. Depending on the configuration,
   they can also upload files to the FTP server. &yast; provides a unified
   configuration interface for various FTP server daemons installed on your
   system.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <para>
  You can use the &yast; <guimenu>FTP Server</guimenu> configuration module
  to configure two different FTP server daemons:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <systemitem class="daemon">vsftpd</systemitem> (Very Secure FTP Daemon)
    and
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <systemitem class="daemon">pure-ftpd</systemitem>
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  Only installed servers can be configured. <phrase os="osuse"> Standard
  &opensusereg; media do not contain the
  <systemitem class="resource"
    >pure-ftpd</systemitem> package. However,
  if the <systemitem class="resource">pure-ftpd</systemitem> package is
  installed from another repository, it can be configured using the &yast;
  module. </phrase>
 </para>
 <para>
  The vsftpd and pure-ftpd servers have slightly different configuration
  options, especially in the <guimenu>Experts Settings</guimenu> dialog.
  This chapter describes the settings of the vsftpd server
  <phrase os="osuse">, being the default server for &opensuse;</phrase> .
 </para>
 <para>
  If the &yast; FTP Server module is not available in your system, install
  the <systemitem class="resource">yast2-ftp-server</systemitem> package.
 </para>
 <para>
  To configure the FTP server using &yast;, follow these steps:
 </para>
 <procedure>
  <step>
   <para>
    Open &yast; Control Center and choose <menuchoice> <guimenu>Network
    Services</guimenu> <guimenu>FTP Server</guimenu> </menuchoice> or run
    the <command>yast2 ftp-server</command> command as &rootuser;.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    If there is not any FTP server installed in your system, you will be
    asked which server to install when the &yast; FTP Server module starts.
    Choose a server <phrase os="osuse">(vsftpd is the standard server for
    &opensuse;) </phrase>and confirm the dialog. If there are two servers
    installed, choose the preferred server and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    In the <guimenu>Start-Up</guimenu> dialog, configure the options for
    starting of the FTP server. For more information, see
    <xref linkend="sec.ftp.start"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    In the <guimenu>General</guimenu> dialog, configure FTP directories,
    welcome message, file creation masks and various other parameters. For
    more information, see <xref
     linkend="sec.ftp.general"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    In the <guimenu>Performance</guimenu> dialog, set the parameters that
    affect the load on the FTP server. For more information, see
    <xref linkend="sec.ftp.performance"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    In the <guimenu>Authentication</guimenu> dialog, set whether the FTP
    server should be available for anonymous and/or authenticated users. For
    more information, see <xref
     linkend="sec.ftp.auth"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    In the <guimenu>Expert Settings</guimenu> dialog, configure the
    operation mode of the FTP server, SSL connections and firewall settings.
    For more information, see <xref
     linkend="sec.ftp.expert"/>.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Press <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> to save the configurations.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
 <sect1 id="sec.ftp.start">
  <title>Starting the FTP Server</title>

  <para>
   In the <guimenu>Service Start</guimenu> frame of the <guimenu>FTP
   Start-Up</guimenu> dialog set the way the FTP server is started up. You
   can choose between starting the server automatically during the system
   boot and starting it manually. If the FTP server should be started only
   after an FTP connection request, choose <guimenu>Via xinetd</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   The current status of the FTP server is shown in the <guimenu>Switch On
   and Off</guimenu> frame of the <guimenu>FTP Start-Up</guimenu> dialog.
   Start the FTP server by clicking <guimenu>Start FTP Now</guimenu>. To
   stop the server, click <guimenu>Stop FTP Now</guimenu>. After having
   changed the settings of the server click <guimenu>Save Settings and
   Restart FTP Now</guimenu>. Your configurations will be saved by leaving
   the configuration module with <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   The <guimenu>Selected Service</guimenu> frame of the <guimenu>FTP
   Start-Up</guimenu> dialog shows which FTP server is used: either vsftpd
   or pure-ftpd. If both servers are installed, you can switch between
   them&mdash;the current configuration will automatically be converted.
   <phrase os="osuse">The pure-ftpd package is not included in the standard
   &opensuse; media so you have to install it from a different installation
   source if you want to use it.</phrase>
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.yast2.ftp-start-up">
   <title>FTP Server Configuration — Start-Up</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="yast2_ftp-start-up.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="yast2_ftp-start-up.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.ftp.general">
  <title>FTP General Settings</title>

  <para>
   In the <guimenu>General Settings</guimenu> frame of the <guimenu>FTP
   General Settings</guimenu> dialog you can set the <guimenu>Welcome
   message</guimenu> which is shown after connecting to the FTP server.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you check the <guimenu>Chroot Everyone</guimenu> option, all local
   users will be placed in a chroot jail in their home directory after
   login. This option has security implications, especially if the users
   have upload permission or shell access, so be careful enabling this
   option.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you check the <guimenu>Verbose Logging</guimenu> option, all FTP
   requests and responses are logged.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can limit permissions of files created by anonymous and/or
   authenticated users with umask. Set the file creation mask for anonymous
   users in <guimenu>Umask for Anonymous</guimenu> and the file creation
   mask for authenticated users in <guimenu>Umask for Authenticated
   Users</guimenu>. The masks should be entered as octal numbers with a
   leading zero. For more information about umask, see the umask man page
   (<command>man&nbsp;1p&nbsp;umask</command>).
  </para>

  <para>
   In the <guimenu>FTP Directories</guimenu> frame set the directories used
   for anonymous and authorized users. With <guimenu>Browse</guimenu>, you
   can select a directory to be used from the local filesystem. The default
   FTP directory for anonymous users is <filename>/srv/ftp</filename>. Note
   that vsftpd does not allow this directory to be writable for all users.
   The subdirectory <filename>upload</filename> with write permissions for
   anonymous users is created instead.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>Write Permissions in FTP Directory</title>
   <para>
    The pure-ftpd server allows the FTP directory for anonymous users to be
    writable. When switching between servers, make sure you remove the write
    permissions in the directory that was used with pure-ftpd before
    switching back to the vsftpd server.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.ftp.performance">
  <title>FTP Performance Settings</title>

  <para>
   In the <guimenu>Performance</guimenu> dialog set the parameters which
   affect the load on the FTP server. <guimenu>Max Idle Time</guimenu> is
   the maximum time (in minutes) the remote client may spend between FTP
   commands. In case of longer inactivity, the remote client is
   disconnected. <guimenu>Max Clients for One IP</guimenu> determines the
   maximum number of clients which can be connected from a single IP
   address. <guimenu>Max Clients</guimenu> determines the maximum number of
   clients which may be connected. Any additional clients will get an error
   message.
  </para>

  <para>
   The maximum data transfer rate (in KB/s) is set in <guimenu>Local Max
   Rate</guimenu> for local authenticated users, and in <guimenu>Anonymous
   Max Rate</guimenu> for anonymous clients respectively. The default value
   for the rate settings is <literal>0</literal>, which means unlimited data
   transfer rate.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.ftp.auth">
  <title>Authentication</title>

  <para>
   In the <guimenu>Enable/Disable Anonymous and Local Users</guimenu> frame
   of the <guimenu>Authentication</guimenu> dialog, you are able to set
   which users are allowed to access your FTP server. You can choose between
   the following options: granting access to anonymous users only, to
   authenticated users only (with accounts on the system) or to both types
   of users.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you want to allow users to upload files to the FTP server, check
   <guimenu>Enable Upload</guimenu> in the <guimenu>Uploading</guimenu>
   frame of the <guimenu>Authentication</guimenu> dialog. Here you are able
   to allow uploading or creating directories even for anonymous users by
   checking the respective box.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>vsftp&mdash;Allowing File Upload for Anonymous Users</title>
   <para>
    If a vsftpd server is used and you want anonymous users to be able to
    upload files or create directories, a subdirectory with writing
    permissions for all users has to be created in the anonymous FTP
    directory.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.ftp.expert">
  <title>Expert Settings</title>

  <para>
   An FTP server can run in active or in passive mode. By default the server
   runs in passive mode. To switch into active mode, just uncheck
   <guimenu>Enable Passive Mode</guimenu> option in <guimenu>Expert
   Settings</guimenu> dialog. You can also change the range of ports on the
   server used for the data stream by tweaking the <guimenu>Min Port for
   Pas. Mode</guimenu> and <guimenu>Max Port for Pas. Mode</guimenu>
   options.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you want encrypted communication between clients and the server, you
   can <guimenu>Enable SSL</guimenu>. Check the versions of the protocol to
   be supported and specify the DSA certificate to be used for SSL encrypted
   connections.
<!--use the FTPS protocol (FTP/SSH). However note that FTPS is different
   from the much more common SFTP (SSH File Transport Protocol) protocol.
    If you want to use the FTPS, you can set SSL options in the
    <guimenu>Expert Settings</guimenu> dialog.-->
  </para>

  <para>
   If your system is protected by a firewall, check <guimenu>Open Port in
   Firewall</guimenu> to enable a connection to the FTP server.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.ftp.info">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   For more information about FTP servers read the manual pages of
   <phrase os="sles"
     ><command>pure-ftpd</command>, </phrase>
   <command>vsftpd</command> and <command>vsftpd.conf</command>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
