<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<sect1 id="sec.y2.sw.instsource">
 <title>Managing Software Repositories and Services</title>

 <para>
  If you want to install third-party software, add additional software
  repositories to your system. By default, the product repositories such as
  &productname;-DVD &productnumber; and a matching update repository are
  automatically configured after you have registered your system. For more
  information about registration, see
  <xref
  linkend="sec.i.yast2.conf.manual.cc"/> or
  <xref linkend="sec.add-ons.register"/>. Depending on the initially
  selected product, a separate language add-on repository with translations,
  dictionaries, etc. might also be configured.
 </para>

 <para>
  To manage repositories, start &yast; and select <menuchoice>
  <guimenu>Software</guimenu> <guimenu>Software Repositories</guimenu>
  </menuchoice>. The <guimenu>Configured Software Repositories</guimenu>
  dialog opens. Here, you can also manage subscriptions to so-called
  <guimenu>Services</guimenu> by changing the <guimenu>View</guimenu> at the
  right corner of the dialog to <guimenu>All Services</guimenu>. A Service
  in this context is a <guimenu>Repository Index Service</guimenu> (RIS)
  that can offer one or more software repositories. Such a Service can be
  changed dynamically by its administrator or vendor.
 </para>

 <para>
  Each repository provides files describing content of the repository
  (package names, versions, etc.). These repository description files are
  downloaded to a local cache that is used by &yast;. To ensure their
  integrity, software repositories can be signed with the &gpg; Key of the
  repository maintainer. Whenever you add a new repository, &yast; offers
  the ability to import its key.
 </para>

 <warning>
  <title>Trusting External Software Sources</title>
  <para>
   Before adding external software repositories to your list of
   repositories, make sure this repository can be trusted. &productname; is
   not responsible for any potential problems arising from software
   installed from third-party software repositories.
  </para>
 </warning>

 <sect2 id="sec.y2.sw.instsource.add">
  <title>Adding Software Repositories</title>
  <para>
   You can either add repositories from DVD/CD, USB mass storage devices
   (such as USB flash disks), or a local directory or ISO image.
  </para>
  <para>
   To add repositories from the <guimenu>Configured Software
   Repositories</guimenu> dialog in &yast; proceed as follows:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select one of the options listed in the dialog:
    </para>
    <figure id="fig.y2.sw.repo.new">
     <title>Adding A Software Repository</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_addon_new.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_addon_new.png" width="65%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To scan your network for installation servers announcing their
       services via SLP, select <guimenu>Scan Using SLP</guimenu> and click
       <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To add a repository from a removable medium, choose the relevant
       option and insert the medium or connect the USB device to the
       machine, respectively. Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to start the
       installation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For the majority of repositories, you will be asked to specify the
       path (or URL) to the media after selecting the respective option and
       clicking <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. Specifying a <guimenu>Repository
       Name</guimenu> is optional. If none is specified, &yast; will use the
       product name or the URL as repository name.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     The option <guimenu>Download Repository Description Files</guimenu> is
     activated by default. If you deactivate the option, &yast; will
     automatically download the files later, if needed.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Depending on the repository you have added, you may be asked if you
     want to import the &gpg; key with which it is signed or asked to agree
     to a license.
    </para>
    <para>
     After confirming these messages, &yast; will download and parse the
     metadata. It will add the repository to the list of <guimenu>Configured
     Repositories</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If needed, adjust the repository <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> as
     described in <xref linkend="sec.y2.sw.instsource.manage"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Confirm your changes with <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to close the
     configuration dialog.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After having successfully added the repository, the software manager
     starts and you can install packages from this repository. For details,
     refer to <xref
      linkend="cha.y2.sw"/><phrase os="sled"> or
     <xref
        linkend="sec.y2.sw.gtk"/></phrase>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.y2.sw.instsource.manage">
  <title>Managing Repository Properties</title>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Configured Software Repositories</guimenu> overview of the
   <guimenu>Software Repositories</guimenu> lets you change the following
   repository properties:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Status</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The repository status can either be <guimenu>Enabled</guimenu> or
      <guimenu>Disabled</guimenu>. You can only install packages from
      repositories that are enabled. To turn a repository off temporarily,
      select it and deactivate <guimenu>Enable</guimenu>. You can also
      double-click a repository name to toggle its status. If you want to
      remove a repository completely, click <guimenu>Delete</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Refresh</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      When refreshing a repository, its content description (package names,
      versions, etc.) is downloaded to a local cache that is used by &yast;.
      It is sufficient to do this once for static repositories such as CDs
      or DVDs, whereas repositories whose content changes often should be
      refreshed frequently. The easiest way to keep a repository's cache
      up-to-date is to choose <guimenu>Automatically Refresh</guimenu>. To
      do a manual refresh click <guimenu>Refresh</guimenu> and select one of
      the options.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Keep Downloaded Packages</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Packages from remote repositories are downloaded before being
      installed. By default, they are deleted upon a successful
      installation. Activating <guimenu>Keep Downloaded Packages</guimenu>
      prevents the deletion of downloaded packages. The download location is
      configured in <filename>/etc/zypp/zypp.conf</filename>, by default it
      is <filename>/var/cache/zypp/packages</filename>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Priority</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The <guimenu>Priority</guimenu> of a repository is a value between
      <literal>1</literal> and <literal>200</literal>, with
      <literal>1</literal> being the highest priority and
      <literal>200</literal> the lowest priority. Any new repositories that
      are added with &yast; get a priority of <literal>99</literal> by
      default. If you do not care about a priority value for a certain
      repository, you can also set the value to <literal>0</literal> to
      apply the default priority to that repository (<literal>99</literal>).
      If a package is available in more than one repository, then the
      repository with the highest priority takes precedence. This is useful
      if you want to avoid downloading packages unnecessarily from the
      Internet by giving a local repository (for example, a DVD) a higher
      priority.
     </para>
     <important>
      <title>Priority vs. Version</title>
      <para>
       The repository with the highest priority takes precedence in any
       case. Therefore, make sure that the update repository always has the
       highest priority, otherwise you might install an outdated version
       that will not be updated until the next online update.
      </para>
     </important>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Name and URL</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To change a repository name or its URL, select it from the list with a
      single-click and then click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.y2.sw.repo.gpg-keys">
  <title>Managing Repository Keys</title>
  <para>
   To ensure their integrity, software repositories can be signed with the
   &gpg; Key of the repository maintainer. Whenever you add a new
   repository, &yast; offers to import its key. Verify it as you would do
   with any other &gpg; key and make sure it does not change. If you detect
   a key change, something might be wrong with the repository. Disable the
   repository as an installation source until you know the cause of the key
   change.
  </para>
  <para>
   To manage all imported keys, click <guimenu>GPG Keys</guimenu> in the
   <guimenu>Configured Software Repositories</guimenu> dialog. Select an
   entry with the mouse to show the key properties at the bottom of the
   window. <guimenu>Add</guimenu>, <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> or
   <guimenu>Delete</guimenu> keys with a click on the respective buttons.
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
