<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha-add-ons"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Installing Modules, Extensions, and Third Party Add-On Products</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    Modules and extensions add parts or functionality to the system.
    Modules are fully supported parts of &productname; with a different life
    cycle and update timeline. They are a set of packages, have a clearly
    defined scope and are delivered via online channel only.
   </para>
   <para>
    Extensions, such as the Workstation Extension or the High Availability
    Extension, add extra functionality to the system and require an own
    registration key that is liable for costs. Extensions are delivered via
    online channel or physical media. Registering at the &scc; or a local
    registration server is a prerequisite for subscribing to the
    online channels. The Package Hub (<xref linkend="sec-add-ons-package-hub" />)
    and &sdk; (<xref linkend="sec-add-ons-sdk" />) extensions are exceptions which
    do not require a registration key and are not covered by SUSE support agreements.
   </para>
   <para>
    A list of modules and extensions for your product is available
    after having registered your system at &scc; or a local registration
    server. If you skipped the registration step during the installation, you
    can register your system at any time using the <guimenu>&scc;
    Configuration</guimenu> module in &yast;. <phrase os="sles;sled">For
    details, refer to <xref linkend="sec-update-registersystem"/>.</phrase>
   </para>
   <para>
    Some add-on products are also provided by third parties, for example,
    binary-only drivers that are needed by certain hardware to function
    properly. If you have such hardware, refer to the release notes for more
    information about availability of binary drivers for your system. The
    release notes are available from
    <phrase os="sles;sled"><link
    xlink:href="http://www.suse.com/releasenotes/"/></phrase><phrase
    os="osuse"><link
    xlink:href="https://doc.opensuse.org/release-notes/"/></phrase>,
    from &yast; or from <filename>/usr/share/doc/release-notes/</filename> in
    your installed system.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-add-ons-modulelist">
  <title>List of Optional Modules</title>
  <para>
   Besides the base server operating system, &productname; 12 provides optional
   modules included in the subscription. Each module has a different lifecycle.
   This approach offers faster integration with upstream updates. Below is a
   list of all optional modules together with brief descriptions:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry os="sles;sled">
    <term>Software Development Kit</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This is the Software Development Kit (SDK) for the family of &sle;
      products. It is a free of charge extension for partners and customers
      working with &sls;, Desktop, and derived products.
     </para>
     <para>
      For more information about &sdk;, refer to
      <xref linkend="sec-add-ons-sdk"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry os="sles;sled">
    <term>Package Hub</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      &suse; Package Hub provides access to community maintained packages built
      to run on &productname;. Built from the same sources used in the
      &opensuse; distributions, these quality packages provide additional
      software to what is found in &productname;.
     </para>
     <para>
      For more information about &suse; Package Hub, refer to
      <xref linkend="sec-add-ons-package-hub"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry os="sles">
    <term>Advanced Systems Management Module</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This module contains three components to support system administrators in
      automating tasks in the data center and cloud: the configuration
      management tools 'CFEngine' and 'puppet', and the new "machinery"
      infrastructure. Machinery is a systems management toolbox that allows you
      to inspect systems remotely, store their system descriptions, and create
      new system images to deploy in data centers and clouds.
     </para>
     <para>
      For more information about the Machinery project, see <link
       xlink:href="http://machinery-project.org/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry os="sles;sled">
    <term>Containers Module</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This module contains several packages revolving around containers and
      related tools, including the &deng; and prepackaged images for &sls; 11
      and &sls; 12.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry os="sles">
    <term>HPC Module</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The HPC Module provides a selected set of tools and components used in
      High Performance Computing environments. To fulfill changing customer
      needs for leading edge HPC support on both hardware and software, this
      module provides software components frequently updated to the latest
      versions available. The selection of software components has been inspired
      by (but not limited to) what is provided by the OpenHPC community project
      at <link xlink:href="http://openhpc.community/"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry os="sles">
    <term>Legacy Module</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The Legacy Module helps you migrate applications from older systems to
      &productname; 12. For organizations moving from UNIX to Linux, this module
      may be essential. Many older applications require packages that are no
      longer available with the latest &productname; version.  This module
      provides those packages. It includes packages such as sendmail, syslog-ng,
      IBM Java6 and a number of libraries (for example, openssl-0.9.8).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry os="sles">
    <term>Public Cloud Module</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The Public Cloud Module is a collection of tools to create and manage
      public cloud images from the command line.  When building your own images
      with &kiwi; or &susestudio;, initialization code specific to the target
      cloud is included in that image.
     </para>
     <para>
      The Public Cloud Module contains four patterns:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Amazon–Web–Services (aws–cli, cloud–init)
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Microsoft–Azure (WALinuxAgent)
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Google–Cloud–Platform (gcimagebundle,
        google–api–python–client, google–cloud–sdk, google–daemon,
        google–startup–scripts)
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        OpenStack (OpenStack–heat–cfntools, cloud–init)
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry os="sles">
    <term>&suse; &cap; Tools Module</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The &suse; &cap; Tools Module is a collection of tools that enables you
      to interact with the &suse; &cap; product itself, providing the
      commandline client for instance.
     </para>
     <para>
      The module has a different lifecycle than &sls; itself; please check the
      Release Notes for further details.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry os="sles">
    <term>Toolchain Module</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This module offers software developers a current toolchain consisting of
      GNU Compiler Collection (GCC) and related packages as well as updated
      applications, improvements, new standards and additional hardware
      features. It allows software developers to benefit of new features of the
      most recent GCC release and brings improvements in language support, like
      for most C++14 changes and more Fortran 2008 and 2015 support, as well as
      many new optimizations. For more details, see <link
       xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/gcc-5/changes.html"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry os="sles">
    <term>Web and Scripting Module</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The Web and Scripting Module delivers a comprehensive set of scripting
      languages, frameworks and related tools to help developers and system
      administrators accelerate the creation of stable, modern web
      applications. The module includes recent versions of dynamic languages,
      such as PHP and Python. If you intend to run a web server or host
      applications that have web portals or require server-side scripts, then
      the Web and Scripting Module is a must.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-add-ons-extensions" os="sles">
  <title>List of Available Extensions</title>
  <!-- para taken from SLE15 Modules & Extensions Guide  -->
  <para>
   Extensions provide advanced capabilities for tasks such as live patching
   and high availability clustering to &productname;. They are offered as
   subscriptions and require a registration key that is liable for costs.
   Usually, extensions have their own release notes that are available from
   <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes"/>.
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>&ha;</term>
    <listitem>
     <!-- description taken from https://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1110097#c3 -->
     <para>
      &sle; &ha; provides mature, industry-leading open-source
      high-availability clustering technologies that are easy to set up and
      use. It can be deployed in physical and/or virtual environments, and can
      cluster physical servers, virtual servers, or any combination of the two
      to suit your business needs.
     </para>
     <para>
      &ha; support is included in subscription for &sles4sap;. It is also
      available as an extension for &sls; and &slehpc;.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>&ha; Geo Clustering</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      &hageo; is an industry-leading open source high availability system
      designed to manage cluster servers in data centers anywhere in the world.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Live Patching</term>
    <listitem>
     <!-- description taken from / based on description from SCC -->
     <para>
      With &sle; Live Patching, you can perform critical kernel patching
      without shutting down your system, reducing the need for planned downtime
      and increasing service availability.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Workstation Extension</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The Workstation Extension extends the functionality of &sls; with
      packages of &sled;, like additional desktop applications and libraries.
      It allows to combine both products to create a full featured workstation.
     </para>
     <warning>
      <title>Unsupported Kernel Modules</title>
      <para>
       The Workstation Extension installs the
       <package>kernel-default-extra</package> package, which includes additional
       kernel modules for desktop usage and enables loading of unsupported
       modules. If actually loaded, these modules may compromise your &slea;
       support status.
      </para>
      <para>
       Please evaluate if your hardware really requires additional kernel modules,
       and if so, test this expanded driver set in addition to the default set
       from the <package>kernel-default</package> package for possible
       configuration conflicts.
      </para>
      <para>
       To prevent installation of the <package>kernel-default-extra</package>
       package, run <command>zypper addlock kernel-default-extra</command>.
      </para>
     </warning>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>&susemgr; Server</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      &susemgr; lets you efficiently manage physical, virtual, and cloud-based
      Linux systems. It provides automated and cost-effective configuration and
      software management, asset management, and system provisioning.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>&susemgr; Proxy</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      &susemgr; Proxies extend large and/or geographically dispersed &susemgr;
      environments to reduce load on the &susemgr; Server, lower bandwidth
      needs, and provide faster local updates.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>&cloud; 9</term>
    <listitem>
     <!-- cwickert 2018-09-25 FIXME Add better description. In the meantime, use
      the one from https://www.suse.com/documentation/suse-openstack-cloud-8/ -->
     <para>
      &cloud; is powered by &ostack;, the leading community driven, open
      source, cloud infrastructure project, and packaged with &sls;. The
      product is fully integrated with &suse; maintenance and support
      infrastructure. It is an ideal solution for customers looking to
      deploy a cloud with enterprise levels of stability and support.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>&cloud-crow; 9</term>
    <listitem>
     <!-- cwickert 2018-09-25 FIXME Add better description. In the meantime, use
      the one from https://www.suse.com/documentation/suse-openstack-cloud-8/singlehtml/book_deployment/book_deployment.html#pre.cloud.deploy -->
     <para>
      &cloud-crow; is an open source software solution that provides the
      fundamental capabilities to deploy and manage a cloud infrastructure
      powered by &ostack;, the leading community-driven, open source cloud
      infrastructure project. It seamlessly manages and provisions workloads
      across a heterogeneous cloud environment in a secure, compliant, and
      fully-supported manner.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-add-ons-installation">
  <title>Installing Modules and Extensions from Online Channels</title>

  <tip os="sles;sled">
   <title>&sled;</title>
   <para>
    As of &sle; 12, &sled; is not only available as a separate product, but
    also as a Workstation Extension for &sls;. If you register at the &scc;,
    the Workstation Extension can be selected for installation. Note that
    installing it requires a valid registration key.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <para os="sles;sled">
   The following procedure requires that you have registered your system with
   &scc;, or a local registration server. When
   registering your system, you will see a list of extensions and modules
   immediately after having completed <xref linkend="step-y2-register-final"/>
   of <xref linkend="sec-update-registersystem"/>. In that case, skip the next
   steps and proceed with <xref linkend="step-y2-extensions-list"/>.
  </para>
   <note>
    <title>Viewing Already Installed Add-Ons</title>
    <para>
     To view already installed add-ons, start &yast; and select
     <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Add-Ons</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>
    </para>
   </note>
  <procedure xml:id="pro-add-ons-extensions">
   <title>Installing Add-ons and Extensions from Online Channels with &yast;</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start &yast; and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Add System Extensions or Modules</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para>
     &yast; connects to the registration server and displays a list of
     <guimenu>Available Extensions and Modules</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <note>
     <title>Available Extensions and Modules</title>
     <para>
      The amount of available extensions and modules depends on the
      registration server. A local registration server may only offer update
      repositories and no additional extensions.
     </para>
    </note>
    <note>
     <title>Module Life Cycles</title>
     <para>
      Life cycle end dates of modules are available at
      <link xlink:href="https://scc.suse.com/docs/lifecycle/sle/12/modules"/>.
     </para>
    </note>
   </step>
   <step xml:id="step-y2-extensions-list">
    <para>
     Click an entry to see its description.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select one or multiple entries for installation by activating their check
     marks.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Installation of System Extensions</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_extension_list.png" width="70%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_extension_list.png" width="65%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step xml:id="step-y2-extensions-final">
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Depending on the repositories to be added for the extension or module, you
     may be prompted to import the repository's &gpg; key or asked to agree to a license.
    </para>
    <para>
     After confirming these messages, &yast; will download and parse the
     metadata. The repositories for the selected extensions will be added to
     your system&mdash;no additional installation sources are required.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If needed, adjust the repository <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> as
     described in <xref linkend="sec-y2-sw-instsource-manage"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <note>
   <title>For More Information</title>
   <para>
    White paper
    <link
   xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/docrep/documents/huz0a6bf9a/suse_linux_enterprise_server_12_modules_white_paper.pdf">
    SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 Modules</link>.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-add-ons-install">
  <title>Installing Extensions and Third Party Add-On Products from Media</title>

  <para>
   When installing an extension or add-on product from media, you can select
   various types of product media, like DVD/CD, removable mass storage devices
   (such as flash disks), or a local directory or ISO image. The media can also
   be provided by a network server, for example, via HTTP, FTP, NFS, or Samba.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start &yast; and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Add-On Products</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Alternatively, start the
     &yast; <guimenu>Add-On Products</guimenu> module from the command line
     with <command>sudo yast2 add-on</command>.
    </para>
    <para>
     The dialog will show an overview of already installed add-on products,
     modules and extensions.
    </para>
    <figure xml:id="fig-y2-sw-addon-installed">
     <title>List of Installed Add-on Products, Modules and Extensions</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_addon_installed.png" width="90%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_addon_installed.png" width="80%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Choose <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to install a new add-on product.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step xml:id="step-y2-add-ons-type">
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Add-On Product</guimenu> dialog, select the option that
     matches the type of medium from which you want to install:
    </para>
    <figure xml:id="fig-y2-sw-addon-new">
     <title>Installation of an Add-on Product or an Extension</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_addon_new.png" width="70%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_addon_new.png" width="65%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To scan your network for installation servers announcing their services
       via SLP, select <guimenu>Scan Using SLP</guimenu> and click
       <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To add a repository from a removable medium, choose the relevant option
       and insert the medium or connect the USB device to the machine,
       respectively. Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to start the installation.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       For most media types, you will be prompted to specify the path
       (or URL) to the media after selecting the respective option and clicking
       <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. Specifying a <guimenu>Repository Name</guimenu>
       is optional. If none is specified, &yast; will use the product name or
       the URL as the repository name.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     The option <guimenu>Download Repository Description Files</guimenu> is
     activated by default. If you deactivate the option, &yast; will
     automatically download the files later, if needed.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Depending on the repository you have added, you may be prompted
     to import the repository's &gpg; key or asked to agree to a
     license.
    </para>
    <para>
     After confirming these messages, &yast; will download and parse the
     metadata. It will add the repository to the list of <guimenu>Configured
     Repositories</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If needed, adjust the repository <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> as
     described in <xref linkend="sec-y2-sw-instsource-manage"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Confirm your changes with <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to close the configuration
     dialog.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After having successfully added the repository for the add-on media, the
     software manager starts and you can install packages. For details, refer
     to <xref linkend="cha-y2-sw"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-add-ons-sdk">
  <title>&sdk; (SDK) &productnumber;</title>
  <para>
   &sdk; &productnumber; is an extension for &sle; &productnumber;. It is a
   complete tool kit for application development. In fact, to provide a
   comprehensive build system, &sdk; &productnumber; includes all the open
   source tools that were used to build the &sls; product. It provides you as a
   developer, independent software vendor (ISV), or independent hardware vendor
   (IHV) with all the tools needed to port applications to all the platforms
   supported by &sled; and &sls;.
  </para>

  <para>
   The &sdk; does not require a registration key and is not covered
   by SUSE support agreements.
  </para>

  <para>
   &sdk; also contains integrated development environments (IDEs), debuggers,
   code editors, and other related tools. It supports most major programming
   languages, including C, C++, Java, and most scripting languages. For your
   convenience, &sdk; includes multiple Perl packages that are not included in
   &sle;.
  </para>

  <para>
   The SDK extension is available via an online channel from the &scc;.
   Alternatively, go to
   <link
   xlink:href="http://download.suse.com/"/>, search for <literal>&sle;
   Software Development Kit</literal> and download it from there. Refer to
   <xref linkend="cha-add-ons"/> for details.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-add-ons-package-hub">
  <title>&suse; Package Hub</title>
  <para>
   In the list of <emphasis>Available Extensions and Modules</emphasis>
   you find the &suse; Package Hub. It is available without any additional
   fee. It provides a large set of additional community packages for &sle;
   that can  easily be installed but are <emphasis>not</emphasis>
   supported by &suse;.
  </para>
  <para>
   More information about &suse; Package Hub and how to contribute is
   available at <link xlink:href="https://packagehub.suse.com/"/>
  </para>
  <important>
   <title>&suse; Package Hub is Not Supported</title>
   <para>
    Be aware that packages provided in the &suse; Package Hub are not
    officially supported by &suse;. &suse; only provides support for
    enabling the Package Hub repository and help with
    installation or deployment of the RPM packages.
   </para>
  </important>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
