<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<!--taroth 2010-01-08: yast2 module maintainer: jsuchome@suse.cz-->
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="cha.y2.lang"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Changing Language and Country Settings with &yast;</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info><indexterm>
 <primary>system</primary>
 <secondary>languages</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>YaST</primary>
 <secondary>languages</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>languages</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>configuring</primary>
 <secondary>languages</secondary></indexterm>
 <para>
  Working in different countries or having to work in a multilingual
  environment requires your computer to be set up to support this.
  &productnamereg; can handle different <literal>locales</literal> in parallel.
  A locale is a set of parameters that defines the language and country
  settings reflected in the user interface.
 </para>
 <para>
  The main system language was selected during installation and keyboard and
  time zone settings were adjusted. However, you can install additional
  languages on your system and determine which of the installed languages
  should be the default.
 </para>
 <para>
  For those tasks, use the &yast; language module as described in
  <xref linkend="sec.y2.langmod"/>. Install secondary languages to get optional
  localization if you need to start applications or desktops in languages other
  than the primary one.
 </para>
 <para>
  Apart from that, the &yast; timezone module allows you to adjust your country
  and timezone settings accordingly. It also lets you synchronize your system
  clock against a time server. For details, refer to
  <xref linkend="sec.y2.country"/>.
 </para>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.y2.langmod">
  <title>Changing the System Language</title>

  <para>
   Depending on how you use your desktop and whether you want to switch the
   entire system to another language or only the desktop environment itself,
   there are several ways to do this:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry xml:id="vle.lang.system">
    <term>Changing the System Language Globally</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Proceed as described in <xref linkend="sec.y2.lang.primsec"/> and
      <xref linkend="sec.y2.lang.switch"/> to install additional localized
      packages with &yast; and to set the default language. Changes are
      effective after the next login. To ensure that the entire system reflects
      the change, reboot the system or close and restart all running services,
      applications, and programs.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry xml:id="vle.lang.desktop">
    <term>Changing the Language for the Desktop Only</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Provided you have previously installed the desired language packages for
      your desktop environment with &yast; as described below, you can switch
      the language of your desktop using the desktop's control center.
      <phrase os="sled;osuse">Refer to
      <xref linkend="sec.gnome.settings.lang"/> for details.</phrase> After the
      X server has been restarted, your entire desktop reflects your new choice
      of language. Applications not belonging to your desktop framework are not
      affected by this change and may still appear in the language that was set
      in &yast;.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry xml:id="vle.lang.application">
    <term>Temporarily Switching Languages for One Application Only</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      You can also run a single application in another language (that has
      already been installed with &yast;). To do so, start it from the command
      line by specifying the language code as described in
      <xref linkend="sec.y2.lang.applications"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.y2.lang.primsec">
   <title>Modifying System Languages with &yast;</title>
   <para>
    &yast; knows two different language categories:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Primary Language</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The primary language set in &yast; applies to the entire system,
       including &yast; and the desktop environment. This language is used
       whenever available unless you manually specify another language.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Secondary Languages</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Install secondary languages to make your system multilingual. Languages
       installed as secondary languages can be selected manually for a specific
       situation. For example, use a secondary language to start an application
       in a certain language to do word processing in this language.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    Before installing additional languages, determine which of them should be
    the default system language (primary language).
   </para>
   <para>
    To access the &yast; language module, start &yast; and click <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>System</guimenu> <guimenu>Language</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    Alternatively, start the <guimenu>Languages</guimenu> dialog directly by
    running <command>sudo yast2 language &amp;</command> from a command line.
   </para>
   <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="yast2-language.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="yast2-language.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </informalfigure>
   <procedure xml:id="pro.yast.lang.additional">
    <title>Installing Additional Languages</title>
    <para>
     When installing additional languages, &yast; also allows you to set
     different locale settings for the user &rootuser;, see
     <xref linkend="step.yast.lang.additional.root"/>. The option
     <guimenu>Locale Settings for User root</guimenu> determines how the locale
     variables (<envar>LC_*</envar>) in the file
     <filename>/etc/sysconfig/language</filename> are set for &rootuser;. You
     can either set them to the same locale as for normal users, keep it
     unaffected by any language changes or only set the variable
     <envar>RC_LC_CTYPE</envar> to the same values as for the normal users.
     This variable sets the localization for language-specific function calls.
    </para>
    <step>
     <para>
      To add additional languages in the &yast; language module, select the
      <guimenu>Secondary Languages</guimenu> you want to install.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To make a language the default language, set it as <guimenu>Primary
      Language</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Additionally, adapt the keyboard to the new primary language and adjust
      the time zone, if appropriate.
     </para>
<!-- bnc#359220 -->
     <tip>
      <title>Advanced Settings</title>
      <para>
       For advanced keyboard or time zone settings, select <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu> <guimenu>System Keyboard Layout</guimenu>
       </menuchoice> or <menuchoice> <guimenu>System</guimenu> <guimenu>Date
       and Time</guimenu> </menuchoice> in &yast; to start the respective
       dialogs. For more information, refer to <xref linkend="cha.y2.hw.keym"/>
       and <xref linkend="sec.y2.country"/>.
      </para>
     </tip>
    </step>
    <step xml:id="step.yast.lang.additional.root">
     <para>
      To change language settings specific to the user &rootuser;, click
      <guimenu>Details</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <substeps performance="required">
      <step>
       <para>
        Set <guimenu>Locale Settings for User root</guimenu> to the desired
        value. For more information, click <guimenu>Help</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>
        Decide if you want to <guimenu>Use UTF-8 Encoding</guimenu> for
        &rootuser; or not.
       </para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      If your locale was not included in the list of primary languages
      available, try specifying it with <guimenu>Detailed Locale
      Setting</guimenu>. However, some localization may be incomplete.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Confirm your changes in the dialogs with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. If you
      have selected secondary languages, &yast; installs the localized software
      packages for the additional languages.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    The system is now multilingual. However, to start an application in a
    language other than the primary one, you need to set the desired language
    explicitly as explained in <xref linkend="sec.y2.lang.applications"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.y2.lang.switch">
   <title>Switching the Default System Language</title>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      To globally switch the default system language, start the &yast; language
      module.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select the desired new system language as <guimenu>Primary
      Language</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <important>
      <title>Deleting Former System Languages</title>
      <para>
       If you switch to a different primary language, the localized software
       packages for the former primary language will be removed from the
       system. To switch the default system language but keep the former
       primary language as additional language, add it as <guimenu>Secondary
       Language</guimenu> by enabling the respective check box.
      </para>
     </important>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Adjust the keyboard and time zone options as desired.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Confirm your changes with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      After &yast; has applied the changes, restart current X sessions (for
      example, by logging out and logging in again) to make &yast; and the
      desktop applications reflect your new language settings.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.y2.lang.applications">
   <title>Switching Languages for Standard X and &gnome; Applications</title>
   <para>
    After you have installed the respective language with &yast;, you can run a
    single application in another language.
   </para>
   <para>
    Start the application from the command line by using the following command:
   </para>
<screen>LANG=<replaceable>LANGUAGE</replaceable>&nbsp;<replaceable>application</replaceable></screen>
   <para>
    For example, to start f-spot in German, run
    <command>LANG=de_DE&nbsp;f-spot</command>. For other languages, use the
    appropriate language code. Get a list of all language codes available with
    the <command>locale&nbsp;</command> <option>-av</option> command.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.y2.country">
  <title>Changing the Country and Time Settings</title>

  <para>
   Using the &yast; date and time module, adjust your system date, clock and
   time zone information to the area you are working in. To access the &yast;
   module, start &yast; and click <menuchoice> <guimenu>System</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Date and Time</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Alternatively, start the
   <guimenu>Clock and Time Zone</guimenu> dialog directly by running
   <command>sudo yast2 timezone &amp;</command> from a command line.
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="yast2-timezone.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="yast2-timezone.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para>
   First, select a general region, such as <guimenu>Europe</guimenu>. Choose an
   appropriate country that matches the one you are working in, for example,
   <guimenu>Germany</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Depending on which operating systems run on your workstation, adjust the
   hardware clock settings accordingly:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If you run another operating system on your machine, such as Microsoft
     Windows*, it is likely your system does not use UTC, but local time. In
     this case, deactivate <guimenu>Hardware Clock Set To UTC</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If you only run Linux on your machine, set the hardware clock to UTC and
     have the switch from standard time to daylight saving time performed
     automatically.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <important>
   <title>Set the Hardware Clock to UTC</title>
   <para>
    The switch from standard time to daylight saving time (and vice versa) can
    only be performed automatically when the hardware clock (CMOS clock) is set
    to UTC. This also applies if you use automatic time synchronization with
    NTP, because automatic synchronization will only be performed if the time
    difference between the hardware and system clock is less than 15 minutes.
   </para>
   <para>
    Since a wrong system time can cause serious problems (missed backups,
    dropped mail messages, mount failures on remote file systems, etc.) it is
    strongly recommended to <emphasis>always</emphasis> set the hardware clock
    to UTC.
   </para>
  </important>

  <para>
   You can change the date and time manually or opt for synchronizing your
   machine against an NTP server, either permanently or only for adjusting your
   hardware clock.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Manually Adjusting Time and Date</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the &yast; timezone module, click <guimenu>Other Settings</guimenu> to
     set date and time.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Manually</guimenu> and enter date and time values.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Confirm your changes.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure>
   <title>Setting Date and Time With NTP Server</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Other Settings</guimenu> to set date and time.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Synchronize with NTP Server</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the address of an NTP server, if not already populated.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2-timezone-ntp.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="pdf">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2-timezone-ntp.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Synchronize Now</guimenu> to get your system time set
     correctly.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To use NTP permanently, enable <guimenu>Save NTP Configuration</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     With the <guimenu>Configure</guimenu> button, you can open the advanced
     NTP configuration. For details, see <xref linkend="sec.ntp.yast"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Confirm your changes.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
