<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-onlineupdate-you">
 <title>&yast; Online Update</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  &suse; offers a continuous stream of software security updates for your
  product. By default, the update applet is used to keep your system
  up-to-date. Refer to <xref linkend="sec-updater"/> for further information on
  the update applet. This chapter covers the alternative tool for updating
  software packages: &yast; Online Update.
 </para>
 <para>
  The current patches for &productnamereg; are available from an update
  software repository<phrase os="osuse">, which is automatically configured
  during the installation</phrase>. <phrase os="sles;sled">If you have
  registered your product during the installation, an update repository is
  already configured. If you have not registered &productname;, you can do so
  by starting the <guimenu>Product Registration</guimenu> in &yast;.</phrase>
  Alternatively, you can manually add an update repository from a source you
  trust. To add or remove repositories, start the Repository Manager with
  <menuchoice> <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
  <guimenu>Software Repositories</guimenu> </menuchoice> in &yast;. Learn more
  about the Repository Manager in <xref linkend="sec-yast-software-instsource"/>.
 </para>
 <note os="sles;sled">
  <title>Error on Accessing the Update Catalog</title>
  <para>
   If you are not able to access the update catalog, this might be because of
   an expired subscription. Normally, &productname; comes with a one-year or
   three-year subscription, during which you have access to the update catalog.
   This access will be denied after the subscription ends.
  </para>
  <para>
   If an access to the update catalog is denied, you will see a warning
   message prompting you to visit the &ncc; and check your
   subscription. The &ncc; is available at <link xlink:href="&sccurl;/"/>.
  </para>
 </note>
 <para>
  &suse; provides updates with different relevance levels:
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Security Updates</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Fix severe security hazards and should always be installed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Recommended Updates</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Fix issues that could compromise your computer.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Optional Updates</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Fix non-security relevant issues or provide enhancements.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-onlineupdate-you-overview">
  <title>The Online Update Dialog</title>

  <para>
   To open the &yast; <guimenu>Online Update</guimenu> dialog, start &yast; and
   select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Software </guimenu> <guimenu>Online
   Update</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Alternatively, start it from the command
   line with <command>yast2 online_update</command>.
  </para>

  <para>
   The <guimenu>Online Update</guimenu> window consists of four sections.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>&yast; Online Update</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="yast2_you.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="yast2_you.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   The <guimenu>Summary</guimenu> section on the left lists the available
   patches for &productname;. The patches are sorted by security relevance:
   <literal>security</literal>, <literal>recommended</literal>, and
   <literal>optional</literal>. You can change the view of the
   <guimenu>Summary</guimenu> section by selecting one of the following options
   from <guimenu>Show Patch Category</guimenu>:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Needed Patches</guimenu> (default view)</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Non-installed patches that apply to packages installed on your system.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Unneeded Patches</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Patches that either apply to packages not installed on your system, or
      patches that have requirements which have already have been fulfilled
      (because the relevant packages have already been updated from another
      source).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>All Patches</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      All patches available for &productname;.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   Each list entry in the <guimenu>Summary</guimenu> section consists of a
   symbol and the patch name. For an overview of the possible symbols and their
   meaning, press <keycombo> <keycap function="shift"/> <keycap>F1</keycap>
   </keycombo>. Actions required by <literal>Security</literal> and
   <literal>Recommended</literal> patches are automatically preset. These
   actions are <guimenu>Autoinstall</guimenu>, <guimenu>Autoupdate</guimenu>
   and <guimenu>Autodelete</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you install an up-to-date package from a repository other than the update
   repository, the requirements of a patch for this package may be fulfilled
   with this installation. In this case a check mark is displayed in front of
   the patch summary. The patch will be visible in the list until you mark it
   for installation. This will in fact not install the patch (because the
   package already is up-to-date), but mark the patch as having been installed.
  </para>

  <para>
   Select an entry in the <guimenu>Summary</guimenu> section to view a short
   <guimenu>Patch Description</guimenu> at the bottom left corner of the
   dialog. The upper right section lists the packages included in the selected
   patch (a patch can consist of several packages). Click an entry in the upper
   right section to view details about the respective package that is included
   in the patch.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-onlineupdate-you-install">
  <title>Installing Patches</title>

  <para>
   The &yast; Online Update dialog allows you to either install all available
   patches at once or manually select the desired patches. You may also revert patches that have been applied to the
   system.
  </para>

  <para>
   By default, all new patches (except <literal>optional</literal> ones) that
   are currently available for your system are already marked for installation.
   They will be applied automatically once you click <guimenu>Accept</guimenu>
   or <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>.
<!--taroth 2014-05-27:  http://fate.suse.com/312509-->
   If one or multiple patches require a system reboot, you will be notified
   about this before the patch installation starts. You can then either decide
   to continue with the installation of the selected patches, skip the
   installation of all patches that need rebooting and install the rest, or go
   back to the manual patch selection.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Applying Patches with &yast; Online Update</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start &yast; and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Online Update</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To automatically apply all new patches (except <literal>optional</literal>
     ones) that are currently available for your system, click
     <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> or <guimenu>Accept</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     First modify the selection of patches that you want to apply:
    </para>
    <substeps performance="required">
     <step>
      <para>
       Use the respective filters and views that the interface provides. For
       details, refer to <xref linkend="sec-onlineupdate-you-overview"/>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select or deselect patches according to your needs and wishes by
       right-clicking the patch and choosing the respective action from the
       context menu.
      </para>
      <important>
       <title>Always Apply Security Updates</title>
       <para>
        Do not deselect any <literal>security</literal>-related patches without
        a very good reason. These patches fix severe security hazards and
        prevent your system from being exploited.
       </para>
      </important>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Most patches include updates for several packages. To change
       actions for single packages, right-click a package in the package view
       and choose an action.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To confirm your selection and apply the selected patches, proceed with
       <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> or <guimenu>Accept</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After the installation is complete, click <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> to
     leave the &yast; <guimenu>Online Update</guimenu>. Your system is now
     up-to-date.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-onlineupdate-you-automatically">
  <title>Automatic Online Update</title>

  <para>
   You may configure automatic updates with a daily, weekly, or 
   monthly schedule with &yast;. Install the
   <systemitem class="resource">yast2-online-update-configuration</systemitem>
   package.
  </para>

  <para>
   By default, updates are downloaded as delta RPMs. Since rebuilding RPM
   packages from delta RPMs is a memory- and processor-intensive task, certain
   setups or hardware configurations might require you to disable the use of
   delta RPMs for the sake of performance.
  </para>

  <para>
   Some patches, such as kernel updates or packages requiring license
   agreements, require user interaction, which would cause the automatic update
   procedure to stop. You can configure skipping patches that require user
   interaction.
  </para>
  
  <para>
      Use the <guimenu>Patches</guimenu> tab in the &yast;
      <guimenu>Software</guimenu> module to review available and installed
      patches, including references to bug reports and CVE bulletins.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Configuring the Automatic Online Update</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     After installation, start &yast; and select <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Software</guimenu> <guimenu>Online Update</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>. Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Configuration</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Online Update</guimenu></menuchoice>. If the
     <package>yast2-online-update-configuration</package> is not installed, you
     will be prompted to do that.
    </para>
      <figure>
   <title>&yast; Online Update Configuration</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="yast2_autoupdate.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="yast2_autoupdate.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
    <para>
     Alternatively, start the module with
     <command>yast2&nbsp;online_update_configuration</command> from the command
     line.
    </para>
    
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Choose the update interval: <guimenu>Daily</guimenu>,
     <guimenu>Weekly</guimenu>, or <guimenu>Monthly</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Sometimes patches may require the attention of the administrator, for
     example when restarting critical services. For example, this might be an
     update for &deng; that requires all containers to be restarted. Before
     these
     patches are installed, the user is informed about the consequences and is
     asked to confirm the installation of the patch. Such patches are called
     <quote>Interactive Patches</quote>.
    </para>
    <para>
     When installing patches automatically, it is assumed that you have
     accepted the installation of interactive patches. If you prefer to
     review these patches before they get installed, check <guimenu>Skip
     Interactive Patches</guimenu>. In this case, interactive patches will be
     skipped during automated patching. Make sure to periodically run a manual
     online update, to check whether interactive patches are waiting to be
     installed.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To automatically accept any license agreements, activate <guimenu>Agree
     with Licenses</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To automatically install all packages recommended by updated packages,
     activate <guimenu>Include Recommended Packages</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
<!--taroth 2014-05-27: http://fate.suse.com/314867-->
   <step>
    <para>
     To disable the use of delta RPMs (for performance reasons), un-check
     <guimenu>Use Delta RPMs</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To filter the patches by category (such as security or recommended),
     check <guimenu>Filter by Category</guimenu> and add the appropriate
     patch categories from the list. Only patches of the selected categories
     will be installed. It is a good practice to enable only automatic
     <guimenu>Security</guimenu> updates, and to manually review all others.
     Patching is usually reliable, but you may wish to test non-security
     patches, and roll them back if you encounter any problems. 
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para><guimenu>Packagemanager and YaST</guimenu> supply patches
                for package management and YaST features and modules.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><guimenu>Security</guimenu> patches provide crucial
                updates and bugfixes.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><guimenu>Recommended</guimenu> patches are optional
                bugfixes and enhancements.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><guimenu>Optional</guimenu> are new packages.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><guimenu>Other</guimenu> is equivalent to miscellaneous.
                </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><guimenu>Document</guimenu> is unused.
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>            
    
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Confirm your configuration by clicking <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   The automatic online update does not automatically restart the system
   afterward. If there are package updates that require a system reboot, you
   need to do this manually.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
