<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<sect1 id="sec.y2.sw.gtk">
 <title>Using the GNOME Interface (GTK+)</title><indexterm>

 <primary>&yast;</primary>

 <secondary>software</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

 <primary>configuring</primary>

 <secondary>software</secondary></indexterm>

 <remark role="proofing">taroth 2010-07-14: CAVE while proofing - keep in sync
  with yast2_sw.xml!</remark>

<!-- <abstract> -->

 <para>
  The &yast; GTK+ interface is started by default when using the desktops
  GNOME and XFCE. Start the software manager from the &yast; Control Center
  by clicking <menuchoice><guimenu>Software</guimenu> <guimenu>Software
  Management</guimenu></menuchoice>.
 </para>

 <informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="yast2_sw_manager_gtk.png" width="70%" format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="yast2_sw_manager_gtk.png" width="65%" format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </informalfigure>

 <sect2 id="sec.y2.sw.gtk.search">
  <title>Views for Searching Packages or Patterns</title>
  <para>
   The easiest way to find a package is to use the search field in the upper
   right corner of the software manager. Enter a search term and press
   <keycap function="enter"/>. By default it will search package names and
   summaries. Press the search item to change this filter and search the
   file lists, for example.
  </para>
  <para>
   The software manager also offers different views and filters for
   displaying package lists. These are available from the pull-down menu in
   the upper left corner:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Groups</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The default view lists all packages sorted by groups such as
      <guimenu>Admin Tools</guimenu>, <guimenu>Graphics</guimenu>,
      <guimenu>Programming</guimenu>, or <guimenu>Security</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>RPM Groups</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Lists all packages sorted by functionality with groups and subgroups.
      For example <menuchoice> <guimenu>Networking</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Email</guimenu> <guimenu>Clients</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Repositories</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Filter to list packages by repository. In order to select more than
      one repository, hold the <keycap function="control"/> key while
      clicking on repository names. The <quote>pseudo repository</quote>
      <guimenu>@System</guimenu> lists all packages currently installed.
     </para>
     <para>
      To add, edit, or remove available repositories, click <guimenu>Edit
      Repositories</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
<!--taroth 2010-07-22: only for SLE, will be removed for osuse according to
    rpmcruz-->
   <varlistentry os="sled;sles">
    <term>Support</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Filter to list packages by support contract.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Patterns</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Lists all patterns available for installation on your system.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Languages</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Filter to list all packages needed to add a new system language.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
   The box in the lower right corner of the dialog also allows to filter for
   packages that are <guimenu>Installed</guimenu>, <guimenu>Not
   Installed</guimenu> or <guimenu>Upgradable</guimenu>. If you select the
   <guimenu>No Status</guimenu> entry, all available packages from the
   configured repositories are displayed, independent of their status.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.y2.sw.gtk.install">
  <title>Installing and Removing Packages or Patterns</title>
<!-- fs 2009-10-07: Everything in one procedure, since this topic is already
     covered in the Start-Up cha.software (software.xml) -->
  <procedure>
   <para>
    Certain packages are dependent on other packages, such as shared
    libraries. On the other hand, some packages cannot coexist with others
    on the system. If possible, &yast; automatically resolves these
    dependencies or conflicts. If your choice results in a dependency
    conflict that cannot be automatically solved, you need to solve it
    manually as described in <xref linkend="sec.y2.sw.deps"/>.
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>
     Search for packages as described in
     <xref
      linkend="sec.y2.sw.gtk.search"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The packages found are listed in the right pane. To further filter the
     search results according to package status (<guimenu>Any
     Status</guimenu>, <guimenu>Not Installed</guimenu>,
     <guimenu>Installed</guimenu>, <guimenu>Upgradable)</guimenu>, select
     one of the entries in the box at the lower left corner of the dialog.
     For details about a package, click the package in the list. Information
     like available versions, authors and changelog of the package are
     displayed in the lower right corner of the window.
    </para>
    <para>
     To mark a package for installation, re-installation, removal, or
     upgrade, right-click the package and choose the appropriate action from
     the menu.
    </para>
    <tip>
     <title>Applying an Action to All Packages Listed</title>
     <para>
      To apply an action to all packages listed in the right pane,
      right-click a package, choose <guimenu>Select All</guimenu>,
      right-click again and choose an action.
     </para>
    </tip>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To install a pattern, right-click the pattern name and choose
     <guimenu>Install</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     It is not possible to remove a pattern per se. Instead, select the
     packages of a pattern you want to remove and mark them for removal.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In order to select more packages, repeat the steps mentioned above.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Before applying your changes, you can review or modify them by clicking
     <guimenu>View All Changes</guimenu> at the bottom of the dialog. By
     default, all packages that will change status are listed.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To revert changes for a package, click the <guimenu>Undo</guimenu> icon
     with the yellow arrow. To finish the review, click
     <guimenu>Close</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     When you are finished with the selection of packages to install or
     remove, <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> your changes.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In case &yast; found dependencies on other packages, a list of packages
     that have additionally been chosen for installation, update or removal
     is presented. Click <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> to accept them.
    </para>
    <para>
     After all selected packages are installed, updated or removed, the
     &yast; Software Manager automatically terminates.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <note>
   <title>Installing Source Packages</title>
   <para>
    Installing source packages with &yast; Software Manager is not possible
    at the moment. Use the command line tool <command>zypper</command> for
    this purpose. For more information, see
    <xref
     linkend="sec.zypper.softman.sources"/>.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.y2.sw.gtk.update">
  <title>Updating Packages</title>
  <para>
   Instead of updating individual packages, you can also update all
   installed packages or all packages from a certain repository. When mass
   updating packages, the following aspects are generally considered:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     priorities of the repositories that provide the package,
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     architecture of the package (for example, x86_64),
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     version number of the package,
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     package vendor.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   Which of the aspects has the highest importance for choosing the update
   candidates depends on the respective update option you choose.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     To view the list of packages that can be updated (packages with higher
     versions are available), select <guimenu>Upgradable</guimenu> in the
     bottom left box.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To update all packages listed there, click <guimenu>Upgrade
     All</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     To install only upgradable packages for which an official patch has
     been issued, click <guimenu>Upgrade Patches</guimenu>. Those packages
     are marked by a patch tag next to their version number. Choosing this
     option is equivalent to doing an online update with &yast; as described
     in <xref
      linkend="cha.onlineupdate.you"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
     If no patches have been issued since last applying patches, the button
     is disabled.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To make sure that the packages for a mass update derive from a certain
     repository:
    </para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       Choose the repository from which to update as described in
       <xref
        linkend="sec.y2.sw.gtk.search"/> .
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       On the right hand side of the window, click <guimenu>Switch system
       packages to the versions in this repository</guimenu>. This
       explicitly allows &yast; to change the package vendor when replacing
       the packages.
      </para>
      <para>
       All installed packages will be replaced by packages deriving from
       this repository, if available. This may lead to changes in vendor and
       architecture and even to downgrading some packages.
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Before applying the changes, you can review or modify them by clicking
     <guimenu>View All Changes</guimenu> at the bottom of the dialog. By
     default, all packages that will change status are listed.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To refrain from switching the system packages to the versions in this
     repository, click the <guimenu>Undo</guimenu> button next to the
     respective option.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If all options are set according to your wishes, confirm your changes
     with <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> to start the mass update.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.y2.sw.gtk.deps">
  <title>Checking Software Dependencies</title>
  <para>
   Most packages are dependent on other packages. If a package, for example,
   uses a shared library, it will be dependent on the package providing this
   library. On the other hand, some packages cannot coexist with each other,
   causing a conflict (for example, you can only install one mail transfer
   agent: sendmail or postfix). When installing or removing software, the
   Software Manager makes sure no dependencies or conflicts remain
   unresolved to ensure system integrity.
  </para>
  <para>
   In case there exists only one solution to resolve a dependency or a
   conflict, it is resolved automatically. Multiple solutions always cause a
   conflict which needs to be resolved manually. If solving a conflict
   involves a vendor or architecture change, it also needs to be solved
   manually. When clicking <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> to apply any changes in
   the Software Manager, you get an overview of all actions triggered by the
   automatic resolver which you need to confirm.
  </para>
  <para>
   By default, dependencies are automatically checked. A check is performed
   every time you change a package status (for example, by marking a package
   for installation or removal). This is generally useful, but can become
   exhausting when manually resolving a dependency conflict. To disable this
   function, uncheck <menuchoice> <guimenu>Dependencies</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Autocheck</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Manually perform a dependency
   check with <menuchoice> <guimenu>Dependencies</guimenu> <guimenu>Check
   Now</guimenu></menuchoice>. A consistency check is always performed when
   you confirm your selection with <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>.
  </para>
  <note>
   <title>Manually Solving Package Conflicts</title>
   <para>
    Unless you are very experienced, follow the suggestions &yast; makes
    when handling package conflicts, otherwise you may not be able to
    resolve them. Keep in mind that every change you make, potentially
    triggers other conflicts, so you can easily end up with a steadily
    increasing number of conflicts. In case this happens, click
    <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu> and <guimenu>Quit</guimenu> the software
    manager. Relaunch it to start again.
   </para>
  </note>
  <figure id="fig.y2.sw.gtk.packconfl">
   <title>Conflict Management of the Software Manager</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="yast2_gtk_package_conflict.png" width="70%" format="PNG"></imagedata>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="yast2_gtk_package_conflict.png" width="65%" format="PNG"></imagedata>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
