<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<sect1 version="5.0" xml:id="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Using the &yast; Partitioner</title>
  <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
        </dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <indexterm>
 <primary>YaST</primary>
 <secondary>partitioning</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>partitions</primary>
 <secondary>creating</secondary></indexterm>

 <para>
  With the expert partitioner, shown in
  <xref linkend="fig.yast2.i_y2_disk_part"/>, manually modify the
  partitioning of one or several hard disks. You can add, delete, resize,
  and edit partitions, or access the soft RAID, and LVM
  configuration.
 </para>

 <warning>
  <title>Repartitioning the Running System</title>
  <para>
   Although it is possible to repartition your system while it is running,
   the risk of making a mistake that causes data loss is very high. Try
   to avoid repartitioning your installed system and always do a complete
   backup of your data before attempting to do so.
  </para>
 </warning>

 <figure xml:id="fig.yast2.i_y2_disk_part">
  <title>The &yast; Partitioner</title>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="i_y2_disk_part.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="i_y2_disk_part.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>

 <tip arch="zseries" os="sles">
  <title>IBM &zseries;: Device Names</title>
  <para>
   IBM &zseries; recognizes only DASD and SCSI hard disks. IDE hard disks
   are not supported. This is why these devices appear in the partition
   table as <filename>dasda</filename> or <filename>sda</filename> for the
   first recognized device.
  </para>
 </tip>

 <para>
  All existing or suggested partitions on all connected hard disks are
  displayed in the list of <guimenu>Available Storage</guimenu> in the
  &yast; <guimenu>Expert Partitioner</guimenu> dialog. Entire hard disks
  are listed as devices without numbers, such as
  <filename>/dev/sda</filename><phrase arch="zseries" os="sles"> (or
  <filename>/dev/dasda</filename>)</phrase>. Partitions are listed as parts
  of these devices, such as
  <filename>/dev/sda1</filename><phrase arch="zseries" os="sles"> (or
  <filename>/dev/dasda1</filename>, respectively)</phrase>. The size, type,
  encryption status, file system, and mount point of the hard disks and
  their partitions are also displayed. The mount point describes where the
  partition appears in the Linux file system tree.
 </para>

 <para>
  Several functional views are available on the left hand <guimenu>System
  View</guimenu>. Use these views to gather information about existing
  storage configurations, or to configure functions like
  <literal>RAID</literal>, <literal>Volume Management</literal>,
  <literal>Crypt Files</literal>, or view file systems with additional
  features, such as Btrfs, NFS, or <literal>TMPFS</literal>.
 </para>

 <para>
  If you run the expert dialog during installation, any free hard disk space
  is also listed and automatically selected. To provide more disk space to
  &productnamereg;, free the needed space starting from the bottom toward
  the top of the list (starting from the last partition of a hard disk
  toward the first).
 </para>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.IB.part.typen">
  <title>Partition Types</title><indexterm>
  <primary>partitions</primary>
  <secondary>types</secondary></indexterm>
  <tip arch="zseries" os="sles">
   <title>IBM &zseries;: Hard Disks</title>
   <para>
    On IBM &zseries; platforms, &sls; supports SCSI hard disks and DASDs
    (direct access storage devices). While SCSI disks can be partitioned as
    described below, DASDs can have no more than three partition entries in
    their partition tables.
   </para>
  </tip>
  <para>
   Every hard disk has a partition table with space for four entries. Every
   entry in the partition table corresponds to a primary partition or an
   extended partition. Only one extended partition entry is allowed,
   however.
  </para>
  <para>
   A primary partition simply consists of a continuous range of cylinders
   (physical disk areas) assigned to a particular operating system. With
   primary partitions you would be limited to four partitions per hard disk,
   because more do not fit in the partition table. This is why extended
   partitions are used. Extended partitions are also continuous ranges of
   disk cylinders, but an extended partition may be divided into
   <emphasis>logical partitions</emphasis> itself. Logical partitions do not
   require entries in the partition table. In other words, an extended
   partition is a container for logical partitions.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you need more than four partitions, create an extended partition as
   the fourth partition (or earlier). This extended partition should occupy
   the entire remaining free cylinder range. Then create multiple logical
   partitions within the extended partition. The maximum number of logical
   partitions is 63, independent of the disk type. It does not matter which
   types of partitions are used for Linux. Primary and logical partitions
   both function normally.
  </para>
  <tip os="sles">
   <title>GPT Partition Table</title>
   <para>
    If you need to create more than 4 primary partitions on one hard disk,
    you need to use the GPT partition type. This type removes the primary
    partitions number restriction, and supports partitions bigger than
    2&nbsp;TB as well.
   </para>
   <para>
    To use GPT, run the &yast; Partitioner, click the relevant disk name
    in the <guimenu>System View</guimenu> and choose
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Expert</guimenu> <guimenu>Create New Partition
    Table</guimenu> <guimenu>GPT</guimenu></menuchoice>.
   </para>
  </tip>
 </sect2>

<!-- <sect2>
  <title>Default File systems</title>
  <para>
   The default file system for all partitions except <filename>/home</filename>
   and swap is Btrfs. The default file system for <filename>/home</filename>
   is XFS.
  </para>
 </sect2>-->

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert.newpart">
  <title>Creating a Partition</title><indexterm>
  <primary>partitions</primary>
  <secondary>creating</secondary></indexterm>
  <para>
   To create a partition from scratch select <guimenu>Hard Disks</guimenu>
   and then a hard disk with free space. The actual modification can be done
   in the <guimenu>Partitions</guimenu> tab:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Add</guimenu> and specify the partition type (primary
     or extended). Create up to four primary partitions or up to three
     primary partitions and one extended partition. Within the extended
     partition, create several logical partitions (see
     <xref linkend="sec.IB.part.typen"/>).
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Specify the size of the new partition. You can either choose to occupy
     all the free unpartitioned space, or enter a custom size.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the file system to use and a mount point. &yast; suggests a
     mount point for each partition created. To use a different mount
     method, like mount by label, select <guimenu>Fstab Options</guimenu>.
     For more information on supported file systems, see
     <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Specify additional file system options if your setup requires them.
     This is necessary, for example, if you need persistent device names.
     For details on the available options, refer to
     <xref linkend="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert.options"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> to apply your partitioning setup and
     leave the partitioning module.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you created the partition during installation, you are returned to
     the installation overview screen.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <sect3 xml:id="yast2.btrfs">
   <title>Btrfs Partitioning</title>
   <para>
    The default file system for the root partition is Btrfs (see
    <xref linkend="cha.snapper"/><phrase os="sles"> and
    <xref linkend="cha.filesystems"/></phrase> for more information on
    Btrfs). The root file system is the default subvolume and it is not
    listed in the list of created subvolumes. As a default Btrfs subvolume,
    it can be mounted as a normal file system.
   </para>
   <important>
    <title>Btrfs on an Encrypted Root Partition</title>
    <para>
     The default partitioning setup suggests the root partition as Btrfs
     with <filename>/boot</filename> being a directory. If you need to have the
     root partition encrypted in this setup, make sure to use the GPT
     partition table type instead of the default MSDOS type. Otherwise
     the GRUB2 boot loader may not have enough space for the second stage loader.
    </para>
   </important>
   <para>
    It is possible to create snapshots of Btrfs subvolumes&mdash;either
    manually, or automatically based on system events. For example when
    making changes to the file system, <command>zypper</command> invokes the
    <command>snapper</command> command to create snapshots before and after
    the change. This is useful if you are not satisfied with the change
    <command>zypper</command> made and want to restore the previous state.
    As <command>snapper</command> invoked by <command>zypper</command>
    snapshots the <emphasis>root</emphasis> file system by default, it is
    reasonable to exclude specific directories from being snapshot,
    depending on the nature of data they hold. And that is why &yast;
    suggests creating the following separate subvolumes.
   </para>
   <para>
    <remark>taroth 2015-08-19: a similar variablelist is included in
     storage_filesystems.xml, @maintainer: please find a better solution for the
     future (mention only in one place, use xref from the other, or use a
     phrases entity that can be included multiple times)</remark>
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <title>Suggested Btrfs Subvolumes</title>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>/tmp /var/tmp /var/run</filename>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Directories with frequently changed content.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>/var/spool</filename>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Contains user data, such as mails.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>/var/lib</filename>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>Holds dynamic data libraries and files plus state information
       pertaining to an application or the system. </para>
      <para>By default, subvolumes with the option <literal>no copy on
       write</literal> are created for: <filename>/var/lib/mariadb</filename>,
       <filename>/var/lib/pgsql</filename>, and
       <filename>/var/lib/libvirt/images</filename>.</para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>/var/log</filename>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Contains system and applications' log files which should never be
       rolled back.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>/var/crash</filename>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Contains memory dumps of crashed kernels.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>/srv</filename>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Contains data files belonging to FTP and HTTP servers.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>/opt</filename>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Contains third party software.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <tip>
    <title>Size of Btrfs Partition</title>
    <para>
     Because saved snapshots require more disk space, it is recommended to
     reserve more space for Btrfs partition than for a partition not capable
     of snapshotting (such as Ext3). Recommended size for a root Btrfs
     partition with suggested subvolumes is 20GB.
    </para>
   </tip>
   <sect4 xml:id="yast2.btrfs.yast">
    <title>Managing Btrfs Subvolumes using &yast;</title>
    <para>
     Subvolumes of a Btrfs partition can be now managed with the &yast;
     <guimenu>Expert partitioner</guimenu> module. You can add new or remove
     existing subvolumes.
    </para>
    <procedure>
     <title>Btrfs Subvolumes with &yast;</title>
     <step>
      <para>
       Start the &yast; <guimenu>Expert Partitioner</guimenu> with
       <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guimenu>Partitioner</guimenu></menuchoice>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Choose <guimenu>Btrfs</guimenu> in the left <guimenu>System
       View</guimenu> pane.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select the Btrfs partition whose subvolumes you need to manage and
       click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>Subvolume Handling</guimenu>. You can see a list off
       all existing subvolumes of the selected Btrfs partition. You can
       notice several <literal>@/.snapshots/xyz/snapshot</literal>
       entries&mdash;each of these subvolumes belongs to one existing
       snapshot.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Depending on whether you want to add or remove subvolumes, do the
       following:
      </para>
      <substeps performance="required">
       <step>
        <para>
         To remove a subvolume, select it from the list of <guimenu>Exisitng
         Subvolumes</guimenu> and click <guimenu>Remove</guimenu>.
        </para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>
         To add a new subvolume, enter its name to the <guimenu>New
         Subvolume</guimenu> text box and click <guimenu>Add new</guimenu>.
        </para>
        <figure xml:id="fig.yast2.btrfs.subvolumes">
         <title>Btrfs Subvolumes in &yast; Partitioner</title>
         <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
           <imagedata fileref="yats2_btrfs_subvolumes.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
           <imagedata fileref="yats2_btrfs_subvolumes.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
         </mediaobject>
        </figure>
       </step>
      </substeps>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Confirm with <guimenu>OK</guimenu> and <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Leave the partitioner with <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect4>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert.options">
  <title>Editing a Partition</title><indexterm>
  <primary>partitions</primary>
  <secondary>parameters</secondary></indexterm>
  <para>
   When you create a new partition or modify an existing partition, you can
   set various parameters. For new partitions, the default parameters set by
   &yast; are usually sufficient and do not require any modification. To
   edit your partition setup manually, proceed as follows:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the partition.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> to edit the partition and set the
     parameters:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>File System ID</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <indexterm>
        <primary>partitions</primary>
        <secondary>LVM</secondary>
        </indexterm> <phrase os="sles"> </phrase> <indexterm>
        <primary>partitions</primary>
        <secondary>RAID</secondary>
        </indexterm> Even if you do not want to format the partition at this
        stage, assign it a file system ID to ensure that the partition is
        registered correctly. Typical values are <guimenu>Linux</guimenu>,
        <guimenu>Linux swap</guimenu>, <guimenu>Linux LVM</guimenu>, and
        <guimenu>Linux RAID</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       File System
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <indexterm>
        <primary>file systems</primary>
        <secondary>changing</secondary>
        </indexterm> <indexterm>
        <primary>partitions</primary>
        <secondary>reformatting</secondary>
        </indexterm> To change the partition file system, click
        <guimenu>Format Partition</guimenu> and select file system type in
        the <guimenu>File System</guimenu> list.
       </para>
       <para>
        &productname; supports several types of file systems. Btrfs is
        the Linux file system of choice for the root partition because of
        its advanced features. It supports copy-on-write functionality,
        creating snapshots, multi-device spanning, subvolumes, and other
        useful techniques. XFS, Ext3 and JFS are journaling file systems.
        These file systems can restore the system very quickly after
        a system crash, using write processes logged during the operation.
        Ext2 is not a journaling file system, but it is adequate for smaller
        partitions because it does not require much disk space for
        management.
       </para>
       <para>
        The default file system for the root partition is Btrfs. The default
        file system for additional partitions is XFS.
       </para>
       <para>
        Swap is a special format that allows the partition to be used as a
        virtual memory. Create a swap partition of at least 256&nbsp;MB.
        However, if you use up your swap space, consider adding more memory
        to your system instead of adding more swap space.
       </para>
       <warning>
        <title>Changing the File System</title>
        <para>
         Changing the file system and reformatting partitions irreversibly
         deletes all data from the partition.
        </para>
       </warning>
       <para>
        For details on the various file systems, refer to
        &storage_guide;.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       Encrypt Device 
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If you activate the encryption, all data is written to the hard disk
        in encrypted form. This increases the security of sensitive data,
        but reduces the system speed, as the encryption takes some time to
        process. More information about the encryption of file systems is
        provided in <xref linkend="cha.security.cryptofs"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       Mount Point
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Specify the directory where the partition should be mounted in the
        file system tree. Select from &yast; suggestions or enter any
        other name.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>
       Fstab Options
      </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Specify various parameters contained in the global file system
        administration file (<filename>/etc/fstab</filename>). The default
        settings should suffice for most setups. You can, for example,
        change the file system identification from the device name to a
        volume label. In the volume label, use all characters except
        <literal>/</literal> and space.
       </para>
       <para>
        To get persistent devices names, use the mount option
        <guimenu>Device ID</guimenu>, <guimenu>UUID</guimenu> or
        <guimenu>LABEL</guimenu>. In &productname;, persistent device
        names are enabled by default.
       </para>
       <note os="sles" arch="zseries">
        <title>IBM &zseries;: Mounting by Path</title>
        <para>
         Since mounting by ID causes problems on IBM &zseries; when using
         disk-to-disk copying for cloning purposes, devices are mounted by
         path in <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> on IBM &zseries; by
         default.
        </para>
       </note>
       <para>
        If you prefer to mount the partition by its label, you need to
        define one in the <guimenu>Volume label</guimenu> text entry. For
        example, you could use the partition label <literal>HOME</literal>
        for a partition intended to mount to <filename>/home</filename>.
       </para>
       <para>
        If you intend to use quotas on the file system, use the mount option
        <guimenu>Enable Quota Support</guimenu>. This must be done before
        you can define quotas for users in the &yast; <guimenu>User
        Management</guimenu> module. For further information on how to
        configure user quota, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.y2.userman.adv.quota"/>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> to save the changes.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <note>
   <title>Resize File Systems</title>
   <para>
    To resize an existing file system, select the partition and use
    <guimenu>Resize</guimenu>. Note, that it is not possible to resize
    partitions while mounted. To resize partitions, unmount the relevant
    partition before running the partitioner.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert.options2">
  <title>Expert Options</title>
  <para>
   After you select a hard disk device (like <guimenu>sda</guimenu>) in the
   <guimenu>System View</guimenu> pane, you can access the
   <guimenu>Expert</guimenu> menu in the lower
   right part of the
   <guimenu>Expert Partitioner</guimenu> window. The menu contains the
   following commands:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Create New Partition Table</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option helps you create a new partition table on the selected
      device.
     </para>
     <warning>
      <title>Creating a New Partition Table</title>
      <para>
       Creating a new partition table on a device irreversibly removes all
       the partitions and their data from that device.
      </para>
     </warning>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Clone This Disk</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This option helps you clone the device partition layout (but not the
      data) to other available disk devices.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert.configure_options">
  <title>Advanced Options</title>
  <para>
   After you select the host name of the computer (the top-level of the tree
   in the <guimenu>System View</guimenu> pane), you can access the
   <guimenu>Configure</guimenu> menu in the lower right part of the
   <guimenu>Expert Partitioner</guimenu> window. The menu contains the
   following commands:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Configure iSCSI</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To access SCSI over IP block devices, you first need to configure
      iSCSI. This results in additionally available devices in the main
      partition list.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Configure Multipath</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Selecting this option helps you configure the multipath enhancement to
      the supported mass storage devices.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert.info">
  <title>More Partitioning Tips</title>
  <para>
   The following section includes a few hints and tips on partitioning that
   should help you make the right decisions when setting up your system.
  </para>
  <tip>
   <title>Cylinder Numbers</title>
   <para>
    Note, that different partitioning tools may start counting the cylinders
    of a partition with <literal>0</literal> or with <literal>1</literal>.
    When calculating the number of cylinders, you should always use the
    difference between the last and the first cylinder number and add one.
   </para>
  </tip>
  <sect3 xml:id="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert.info.swap">
   <title>Using <literal>swap</literal></title>
   <para>
    Swap is used to extend the available physical memory. It is then
    possible to use more memory than physical RAM available. The memory
    management system of kernels before 2.4.10 needed swap as a safety
    measure. Then, if you did not have twice the size of your RAM in swap,
    the performance of the system suffered. These limitations no longer
    exist.
   </para>
   <para>
    Linux uses a page called <quote>Least Recently Used</quote> (LRU) to
    select pages that might be moved from memory to disk. Therefore, running
    applications have more memory available and caching works more smoothly.
   </para>
   <para>
    If an application tries to allocate the maximum allowed memory, problems
    with swap can arise. There are three major scenarios to look at:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>System with no swap</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The application gets the maximum allowed memory. All caches are
       freed, and thus all other running applications are slowed. After a
       few minutes, the kernel's out-of-memory kill mechanism activates and
       kills the process.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>System with medium sized swap (128 MB&ndash;512 MB)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       At first, the system slows like a system without swap. After all
       physical RAM has been allocated, swap space is used as well. At this
       point, the system becomes very slow and it becomes impossible to run
       commands from remote. Depending on the speed of the hard disks that
       run the swap space, the system stays in this condition for about 10
       to 15 minutes until the out-of-memory kill mechanism resolves the
       issue. Note that you will need a certain amount of swap if the
       computer needs to perform a <quote>suspend to disk</quote>. In that
       case, the swap size should be large enough to contain the necessary
       data from memory (512 MB&ndash;1GB).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>System with lots of swap (several GB)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       It is better to not have an application that is out of control and
       swapping excessively in this case. If you use such application, the
       system will need many hours to recover. In the process, it is likely
       that other processes get timeouts and faults, leaving the system in
       an undefined state, even after terminating the faulty process. In
       this case, do a hard machine reboot and try to get it running again.
       Lots of swap is only useful if you have an application that relies on
       this feature. Such applications (like databases or graphics
       manipulation programs) often have an option to directly use hard disk
       space for their needs. It is advisable to use this option instead of
       using lots of swap space.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    If your system is not out of control, but needs more swap after some
    time, it is possible to extend the swap space online. If you prepared a
    partition for swap space, add this partition with &yast;. If you do
    not have a partition available, you can also use a swap file to extend
    the swap. Swap files are generally slower than partitions, but compared
    to physical RAM, both are extremely slow so the actual difference is
    negligible.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Adding a Swap File Manually</title>
    <para>
     To add a swap file in the running system, proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <step>
     <para>
      Create an empty file in your system. For example, if you want to add a
      swap file with 128&nbsp;MB swap at
      <filename>/var/lib/swap/swapfile</filename>, use the commands:
     </para>
<screen>mkdir -p /var/lib/swap
dd if=/dev/zero of=/var/lib/swap/swapfile bs=1M count=128</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Initialize this swap file with the command
     </para>
<screen>mkswap /var/lib/swap/swapfile</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Activate the swap with the command
     </para>
<screen>swapon /var/lib/swap/swapfile</screen>
     <para>
      To disable this swap file, use the command
     </para>
<screen>swapoff /var/lib/swap/swapfile</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Check the current available swap spaces with the command
     </para>
<screen>cat /proc/swaps</screen>
     <para>
      Note that at this point, it is only temporary swap space. After the
      next reboot, it is no longer used.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To enable this swap file permanently, add the following line to
      <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>:
     </para>
<screen>/var/lib/swap/swapfile swap swap defaults 0 0</screen>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec.yast2.i_y2_part_expert.lvm">
  <title>Partitioning and LVM</title>
  <para>
   From the <guimenu>Expert partitioner</guimenu>, access the LVM
   configuration by clicking the <guimenu>Volume Management</guimenu> item
   in the <guimenu>System View</guimenu> pane. However, if a working LVM
   configuration already exists on your system, it is automatically
   activated upon entering the initial LVM configuration of a session. In
   this case, all disks containing a partition (belonging to an activated
   volume group) cannot be repartitioned. The Linux kernel cannot reread the
   modified partition table of a hard disk when any partition on this disk
   is in use. If you already have a working LVM configuration on your
   system, physical repartitioning should not be necessary. Instead, change
   the configuration of the logical volumes.
  </para>
  <para>
   At the beginning of the physical volumes (PVs), information about the
   volume is written to the partition. To reuse such a partition for other
   non-LVM purposes, it is advisable to delete the beginning of this volume.
   For example, in the VG <literal>system</literal> and PV
   <filename>/dev/sda2</filename>, do this with the command
   <command>dd</command>&nbsp;<option>if=/dev/zero of=/dev/sda2 bs=512
   count=1</option>.
  </para>
  <warning>
   <title>File System for Booting</title>
   <para>
    The file system used for booting (the root file system or
    <filename>/boot</filename>) must not be stored on an LVM logical volume.
    Instead, store it on a normal physical partition.
   </para>
  </warning>
  <para>
    In case you want to change your <filename>/usr</filename> or
    <systemitem>swap</systemitem>, refer to <xref
      linkend="pro.boot.linuxrc.lvm"/>.
  </para>
  <para os="sles">
   For more details about LVM, see <xref linkend="stor_admin"/>.
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
