<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.onlineupdate.you">
 <title>&yast; Online Update</title>
 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
          </dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <indexterm>
 <primary>updating</primary>
 <secondary>online</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>&yast;</primary>
 <secondary>online update</secondary></indexterm>
 <para>
  &suse; offers a continuous stream of software security updates for your
  product. By default, the update applet is used to keep your system
  up-to-date. Refer to <xref linkend="sec.updater"/> for further information
  on the update applet. This chapter covers the alternative tool for
  updating software packages: &yast; Online Update.
 </para>
 <para>
  The current patches for &productnamereg; are available from an update
  software repository<phrase os="osuse">, which is automatically configured
  during the installation</phrase>. If you have registered your product
  during the installation, an update repository is already configured. If
  you have not registered &productname;, you can do so by starting the
  <guimenu>Product Registration</guimenu> in &yast;. Alternatively, you
  can manually add an update repository from a source you trust. To add or
  remove repositories, start the Repository Manager with <menuchoice>
  <guimenu>Software</guimenu> <guimenu>Software Repositories</guimenu>
  </menuchoice> in &yast;. Learn more about the Repository Manager in
  <xref linkend="sec.y2.sw.instsource"/>.
 </para>
 <note>
  <title>Error on Accessing the Update Catalog</title>
  <para>
   <remark condition="generic"> 2008-02-29 - fs: Fate #303284 </remark>
   If you are not able to access the update catalog, this might be because
   of an expired subscription. Normally, &productname; comes with a
   one-year or three-year subscription, during which you have access to the
   update catalog. This access will be denied after the subscription ends.
  </para>
  <para>
   In case of an access denial to the update catalog you will see a warning
   message with a recommendation to visit the &ncc; and check your
   subscription. The &ncc; is available at
   <link xlink:href="&sccurl;/"/>.
  </para>
 </note>
 <para>
  &suse; provides updates with different relevance levels:
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Security Updates</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Fix severe security hazards and should always be installed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Recommended Updates</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Fix issues that could compromise your computer.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Optional Updates</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Fix non-security relevant issues or provide enhancements.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.onlineupdate.you.overview">
  <title>The Online Update Dialog</title>

  <para>
   To open the &yast; <guimenu>Online Update</guimenu> dialog, start
   &yast; and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Software </guimenu>
   <guimenu>Online Update</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Alternatively, start it
   from the command line with <command>yast2 online_update</command>.
  </para>

  <para>
   The <guimenu>Online Update</guimenu> window consists of four sections.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>&yast; Online Update</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="yast2_you.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="yast2_you.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   The <guimenu>Summary</guimenu> section on the left lists the available
   patches for &productname;. The patches are sorted by security
   relevance: <literal>security</literal>, <literal>recommended</literal>,
   and <literal>optional</literal>. You can change the view of the
   <guimenu>Summary</guimenu> section by selecting one of the following
   options from <guimenu>Show Patch Category</guimenu>:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Needed Patches</guimenu> (default view)</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Non-installed patches that apply to packages installed on your system.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>Unneeded Patches</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Patches that either apply to packages not installed on your system, or
      patches that have requirements which have already have been fulfilled
      (because the relevant packages have already been updated from another
      source).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><guimenu>All Patches</guimenu>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      All patches available for &productname;.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   Each list entry in the <guimenu>Summary</guimenu> section consists of a
   symbol and the patch name. For an overview of the possible symbols and
   their meaning, press <keycombo> <keycap function="shift"/>
   <keycap>F1</keycap> </keycombo>. Actions required by
   <literal>Security</literal> and <literal>Recommended</literal> patches
   are automatically preset. These actions are
   <guimenu>Autoinstall</guimenu>, <guimenu>Autoupdate</guimenu> and
   <guimenu>Autodelete</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you install an up-to-date package from a repository other than the
   update repository, the requirements of a patch for this package may be
   fulfilled with this installation. In this case a check mark is displayed
   in front of the patch summary. The patch will be visible in the list
   until you mark it for installation. This will in fact not install the
   patch (because the package already is up-to-date), but mark the patch as
   having been installed.
  </para>

  <para>
   Select an entry in the <guimenu>Summary</guimenu> section to view a short
   <guimenu>Patch Description</guimenu> at the bottom left corner of the
   dialog. The upper right section lists the packages included in the
   selected patch (a patch can consist of several packages). Click an entry
   in the upper right section to view details about the respective package
   that is included in the patch.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.onlineupdate.you.install">
  <title>Installing Patches</title>

  <para>
   The &yast; Online Update dialog allows you to either install all
   available patches at once or to manually select the patches that you want
   to apply to your system. You may also revert patches that have been
   applied to the system.
  </para>

  <para>
   By default, all new patches (except <literal>optional</literal> ones)
   that are currently available for your system are already marked for
   installation. They will be applied automatically once you click
   <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> or <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>.
<!--taroth 2014-05-27:  http://fate.suse.com/312509-->
   If one or multiple patches require a system reboot, you will be notified
   about this before the patch installation starts. You can then either
   decide to continue with the installation of the selected patches, skip
   the installation of all patches that need rebooting and install the rest,
   or go back to the manual patch selection.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Applying Patches with &yast; Online Update</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start &yast; and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Online Update</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To automatically apply all new patches (except
     <literal>optional</literal> ones) that are currently available for your
     system, proceed with <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> or
     <guimenu>Accept</guimenu> to start the installation of the preselected
     patches.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     First modify the selection of patches that you want to apply:
    </para>
    <substeps performance="required">
     <step>
      <para>
       Use the respective filters and views that the interface provides. For
       details, refer to <xref linkend="sec.onlineupdate.you.overview"/>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select or deselect patches according to your needs and wishes by
       right-clicking the patch and choosing the respective action from the
       context menu.
      </para>
      <important>
       <title>Always Apply Security Updates</title>
       <para>
        Do not deselect any <literal>security</literal>-related patches
        without a very good reason. These patches fix severe security
        hazards and prevent your system from being exploited.
       </para>
      </important>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Most patches include updates for several packages. If you want to
       change actions for single packages, right-click a package in the
       package view and choose an action.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To confirm your selection and apply the selected patches, proceed
       with <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> or <guimenu>Accept</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After the installation is complete, click <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> to
     leave the &yast; <guimenu>Online Update</guimenu>. Your system is
     now up-to-date.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.onlineupdate.you.automatically">
  <title>Automatic Online Update</title>

  <para>
   &yast; also offers the possibility to set up an automatic update with
   daily, weekly or monthly schedule. To use the respective module, you need
   to install the
   <systemitem class="resource">yast2-online-update-configuration</systemitem>
   package first.
  </para>

  <para>
   By default, updates are downloaded as delta RPMs. Since rebuilding RPM
   packages from delta RPMs is a memory- and processor-consuming task,
   certain setups or hardware configurations might require you to disable
   the use of delta RPMs for the sake of performance.
  </para>

  <para>
   Some patches, such as kernel updates or packages requiring license
   agreements, require user interaction, which would cause the automatic
   update procedure to stop. You can configure to skip patches that require
   user interaction.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Configuring the Automatic Online Update</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     After installation, start &yast; and select <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Software</guimenu> <guimenu>Online Update
     Configuration</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Alternatively, start the module with
     <command>yast2&nbsp;online_update_configuration</command> from the
     command line.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Activate <guimenu>Automatic Online Update</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Choose the update interval: <guimenu>Daily</guimenu>,
     <guimenu>Weekly</guimenu>, or <guimenu>Monthly</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To automatically accept any license agreements, activate <guimenu>Agree
     with Licenses</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select if you want to <guimenu>Skip Interactive Patches</guimenu> in
     case you want the update procedure to proceed fully automatically.
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>Skipping Patches</title>
     <para>
      If you select to skip any packages that require interaction, run a
      manual <guimenu>Online Update</guimenu> occasionally to
      install those patches, too. Otherwise you might miss important
      patches.
     </para>
    </important>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To automatically install all packages recommended by updated packages,
     activate <guimenu>Include Recommended Packages</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
<!--taroth 2014-05-27: http://fate.suse.com/314867-->
   <step>
    <para>
     To disable the use of delta RPMs (for performance reasons), deactivate
     <guimenu>Use Delta RPMs</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To filter the patches by category (such as security or recommended),
     activate <guimenu>Filter by Category</guimenu> and add the appropriate
     patch categories from the list. Only patches of the selected categories
     will be installed. Others will be skipped.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Confirm your configuration with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>The automatic online update does not automatically restart the system
   afterwards. If there are package updates that require a system reboot, you
   need to do this manually.</para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
