<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
  ]>
<chapter id="cha.y2.userman">
 <title>Managing Users with &yast;</title>
 <para>
  During installation, were able to create a local user for your system. With
  the &yast; module <guimenu>User and Group Management</guimenu> you can add
  more users or edit existing ones. It also let's you configure your system to
  authenticate users with a network server.
 </para>

 <sect1 id="sec.y2.userman.main">
  <title>User and Group Administration Dialog</title>

  <para>
   To administer users or groups, start &yast; and click <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Security and Users</guimenu> <guimenu>User and Group
   Management</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Alternatively, start the
   <guimenu>User and Group Administration</guimenu> dialog directly by
   running <command>sudo yast2 users &amp;</command> from a command line.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig.y2.userman.main">
   <title>&yast; User and Group Administration</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="yast2_users_main_gtk.png" width="90%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="yast2_users_main_gtk.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

 <para>
  Every user is assigned a system-wide user ID (UID). Apart from the users
  which can log in to your machine, there are also a number of
  <emphasis>system users</emphasis> for internal use only. Each user is
  assigned to one or more groups. Similar to <emphasis>system
  users</emphasis>, there are also <emphasis>system groups</emphasis> for
  internal use.
 </para>

  <para>
   Depending on the set of users you choose to view and modify with, the
   dialog (local users, network users, system users), the main window shows
   several tabs. These allow you to execute the following tasks:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Managing User Accounts</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      From the <guimenu>Users</guimenu> tab create, modify, delete or
      temporarily disable user accounts as described in
      <xref linkend="sec.y2.userman.users"/>. Learn about advanced options
      like enforcing password policies, using encrypted home directories,
      or managing disk quotas in
      <xref linkend="sec.y2.userman.adv"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Changing Default Settings</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Local users accounts are created according to the settings defined on
      the <guimenu>Defaults for New Users</guimenu> tab. Learn how to change
      the default group assignment, or the default path and access
      permissions for home directories in
      <xref
       linkend="sec.y2.userman.defaults"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Assigning Users to Groups</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Learn how to change the group assignment for individual users in
      <xref
       linkend="sec.y2.userman.assign"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Managing Groups</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      From the <guimenu>Groups</guimenu> tab, you can add, modify or delete
      existing groups. Refer to <xref linkend="sec.y2.userman.groups"/> for
      information on how to do this.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Changing the User Authentication Method</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      When your machine is connected to a network that provides user
      authentication methods like NIS or LDAP, you can choose between
      several authentication methods on the <guimenu>Authentication
      Settings</guimenu> tab. For more information, refer to
      <xref
       linkend="cha.y2.userman.authent"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   For user and group management, the dialog provides similar functionality.
   You can easily switch between the user and group administration view by
   choosing the appropriate tab at the top of the dialog.
  </para>

  <para>
   Filter options allow you to define the set of users or groups you want to
   modify: On the <guimenu>Users</guimenu> or <guimenu>Group</guimenu> tab,
   click <guimenu>Set Filter</guimenu> to view and edit users or groups
   according to certain categories, such as <guimenu>Local Users</guimenu>
   or <guimenu>LDAP Users</guimenu>, for instance (if you are part of a
   network which uses LDAP). With <menuchoice> <guimenu>Set Filter</guimenu>
   <guimenu>Customize Filter</guimenu> </menuchoice> you can also set up and
   use a custom filter.
  </para>

  <para>
   Depending on the filter you choose, not all of the following options and
   functions will be available from the dialog.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.y2.userman.users">
  <title>Managing User Accounts</title>

  <para>
   <indexterm>
   <primary>users</primary>
   <secondary>creating accounts</secondary>
   </indexterm> <indexterm>
   <primary>users</primary>
   <secondary>modifying accounts</secondary>
   </indexterm> &yast; offers to create, modify, delete or temporarily
   disable user accounts. Do not modify user accounts unless you are an
   experienced user or administrator.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>Changing User IDs of Existing Users</title>
   <para>
    File ownership is bound to the user ID, not to the user name. After a
    user ID change, the files in the user's home directory are automatically
    adjusted to reflect this change. However, after an ID change, the user
    no longer owns the files he created elsewhere in the file system unless
    the file ownership for those files are manually modified.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   In the following, learn how to set up default user accounts. For some
   further options, such as auto login, login without password, setting up
   encrypted home directories or managing quotas for users and groups, refer
   to <xref linkend="sec.y2.userman.adv"/>.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Adding or Modifying User Accounts</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open the &yast; <guimenu>User and Group Administration</guimenu> dialog
     and click the <guimenu>Users</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     With <guimenu>Set Filter</guimenu> define the set of users you want to
     manage. The dialog shows a list of users in the system and the groups
     the users belong to.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To modify options for an existing user, select an entry and click
     <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
    </para>
    <para>
     To create a new user account, click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the appropriate user data on the first tab, such as
     <guimenu>Username </guimenu> (which is used for login) and
     <guimenu>Password</guimenu>. This data is sufficient to create a new
     user. If you click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> now, the system will
     automatically assign a user ID and set all other values according to
     the default.
    </para>
   </step>
<!--Fate #302264-->
   <step os="sled">
    <para>
     Activate <guimenu>Receive System Mail</guimenu> if you want any kind of
     system notifications to be delivered to this user's mailbox. This
     creates a mail alias for &rootuser; and the user can read the system
     mail without having to first log in as &rootuser;.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If you want to adjust further details such as the user ID or the path
     to the user's home directory, do so on the <guimenu>Details</guimenu>
     tab.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you need to relocate the home directory of an existing user, enter
     the path to the new home directory there and move the contents of the
     current home directory with <guimenu>Move to New Location</guimenu>.
     Otherwise, a new home directory is created without any of the existing
     data.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To force users to regularly change their password or set other password
     options, switch to <guimenu>Password Settings</guimenu> and adjust the
     options. For more details, refer to
     <xref
      linkend="sec.y2.userman.adv.passw"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If all options are set according to your wishes, click
     <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
      Click  <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to close the administration dialog and to save
     the changes. A newly added user can now log in to the system using the
     login name and password you created.
    </para>
    <para>Alternatively, if you want to save all changes without exiting the
      <guimenu>User and Group Administration</guimenu> dialog, click <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Expert Options</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Write Changes Now</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <tip>
   <title>Matching User IDs</title>
   <para>
    For a new (local) user on a laptop which also needs to integrate into a
    network environment where this user already has a user ID, it is useful
    to match the (local) user ID to the ID in the network. This ensures that
    the file ownership of the files the user creates <quote>offline</quote>
    is the same as if he had created them directly on the network.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <procedure>
   <title>Disabling or Deleting User Accounts</title><indexterm>
   <primary>users</primary>
   <secondary>disabling accounts</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>users</primary>
   <secondary>deleting accounts</secondary></indexterm>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open the &yast; <guimenu>User and Group Administration</guimenu> dialog
     and click the <guimenu>Users</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To temporarily disable a user account without deleting it, select the
     user from the list and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>. Activate
     <guimenu>Disable User Login</guimenu>. The user cannot log into your
     machine until you enable the account again.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To delete a user account, select the user from the list and click
     <guimenu>Delete</guimenu>. Choose if you also want to delete the user's
     home directory or if you want to retain the data.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.y2.userman.adv">
  <title>Additional Options for User Accounts</title>

  <para>
   In addition to the settings for a default user account, &productnamereg;
   offers further options, such as options to enforce password policies, use
   encrypted home directories or define disk quotas for users and groups.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="cha.y2.userman.adv.login">
   <title>Automatic Login and Passwordless Login</title>
   <para>
      If you use the GNOME desktop environment you can configure
    <emphasis>Auto Login</emphasis> for a certain user as well as
    <emphasis>Passwordless Login</emphasis> for all users. Auto login causes
    a user to become automatically logged in to the desktop environment on
    boot. This functionality can only be activated for one user at a time.
    Login without password allows all users to log in to the system after
    they have entered their username in the login manager.
   </para>
   <warning>
    <title>Security Risk</title>
    <para>
     Enabling <emphasis>Auto Login</emphasis> or <emphasis>Passwordless
     Login</emphasis> on a machine that can be accessed by more than one
     person is a security risk. Without the need to authenticate, any user
     can gain access to your system and your data. If your system contains
     confidential data, do not use this functionality.
    </para>
   </warning>
   <para>
    If you want to activate auto login or login without password, access
    these functions in the &yast; <guimenu>User and Group
    Administration</guimenu> with <menuchoice> <guimenu>Expert
    Options</guimenu> <guimenu>Login Settings</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.y2.userman.adv.passw">
   <title>Enforcing Password Policies</title>
   <para>
    On any system with multiple users, it is a good idea to enforce at least
    basic password security policies. Users should change their passwords
    regularly and use strong passwords that cannot easily be exploited. For
    local users, proceed as follows:
<!--taroth
     080930: enable link as soon as we have added comparable
     contents: For information about how to enforce stricter password rules, refer to <xref
     linkend="sec.yast2.security.settings"/>.-->
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Configuring Password Settings</title><indexterm>
    <primary>users</primary>
    <secondary>password settings</secondary></indexterm>
    <step>
     <para>
      Open the &yast; <guimenu>User and Group Administration</guimenu>
      dialog and select the <guimenu>Users</guimenu> tab.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select the user for which to change the password options and click
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Switch to the <guimenu>Password Settings</guimenu> tab. The user's
      last password change is displayed on the tab.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To make the user change his password at next login, activate
      <guimenu>Force Password Change</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To enforce password rotation, set a <guimenu>Maximum Number of Days
      for the Same Password</guimenu> and a <guimenu>Minimum Number of Days
      for the Same Password</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To remind the user to change his password before it expires, set a
      number of <guimenu>Days before Password Expiration to Issue
      Warning</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To restrict the period of time the user can log in after his password
      has expired, change the value in <guimenu>Days after Password Expires
      with Usable Login</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      You can also specify a certain expiration date for a password. Enter
      the <guimenu>Expiration Date</guimenu> in
      <replaceable>YYYY-MM-DD</replaceable> format.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      For more information about the options and about the default values,
      click <guimenu>Help</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Apply your changes with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.y2.userman.adv.crypto">
   <title>Managing Encrypted Home Directories</title><indexterm>
   <primary>home directories</primary>
   <secondary>encrypting</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>users</primary>
   <secondary>encrypted home directories</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    To protect data in home directories against theft and hard disk removal,
    you can create encrypted home directories for users. These are encrypted
    with LUKS (Linux Unified Key Setup), which results in an image and an
    image key being generated for the user. The image key is protected with
    the user's login password. When the user logs into the system, the
    encrypted home directory is mounted and the contents are made available
    to the user.
   </para>
   <para>
    With &yast;, you can create encrypted home directories for new or
    existing users. To encrypt or modify encrypted home directories of
    already existing users, you need to know the user's current login
    password. By default, all existing user data is copied to the new
    encrypted home directory, but it is not deleted from the unencrypted
    directory.
   </para>
   <warning>
    <title>Security Restrictions</title>
    <para>
     Encrypting a user's home directory does not provide strong security
     from other users. If strong security is required, the system should not
     be physically shared.
    </para>
   </warning>
   <para>
    Find background information about encrypted home directories and which
    actions to take for stronger security in
    <xref linkend="sec.security.cryptofs.y2.homes"/>.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Creating Encrypted Home Directories</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Open the &yast; <guimenu>User and Group Management</guimenu> dialog
      and click the <guimenu>Users</guimenu> tab.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To encrypt the home directory of an existing user, select the user and
      click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <para>
      Otherwise, click <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to create a new user account
      and enter the appropriate user data on the first tab.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the <guimenu>Details</guimenu> tab, activate <guimenu>Use Encrypted
      Home Directory</guimenu>. With <guimenu>Directory Size in
      MB</guimenu>, specify the size of the encrypted image file to be
      created for this user.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="yast2_users_crypto_gtk.png" width="90%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="yast2_users_crypto_gtk.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Apply your settings with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Enter the user's current login password to proceed if &yast; prompts
      for it.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to close the administration dialog and save the changes.
     </para>
     <para>Alternatively, if you want to save all changes without exiting the
      <guimenu>User and Group Administration</guimenu> dialog, click <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Expert Options</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Write Changes Now</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>.</para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  <procedure>
    <title>Modifying or Disabling Encrypted Home Directories</title>
    <para>
     Of course, you can also disable the encryption of a home directory or
     change the size of the image file at any time.
    </para>
    <step>
     <para>
      Open the &yast; <guimenu>User and Group Administration</guimenu>
      dialog in the <guimenu>Users</guimenu> view.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select a user from the list and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      If you want to disable the encryption, switch to the
      <guimenu>Details</guimenu> tab and disable <guimenu>Use Encrypted Home
      Directory</guimenu>.
     </para>
     <para>
      If you need to enlarge or reduce the size of the encrypted image file
      for this user, change the <guimenu>Directory Size in MB</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Apply your settings with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Enter the user's current login password to proceed if &yast; prompts
      for it.
     </para>
    </step>
   <step>
    <para>Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to close the administration dialog and save the changes.
    </para>
    <para>Alternatively, if you want to save all changes without exiting the
     <guimenu>User and Group Administration</guimenu> dialog, click <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Expert Options</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Write Changes Now</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.</para>
   </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.y2.userman.adv.quota">
   <title>Managing Quotas</title><indexterm>
   <primary>users</primary>
   <secondary>quotas</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>quotas</primary>
   <secondary>users, groups</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    To prevent system capacities from being exhausted without notification,
    system administrators can set up quotas for users or groups. Quotas can
    be defined for one or more file systems and restrict the amount of disk
    space that can be used and the number of inodes (index nodes) that can
    be created there. Inodes are data structures on a file system that store
    basic information about a regular file, directory, or other file system
    object. They store all attributes of a file system object (like user and
    group ownership, read, write, or execute permissions), except file name
    and contents.
   </para>
   <para>
    &productname; allows usage of <literal>soft</literal> and
    <literal>hard</literal> quotas. Soft quotas usually define a warning
    level at which users are informed that they are nearing their limit,
    whereas hard quotas define the limit at which write requests are denied.
    Additionally, grace intervals can be defined that allow users or groups
    to temporarily violate their quotas by certain amounts.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Enabling Quota Support for a Partition</title>
    <para>
     In order to configure quotas for certain users and groups, you need to
     enable quota support for the respective partition in the &yast; Expert
     Partitioner first.
    </para>
    <step>
     <para>
      In &yast;, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>System</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Partitioner</guimenu> </menuchoice> and click
      <guimenu>Yes</guimenu> to proceed.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the <guimenu>Expert Partitioner</guimenu>, select the partition for
      which to enable quotas and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para><remark>taroth 2014-05-28: unfortunately, could not find the "Enable
      Quota Support" option for a btrfs file system - pinged lpechacek and
      dsterba about this, see https://fate.suse.com/315690, c#4 </remark>
      Click <guimenu>Fstab Options</guimenu> and activate <guimenu>Enable
      Quota Support</guimenu>. If the <systemitem>quota</systemitem> package
      is not already installed, it will be installed once you confirm the
      respective message with <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Confirm your changes and leave the <guimenu>Expert
      Partitioner</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure>
    <title>Setting Up Quotas for Users or Groups</title>
    <para>
     Now you can define soft or hard quotas for specific users or groups and
     set time periods as grace intervals.
    </para>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the &yast; <guimenu>User and Group Administration</guimenu>, select
      the user or the group you want to set the quotas for and click
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      On the <guimenu>Plug-Ins</guimenu> tab, select the <guimenu>Manage
      User Quota</guimenu> entry and click <guimenu>Launch</guimenu> to open
      the <guimenu>Quota Configuration</guimenu> dialog.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      From <guimenu>File System</guimenu>, select the partition to which the
      quota should apply.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="yast2_users_quota_gtk.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="yast2_users_quota_gtk.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Below <guimenu>Size Limits</guimenu>, restrict the amount of disk
      space. Enter the number of 1 KB blocks the user or group may have on
      this partition. Specify a <guimenu>Soft Limit</guimenu> and a
      <guimenu>Hard Limit</guimenu> value.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Additionally, you can restrict the number of inodes the user or group
      may have on the partition. Below <guimenu>Inodes Limits</guimenu>,
      enter a <guimenu>Soft Limit</guimenu> and <guimenu>Hard
      Limit</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      You can only define grace intervals if the user or group has already
      exceeded the soft limit specified for size or inodes. Otherwise, the
      time-related input fields are not activated. Specify the time period
      for which the user or group is allowed to exceed the limits set above.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Confirm your settings with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to close the administration dialog and save the changes.
     </para>
     <para>Alternatively, if you want to save all changes without exiting the
      <guimenu>User and Group Administration</guimenu> dialog, click <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Expert Options</guimenu>
       <guimenu>Write Changes Now</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>.</para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    &productname; also ships command line tools like
    <literal>repquota</literal> or <literal>warnquota</literal> with which
    system administrators can control the disk usage or send e-mail
    notifications to users exceeding their quota. With
    <command>quota_nld</command>, administrators can also forward kernel
    messages about exceeded quotas to D-BUS. For more information, refer to
    the <systemitem>repquota</systemitem>, the
    <systemitem>warnquota</systemitem> and the <command>quota_nld</command>
    man page.
<!--taroth 2011-07-21: all of the above are included in quota.rpm-->
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.y2.userman.defaults">
  <title>Changing Default Settings for Local Users</title><indexterm>

  <primary>users</primary>

  <secondary>default settings</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   When creating new local users, several default settings are used by
   &yast;. These include, for example, the primary group and the secondary
   groups the user belongs to, or the access permissions of the user's home
   directory. You can change these default settings to meet your
   requirements:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open the &yast; <guimenu>User and Group Administration</guimenu> dialog
     and select the <guimenu>Defaults for New Users</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To change the primary group the new users should automatically belong
     to, select another group from <guimenu>Default Group</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To modify the secondary groups for new users, add or change groups in
     <guimenu>Secondary Groups</guimenu>. The group names must be separated
     by commas.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If you do not want to use
     <filename>/home/<replaceable>username</replaceable></filename> as
     default path for new users' home directories, modify the <guimenu>Path
     Prefix for Home Directory</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To change the default permission modes for newly created home
     directories, adjust the umask value in <guimenu>Umask for Home
     Directory</guimenu>. For more information about umask, refer to
     <xref linkend="cha.security.acls"/> and to the <command>umask</command>
     man page.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     For information about the individual options, click
     <guimenu>Help</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Apply your changes with <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.y2.userman.assign">
  <title>Assigning Users to Groups</title>

  <para>
   <indexterm>
   <primary>users</primary>
   <secondary>group assignment</secondary>
   </indexterm> Local users are assigned to several groups according to the
   default settings which you can access from the <guimenu>User and Group
   Administration</guimenu> dialog on the <guimenu>Defaults for New
   Users</guimenu> tab. In the following, learn how to modify an individual
   user's group assignment. If you need to change the default group
   assignments for new users, refer to
   <xref linkend="sec.y2.userman.defaults"/>.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Changing a User's Group Assignment</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open the &yast; <guimenu>User and Group Administration</guimenu> dialog
     and click the <guimenu>Users</guimenu> tab. It shows a list of users
     and of the groups the users belong to.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> and switch to the
     <guimenu>Details</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To change the primary group the user belongs to, click <guimenu>Default
     Group</guimenu> and select the group from the list.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To assign the user additional secondary groups, activate the
     corresponding check boxes in the <guimenu>Additional Groups</guimenu>
     list.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to apply your changes.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to close the administration dialog and save the changes.
    </para>
    <para>Alternatively, if you want to save all changes without exiting the
     <guimenu>User and Group Administration</guimenu> dialog, click <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Expert Options</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Write Changes Now</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.</para>
   </step>
   </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.y2.userman.groups">
  <title>Managing Groups</title><indexterm>

  <primary>groups</primary>

  <secondary>managing</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>YaST</primary>

  <secondary>group management</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>configuring</primary>

  <secondary>groups</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   With &yast; you can also easily add, modify or delete groups.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Creating and Modifying Groups</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open the &yast; <guimenu>User and Group Management</guimenu> dialog and
     click the <guimenu>Groups</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     With <guimenu>Set Filter</guimenu> define the set of groups you want to
     manage. The dialog shows a list of groups in the system.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To create a new group, click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To modify an existing group, select the group and click
     <guimenu>Edit.</guimenu>
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the following dialog, enter or change the data. The list on the
     right shows an overview of all available users and system users which
     can be members of the group.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_groups_edit_gtk.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="yast2_groups_edit_gtk.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To add existing users to a new group select them from the list of
     possible <guimenu>Group Members</guimenu> by checking the corresponding
     box. To remove them from the group uncheck the box.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to apply your changes.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to close the administration dialog and save the changes.
    </para>
    <para>Alternatively, if you want to save all changes without exiting the
     <guimenu>User and Group Administration</guimenu> dialog, click <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Expert Options</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Write Changes Now</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para> In order to delete a group, it must not contain any group members. To
   delete a group, select it from the list and click <guimenu>Delete</guimenu>.
   Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to close the administration dialog and save the
   changes. Alternatively, if you want to save all changes without exiting the
     <guimenu>User and Group Administration</guimenu> dialog, click <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Expert Options</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Write Changes Now</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.</para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="cha.y2.userman.authent">
  <title>Changing the User Authentication Method</title><indexterm>

  <primary>users</primary>

  <secondary>authentication</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   When your machine is connected to a network, you can change the
   authentication method. The following options
   are available:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>NIS</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Users are administered centrally on a NIS server for all systems in
      the network. For details, see <xref linkend="cha.nis"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>LDAP</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Users are administered centrally on an LDAP server for all systems in
      the network. For details about LDAP, see
      <xref linkend="cha.security.ldap"/>.
     </para>
     <para>
      You can manage LDAP users with the &yast; user module. All other LDAP
      settings, including the default settings for LDAP users, have to be
      defined with the &yast; LDAP client module as described in
      <xref linkend="sec.security.ldap.yast.client"/> .
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Kerberos</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      With Kerberos, a user registers once and then is trusted in the entire
      network for the rest of the session.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Samba</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SMB authentication is often used in mixed Linux and Windows networks.
      For details, see <xref linkend="cha.samba"/><phrase os="sled">
      and <xref linkend="cha.security.ad"/></phrase>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <!--<varlistentry>
    <term>eDirectory LDAP</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <remark>taroth 2011-07-20: todo - check if this is still available</remark>
      eDirectory authentication is used in Novell networks.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>-->
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   To change the authentication method, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open the <guimenu>User and Group Administration</guimenu> dialog in
     &yast;.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the <guimenu>Authentication Settings</guimenu> tab to show an
     overview of the available authentication methods and the current
     settings.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To change the authentication method, click <guimenu>Configure</guimenu>
     and select the authentication method you want to modify. This takes you
     directly to the client configuration modules in &yast;. For information
     about the configuration of the appropriate client, refer to the
     following sections:
    </para>
    <formalpara>
     <title>NIS:</title>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="sec.nis.client"/>
     </para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
     <title>LDAP:</title>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="sec.security.ldap.yast.client"/>
     </para>
    </formalpara>
<!-- net_samba.xml has been dropped for 11.0 -->
    <formalpara>
     <title>Samba:</title>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="sec.samba.client.inst.yast"/>
     </para>
    </formalpara>
  <!-- taroth 2014-05-28: enable as soon as we have something about SSSD in
   Security Guide:
   <formalpara>
     <title>SSSD:</title>
     <para>
      <remark>taroth 2014-05-28: FIXME, add xref if we have a chapter about this</remark>
     </para>
    </formalpara>-->
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After accepting the configuration, return to the <guimenu>User and
     Group Administration</guimenu> overview.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to close the administration dialog.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
