<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<!-- Only include this file in openSUSE documentation. For SLE, there are
better supported methods. -->

<sect2 version="5.0" xml:id="sec-update-zypper"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Distribution upgrade with Zypper</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  With the <command>zypper</command> command line utility you can upgrade to
  the next version of the distribution. Most importantly, you can initiate
  the system upgrade process from within the running system.
 </para>
 <para>
  This feature is attractive for advanced users who want to run remote
  upgrades or upgrades on many similarly configured systems.
 </para>
 <sect3 xml:id="sec-update-zypper-prep">
  <title>Preparing the upgrade with Zypper</title>
  <para>
   To avoid unexpected errors during the upgrade process using
   <command>zypper</command>, minimize risky constellations.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Quit as many applications and stop unneeded services as possible and
     log out all regular users.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Disable third-party repositories before starting the upgrade, or lower
     the priority of these repositories to make sure packages from the
     default system repositories will get preference. Enable them again
     after the upgrade and edit their version string to match the version
     number of the distribution of the upgraded now running system.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect3>
 <sect3 xml:id="sec-update-zypper-proc">
  <title>The upgrade procedure</title>
  <warning>
   <title>Check your system backup</title>
   <para>
    Before actually starting the upgrade procedure, check that your system
    backup is up-to-date and restorable. This is especially important
    because you need to enter many of the following steps manually.
   </para>
  </warning>
  <para>
   The program <command>zypper</command> supports long and short command
   names. For example, you can abbreviate <command>zypper install</command>
   as <command>zypper in</command>. In the following text, the short
   variants are used.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run the online update to make sure the software management stack is
     up-to-date:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;zypper patch</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Configure the repositories you want to use as update sources. Getting
     this right is crucial. Either use &yast; (see
     <xref linkend="sec-yast-software-instsource"/>) or <command>zypper</command>
     (see <xref linkend="sec-zypper"/>) in this example.
     The name of the repositories used in the following steps may vary
     depending on the customization of your OS.
    </para>
    <para>
     To view your current repositories enter:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;zypper --releasever=15.3 lr -u</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the result of the previous command, check the last column
     (<guimenu>URL</guimenu>). All repository links should contain
     <literal>15.3</literal> or <literal>openSUSE_Leap_15.3</literal> as a
     version number. If this is not the case, proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       Decide whether this repository is still needed. If not, delete it using
       the following command:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;zypper rr <replaceable>NAME</replaceable></screen>
      <para>
       Repeat this for all repositories you no longer need.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       In case you still need a repository, continue as follows.
      </para>
      <para>
       For third-party repositories that do not include a version number, check
       with the provider of the repository whether &productname;
       &productnumber; is supported. If so, keep the repository. If not,
       remove it as described above.
      </para>
      <para>
       All remaining repositories you want to keep need to be updated to the
       new version. For this you need to remove the old version and add the
       new one. This procedure is done in the following with an example
       repository that has the following data:
      </para>
      <simplelist>
       <member>Name: <literal>M17N:fonts</literal></member>
       <member>URI: <literal>https://download.opensuse.org/repositories/M17N:/fonts/openSUSE_Leap_15.2/</literal></member>
      </simplelist>
      <substeps>
       <step>
        <para>
         Remove the old repository:
        </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;zypper rr "M17N:fonts"</screen>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>
         Add the new repository:
        </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;zypper ar -f \
https://download.opensuse.org/repositories/M17N:/fonts/openSUSE_Leap_15.3/ \
"M17N:fonts"</screen>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>
         Repeat this step for every repository that needs to be lifted to the
         new version.
        </para>
        <para>
         If adding a new repository fails, check in your browser whether the
         URL is correct. If not, a new version of the repository may not
         exist yet. Deactivate the repository and try again later. Packages
         from deactivated repositories will not be removed if all dependencies
         are still fulfilled.
        </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;zypper mr -d <replaceable>NAME</replaceable></screen>
       </step>
      </substeps>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Finally, check the current repository configuration again
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;zypper --releasever=15.3 lr -u</screen>
    <para>
     All repositories should now point to a <literal>15.3</literal>
     version (except for third-party repositories without versioning that
     support new releases). Repositories still pointing to an old version
     should at least be disabled (the column <guimenu>Enabled</guimenu>
     needs to show <literal>No</literal>).
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Update the repository metadata by running:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;zypper --releasever=15.3 ref</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the distribution upgrade that will lift your system to
     the new version:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.sudo;zypper --releasever=15.3 dup</screen>
    <para>
     Depending on the software selection you may need to approve one or more
     licenses. Check the output of the command. If everything is OK, approve
     with <guimenu>y</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Finally, restart your machine to boot into the new &productname; version:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;shutdown -r now</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   You can upgrade your system by using <command>zypper dup</command>.
   When using this command, take the following into account:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
     <para>
     If you are using <command>zypper dup</command> and there is not enough disk
      space available, the upgrade fails. In this case, use
      <option>--pkg-cache-dir <replaceable>DIR</replaceable></option> to set an
      alternative package cache directory.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
      All packages with unresolved dependencies will be removed. Packages
      installed from disabled repositories are kept as long as their
      dependencies are satisfied. Packages that are no longer available in the
      repositories are considered orphaned. Such packages are uninstalled if
      their dependencies cannot be satisfied. If they can be satisfied, such
      packages stay installed.
    </para>
    </listitem>
   <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>zypper dup</command> ensures that all installed packages come
      from one of the available repositories. It does not consider the version
      or architecture, but prevents changing the vendor of the installed
      packages by default, using the <option>--no-allow-vendor-change</option>
      option. If you have third-party repositories enabled, some repositories
      may break during the upgrade. In this case, use
      <option>--allow-vendor-change</option> instead.
     </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect3>
</sect2>
