<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.docker.overview" xml:lang="en">
 <title>Docker Overview</title>
 <para>
  Docker is a lightweight virtualization solution to run multiple virtual
  units (containers) simultaneously on a single control host. Containers are
  isolated with Kernel Control Groups (<xref linkend="vle.docker.cgroup"/>)
  and <xref linkend="vle.docker.namespace"/>.
 </para>
 <para>
  Full virtualization solutions such as &xen;, &kvm;, or &libvirt; are based
  on the processor simulating a complete hardware environment and
  controlling the virtual machines. However, Docker only provides operating
  system-level virtualization where the Linux kernel controls isolated
  containers.
 </para>
 <para>
  Before going into detail about Docker, let's define some of the terms used:
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry xml:id="Docker_engine">
   <term>
    Docker engine
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The docker engine is a server-client type application that performs all tasks related to virtual machines. The Docker engine comprises the following:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       daemon - is the server side of the docker engine that manages all docker objects (images, containers, network used by containers, etc.)
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       REST API - applications can use this API to communicate directly with the daemon
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       a CLI client - that enables you to communicate with the daemon. If the daemon is running on a different machine than the CLI client, the CLI client can communicate by using network sockets or the REST API provided by the docker engine.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry xml:id="Docker_Image">
   <term>Image</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     An <emphasis>image</emphasis> is a read-only template used to create a <emphasis>virtual machine</emphasis> on the host server. A Docker
     image is made by a series of layers built one over the other. Each layer
     corresponds to a permanent change, for example an update of an application. The changes are stored in a file called a <emphasis>dockerfile</emphasis>. For more details see  <link xlink:href="http://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/glossary#image">the official Docker documentation</link>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>
    Dockerfile
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A <emphasis>dockerfile</emphasis> stores changes made on top of the base image. The <xref linkend="Docker_engine"/> reads instructions in the <emphasis>dockerfile</emphasis> and builds a new image according to the instructions.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>
    Container
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A <emphasis>container</emphasis> is a running instance based on a particular Docker <xref linkend="Docker_Image"/>. Each <emphasis>container</emphasis> can be distinguished by a unique container ID.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>
    Registry
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A <emphasis>registry</emphasis> is storage for already created images. It typically contains several <emphasis>repositories</emphasis> There are two types of registry:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       public registry - where everyone (usually registered) can download and use images. A typical public registry is <link xlink:href="https://hub.docker.com/">Docker Hub</link>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       private registry - these are accessible for particular users or from a particular private network.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>
    Repository
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A <emphasis>repository</emphasis> is storage in a <emphasis>registry</emphasis> that stores a different version of a particular image. You can pull or push images from or to a repository.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry xml:id="vle.docker.cgroup">
   <term>
    Control groups
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Control groups</emphasis>, also called <literal>cgroups</literal>, is a Linux kernel feature that allows aggregating or
     partitioning tasks (processes) and all their children into
     hierarchically organized groups to isolate resources.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry xml:id="vle.docker.namespace">
   <term>
    Namespace
   </term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Docker uses <emphasis>namespaces</emphasis> for its containers that isolates resources reserved for particular containers.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Orchestration</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In a production environment you typically need a cluster with many
     containers on each cluster node. The containers must cooperate and you
     need a framework that enables you to manage the containers
     automatically. The act of automatic container management is called
     container orchestration and is typically handled by Kubernetes.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>


 </variablelist>
 <para>
  Docker is a platform that allows developers and system administrators to manage the complete life cycle of images. Docker makes it easy to build, ship and run images containing applications.
 </para>
 <para>
  Docker provides you with the following advantages:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Isolation of applications and operating systems through containers.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para> Near native performance, as Docker manages allocation of
   resources in real time. </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Controls network interfaces and resources available inside containers
    through cgroups.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Versioning of images.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Allows building new images based on existing ones.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Provides you with container orchestration.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  On the other hand, Docker has the following limitations:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
  <title>Limitations of Docker</title>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Containers run inside the host system's kernel and cannot use a
    different kernel.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Only allows Linux <emphasis>guest</emphasis> operating systems.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Docker is not a full virtualization stack like &xen;, &kvm;, or
    &libvirt;.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Security depends on the host system. Refer to the
    <link xlink:href="http://docs.docker.com/articles/security/">official
    security documentation</link> for more details.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>

 <sect1 xml:id="Docker_Architecture">
  <title>Docker Architecture</title>
  <para>
   Docker uses a client/server architecture. You can use the <emphasis>CLI client</emphasis> to communicate with the <emphasis>daemon</emphasis>. The <emphasis>daemon</emphasis> then performs operations with containers and manages images locally or in registry. The <emphasis>CLI client</emphasis> can run on the same server as the host daemon or on a different machine. The <emphasis>CLI client</emphasis> communicates with the <emphasis>daemon</emphasis> by using network sockets. The architecture is depicted in <xref linkend="Docker_architecture"/>.
  </para>
  <figure xml:id="Docker_architecture">
   <title>The docker architecture</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="docker_architecture.png" format="PNG" width="70%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="Docker_Used_Drivers">
  <title>Docker Drivers</title>
  <sect2 xml:id="Container_Drivers">
   <title>Container Drivers</title>
   <para>
    Docker uses <link xlink:href="https://github.com/docker/libcontainer">libcontainer</link> as the back-end driver to handle containers.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec.docker.storaged">
   <title>Storage Drivers</title>
   <para>
    Docker supports different storage drivers:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <systemitem class="resource">vfs</systemitem>: this driver is
      automatically used when the Docker host file system does not support
      copy-on-write. This is a simple driver which does not offer some
      advantages of Docker (like sharing layers, more on that in the
      next sections). It is highly reliable but also slow.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <systemitem class="resource">devicemapper</systemitem>: this driver
      relies on the device-mapper thin provisioning module. It supports
      copy-on-write, hence it offers all the advantages of Docker.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <systemitem class="resource">btrfs</systemitem>: this driver relies on
      Btrfs to provide all the features required by Docker. To use this
      driver the <filename>/var/lib/docker</filename> directory must be on a
      Btrfs file system.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <systemitem class="resource">AUFS</systemitem>: this driver
      relies on the AUFS union file system. Neither the upstream
      kernel nor the SUSE one supports this file system. Hence the
     AUFS driver is not built into the SUSE Docker package. </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    &slea;&nbsp;12 uses the Btrfs file system by default, which leads Docker
    to use the <systemitem class="resource">btrfs</systemitem> driver.
   </para>
   <para>
    It is possible to specify which driver to use by changing the value of
    the <envar>DOCKER_OPTS</envar> variable defined inside of the
    <filename>/etc/sysconfig/docker</filename> file. This can be done either
    manually or using &yast; by browsing to <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>System</guimenu> <guimenu>/etc/sysconfig Editor</guimenu>
    <guimenu>System</guimenu> <guimenu>Management</guimenu>
    <guimenu>DOCKER_OPTS</guimenu> </menuchoice> menu and entering the
    <systemitem class="library">-s storage_driver</systemitem> string.
   </para>
   <para>
    For example, to force the usage of the
    <systemitem class="resource">devicemapper</systemitem> driver enter the
    following text:
   </para>
<screen>DOCKER_OPTS="-s devicemapper"</screen>
   <important>
    <title>Mounting <filename>/var/lib/docker</filename></title>
    <para>
     It is recommended to have <filename>/var/lib/docker</filename> mounted
     on a separate partition or volume to not affect the Docker host operating
     system in case of a file system corruption.
    </para>

    <remark condition="clarity">
     2017-03-13 - fs: For SLE 12 SP3, check whether this still applies. Maybe a
     subvolume will be created by default, see bsc #102029.
    </remark>

    <para>
     In case you choose the Btrfs file system for
     <filename>/var/lib/docker</filename>, it is strongly recommended to create
     a subvolume for it.  This ensures that the directory is excluded from file
     system snapshots. If not excluding <filename>/var/lib/docker</filename>
     from snapshots, the file system will likely run out of disk space soon
     after you start deploying containers. What's more, a rollback to a previous
     snapshot will also reset the Docker database and images.  Disabling
     copy-on-write for this subvolume is also recommended, to avoid duplication
     of data blocks. Refer to <citetitle>Creating and Mounting New
     Subvolumes</citetitle> at <link
     xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/documentation/sles-12/book_sle_admin/data/sec_snapper_setup.html"/>
     for details.
    </para>
   </important>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

</chapter>
