<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.gnome.network" xml:lang="en">
 <title>Accessing Network Resources</title>
 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
          </dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <para>
  From your desktop, you can access files and directories or certain
  services on remote hosts or make your own files and directories available
  to other users in your network. &productnamereg; offers the following
  ways of accessing and creating network shared resources.
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Network Browsing</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Your file manager, &nautilus;, lets you browse your network for shared
     resources and services. Learn more about this in
     <xref linkend="sec.gnome.network.accshare"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Sharing Directories in Mixed Environments</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Using &nautilus;, configure your files and directories to share with
     other members of your network. Make your data readable or writable for
     users from any Windows or Linux workstation. Learn more about this in
     <xref linkend="sec.gnome.network.smbshare"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Managing Windows Files</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &productname; can be configured to integrate into an existing
     Windows network. Your Linux machine then behaves like a Windows client.
     It takes all account information from the Active Directory domain
     controller, just as the Windows clients do. Learn more about this in
     <xref linkend="sec.gnome.network.ad.data"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Configuring and Accessing a Windows Network Printer</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You can configure a Windows network printer through the &gnome; control
     center. Learn how to do this in
     <xref linkend="sec.gnome.network.ad.printer"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnomeuser.start.network.connect">
  <title>Connecting to a Network</title>

  <para>
   You can connect to a network with wired and wireless connections. To view
   your network connection, check the icon in the right part of the main
   panel. If you click the icon, you can see more details in the menu. Click
   the connection name to see more details and access the settings.
  </para>
  <para>
    To learn more about connecting to a network, see
    <xref linkend="cha.nm"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.network.general">
  <title>General Notes on File Sharing and Network Browsing</title>

  <important os="sles;sled">
   <title>Contact Your Administrator Before Setup</title>
   <para>
    Whether and to what extent you can use file sharing and network browsing
    and in your network highly depends on the network structure and on the
    configuration of your machine.
   </para>
   <para>
    Before setting up either of them, contact your system administrator.
    Check whether your network structure supports a feature and 
    whether your company's security policies permit it.
   </para>
  </important>

  <para>
   Network browsing, be it SMB browsing for Windows shares or SLP browsing
   for remote services, relies heavily on the machine's ability to send
   broadcast messages to all clients in the network. These messages and the
   clients' replies to them enable your machine to detect any available
   shares or services.
  </para>
  <para>
   For broadcasts to work effectively, your machine must
   be part of the same subnet as all other machines it is querying. If
   network browsing does not work on your machine or the detected shares and
   services do not meet your expectations,
   <phrase os="sles;sled">contact your system administrator to</phrase>
   ensure that you are connected to the appropriate subnet.
  </para>

  <para>
   To allow network browsing, your machine needs to keep several network
   ports open to send and receive network messages that provide details on
   the network and the availability of shares and services.
   <phrase os="sled;sles">The standard &productname; is configured for tight
   security and has a firewall that protects your machine against the Internet.
   </phrase>
  </para>
  <para>
   <phrase os="sled;sles">To adjust the firewall configuration, you would either
   need to ask your system administrator to
   put your interface into the internal zone or to tear down the firewall
   entirely (depending on your company's security policy).</phrase>
   If you try to browse a network with a restrictive firewall running on your
   machine, &nautilus; warns you that your security restrictions are not
   allowing it to query the network.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.network.accshare">
  <title>Accessing Network Shares</title>

  <para>
   Networking workstations can be set up to share directories. Typically,
   files and directories are marked to allow users remote access. These are
   called <emphasis>network shares</emphasis>. If your system is configured
   to access network shares, you can use your file manager to access these
   shares and browse them just as easily as if they were located on your
   local machine. Your level of access to the shared directories (whether
   read-only or write access, as well) is dependent on the permissions
   granted to you by the owner of the shares.
  </para>

  <para>
   To access network shares, open &nautilus; and click <guimenu>Browse
   Network</guimenu> from the <guimenu>Places</guimenu> pane. &nautilus;
   displays the servers and networks that you can access. Double-click a
   server or network to access its shares. You might be required to
   authenticate to the server by providing a user name and password. Common
   network shares are SFTP-accessible resources (SSH File Transfer Protocol)
   or Windows shares.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Network File Browser</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="network_browser.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="network_browser.png" width="70%" format="png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <procedure>
   <title>Adding a Network Place</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Accessories</guimenu> <guimenu>Files</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Connect to Server</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Connect to the Server Dialog</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="connect_server_a.png" format="PNG" width="50%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="connect_server_a.png" format="png" width="50%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the server address.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Connect</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.network.smbshare">
  <title>Sharing Directories</title>

  <para>
   Sharing and exchanging documents is a must-have in corporate
   environments. &nautilus; offers you file sharing, which makes your files
   and directories available to both Linux and Windows users.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.gnome.network.sharingcomputer">
   <title>Enabling Sharing on the Computer</title>
   <para>
    Before you can share a directory, you must enable sharing on your
    computer. To enable sharing:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start &yast; from the main menu.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Enter the &rootuser; password.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the category <guimenu>Network Services</guimenu>, click
      <guimenu>Windows Domain Membership</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Allow Users to Share Their Directories</guimenu>, then
      click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.gnome.network.sharingfolder">
   <title>Enabling Sharing for a Directory</title>
   <para>
    To configure file sharing for a directory:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Open &nautilus;.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Right-click a directory, then select <guimenu>Sharing
      Options</guimenu> from the context menu.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="folder_sharing_1_a.png" width="35%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="folder_sharing_1_a.png" width="35%" format="png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select <guimenu>Share this folder</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      If you want other people to be able to write to the directory, select
      <guimenu>Allow other people to write in this folder</guimenu>. To
      allow access for people without a user account check <guimenu>Guest
      Access</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Create Share</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      If the directory does not already have the permissions that are
      required for sharing, a dialog appears. Click <guimenu>Add the
      permissions automatically</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    The directory icon changes to indicate that the directory is now shared.
   </para>
   <important>
    <title>Samba Domain Browsing and Firewalls</title>
    <para>
     Samba domain browsing only works if your system's firewall is
     configured accordingly. Either disable the firewall entirely or assign
     the browsing interface to the internal firewall zone.
     <phrase os="sles;sled">Ask your system administrator how to proceed.
     </phrase>
    </para>
   </important>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.network.ad.data">
  <title>Managing Windows Files</title>

  <para>
   With your &productname; machine being an Active Directory client, you
   can browse, view and manipulate data located on Windows servers. The
   following examples are the most prominent ones:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Browsing Windows Files with &nautilus;</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use &nautilus;'s network browsing features to browse your Windows data.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Viewing Windows Data with &nautilus;</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Use &nautilus; to display the contents of your Windows user directory as
      you would for displaying a Linux directory. Create new files and
      directories on the Windows server.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Manipulating Windows Data with &gnome; Applications</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Many &gnome; applications allow you to open files on the Windows server,
      manipulate them and save them back to the Windows server.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Single Sign-On</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      &gnome; applications, including &nautilus;, support Single Sign-On.
      This means that you do not need to re-authenticate when you access other
      Windows resources. These can be Web servers, proxy servers or groupware
      servers like Microsoft Exchange*.
      Authentication against all these is handled silently in the background
      using the user name and password you provided when you logged in.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   To access your Windows data using &nautilus;, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open &nautilus; and click <guimenu>Network</guimenu> in the Places pane.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Double-click <guimenu>Windows Network</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Double-click the icon of the workgroup containing the computer you want
     to access.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the computer’s icon (and authenticate if prompted to do so) and
     navigate to the shared directory on that computer.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   To create directories in your Windows user directory using &nautilus;,
   proceed as you would when creating a Linux directory.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.gnome.network.ad.printer">
  <title>Configuring and Accessing a Windows Network Printer</title>

  <remark>Printing is so far unchecked for SLE 12 SP1 - beta 3 always showed
   "Sorry! System printing service not available", despite CUPS being installed.
   -- sknorr, 2015-09-16
  </remark>

  <para>
   Being part of a corporate network and authenticating against a Windows
   Active Directory server, you can access corporate resources such as
   printers. &gnome; allows you to configure printing from your Linux client
   to a Windows network printer.
  </para>

  <para>
   To configure a Windows network printer for use through your Linux
   workstation, proceed as follows:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the &gnome; control center from the main menu by clicking
     <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guimenu>System Tools</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenu>Printers</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Unlock</guimenu> and enter the
     <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> password.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the plus icon.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select a Windows printer connected via Samba.
    </para>
   </step>
<!-- <step>
    <para>
     Open the SMB Browser with <guimenu>Browse</guimenu> and select a
     workgroup, a server and the printer. Either enter the authentication
     credentials or choose to be prompted for authentication each time when
     accessing the printer. Click <guimenu>Forward</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Choose the printer's manufacturer and the printer model from the list
     and select a driver. The one that is marked with
     <guimenu>recommended</guimenu> normally produces the best results.
     Proceed with <guimenu>Forward</guimenu> and provide a name, a
     description and a location for the printer. Click
     <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>-->
  </procedure>

  <para>
   To print to the Windows network printer configured above, select it from
   the list of available printers.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
