<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.security.cryptofs">
 <title>Encrypting Partitions and Files</title><indexterm id="idx.encrypting" class="startofrange">
 <primary>encrypting</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>file systems</primary>
 <secondary>encrypting</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>file systems</primary>
 <secondary>cryptofs</secondary></indexterm>
 <para>
  Most users have some confidential data on their computer that third
  parties should not be able to access. The more you rely on mobile
  computing and on working in different environments and networks, the more
  carefully you should handle your data. The encryption of files or entire
  partitions is recommended if others have network or physical access to
  your system. Laptops or removable media, such as external hard disks or
  flash disks, are prone to being lost or stolen. Thus, it is recommended to
  encrypt the parts of your file system that hold confidential data.
 </para>
 <para>
  There are several ways to protect your data by means of encryption:
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Encrypting a Hard Disk Partition</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You can create an encrypted partition with &yast; during installation
     or in an already installed system. Refer to
     <xref linkend="sec.security.cryptofs.y2.part_inst"/> and
     <xref linkend="sec.security.cryptofs.y2.part_run"/> for details. This
     option can also be used for removable media, such as external hard
     disks, as described in
     <xref linkend="sec.security.cryptofs.y2.removables"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Creating an Encrypted File as Container</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You can create an encrypted file on your hard disk or on a removable
     medium with &yast; at any time. The encrypted file can then be used to
     <emphasis>store</emphasis> other files or directories. For more
     information, refer to
     <xref linkend="sec.security.cryptofs.y2.container"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Encrypting Home Directories</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     With &productname;, you can also create encrypted user home
     directories. When the user logs in to the system, the encrypted home
     directory is mounted and the contents are made available to the user.
     Refer to <xref linkend="sec.security.cryptofs.y2.homes"/> for more
     information.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Encrypting Single ASCII Text Files</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If you only have a small number of ASCII text files that hold sensitive
     or confidential data, you can encrypt them individually and protect
     them with a password using the vi editor. Refer to
     <xref linkend="sec.security.cryptofs.vi"/> for more information.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <warning>
  <title>Encrypted Media Offers Limited Protection</title>
  <para>
   The methods described in this chapter offer only a limited protection.
   You cannot protect your running system from being compromised. After the
   encrypted medium is successfully mounted, everybody with appropriate
   permissions has access to it. However, encrypted media are useful in case
   of loss or theft of your computer, or to prevent unauthorized individuals
   from reading your confidential data.
  </para>
 </warning>
 <sect1 id="sec.security.cryptofs.y2">
  <title>Setting Up an Encrypted File System with &yast;</title><indexterm id="idx.encrypting.partitions" class="startofrange">

  <primary>encrypting</primary>

  <secondary>partitions</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>encrypting</primary>

  <secondary>&yast;, with</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Use &yast; to encrypt partitions or parts of your file system during
   installation or in an already installed system. However, encrypting a
   partition in an already-installed system is more difficult, because you
   need to resize and change existing partitions. In such cases, it may be
   more convenient to create an encrypted file of a defined size, in which
   to <emphasis>store</emphasis> other files or parts of your file system.
   To encrypt an entire partition, dedicate a partition for encryption in
   the partition layout. The standard partitioning proposal as suggested by
   &yast;, does not include an encrypted partition by default. Add it
   manually in the partitioning dialog.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.security.cryptofs.y2.part_inst">
   <title>Creating an Encrypted Partition during Installation</title><indexterm>
   <primary>partitions</primary>
   <secondary>encrypting</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>encrypting</primary>
   <secondary>creating partitions</secondary></indexterm>
   <warning>
    <title>Password Input</title>
    <para>
     Make sure to memorize the password for your encrypted partitions well.
     Without that password, you cannot access or restore the encrypted data.
    </para>
   </warning>
   <para>
    The &yast; expert dialog for partitioning offers the options needed for
    creating an encrypted partition. To create a new encrypted partition
    proceed as follows:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Run the &yast; Expert Partitioner with <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>System</guimenu><guimenu>Partitioner</guimenu></menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select a hard disk, click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>, and select a primary
      or an extended partition.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select the partition size or the region to use on the disk.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select the file system, and mount point of this partition.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Activate the <guimenu>Encrypt device</guimenu> check box.
     </para>
     <note>
      <title>Additional Software Required</title>
      <para>
       After checking <guimenu>Encrypt device</guimenu>, a pop-up window
       asking for installing additional software may appear. Confirm to
       install all the required packages to ensure that the encrypted
       partition works well.
      </para>
     </note>
    </step>
<!-- 2009-10-02 toba: this option is grayed out and not accessible for
    encrypted partitions on opensuse 11.2m8 -->
<!-- FIXME: checkit! 2010-09-17, ke -->
    <step>
     <para>
      If the encrypted file system needs to be mounted only when necessary,
      enable <guimenu>Do not mount partition</guimenu> in the <guimenu>Fstab
      Options</guimenu>. otherwise enable <guimenu>Mount partition</guimenu>
      and enter the mount point.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> and enter a password which is used to
      encrypt this partition. This password is not displayed. To prevent
      typing errors, you need to enter the password twice.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Complete the process by clicking <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>. The
      newly-encrypted partition is now created.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    During the boot process, the operating system asks for the password
    before mounting any encrypted partition which is set to be auto-mounted
    in <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>. Such a partition is then available
    to all users when it has been mounted.
   </para>
   <para>
    To skip mounting the encrypted partition during start-up, press
    <keycap function="enter"/> when prompted for the password. Then decline
    the offer to enter the password again. In this case, the encrypted file
    system is not mounted and the operating system continues booting,
    blocking access to your data.
   </para>
   <para>
    When you need to mount an encrypted partition which is not mounted
    during the boot process, open a file manager and click the partition
    entry in the pane listing common places on your file system. You will be
    prompted for a password and the partition will be mounted.
   </para>
   <para>
    When you are installing your system on a machine where partitions
    already exist, you can also decide to encrypt an existing partition
    during installation. In this case follow the description in
    <xref linkend="sec.security.cryptofs.y2.part_run"/> and be aware that
    this action destroys all data on the existing partition.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.security.cryptofs.y2.part_run">
   <title>Creating an Encrypted Partition on a Running System</title><indexterm>
   <primary>encrypting</primary>
   <secondary>partitions</secondary></indexterm>
   <warning>
    <title>Activating Encryption on a Running System</title>
    <para>
     It is also possible to create encrypted partitions on a running system.
     However, encrypting an existing partition destroys all data on it, and
     requires resizing and restructuring of existing partitions.
    </para>
   </warning>
   <para>
    On a running system, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>System</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Partitioner</guimenu> </menuchoice> in the &yast; Control
    Center. Click <guimenu>Yes</guimenu> to proceed. In the <guimenu>Expert
    Partitioner</guimenu>, select the partition to encrypt and click
    <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>. The rest of the procedure is the same as
    described in <xref linkend="sec.security.cryptofs.y2.part_inst"/>.
   </para><indexterm startref="idx.encrypting.partitions" class="endofrange"/>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.security.cryptofs.y2.container">
   <title>Creating an Encrypted File as a Container</title><indexterm>
   <primary>files</primary>
   <secondary>encrypting</secondary></indexterm><indexterm id="idx.encrypting.files" class="startofrange">
   <primary>encrypting</primary>
   <secondary>files</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    Instead of using a partition, it is possible to create an encrypted
    file, which can hold other files or directories containing confidential
    data. Such container files are created from the &yast; Expert
    Partitioner dialog. Select <menuchoice><guimenu>Crypt Files</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Add Crypt File</guimenu></menuchoice> and enter the full path
    to the file and its size. If &yast; should create the container file,
    activate the check box <guimenu>Create Loop File</guimenu>. Accept or
    change the proposed formatting settings and the file system type.
    Specify the mount point and make sure that <guimenu>Encrypt
    Device</guimenu> is checked.
   </para>
   <para>
    Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu>, enter your password for decrypting the
    file, and confirm with <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The advantage of encrypted container files over encrypted partitions is
    that they can be added without repartitioning the hard disk. They are
    mounted with the help of a loop device and behave like normal
    partitions.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.security.cryptofs.y2.removables">
   <title>Encrypting the Content of Removable Media</title><indexterm id="idx.encrypting.remmedia" class="startofrange">
   <primary>encrypting</primary>
   <secondary>removable media</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    &yast; treats removable media (like external hard disks or flash disks)
    the same as any other hard disk. Container files or partitions on such
    media can be encrypted as described above. Do not, however, enable
    mounting at boot time, because removable media are usually only
    connected while the system is running.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you encrypted your removable device with &yast;, the GNOME desktop
    automatically recognizes the encrypted partition and prompt for the
    password when the device is detected. If you plug in a FAT formatted
    removable device while running GNOME, the desktop user entering the
    password automatically becomes the owner of the device and can read and
    write files. For devices with a file system other than FAT, change the
    ownership explicitly for users other than &rootuser; to enable these
    users to read or write files on the device.
   </para><indexterm startref="idx.encrypting.remmedia" class="endofrange"/>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.security.cryptofs.y2.homes">
  <title>Using Encrypted Home Directories</title>

  <para>
   To protect data in home directories from being stolen and consequent
   unauthorized access, use the &yast; user management module to enable
   encryption of home directories. You can create encrypted home directories
   for new or existing users. To encrypt or decrypt home directories of
   already existing users, you need to know their login password. See
   <xref linkend="sec.y2.userman.adv.crypto"/> for instructions.
  </para>

  <para>
   Encrypted home partitions are created within a file container as
   described in <xref linkend="sec.security.cryptofs.y2.container"/>. Two
   files are created under <filename>/home</filename> for each encrypted
   home directory:
  </para>

<!-- bg: 2008-04-22: cannot reproduce, functionality is broken right
  now. However, it looks like the description is correct. -->

<!-- bg: 2008-10-08: comment from april still holds true. -->

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename><replaceable>LOGIN</replaceable>.img</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The image holding the directory
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><filename><replaceable>LOGIN</replaceable>.key</filename>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The image key, protected with the user's login password.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   On login, the home directory automatically gets decrypted. Internally, it
   works through the PAM module called <emphasis>pam_mount</emphasis>. If
   you need to add an additional login method that provides encrypted home
   directories, you need to add this module to the respective configuration
   file in <filename>/etc/pam.d/</filename>. For more information, see
   <xref linkend="cha.pam"/> and the man page of <option>pam_mount</option>.
  </para>

  <warning>
   <title>Security Restrictions</title>
   <para>
    Encrypting a user's home directory does not provide strong security from
    other users. If strong security is required, the system should not be
    shared physically.
   </para>
   <para>
    To enhance security, also encrypt the <filename>swap</filename>
    partition and the <filename>/tmp</filename> and
    <filename>/var/tmp</filename> directories, because these may contain
    temporary images of critical data. You can encrypt
    <filename>swap</filename>, <filename>/tmp</filename>, and
    <filename>/var/tmp</filename> with the &yast; partitioner as described
    in <xref linkend="sec.security.cryptofs.y2.part_inst"/> or
    <xref linkend="sec.security.cryptofs.y2.container"/>.
   </para>
  </warning>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.security.cryptofs.vi">
  <title>Using vi to Encrypt Single ASCII Text Files</title><indexterm>

  <primary>encrypting</primary>

  <secondary>files with vi</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   The disadvantage of using encrypted partitions is obvious: While the
   partition is mounted, at least
   <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> can access the data. To
   prevent this, <command>vi</command> can be used in encrypted mode.
  </para>

  <para>
   Use <command>vi <option>-x</option>
   <replaceable>filename</replaceable></command> to edit a new file.
   <command>vi</command> prompts you to set a password, after which it
   encrypts the content of the file. Whenever you access this file,
   <command>vi</command> requests the correct password.
  </para>

  <para>
   For even more security, you can place the encrypted text file in an
   encrypted partition. This is recommended because the encryption used in
   <command>vi</command> is not very strong.
  </para><indexterm startref="idx.encrypting.files" class="endofrange"/><indexterm startref="idx.encrypting" class="endofrange"/>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
