<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<preface version="5.0" xml:id="pre.sle"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>About This Guide</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  This guide is intended for use by professional network and system
  administrators during the operation of &slereg;. As such, it is solely
  concerned with ensuring that &sle; is properly configured and that the
  required services on the network are available to allow it to function
  properly as initially installed. This guide does not cover the process of
  ensuring that &sle; offers proper compatibility with your enterprise's
  application software or that its core functionality meets those requirements.
  It assumes that a full requirements audit has been done and the installation
  has been requested, or that a test installation for such an audit has been
  requested.
 </para>
 <para>
  This guide contains the following:
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Support and Common Tasks</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &sle; offers a wide range of tools to customize various aspects of the
     system. This part introduces a few of them. <phrase os="sles">A breakdown
     of available device technologies, high availability configurations, and
     advanced administration possibilities introduces the system to the
     administrator.</phrase>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>System</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Learn more about the underlying operating system by studying this part.
     &sle; supports several hardware architectures and you can use this to
     adapt your own applications to run on &sle;. The boot loader and boot
     procedure information assists you in understanding how your Linux system
     works and how your own custom scripts and applications may blend in with
     it.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Services</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &sle; is designed to be a network operating system. <phrase os="sles">It
     offers a wide range of network services, such as DNS, DHCP, Web, proxy,
     and authentication services. It also integrates well into heterogeneous
     environments, including MS Windows clients and servers.</phrase>
     <phrase os="sled">&sledreg; includes client support for many network
     services. It integrates well into heterogeneous environments including MS
     Windows clients and servers. </phrase>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Mobile Computers</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Laptops, and the communication between mobile devices like PDAs, or
     cellular phones and &sle; need some special attention. Take care for power
     conservation and for the integration of different devices into a changing
     network environment. Also get in touch with the background technologies
     that provide the needed functionality.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Troubleshooting</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Provides an overview of finding help and additional documentation
     when you need more information or want to perform specific tasks. There is
     also a list of the most frequent problems with explanations how to
     fix them.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_available_doc_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_feedback_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_typografie_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_making_i.xml"/>
</preface>
