<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.isns" xml:lang="en">
 <title>iSNS for Linux</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker/>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
  Storage area networks (SANs) can contain many disk drives that are dispersed
  across complex networks. This can make device discovery and device ownership
  difficult. iSCSI initiators must be able to identify storage resources in the
  SAN and determine whether they have access to them.
 </para>
 <para>
  Internet Storage Name Service (iSNS) is a standards-based service that
  simplifies the automated discovery, management, and configuration of iSCSI
  devices on a TCP/IP network. iSNS provides intelligent storage discovery and
  management services comparable to those found in Fibre Channel networks.
 </para>
 <important>
  <title>Security Considerations</title>
  <para>
   iSNS should be used only in secure internal networks.
  </para>
 </important>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.isns.overview">
  <title>How iSNS Works</title>

  <para>
   For an iSCSI initiator to discover iSCSI targets, it needs to identify which
   devices in the network are storage resources and what IP addresses it needs
   to access them. A query to an iSNS server returns a list of iSCSI targets
   and the IP addresses that the initiator has permission to access.
  </para>

  <para>
   Using iSNS, you create iSNS discovery domains into which you then group or
   organize iSCSI targets and initiators. By dividing storage nodes into
   domains, you can limit the discovery process of each host to the most
   appropriate subset of targets registered with iSNS, which allows the storage
   network to scale by reducing the number of unnecessary discoveries and by
   limiting the amount of time each host spends establishing discovery
   relationships. This lets you control and simplify the number of targets and
   initiators that must be discovered.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>iSNS Discovery Domains</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="isns_a.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="isns_a.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   Both iSCSI targets and iSCSI initiators use iSNS clients to initiate
   transactions with iSNS servers by using the iSNS protocol. They then
   register device attribute information in a common discovery domain, download
   information about other registered clients, and receive asynchronous
   notification of events that occur in their discovery domain.
  </para>

  <para>
   iSNS servers respond to iSNS protocol queries and requests made by iSNS
   clients using the iSNS protocol. iSNS servers initiate iSNS protocol state
   change notifications and store properly authenticated information submitted
   by a registration request in an iSNS database.
  </para>

  <para>
   Benefits provided by iSNS for Linux include:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Provides an information facility for registration, discovery, and
     management of networked storage assets.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Integrates with the DNS infrastructure.
    </para>
   </listitem>
<!--   <listitem>
    <para>
     Provides access control for registered targets and initiators
    </para>
   </listitem> -->
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Consolidates registration, discovery, and management of iSCSI storage.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Simplifies storage management implementations.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Improves scalability compared to other discovery methods.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   An example of the benefits iSNS provides can be better understood through
   the following scenario:
  </para>

<!-- access control is not supported according to hare. And of
  course, you may always circumvent the iSNS server and discover the
  target directly -->

  <para>
   Suppose you have a company that has 100 iSCSI initiators and 100 iSCSI
   targets. Depending on your configuration, all iSCSI initiators could
   potentially try to discover and connect to any of the 100 iSCSI targets.
   This could create discovery and connection difficulties. By grouping
   initiators and targets into discovery domains, you can prevent iSCSI
   initiators in one department from discovering the iSCSI targets in another
   department. The result is that the iSCSI initiators in a specific department
   only discover those iSCSI targets that are part of the department's
   discovery domain.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.isns.install">
  <title>Installing iSNS Server for Linux</title>

  <para>
   iSNS Server for Linux is included with &productname;, but is not installed
   or configured by default. You need to install the package
   <systemitem class="resource">open-isns</systemitem> and configure the iSNS
   service.
  </para>

<!-- this funtionality defined in rfc, and the slave side seems to be
 sort of implemented, the master іs not available right now.
  <para>
   iSNS needs to be installed on only one server on your network. To
   provide an added level of redundancy, you can configure iSNS to be a
   cluster resource that can be failed over or migrated to another server
   on your network.
  </para>
  -->

  <note>
   <title>iSNS and iSCSI on the Same Server</title>
   <para>
    iSNS can be installed on the same server where iSCSI target or iSCSI
    initiator software is installed. Installing both the iSCSI target software
    and iSCSI initiator software on the same server is not supported.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   To install iSNS for Linux:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start &yast; and select <menuchoice><guimenu>Network Services</guimenu>
     <guimenu>iSNS Server</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In case <systemitem class="resource">open-isns</systemitem> is not
     installed yet, you are prompted to install it now. Confirm by clicking
     <guimenu>Install</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The iSNS Service configuration dialog opens automatically to the
     <guimenu>Service</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="isns_config_a.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="isns_config_a.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
<!-- fs 2014-12-16: Option is no longer present on SLE 12
    <step>
     <para>
      In <guimenu>Address of iSNS Server</guimenu>, specify the DNS name or
      IP address of the iSNS Server.
     </para>
    </step>
-->
   <step>
    <para>
     In <guimenu>Service Start</guimenu>, select one of the following:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
     <listitem>
      <formalpara>
       <title>When Booting:</title>
       <para>
        The iSNS service starts automatically on server start-up.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Manually (Default):</title>
       <para>
        The iSNS service must be started manually by entering <command>sudo
        systemctl start isnsd</command> at the server console of the server
        where you install it.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Specify the following firewall settings:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
     <listitem>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Open Port in Firewall:</title>
       <para>
        Select the check box to open the firewall and allow access to the
        service from remote computers. The firewall port is closed by default.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Firewall Details:</title>
       <para>
        If you open the firewall port, the port is open on all network
        interfaces by default. Click <guimenu>Firewall Details</guimenu> to
        select interfaces on which to open the port, select the network
        interfaces to use, then click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to apply the configuration settings and
     complete the installation.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Continue with
     <xref linkend="sec.isns.domains" xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.isns.domains">
  <title>Configuring iSNS Discovery Domains</title>

  <para>
   For iSCSI initiators and targets to use the iSNS service, they must belong
   to a discovery domain.
  </para>

  <important>
   <title>The iSNS Service Must be Active</title>
   <para>
    The iSNS service must be installed and running to configure iSNS discovery
    domains. For information, see
    <xref linkend="sec.isns.start" xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage"/>.
   </para>
  </important>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.isns.domains.ddcreate">
   <title>Creating iSNS Discovery Domains</title>
   <para>
    A default discovery domain named <guimenu>default DD</guimenu> is
    automatically created when you install the iSNS service. The existing iSCSI
    targets and initiators that have been configured to use iSNS are
    automatically added to the default discovery domain.
   </para>
   <para>
    To create a new discovery domain:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start &yast; and under <guimenu>Network Services</guimenu>, select
      <guimenu>iSNS Server</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>Discovery Domains</guimenu> tab.
     </para>
     <para>
      The <guimenu>Discovery Domains</guimenu> area lists all existing
      discovery domains. You can <guimenu>Create Discovery Domains</guimenu>,
      or <guimenu>Delete</guimenu> existing ones. Deleting a domain removes the
      members from the domain, but it does not delete the iSCSI node members.
     </para>
     <para>
      The <guimenu>Discovery Domain Members</guimenu> area lists all iSCSI
      nodes assigned to a selected discovery domain. Selecting a different
      discovery domain refreshes the list with members from that discovery
      domain. You can add and delete iSCSI nodes from a selected discovery
      domain. Deleting an iSCSI node removes it from the domain, but it does
      not delete the iSCSI node.
     </para>
     <para>
      <guimenu>Create iSCSI Node Member</guimenu> allows a node that is not yet
      registered to be added as a member of the discovery domain. When the
      iSCSI initiator or target registers this node, then it becomes part of
      this domain.
     </para>
     <para role="intro">
      When an iSCSI initiator performs a discovery request, the iSNS service
      returns all iSCSI node targets that are members of the same discovery
      domain.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="isns_discdomains_a.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="isns_discdomains_a.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>Create Discovery Domain</guimenu> button.
     </para>
     <para>
      You can also select an existing discovery domain and click the
      <guimenu>Delete</guimenu> button to remove that discovery domain.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Specify the name of the discovery domain you are creating, then click
      <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Continue with
      <xref linkend="sec.isns.domains.iscsi_nodes" xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.isns.domains.iscsi_nodes">
   <title>Adding iSCSI Nodes to a Discovery Domain</title>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start &yast; and under <guimenu>Network Services</guimenu>, select
      <guimenu>iSNS Server</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>iSCSI Nodes</guimenu> tab.
     </para>
     <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="isns_iscsinodes_a.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="isns_iscsinodes_a.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </informalfigure>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Review the list of nodes to ensure that the iSCSI targets and initiators
      that you want to use the iSNS service are listed.
     </para>
     <para>
      If an iSCSI target or initiator is not listed, you might need to restart
      the iSCSI service on the node. You can do this by running
     </para>
<screen>sudo systemctl restart iscsid.socket
sudo systemctl restart iscsi</screen>
     <para>
      to restart an initiator or
     </para>
<screen>sudo systemctl restart target-isns</screen>
     <para>
      to restart a target.
     </para>
     <para>
      You can select an iSCSI node and click the <guimenu>Delete</guimenu>
      button to remove that node from the iSNS database. This is useful if you
      are no longer using an iSCSI node or have renamed it.
     </para>
     <para>
      The iSCSI node is automatically added to the list (iSNS database) again
      when you restart the iSCSI service or reboot the server unless you remove
      or comment out the iSNS portion of the iSCSI configuration file.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>Discovery Domains</guimenu> tab and select the desired
      discovery domain.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Add existing iSCSI Node</guimenu>, select the node you
      want to add to the domain, then click <guimenu>Add Node</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Repeat the previous step for as many nodes as you want to add to the
      discovery domain, then click <guimenu>Done</guimenu> when you are
      finished adding nodes.
     </para>
     <para>
      Note that an iSCSI node can belong to more than one discovery domain.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.isns.start">
  <title>Starting the iSNS Service</title>

  <para>
   iSNS must be started at the server where you install it. If you have not
   configured it to be started at boot time (see
   <xref linkend="sec.isns.install"/> for details), enter the following command
   at a terminal console:
  </para>

<screen>sudo systemctl start isnsd</screen>

  <para>
   You can also use the <command>stop</command>, <command>status</command>, and
   <command>restart</command> options with iSNS.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.isns.info">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   For information, see the <citetitle>Linux iSNS for iSCSI project</citetitle>
   at <link xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/linuxisns/"/>. The
   electronic mailing list for this project can be found at
   <link xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?forum_name=linuxisns-discussion"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   General information about iSNS is available in <citetitle>RFC 4171: Internet
   Storage Name Service</citetitle> at
   <link xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4171"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
