<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossary
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<glossary xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="gloss.vt.glossary">
<!-- include acronyms -->
 <title>Glossary</title>
 <info>
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
        <dm:bugtracker>
          </dm:bugtracker>
      </dm:docmanager>
    </info>
    <glossdiv xml:id="gloss.vt.general">
  <title>General</title>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.vmm"><glossterm>Virtual Machine Manager</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A software program that provides a graphical user interface for
     creating and managing virtual machines.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.virtualized"><glossterm>Virtualized</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A guest operating system or application running on a virtual machine.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.vm"><glossterm>Virtual Machine</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A virtualized PC environment (VM) capable of hosting a guest operating
     system and associated applications. Could be also called a
     &vmguest;.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.vhs"><glossterm>VHS</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     Virtualization Host Server
    </para>
    <para>
     The physical computer running a &suse; virtualization platform
     software. The virtualization environment consists of the hypervisor,
     the host environment, virtual machines, and associated tools, commands,
     and configuration files. Other commonly used terms include host, Host
     Computer, Host Machine (HM), Virtual Server (VS), Virtual Machine Host
     (VMH), and VM Host Server (VHS).
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.xen"><glossterm>&xen;</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     See <xref linkend="cha.xen.basics" xrefstyle="ChapTitleOnPage"/>
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.kvm"><glossterm>&kvm;</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     See <xref linkend="cha.kvm.intro" xrefstyle="ChapTitleOnPage"/>
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.xl"><glossterm>xl</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A set of commands for &xen; that lets administrators manage virtual
     machines from a command prompt on the host computer. It replaced the
     deprecated <command>xm</command> toolstack.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.hwassisted"><glossterm>hardware-assisted</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     Intel* and AMD* provide virtualization hardware-assisted technology.
     This reduces frequency of VM IN/OUT (fewer VM traps), because software
     is a major source of overhead, and increases the efficiency (the
     execution is done by the hardware). Moreover this reduces the memory
     footprint, provides better resource control, and allows secure
     assignment of specific I/O devices.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.dom0"><glossterm>Dom0</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     The term is used in &xen; environments, and refers to a virtual
     machine. The host operating system is actually a virtual machine
     running in a privileged domain and can be called &dom0;. All
     other virtual machines on the host run in unprivileged domains and can
     be called domain U's.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.createvm"><glossterm>Create Virtual Machine Wizard</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A software program available in &yast; and Virtual Machine Manager
     that provides a graphical interface to guide you through the steps to
     create virtual machines. It can also be run in text mode by entering
     <command>virt-install</command> at a command prompt in the host
     environment.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.hostenv"><glossterm>Host Environment</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     The desktop or command line environment that allows interaction with
     the host computer's environment. It provides a command line environment
     and can also include a graphical desktop, such as &gnome; or IceWM. The
     host environment runs as a special type of virtual machine that has
     privileges to control and manage other virtual machines. Other commonly
     used terms include <xref linkend="gloss.vt.dom0"/>, privileged domain,
     and host operating system.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.hypervisor"><glossterm>Hypervisor</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     The software that coordinates the low-level interaction between virtual
     machines and the underlying physical computer hardware.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.parafb"><glossterm>Paravirtualized Frame Buffer</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     The video output device that drives a video display from a memory
     buffer containing a complete frame of data for virtual machine displays
     running in paravirtual mode.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.virtfs"><glossterm>VirtFS</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     VirtFS is a new paravirtualized file system interface designed for
     improving pass-through technologies in the KVM environment. It is based
     on the VirtIO framework.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
 </glossdiv>
 <glossdiv xml:id="gloss.vt.cpu">
  <title>CPU</title>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.cpu.capping"><glossterm>CPU capping</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     Virtual CPU capping allows you to set vCPU capacity to 1–100 percent
     of the physical CPU capacity.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.cpu.overcommit"><glossterm>CPU over-commitment</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     Virtual CPU over-commitment is the ability to assign more virtual CPUs
     to VMs than the actual number of physical CPUs present in the physical
     system. This procedure does not increase the overall performance of the
     system, but might be useful for testing purposes.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.cpu.hotplug"><glossterm>CPU hotplugging</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     CPU hotplugging is used to describe the functions of
     replacing/adding/removing a CPU without shutting down the system.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.cpu.pinning"><glossterm>CPU pinning</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     Processor affinity, or CPU pinning enables the binding and unbinding of
     a process or a thread to a central processing unit (CPU) or a range of
     CPUs.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
 </glossdiv>
 <glossdiv xml:id="gloss.vt.network">
  <title>Network</title>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.network.bridgenet"><glossterm>Bridged Networking</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A type of network connection that lets a virtual machine be identified
     on an external network as a unique identity that is separate from and
     unrelated to its host computer.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.network.emptybridge"><glossterm>Empty Bridge</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A type of network bridge that has no physical network device or virtual
     network device provided by the host. This lets virtual machines
     communicate with other virtual machines on the same host but not with
     the host or on an external network.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.network.externalnet"><glossterm>External Network</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     The network outside a host's internal network environment.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.network.internalnetwork"><glossterm>Internal Network</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A type of network configuration that restricts virtual machines to
     their host environment.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.network.localbridge"><glossterm>Local Bridge</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A type of network bridge that has a virtual network device but no
     physical network device provided by the host. This lets virtual
     machines communicate with the host and other virtual machines on the
     host. Virtual machines can communicate on an external network through
     the host.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.network.nat"><glossterm>Network Address Translation (NAT)</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A type of network connection that lets a virtual machine use the IP
     address and MAC address of the host.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.network.nohostbridge"><glossterm>No Host Bridge</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A type of network bridge that has a physical network device but no
     virtual network device provided by the host. This lets virtual machines
     communicate on an external network but not with the host. This lets you
     separate virtual machine network communications from the host
     environment.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.network.traditionalbridge"><glossterm>Traditional Bridge</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A type of network bridge that has both a physical network device and a
     virtual network device provided by the host.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
 </glossdiv>
 <glossdiv xml:id="gloss.vt.storage">
  <title>Storage</title>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.storage.ahci"><glossterm>AHCI</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     The Advanced Host Controller Interface (AHCI) is a technical standard
     defined by Intel* that specifies the operation of Serial ATA (SATA)
     host bus adapters in a non-implementation-specific manner.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.storage.bd"><glossterm>Block Device</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     Data storage devices, such as CD-ROM drives or disk drives, that move
     data in the form of blocks. Partitions and volumes are also considered
     block devices.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.storage.fbvd"><glossterm>File-Backed Virtual Disk</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A virtual disk based on a file, also called a disk image file.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.storage.rawdisk"><glossterm>Raw Disk</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A method of accessing data on a disk at the individual byte level
     instead of through its file system.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.storage.sparse"><glossterm>Sparse image file</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A disk image file that does not reserve its entire amount of disk space
     but expands as data is written to it.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.storage.xvda"><glossterm>xvda</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     The drive designation given to the first virtual disk on a paravirtual
     machine.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
 </glossdiv>
 <glossdiv xml:id="gloss.vt.lxc">
  <title>Linux Containers</title>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.lxc.cgroups"><glossterm>cgroups</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     Kernel Control Groups (commonly just called <quote>cgroups</quote>) are a
     Kernel feature that allows aggregating or partitioning tasks (processes)
     and all their children into hierarchical organized groups to isolate
     resources.
    </para>
    <para>
     See also <xref linkend="cha.tuning.cgroups"/>.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.lxc.chroot"><glossterm>chroot</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A <emphasis>change root</emphasis> (chroot, or change root jail) is a
     section in the file system that is isolated from the rest of the file
     system. For this purpose, the <command>chroot</command> or
     <command>pivot_root</command> command is used to change the root of the
     file system. A program that is executed in such a <quote>chroot
     jail</quote> cannot access files outside the designated directory tree.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.lxc.container"><glossterm>container</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     Can be seen as a kind of <quote>virtual machine</quote> on the host
     server that can run any Linux system, for example &opensuse;,
     &sled;, or &sls;. The main difference with a normal virtual
     machine is that the container shares its kernel with the host it runs
     on.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry xml:id="gloss.vt.lxc.namespaces"><glossterm>Kernel namespaces</glossterm>
   <glossdef>
    <para>
     A Kernel feature to isolate some resources like network, users, and
     others for a group of processes.
    </para>
   </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
 </glossdiv>
<!-- include acronyms -->
 <xi:include href="vt_acronyms.xml"/>
</glossary>
