<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
 <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entities;
]>
<sect1 id="sec.y2.hw.print">
 <title>Setting Up a Printer</title>

 <para>
  &yast; can be used to configure a local printer that is directly connected
  to your machine via USB and to set up printing with network printers. It
  is also possible to share printers over the network. Further information
  about printing (general information, technical details, and
  troubleshooting) is available in <xref linkend="cha.p"/>.
 </para>

 <para>
  In &yast;, click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu>
  <guimenu>Printer</guimenu> </menuchoice> to start the printer module. By
  default it opens in the <guimenu>Printer Configurations</guimenu> view,
  displaying a list of all printers that are available and configured. This
  is especially useful when having access to a lot of printers via the
  network. From here you can also <guimenu>Print a Test Page</guimenu> and
  configure printers.
 </para>

 <note>
  <title>Starting CUPS</title>
  <para>
   To be able to print from your system, CUPS must run. In case it is not
   running, you are asked to start it. Answer with <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>,
   or you cannot configure printing. In case CUPS is not started at boot
   time, you will also be asked to enable this feature. It is recommended to
   say <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>, otherwise CUPS would need to be started
   manually after each reboot.
  </para>
 </note>

 <sect2 id="sec.y2.hw.print.local">
  <title>Configuring Printers</title>
  <para>
   Usually a USB printer is automatically detected. There are two possible
   reasons it is not automatically detected:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The USB printer is switched off.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The communication between printer and computer is not possible. Check
     the cable and the plugs to make sure that the printer is properly
     connected. If this is the case, the problem may not be printer-related,
     but rather a USB-related problem.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   Configuring a printer is a three-step process: specify the connection
   type, choose a driver, and name the print queue for this setup.
  </para>
  <para>
   For many printer models, several drivers are available. When configuring
   the printer, &yast; defaults to those marked
   <literal>recommended</literal> as a general rule. Normally it is not
   necessary to change the driver. However, if you want a color printer to
   print only in black and white, it is most convenient to use a driver that
   does not support color printing, for example. If you experience
   performance problems with a PostScript printer when printing graphics, it
   may help to switch from a PostScript driver to a PCL driver (provided
   your printer understands PCL).
  </para>
  <para>
   If no driver for your printer is listed, try to select a generic driver
   with an appropriate standard language from the list. Refer to your
   printer's documentation to find out which language (the set of commands
   controlling the printer) your printer understands. If this does not work,
   refer to <xref linkend="sec.y2.hw.print.local.get_ppd"/> for another
   possible solution.
  </para>
  <para>
   A printer is never used directly, but always through a print queue. This
   ensures that simultaneous jobs can be queued and processed one after the
   other. Each print queue is assigned to a specific driver, and a printer
   can have multiple queues. This makes it possible to set up a second queue
   on a color printer that prints black and white only, for example. Refer
   to <xref linkend="sec.p.workflow"/> for more information about print
   queues.
  </para>
  <procedure id="pro.y2.hw.print.local.config">
   <title>Adding a New Printer</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the &yast; printer module with <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu> <guimenu>Printer</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Printer Configurations</guimenu> screen click
     <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If your printer is already listed under <literal>Specify the
     Connection</literal>, proceed with the next step. Otherwise, try to
     <guimenu>Detect More</guimenu> or start the <guimenu>Connection
     Wizard</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the text box under <literal>Find and Assign a Driver</literal> enter
     the vendor name and the model name and click <guimenu>Search
     for</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Choose a driver that matches your printer. It is recommended to choose
     the driver listed first. If no suitable driver is displayed:
    </para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       Check your search term
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Broaden your search by clicking <guimenu>Find More</guimenu>
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Add a driver as described in
       <xref
	 linkend="sec.y2.hw.print.local.get_ppd"/>
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Specify the <literal>Default paper size</literal>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Set Arbitrary Name</guimenu> field, enter a unique name
     for the print queue.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The printer is now configured with the default settings and ready to
     use. Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to return to the <guimenu>Printer
     Configurations</guimenu> view. The newly configured printer is now
     visible in the list of printers.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <sect3 id="sec.y2.hw.print.local.get_ppd">
   <title>Adding Drivers with &yast;</title>
   <para>
    Not all printer drivers available for &productname; are installed by
    default. If no suitable driver is available in the <guimenu>Find and
    Assign a Driver</guimenu> dialog when adding a new printer install a
    driver package containing drivers for your printers:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Installing Additional Driver Packages</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the &yast; printer module with <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu> <guimenu>Printer</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the <guimenu>Printer Configurations</guimenu> screen, click
      <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the <literal>Find and Assign a Driver</literal> section, click
      <guimenu>Driver Packages</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose one or more suitable driver packages from the list. Do
      <emphasis>not</emphasis> specify the path to a printer description
      file.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose <guimenu>OK</guimenu> and confirm the package installation.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To directly use these drivers, proceed as described in
      <xref
      linkend="pro.y2.hw.print.local.config"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    PostScript printers do not need printer driver software. PostScript
    printers need only a PostScript Printer Description (PPD) file which
    matches the particular model. PPD files are provided by the printer
    manufacturer.
   </para>
   <para>
    If no suitable PPD file is available in the <guimenu>Find and Assign a
    Driver</guimenu> dialog when adding a PostScript printer install a PPD
    file for your printer:
   </para>
   <para>
    Several sources for PPD files are available. It is recommended to first
    try additional driver packages that are shipped with &productname; but
    not installed by default (see below for installation instructions). If
    these packages do not contain suitable drivers for your printer, get PPD
    files directly from your printer vendor or from the driver CD of a
    PostScript printer. For details, see
    <xref
    linkend="sec.drucken.prob.ppd"/>. Alternatively, find PPD
    files at
    <ulink
    url="http://www.linuxfoundation.org/collaborate/workgroups/openprinting/database/databaseintro"/>,
    the <quote>OpenPrinting.org printer database</quote>. When downloading
    PPD files from OpenPrinting, keep in mind that it always shows the
    latest Linux support status, which is not necessarily met by
    &productname;.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Adding a PPD file for PostScript Printers</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the &yast; printer module with <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu> <guimenu>Printer</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the <guimenu>Printer Configurations</guimenu> screen, click
      <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the <literal>Find and Assign a Driver</literal> section, click
      <guimenu>Driver Packages</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Enter the full path to the PPD file into the text box under
      <literal>Make a Printer Description File Available</literal>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to return to the <literal>Add New Printer
      Configuration</literal> screen.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To directly use this PPD file, proceed as described in
      <xref linkend="pro.y2.hw.print.local.config"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect3>
  <sect3 id="sec.y2.hw.print.local.tune">
   <title>Editing a Local Printer Configuration</title>
   <para>
    By editing an existing configuration for a printer you can change basic
    settings such as connection type and driver. It is also possible to
    adjust the default settings for paper size, resolution, media source,
    etc. You can change identifiers of the printer by altering the printer
    description or location.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the &yast; printer module with <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu> <guimenu>Printer</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the <guimenu>Printer Configurations</guimenu> screen, choose a
      local printer configuration from the list and click
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Change the connection type or the driver as described in
      <xref
       linkend="pro.y2.hw.print.local.config"/>. This should
      only be necessary in case you have problems with the current
      configuration.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Optionally, make this printer the default by checking <guimenu>Default
      Printer</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Adjust the default settings by clicking <guimenu>All Options for the
      Current Driver</guimenu>. To change a setting, expand the list of
      options by clicking the relative <literal>+</literal> sign. Change the
      default by clicking an option. Apply your changes with
      <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.y2.hw.print.network">
  <title>Configuring Printing via the Network with &yast;</title>
  <para>
   Network printers are not detected automatically. They must be configured
   manually using the &yast; printer module. Depending on your network
   setup, you can print to a print server (CUPS, LPD, SMB, or IPX) or
   directly to a network printer (preferably via TCP). Access the
   configuration view for network printing by choosing <guimenu>Printing via
   Network</guimenu> from the left pane in the &yast; printer module.
  </para>
  <sect3 id="sec.y2.hw.print.network.cups">
   <title>Using CUPS</title>
   <para>
    In a Linux environment CUPS is usually used to print via the network.
    The simplest setup is to only print via a single CUPS server which can
    directly be accessed by all clients. Printing via more than one CUPS
    server requires a running local CUPS daemon that communicates with the
    remote CUPS servers.
   </para>
   <important>
    <title>Browsing Network Printer Queues</title>
    <para>
     CUPS servers announce their print queues over the network either via
     the traditional CUPS browsing protocol or via Bonjour/DND-SD. Clients
     need to be able to browse these lists, so users can select specific
     printers to send their print jobs to. To be able to browse network
     print queues, the service
     <systemitem class="daemon">cups-browsed</systemitem> provided by the
     package
     <systemitem
     class="resource">cups-filters-cups-browsed</systemitem>
     needs to run on all clients that print via CUPS
     servers.<systemitem
     class="daemon">cups-browsed</systemitem> is
     started automatically when configuring network printing with &yast;.
    </para>
    <para>
     In case browsing does not work after having started
     <systemitem
     class="daemon">cups-browsed</systemitem>, the CUPS
     server(s) probably announce the network printer queues via
     Bonjour/DND-SD. In this case you need to additionally install the
     package <systemitem
     class="resource">avahi</systemitem> and start
     the associated service with <command>sudo systemctl start
     avahi-daemon.service</command> on all clients.
    </para>
   </important>
   <procedure>
    <title>Printing via a Single CUPS Server</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the &yast; printer module with <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu> <guimenu>Printer</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      From the left pane, launch the <guimenu>Print via Network</guimenu>
      screen.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Check <guimenu>Do All Your Printing Directly via One Single CUPS
      Server</guimenu> and specify the name or IP address of the server.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Test Server</guimenu> to make sure you have chosen the
      correct name or IP address.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click OK to return to the <guimenu>Printer Configurations</guimenu>
      screen. All printers available via the CUPS server are now listed.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure>
    <title>Printing via Multiple CUPS Servers</title>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the &yast; printer module with <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu> <guimenu>Printer</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      From the left pane, launch the <guimenu>Print via Network</guimenu>
      screen.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Check <guimenu>Accept Printer Announcements from CUPS
      Servers</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Under <literal>General Settings</literal> specify which servers to
      use. You may accept connections from all networks available or from
      specific hosts. If you choose the latter option, you need to specify
      the host names or IP addresses.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Confirm by clicking <guimenu>OK</guimenu> and then
      <guimenu>Yes</guimenu> when asked to start a local CUPS server. After
      the server has started &yast; will return to the <guimenu>Printer
      Configurations</guimenu> screen. Click <guimenu>Refresh list</guimenu>
      to see the printers detected by now. Click this button again, in case
      more printer are to be available.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect3>
  <sect3 id="sec.y2.hw.print.network.other">
   <title>Using Print Servers other than CUPS</title>
   <para>
    If your network offers print services via print servers other than CUPS,
    start the &yast; printer module with <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu><guimenu>Printer</guimenu></menuchoice> and
    launch the <guimenu>Print via Network</guimenu> screen from the left
    pane. Start the <guimenu>Connection Wizard</guimenu> and choose the
    appropriate <guimenu>Connection Type</guimenu>. Ask your network
    administrator for details on configuring a network printer in your
    environment.
   </para>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.y2.hw.print.share">
  <title>Sharing Printers Over the Network</title>
  <para>
   Printers managed by a local CUPS daemon can be shared over the network
   and so turn your machine into a CUPS server. Usually you share a printer
   by enabling CUPS' so-called <quote>browsing mode</quote>. If browsing is
   enabled, the local print queues are made available on the network for
   listening to remote CUPS daemons. It is also possible to set up a
   dedicated CUPS server that manages all print queues and can directly be
   accessed by remote clients. In this case it is not necessary to enable
   browsing.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <title>Sharing Printers</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the &yast; printer module with <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Hardware</guimenu> <guimenu>Printer</guimenu> </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Launch the <guimenu>Share Printers</guimenu> screen from the left pane.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Allow Remote Access</guimenu>. Also check <guimenu>For
     computers within the local network</guimenu> and enable browsing mode
     by also checking <guimenu>Publish printers by default within the local
     network</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to restart the CUPS server and to return to
     the <guimenu>Printer Configurations</guimenu> screen.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Regarding CUPS and firewall settings, see
     <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/SDB:CUPS_and_SANE_Firewall_settings" />.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
