<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:base="docker_containers.xml" xml:id="cha-working-with-containers" xml:lang="zh-cn" version="5.0">
 <title>Working with Containers</title>
 <para>
  After you have created your images, you can start your containers based on
  that image. You can run an instance of the image by using the <command>docker
  run</command> command. Docker Open Source Engine then creates and starts the
  container. The command <command>docker run</command> takes several arguments:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    A container name. (Giving containers individual names is recommended.)
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Specify a user to use in your container.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Define a mount point.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Specify a particular host name, etc.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  The container typically exits if its main process finishes. For example, if
  your container starts a particular application when you quit the
  application, the container exits. You can start the container again by
  running:
 </para>
 <screen><prompt>tux &gt; </prompt>docker start -ai &lt;container name&gt;</screen>
 <para>
  You may need to remove unused containers. You can do this with the command:
 </para>
 <screen><prompt>tux &gt; </prompt>docker rm &lt;container name&gt;</screen>

 <sect1 xml:id="Linking-Containers">
  <title>Linking Containers</title>

  <para>
   Docker Open Source Engine enables you to link containers together, which allows containers
   on the same host server to communicate with each other. If you use the
   standard networking model, you can link containers by using the
   <literal>--link</literal> option when running containers:
  </para>

  <para>
   First, create a container to link to:
  </para>
  <screen><prompt>tux &gt; </prompt>docker run -d --name sles sles12sp4 /bin/bash</screen>

  <para>
   Then create a container that will link to the <emphasis>sles</emphasis>
   container:
  </para>
  <screen><prompt>tux &gt; </prompt>docker run --link sles:sles sles12sp4 /bin/bash</screen>

  <para>
   This defines environment variables in the new container which enable it to
   link to the container named <emphasis>sles</emphasis>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
