<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:base="ay_introduction.xml" version="5.0" role="General" xml:id="cha-intro-to-autoyast">
 <title>Introduction to AutoYaST</title>
 <info>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker/>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="motiv">
  <title>Motivation</title>

  <para>
   Standard installations of <phrase role="productname"><phrase os="slemicro">SUSE Linux Enterprise Micro</phrase></phrase> are based on a wizard workflow. This
   is user-friendly and efficient when installing on few machines. However, it
   becomes repetitive and time-consuming when installing on many machines.
  </para>

  <para>
   To avoid this, you could do mass deployments by copying the hard disk of the
   first successful installation. Unfortunately, that leads to the issue that
   even minute configuration changes between each machine need to later be
   dealt with individually. For example, when using static IP addresses, these
   IP addresses would need to be reset for each machine.
  </para>

  <para>
   A regular installation of <phrase role="productname"><phrase os="slemicro">SUSE Linux Enterprise Micro</phrase></phrase> is semi-automated by default. The
   user is prompted to select the necessary information at the beginning of the
   installation (usually language only). YaST then generates a proposal for
   the underlying system depending on different factors and system parameters.
   Usually—and especially for new systems—such a proposal can be
   used to install the system and provides a usable installation. The steps
   following the proposal are fully automated.
  </para>

  <para>
   AutoYaST can be used where no user intervention is required or where
   customization is required. Using an AutoYaST profile, YaST prepares the system
   for a custom installation and does not interact with the user, unless
   specified in the file controlling the installation.
  </para>

  <para>
   AutoYaST is not an automated GUI system. This means that usually many screens
   will be skipped—you will never see the language selection interface,
   for example. AutoYaST will simply pass the language parameter to the sub-system
   without displaying any language related interface.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="overviewandconcept">
  <title>Overview and concept</title>

  <para>
   Using AutoYaST, multiple systems can easily be installed in parallel and
   quickly. They need to share the same environment and similar, but not
   necessarily identical, hardware. The installation is defined by an XML
   configuration file (usually named <filename>autoinst.xml</filename>) called
   the <quote>AutoYaST profile</quote>. You can create this using existing
   configuration resources, and easily tailor it for any specific environment.
  </para>

  <para>
   AutoYaST is fully integrated and provides various options for installing and
   configuring a system. The main advantage over other auto-installation
   systems is the ability to configure a computer by using existing
   modules, and avoid using custom scripts which are normally executed at
   the end of the installation.
  </para>

  <para>
   This document will guide you through the three steps of auto-installation:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Preparation: All relevant information about the target system is collected
     and turned into the appropriate directives in the profile. The profile is
     transferred onto the target system where its directives will be parsed and
     fed into YaST.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Installation: YaST performs the installation and basic configuration
     (for example, partitioning, networking, firewall) of the target system
     using the data from the AutoYaST profile.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Post-configuration: After the installation and configuration of the
     basic system, the system can run a second stage to perform any
     additional configurations that require the target system to be
     already running, such as post-installation scripts, third party
     modules, or some YaST modules.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  

  <note os="slemicro">
   <title>Single stage installation</title>
   <para>
    AutoYaST can split the installation process to two stages, where the second
    stage runs after reboot. AutoYaST then can install additional packages,
    configure the system and run post-installation scripts. However, that does
    not apply to <phrase role="productname"><phrase os="slemicro">SUSE Linux Enterprise Micro</phrase></phrase> as being a read-only file system, all options
    must be installed in one stage and the second stage needs to be disabled.
    To do so, set the following:
   </para>
<screen>&lt;general&gt;
  &lt;mode&gt;
    &lt;confirm config:type="boolean"&gt;false&lt;/confirm&gt;
    &lt;second_stage config:type="boolean"&gt;false&lt;/second_stage&gt;
  &lt;/mode&gt;
&lt;/general&gt;</screen>
  </note>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
